{
  "HPL": [
    {
      "question": "It takes about __________ minutes for the cones and __________ minutes for the rods to achieve maximum sensitivity.",
      "choices": [
        "5; 60",
        "1; 5",
        "2; 10",
        "9; 30"
      ],
      "answer": "9; 30"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Rasmussen\u2019s SRK model:\nThe __________ mode involves execution of actions based on __________ which have been learned.",
      "answers": [
        "Rule; rules",
        "Rule; skill",
        "Knowledge; rules",
        "Knowledge; skill"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Rule; rules"
    },
    {
      "question": "Deep-seated tiredness caused by continuous exposure to jet-lag is a characteristic of:",
      "answers": [
        "Incapacitation",
        "Chronic fatigue",
        "Short-term fatigue",
        "Fatigue"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Chronic fatigue"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the __________ is to carry air from the nose or mouth to the lungs.",
      "choices": [
        "pulmonary vein",
        "trachea",
        "pulmonary artery",
        "lungs"
      ],
      "answer": "trachea"
    },
    {
      "question": "Blood pressure is measured in __________ of mercury.",
      "choices": [
        "centimetres",
        "mm",
        "pounds",
        "inches"
      ],
      "answer": "mm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Slight imperfections in the curvature of the cornea or the lens...is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Presbyopia.",
        "Astigmatism.",
        "Cataracts.",
        "Hypermetropia"
      ],
      "answer": "Astigmatism."
    },
    {
      "question": "Blood pressure is lowest at __________.",
      "choices": [
        "heart attack",
        "high pulse",
        "diastole",
        "systole"
      ],
      "answer": "diastole"
    },
    {
      "question": "The normal cardiac output is approximately __________ litres per minute.",
      "choices": [
        "9",
        "7",
        "5",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "question": "Air sickness is caused by a disagreement between accelerations sensed by the __________ system and accelerations and orientation detected by the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "ear drum; eyes",
        "vestibular; eyes",
        "vestibular; brain",
        "ear drum; brain"
      ],
      "answer": "vestibular; eyes"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is the inability to focus on near objects.",
      "choices": [
        "Presbyopia",
        "Astigmatism",
        "Myopia",
        "Hyperopia"
      ],
      "answer": "Hyperopia"
    },
    {
      "question": "A progressive narrowing of the coronary arteries can cause shortness of breath and chest pain when exercising. This condition is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "A heart attack.",
        "A panic attack.",
        "Hypertension.",
        "Angina."
      ],
      "answer": "Angina."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a person seated (at rest) the time of useful consciousness is: 30 to 90 seconds at __________ ft.",
      "choices": [
        "50 000",
        "35 000",
        "25 000",
        "10 000"
      ],
      "answer": "35 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ vision is obtained because of the very slight difference in the perspective between one eye and the other.",
      "choices": [
        "Peripheral",
        "Night",
        "Monocular",
        "Stereoscopic"
      ],
      "answer": "Stereoscopic"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ pumps blood around the body.",
      "choices": [
        "capillaries",
        "heart",
        "arteries",
        "veins"
      ],
      "answer": "heart"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 5 stages of sleep includes: Stage 2: __________ sleep.",
      "choices": [
        "Light",
        "Deep",
        "REM",
        "Deeper"
      ],
      "answer": "Light"
    },
    {
      "question": "Dark adaptation causes increased sensitivity and __________ the threshold for detecting stimuli.",
      "choices": [
        "amplifies",
        "increases",
        "has no effect",
        "lowers"
      ],
      "answer": "lowers"
    },
    {
      "question": "When hyperventilation occurs the blood's:",
      "choices": [
        "Carbon monoxide level falls significantly.",
        "Carbon dioxide level increases significantly.",
        "Carbon monoxide level increases significantly.",
        "Carbon dioxide level falls significantly."
      ],
      "answer": "Carbon dioxide level falls significantly."
    },
    {
      "question": "The accepted time zone adjustment technique states that: For less than 24 hrs in the new zone __________.",
      "choices": [
        "take a long sleep on arrival",
        "take a short nap immediately and a longer sleep before the next duty period",
        "adjust as quickly as possible",
        "maintain home time"
      ],
      "answer": "maintain home time"
    },
    {
      "question": "Conductive deafness is caused by problems in the __________ ear.",
      "choices": [
        "external",
        "middle",
        "outer",
        "inner"
      ],
      "answer": "middle"
    },
    {
      "question": "The amount of oxygen attached to __________ is measured by the blood oxygen saturation level. It is about 98% for a normal healthy human.",
      "choices": [
        "plasma",
        "haemoglobin",
        "carbon dioxide",
        "carbon monoxide"
      ],
      "answer": "haemoglobin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cones used for colour vision are concentrated around the __________ part of the retina, called the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "peripheral; cornea",
        "central; cornea",
        "peripheral; fovea",
        "central; fovea"
      ],
      "answer": "central; fovea"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 1 of the 3 physiological thresholds for hypoxia is: __________ threshold 22 000 ft.",
      "choices": [
        "Critical",
        "Disturbance",
        "Reaction",
        "Intense"
      ],
      "answer": "Critical"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cones are __________ light sensitive than rods.",
      "choices": [
        "slightly",
        "more",
        "less",
        "equally as"
      ],
      "answer": "less"
    },
    {
      "question": "In normal operations, cabin altitude in a pressurised aircraft never exceeds 8000 ft. This protects crew and passengers against hypoxia and __________.",
      "choices": [
        "carbon monoxide",
        "hyperventilation",
        "anaemia",
        "decompression sickness"
      ],
      "answer": "decompression sickness"
    },
    {
      "question": "The vestibular apparatus detects __________.",
      "choices": [
        "vibrations",
        "accelerations",
        "sound waves",
        "day light"
      ],
      "answer": "accelerations"
    },
    {
      "question": "Presbyopia:",
      "choices": [
        "is common over the age of 50.",
        "is partial visual loss due to pressure changes in the eye.",
        "is caused by long-termed exposure to stimuli over 90 dB.",
        "is usually treated by surgical replacement of the lens and is compatible with flying."
      ],
      "answer": "is common over the age of 50."
    },
    {
      "question": "The contraction and relaxation of the ciliary muscle which changes the shape, and thus focal length, of the lens is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Focusing.",
        "Visual acuity.",
        "Accommodation.",
        "Visual field."
      ],
      "answer": "Accommodation."
    },
    {
      "question": "The 1 of the 3 physiological thresholds for hypoxia is: __________ threshold 10 000 to 12 000 ft.",
      "choices": [
        "Critical",
        "Reaction",
        "Disturbance",
        "Stress"
      ],
      "answer": "Disturbance"
    },
    {
      "question": "When deprived of sleep, the individual builds up a __________ which can only be satisfied by one or more longer periods of sleep to catch up.",
      "choices": [
        "insomnia",
        "sleep apnea",
        "sleep deficit",
        "sleep credit"
      ],
      "answer": "sleep deficit"
    },
    {
      "question": "The middle ear contains 3 small bones which conduct vibrations via the oval window to the __________ in the inner ear.",
      "choices": [
        "bones",
        "space",
        "air",
        "fluid"
      ],
      "answer": "fluid"
    },
    {
      "question": "The term \"circadian rhythm\" describes the:",
      "choices": [
        "biological cycle controlled by a 24-hour internal clock in the brain that regulates behavioural and physiological changes.",
        "physiological state in which there is a decreased capacity to perform cognitive tasks and an increased variability in performance.",
        "period of impaired cognitive performance and reduced vigilance following awakening from a regular sleep episode.",
        "natural drive to sleep that increases as the day progresses, and which also affects the ability to sustain attention."
      ],
      "answer": "biological cycle controlled by a 24-hour internal clock in the brain that regulates behavioural and physiological changes."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ reduces the chances of developing coronary disease because it: strengthens the heart muscle, improves circulation, increases the number of red blood cells, improves blood flow and reduces blood pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "Hypotension",
        "Exercise",
        "Hypertension",
        "Anaemia"
      ],
      "answer": "Exercise"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following may cause hyperventilation?",
      "choices": [
        "Excess alveolar carbon dioxide levels.",
        "A sudden decrease in the cabin pressure altitude.",
        "Anxiety or fear.",
        "Relaxation."
      ],
      "answer": "Anxiety or fear."
    },
    {
      "question": "How much does the barometric pressure decrease at 18000 ft in comparison to the mean sea level?",
      "choices": [
        "0.35",
        "0.65",
        "0.5",
        "0.25"
      ],
      "answer": "0.5"
    },
    {
      "question": "In dark conditions the neurons in the retina gradually become physiologically more sensitive to stimuli. This is known as __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "colour blindness",
        "long-sightedness",
        "short-sightedness",
        "dark adaptation"
      ],
      "answer": "dark adaptation"
    },
    {
      "question": "TUC (Time of Useful Consciousness) is:",
      "choices": [
        "the time after pressure loss until decompression sickness sets in.",
        "the time before becoming unconscious at a sudden pressure loss.",
        "measured from the moment at which an individual starts being exposed to hypoxia and death.",
        "the length of time during which an individual can act with both mental and physical efficiency after pressure loss."
      ],
      "answer": "the length of time during which an individual can act with both mental and physical efficiency after pressure loss."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a person seated (at rest) the time of useful consciousness is: 15 to 20 seconds at __________ ft.",
      "choices": [
        "50 000",
        "40 000",
        "10 000",
        "25 000"
      ],
      "answer": "40 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "The threat is then examined in detail by turning your head and eyes to focus the object on the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "iris",
        "blind spot",
        "fovea",
        "cataracts"
      ],
      "answer": "fovea"
    },
    {
      "question": "What can cause a coronary disease that may then lead to angina pectoris and myocardial infarction?",
      "choices": [
        "A cardiac automatism problem.",
        "A partial or complete blockage of coronary arteries.",
        "An abnormality of the cardiac valves.",
        "A congenital malformation of the coronary veins."
      ],
      "answer": "A partial or complete blockage of coronary arteries."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ carry oxygenated blood from the heart to organs and tissues.",
      "choices": [
        "capillaries",
        "arteries",
        "heart",
        "veins"
      ],
      "answer": "arteries"
    },
    {
      "question": "Excessively low blood pressure is known as __________. It can cause dizziness, shortness of breath, fainting and, in extreme cases, coma.",
      "choices": [
        "hypotension",
        "a panic attack",
        "anaemia",
        "hypertension"
      ],
      "answer": "hypotension"
    },
    {
      "question": "Damage to the __________, caused by high-energy blue or UV light can be reduced or avoided by using sunglasses.",
      "choices": [
        "cornea",
        "iris",
        "fovea",
        "retina"
      ],
      "answer": "retina"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is age-related hearing loss.",
      "choices": [
        "tinnitus",
        "Deafness",
        "Presbyopia",
        "Presbycusis"
      ],
      "answer": "Presbycusis"
    },
    {
      "question": "In monocular vision __________ depth perception isn\u2019t possible.",
      "choices": [
        "blurred vision",
        "peripheral",
        "near-field",
        "far field"
      ],
      "answer": "near-field"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a normal, young, healthy adult, systolic pressure is about __________ mm Hg and diastolic pressure is about __________ mm Hg.",
      "choices": [
        "120; 80",
        "120; 40",
        "80; 120",
        "150; 75"
      ],
      "answer": "120; 80"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 5 stages of sleep includes: Stage 5: __________ sleep.",
      "choices": [
        "Drowsiness",
        "REM",
        "Deeper",
        "Deep"
      ],
      "answer": "REM"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 5 stages of sleep includes: Stage 4: __________ sleep.",
      "choices": [
        "Deeper",
        "REM",
        "Drowsiness",
        "Deep"
      ],
      "answer": "Deep"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a result of hypoxia, the short-term memory begins to be affected above an altitude of about __________ ft.",
      "choices": [
        "12 000",
        "5000",
        "7000",
        "10 000"
      ],
      "answer": "5000"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following blood pressure conditions can disqualify a pilot from obtaining a medical clearance to fly?",
      "choices": [
        "Neither hypertension nor hypotension.",
        "Both hypertension and hypotension.",
        "Hypertension, but not hypotension.",
        "Hypotension, but not hypertension."
      ],
      "answer": "Both hypertension and hypotension."
    },
    {
      "question": "The 1 of the 3 physiological thresholds for hypoxia is: Reaction threshold __________ ft",
      "choices": [
        "20 000",
        "10 000",
        "4000",
        "7000"
      ],
      "answer": "7000"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is the body condition in which there is insufficient oxygen to support the metabolism of the tissues.",
      "choices": [
        "Hypoxia",
        "Decompression sickness",
        "Hyperventilation",
        "Anaemic"
      ],
      "answer": "Hypoxia"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ sunglasses must not be used because they make the polarised cockpit display units unreadable.",
      "choices": [
        "Extremely dark",
        "Metal",
        "Polarising",
        "Coloured"
      ],
      "answer": "Polarising"
    },
    {
      "question": "The condition in which sensory signals trigger progressively smaller responses in the brain is known as sensory __________.",
      "choices": [
        "tolerance",
        "clarity",
        "habituation",
        "adaption"
      ],
      "answer": "habituation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The period of time available to an individual after being deprived of oxygen in which s/he is still aware of his or her environment and capable of controlling his or her actions, is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "The effective capacity time.",
        "The internal respiration limit.",
        "The time of useful consciousness.",
        "The external respiration limit."
      ],
      "answer": "The time of useful consciousness."
    },
    {
      "question": "Sensory __________ is a decrease in the physiological response as the result of repeated exposure to a stimulus.",
      "choices": [
        "tolerance",
        "habituation",
        "clarity",
        "adaption"
      ],
      "answer": "adaption"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ travel results in significantly greater circadian dysrhythmia.",
      "choices": [
        "Eastbound",
        "Northbound",
        "Southbound",
        "Westbound"
      ],
      "answer": "Eastbound"
    },
    {
      "question": "The resolving power of the retina, i.e. the ability to discern small details, is described by the term:",
      "choices": [
        "Focusing.",
        "Visual acuity.",
        "Dark adaptation.",
        "Accommodation."
      ],
      "answer": "Visual acuity."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Photopic Vision is the same as Peripheral Vision.",
        "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Cones.",
        "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods.",
        "Scotopic Vision is the same as Photopic Vision."
      ],
      "answer": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods."
    },
    {
      "question": "Air is drawn into the lungs by the action of the diaphragm muscle...This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Hypoxia.",
        "External respiration.",
        "Decompression sickness.",
        "Internal respiration."
      ],
      "answer": "External respiration."
    },
    {
      "question": "Age-related long sightedness caused by a reduction in the elasticity of the lens is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Astigmatism.",
        "Presbyopia.",
        "Cataracts.",
        "Myopia."
      ],
      "answer": "Presbyopia."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ drive the urge to breathe in.",
      "choices": [
        "Excessively low levels of O2",
        "Excessively high level of CO2",
        "Excessively low levels of CO2",
        "Excessively high level of O2"
      ],
      "answer": "Excessively high level of CO2"
    },
    {
      "question": "The heart and blood are essential for transporting oxygen around the body and carrying __________ back to the lungs.",
      "choices": [
        "oxygen",
        "carbon monoxide",
        "carbon dioxide",
        "water"
      ],
      "answer": "carbon dioxide"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the following statement: During an approach with thunderstorms in the vicinity... This is a/an (1 ) __ and it can be (2) __ by a proper briefing.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) Threat; (2) eliminated.",
        "(1) Threat; (2) predicted.",
        "(1) Error; (2) predicted.",
        "(1) Error; (2) eliminated."
      ],
      "answer": "(1) Threat; (2) predicted."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ nerve carries sensory information from the retina to the visual cortex.",
      "choices": [
        "retina",
        "fovea",
        "iris",
        "optic"
      ],
      "answer": "optic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Throughout the night, we cycle progressively through the sleep stages, repeating the cycle at a steadily __________ rate.",
      "choices": [
        "varying",
        "decreasing",
        "increasing",
        "constant"
      ],
      "answer": "increasing"
    },
    {
      "question": "Excessively high blood pressure is known as __________. ...",
      "choices": [
        "anaemia",
        "stroke",
        "hypotension",
        "hypertension"
      ],
      "answer": "hypertension"
    },
    {
      "question": "During normal respiration the blood's __________ level determines the rate of respiration.",
      "choices": [
        "oxygen",
        "carbon dioxide",
        "heavy metal",
        "carbon monoxide"
      ],
      "answer": "carbon dioxide"
    },
    {
      "question": "The REM sleeper is sleeping __________ than in other phases of sleep.",
      "choices": [
        "much lighter",
        "more deeply",
        "lighter",
        "wake"
      ],
      "answer": "more deeply"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ carry de-oxygenated blood from the organs and tissues.",
      "choices": [
        "red cells",
        "veins",
        "heart",
        "arteries"
      ],
      "answer": "veins"
    },
    {
      "question": "In-ear headphones __________ capable of producing damaging levels of sound.",
      "choices": [
        "should not be",
        "should be",
        "are not",
        "are"
      ],
      "answer": "are"
    },
    {
      "question": "The danger to a pilot of becoming habituated to a stimulus, is that:",
      "choices": [
        "It may result in hypo vigilance",
        "It may trigger inappropriate alarm responses.",
        "You may not notice it.",
        "You may become dependent on it."
      ],
      "answer": "You may not notice it."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ is the organ responsible for translating fluid vibrations into electrical signals which are then sent to the brain via the auditory nerve.",
      "choices": [
        "Stapes",
        "tympanic membrane",
        "cochlea",
        "Eustachian tube"
      ],
      "answer": "cochlea"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the most significant factor for causing strokes?",
      "choices": [
        "Coronary artery disease.",
        "Obesity.",
        "Hypertension.",
        "Hypotension."
      ],
      "answer": "Hypertension."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ vision is relatively poor at night.",
      "choices": [
        "Night",
        "Color",
        "Peripheral",
        "Central"
      ],
      "answer": "Central"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hypertension may be correctable with drugs and by addressing the root causes. Hypertension is a major risk factor for __________.",
      "choices": [
        "anaemia",
        "strokes",
        "obesity",
        "diabetes"
      ],
      "answer": "strokes"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ is the central part of the retina and is most densely packed with cones.",
      "choices": [
        "fovea",
        "cataract",
        "optic nerve",
        "iris"
      ],
      "answer": "fovea"
    },
    {
      "question": "Visual acuity is highest in:",
      "choices": [
        "The cornea.",
        "The optic nerve.",
        "The fovea.",
        "The lens."
      ],
      "answer": "The fovea."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following accurately describes the 'sensory threshold'?",
      "choices": [
        "The level above which the intensity of a stimulus is sufficient to generate a response in the organism.",
        "The level at which the senses can generate autonomic reflexes.",
        "An effect where sensory signals trigger progressively smaller responses in the brain.",
        "A decrease in the physiological response as the result of repeated exposure to a stimulus."
      ],
      "answer": "The level above which the intensity of a stimulus is sufficient to generate a response in the organism."
    },
    {
      "question": "Are pilots allowed to wear contact lenses? If yes, which type of contact lenses are permitted?",
      "choices": [
        "Yes, only bifocal contact lenses and contact lenses correcting for near vision are acceptable.",
        "Yes, any type of contact lenses is allowed..., as long as a spare set of similarly correcting spectacles is carried.",
        "Yes, contact lenses may be used as long as they are for distant vision, monofocal, and non-tinted.",
        "The use of contact lenses is not permitted."
      ],
      "answer": "Yes, contact lenses may be used as long as they are for distant vision, monofocal, and non-tinted."
    },
    {
      "question": "The highest level of human error and poorest performance occur when the individual tries to work during __________.",
      "choices": [
        "the circadian high",
        "the window of circadian low",
        "the night time",
        "periods of darkness"
      ],
      "answer": "the window of circadian low"
    },
    {
      "question": "An inability to focus on distant objects requires a concave corrective lens to brings the lens\u2019 point of focus onto the retina. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Myopia.",
        "Hypermetropia.",
        "Long sightedness.",
        "Hyperopia."
      ],
      "answer": "Myopia."
    },
    {
      "question": "Systolic blood pressure is the pressure measured when the heart muscle __________.",
      "choices": [
        "pauses",
        "relaxes",
        "contracts",
        "beats"
      ],
      "answer": "contracts"
    },
    {
      "question": "With increasing cabin altitude, the blood oxygen saturation level holds approximately constant until about 7000 ft. Thereafter it __________.",
      "choices": [
        "fluctuates",
        "continues to remain constant",
        "increases",
        "decreases"
      ],
      "answer": "decreases"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a normal, healthy adult of average age, 1 hour of quality sleep allows for how many hours of activity?",
      "choices": [
        "2 hours.",
        "4 hours.",
        "1 hour.",
        "3 hours."
      ],
      "answer": "2 hours."
    },
    {
      "question": "The volume percentage of the gases in ambient air __________ at which conventional aircraft operate.",
      "choices": [
        "varies with temperature",
        "increases with increasing altitude",
        "remains constant at all altitudes",
        "reduces with increasing altitude"
      ],
      "answer": "remains constant at all altitudes"
    },
    {
      "question": "The body's internal clock, is brought into line with the 24-hour day by zeitgebers (cues). The most important of the cues is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "hunger",
        "bodyheat",
        "daylight",
        "sleepiness and wakefulness"
      ],
      "answer": "daylight"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ vision is one-eyed vision, lacking stereoscopic cues.",
      "choices": [
        "Night",
        "Peripheral",
        "Stereoscopic",
        "Monocular"
      ],
      "answer": "Monocular"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following options is one of the difference between cones and rods in the eye?",
      "choices": [
        "Rods have high visual acuity while cones observe colours.",
        "Cones are more sensitive to colours than rods.",
        "Cones are more sensitive to light than rods.",
        "Most of the rods are in the fovea and most cones are in the outside area."
      ],
      "answer": "Cones are more sensitive to colours than rods."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ contracts and expands rapidly to control the amount of light entering the eye.",
      "choices": [
        "cornea",
        "cataracts",
        "iris",
        "fovea"
      ],
      "answer": "iris"
    },
    {
      "question": "EASA believes that, __________ has the most significant implication for sleep.",
      "choices": [
        "digestion",
        "body temperature",
        "enzyme production",
        "respiration rate"
      ],
      "answer": "body temperature"
    },
    {
      "question": "At night you should look __________ at very dim objects to make them out.",
      "choices": [
        "backwards",
        "slightly off-centre",
        "slightly upwards",
        "directly"
      ],
      "answer": "slightly off-centre"
    },
    {
      "question": "Diastolic blood pressure is the pressure measured when the heart muscle is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "resting",
        "beating",
        "contracted",
        "relaxed"
      ],
      "answer": "relaxed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Free running circadian rhythms normally have a cycle of approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "25 hours",
        "6 hours",
        "8 hours",
        "36 hours"
      ],
      "answer": "25 hours"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most common cause of anaemic hypoxia is __________ poisoning or an insufficient amount of haemoglobin in the red blood cells.",
      "choices": [
        "carbon monoxide",
        "carbon dioxide",
        "oxygen",
        "heavy metal"
      ],
      "answer": "carbon monoxide"
    },
    {
      "question": "Noise induced hearing loss (NIHL) can be caused by prolonged exposure to loud noise levels greater than __________ dB, or a single exposure to an extremely loud noise.",
      "choices": [
        "50",
        "200",
        "25",
        "90"
      ],
      "answer": "90"
    },
    {
      "question": "In accelerated flight (positive or negative g) the __________ detect linear accelerations caused by g, as well as any component of acceleration caused by gravity.",
      "choices": [
        "cochlea",
        "ear bones",
        "otoliths",
        "semicircular canals"
      ],
      "answer": "otoliths"
    },
    {
      "question": "In such cases, a __________ corrective lens is used to move the point of focus forward on to the retina.",
      "choices": [
        "varifocal",
        "bifocal",
        "concave",
        "convex"
      ],
      "answer": "convex"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cardiac output is defined as:",
      "choices": [
        "Heart volume x stroke volume.",
        "Heart volume x stroke rate.",
        "Systolic blood pressure x stroke volume.",
        "Heart rate x stroke volume."
      ],
      "answer": "Heart rate x stroke volume."
    },
    {
      "question": "Sensory __________ lasts much longer than sensory __________ because it isn\u2019t dependent upon short-term physiological changes.",
      "choices": [
        "habituation; adaption",
        "habituation; proprioceptors",
        "adaption; habituation",
        "adaption; proprioceptors"
      ],
      "answer": "habituation; adaption"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a person seated (at rest) the time of useful consciousness is: __________ min at 20 000 ft.",
      "choices": [
        "10",
        "30",
        "5",
        "60"
      ],
      "answer": "30"
    },
    {
      "question": "The semi-circular canals contain fluid which moves when subjected to a __________ acceleration.",
      "choices": [
        "gravitational",
        "linear horizontal",
        "linear vertical",
        "angular"
      ],
      "answer": "angular"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is true regarding hypotension and/or hypertension?",
      "choices": [
        "Both conditions are harmless and therefore are NOT assessed during a pilot's medical.",
        "Having hypertension or hypotension may disqualify a pilot from obtaining medical clearance.",
        "Both conditions are related to the respiratory system.",
        "Hypotension WITHOUT symptoms can disqualify a pilot from obtaining medical clearance."
      ],
      "answer": "Having hypertension or hypotension may disqualify a pilot from obtaining medical clearance."
    },
    {
      "question": "Sensory habituation takes place in the:",
      "choices": [
        "Central nervous system.",
        "Neurones.",
        "Mechanoreceptors.",
        "Proprioceptors."
      ],
      "answer": "Central nervous system."
    },
    {
      "question": "Rods embedded in the retina detect __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "light",
        "colour",
        "black and white and colour",
        "black and white"
      ],
      "answer": "black and white"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rods are concentrated more densely in the __________ part of the retina.",
      "choices": [
        "upper",
        "lower",
        "central",
        "peripheral"
      ],
      "answer": "peripheral"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ is a natural body cycle which prepares the body, depending on the time of day, for rest or action and for fasting or feeding...",
      "choices": [
        "Digestion system",
        "REM Cycle",
        "sleep deficit system",
        "circadian rhythm"
      ],
      "answer": "circadian rhythm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 5 stages of sleep includes: Stage 1: __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Deep",
        "REM",
        "Light",
        "Drowsiness"
      ],
      "answer": "Drowsiness"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the __________ is to absorb oxygen from inspired air.",
      "choices": [
        "lungs",
        "alveoli",
        "trachea",
        "pulmonary artery"
      ],
      "answer": "alveoli"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ hypoxia is caused by a reduced ability of the blood to carry oxygen.",
      "choices": [
        "Hyperventilation",
        "Hypoxic",
        "Decompression sickness",
        "Anaemic"
      ],
      "answer": "Anaemic"
    },
    {
      "question": "The highly sensitive motion-detection capability of __________ vision serves to catch your attention.",
      "choices": [
        "visual",
        "night",
        "central",
        "peripheral"
      ],
      "answer": "peripheral"
    },
    {
      "question": "The normal pulse rate for an adult at rest is about __________ beats per minute. (As a whole number).",
      "choices": [
        "80",
        "60",
        "58",
        "70"
      ],
      "answer": "70"
    },
    {
      "question": "In __________ vision, depth perception is achieved by only taking cues from: colour, contrast, relative size and relative motion.",
      "choices": [
        "normal",
        "regular",
        "stereoscopic",
        "monocular"
      ],
      "answer": "monocular"
    },
    {
      "question": "Glaucoma is due to:",
      "choices": [
        "damage to the eyeball due to high altitude.",
        "an increase in pressure of the liquid within the eye.",
        "excess light on the eyeball.",
        "a drop in pressure of the liquid around the eye."
      ],
      "answer": "an increase in pressure of the liquid within the eye."
    },
    {
      "question": "The rate and depth of respiration is controlled by sensing the level of __________ in the blood stream.",
      "choices": [
        "oxygen",
        "carbon monoxide",
        "carbon dioxide",
        "heavy metal"
      ],
      "answer": "carbon dioxide"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ hypoxia is caused by low saturation levels of oxygen in the blood.",
      "choices": [
        "Decompression sickness",
        "Hyperventilation",
        "Anaemic",
        "Hypoxic"
      ],
      "answer": "Hypoxic"
    },
    {
      "question": "The accepted time zone adjustment technique states that: For 24 hrs in the new zone __________.",
      "choices": [
        "sleep as much as you can",
        "adjust to new zone asap",
        "take a short nap immediately and a longer sleep before the next duty period",
        "maintain home time"
      ],
      "answer": "take a short nap immediately and a longer sleep before the next duty period"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following greatly increase the oxygen-carrying capability of the red blood cells?",
      "choices": [
        "Haemoglobin.",
        "Platelets.",
        "Plasma.",
        "Bilirubin."
      ],
      "answer": "Haemoglobin."
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot is planned for a full week on duty with reduced periods of rest. What is the consequence of this?",
      "choices": [
        "Chronic insomnia.",
        "increasing sleep debt.",
        "Jet lag.",
        "Disrupted Circadian Rhythm."
      ],
      "answer": "increasing sleep debt."
    },
    {
      "question": "A complete blockage of a coronary artery which causes intense chest pain... is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Hypotension.",
        "A panic attack.",
        "A heart attack.",
        "Angina."
      ],
      "answer": "A heart attack."
    },
    {
      "question": "The accepted time zone adjustment technique states that: For more than 24hrs in new zone __________.",
      "choices": [
        "adjust to new zone asap",
        "take a short nap immediately and a longer sleep before the next duty period",
        "take a long sleep on arrival",
        "maintain home time"
      ],
      "answer": "adjust to new zone asap"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 5 stages of sleep includes: Stage 3: __________ sleep",
      "choices": [
        "Light",
        "Deep",
        "Deeper",
        "REM"
      ],
      "answer": "Deeper"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hyperventilation causes",
      "choices": [
        "acidosis",
        "hypochondria",
        "an excess of carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "a reduction of carbon dioxide in the blood"
      ],
      "answer": "a reduction of carbon dioxide in the blood"
    },
    {
      "question": "If cabin pressurisation is lost: immediately don your oxygen mask; make an emergency __________ and land asap.",
      "choices": [
        "stop",
        "landing",
        "call",
        "descent"
      ],
      "answer": "descent"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is a condition in which the individual suffers from a lack of haemoglobin or lack of red blood cells, or both.",
      "choices": [
        "Hypoxia",
        "Anaemia",
        "Hypotension",
        "Hypertension"
      ],
      "answer": "Anaemia"
    },
    {
      "question": "The circadian rhythm operates on an \u2018internal clock\u2019 which has a period of approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "24 hrs.",
        "36 hrs.",
        "24.5. hrs.",
        "25 hrs."
      ],
      "answer": "24 hrs."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ and lens together focus light coming into the eye onto the retina.",
      "choices": [
        "fovea",
        "iris",
        "cornea",
        "cataract"
      ],
      "answer": "cornea"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is the state of breathing faster and/or deeper than is necessary for the body\u2019s current demand for oxygen.",
      "choices": [
        "Hypoxia",
        "Hyperventilation",
        "Anaemia",
        "Decompression sickness"
      ],
      "answer": "Hyperventilation"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is the word used to describe the initiation, direction and energisation of human behaviour.",
      "choices": [
        "Motivation",
        "Rule",
        "Knowledge",
        "Cognitive"
      ],
      "answer": "Motivation"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the two inputs to a simple model of stress?",
      "choices": [
        "The ease of achieving the task and its usefulness in the scheme of things.",
        "The value of the task overall and its usefulness in the scheme of things.",
        "The perceived demand of the task to the pilot and the pilot's perceived ability to complete the task.",
        "The value of the task to the pilot and what the pilot can get out of it."
      ],
      "answer": "The perceived demand of the task to the pilot and the pilot's perceived ability to complete the task."
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ is an intentional deviation from what is known to be the correct action.",
      "choices": [
        "mistake",
        "fault",
        "violation",
        "omission"
      ],
      "answer": "violation"
    },
    {
      "question": "1 of the 3 phases of acquiring a skill is: The __________ phase, in which you consciously identify and develop the component parts of the skill.",
      "choices": [
        "Initial",
        "Cognitive",
        "Associative",
        "Autonomous"
      ],
      "answer": "Cognitive"
    },
    {
      "question": "A countermeasure against ineffective monitoring of automation is to revert to a __________ level of automation, so that the pilot becomes more involved and in-the-loop.",
      "choices": [
        "Variable",
        "Stable",
        "lower",
        "higher"
      ],
      "answer": "lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "High levels of stress may result in high levels of ___________.",
      "choices": [
        "Arousal",
        "anxiety",
        "performance",
        "break points"
      ],
      "answer": "anxiety"
    },
    {
      "question": "Working (short-term) memory capacity can be increased by the technique of __________ information.",
      "choices": [
        "Limiting",
        "Deleting",
        "avoiding",
        "chunking"
      ],
      "answer": "chunking"
    },
    {
      "question": "A faulty interaction between a pilot and an air traffic controller, for example incorrectly hearing a radio frequency change is a type of:",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft handling error.",
        "Procedural error.",
        "Communication error.",
        "Latent threat."
      ],
      "answer": "Communication error."
    },
    {
      "question": "Mental models, once created, __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "Are always false",
        "Are easy to break",
        "are usually flexible and susceptible to change",
        "often become very rigid and unsusceptible to change"
      ],
      "answer": "often become very rigid and unsusceptible to change"
    },
    {
      "question": "A sequence of interdependent errors whose effects are cumulative is the most common cause of aircraft accidents (rather than isolated, individual errors). This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "An active error.",
        "Decision making",
        "An action slip.",
        "An error chain."
      ],
      "answer": "An error chain."
    },
    {
      "question": "A false sense of orientation caused by the fact that the vestibular system interprets positive g as \u2018down\u2019 is the primary reason why the following, so-called, sense is so dangerous:",
      "choices": [
        "Angular sense.",
        "Somatogyral sense.",
        "Seat of the pants sense.",
        "G sense."
      ],
      "answer": "Seat of the pants sense."
    },
    {
      "question": "A human error associated with automation includes: Loss of __________ awareness: caused by failure to monitor mode changes suitably quickly, or lack of understanding about modes and sequences of modes.",
      "choices": [
        "passive",
        "mode",
        "situational",
        "cognitive"
      ],
      "answer": "mode"
    },
    {
      "question": "Informal, often unstated, rules that groups develop to convey expectations about appropriate behaviour is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Group norms.",
        "Synergy.",
        "Groupthink.",
        "Status."
      ],
      "answer": "Group norms."
    },
    {
      "question": "Forgetting or failing to carry out a required action is called an __________.",
      "choices": [
        "omission",
        "violation",
        "fault",
        "mistake"
      ],
      "answer": "omission"
    },
    {
      "question": "A series of defences (analogous to walls) are put in place to interrupt potential accident chains. Holes in the walls can align. When they do, they open an accident trajectory pathway through all the walls. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Safety first culture.",
        "Open culture.",
        "Reason\u2019s Swiss Cheese model.",
        "National cultural norms."
      ],
      "answer": "Reason\u2019s Swiss Cheese model."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft departs for a VFR flight. The route involves a descent into mountainous terrain. En-route an instrument fails, which makes it more difficult to fly without visual reference, and the weather deteriorates to IMC. The pilot continues to attempt to fly under VFR but crashes into the mountains. What type of error best characterises this accident scenario?",
      "choices": [
        "Lapse.",
        "Design-induced error.",
        "Isolated error.",
        "Error chain."
      ],
      "answer": "Error chain."
    },
    {
      "question": "High workload situations such as __________ require multiple rapid actions, and thus carry a risk of insufficient attention being paid to all the necessary tasks because of channelling of attention.",
      "choices": [
        "the go-around",
        "the approach",
        "landing",
        "cruise"
      ],
      "answer": "the go-around"
    },
    {
      "question": "A human error associated with automation includes: __________ concentration, characterised by focusing on just one element of the information displays.",
      "choices": [
        "Passive",
        "Cognitive",
        "Mode",
        "Blinkered"
      ],
      "answer": "Blinkered"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following characteristics apply to short-term memory?",
      "choices": [
        "It is stable and insensitive to disturbances",
        "It is limited in time and unlimited in size.",
        "It is unlimited in time and limited in size.",
        "It is limited in time and size."
      ],
      "answer": "It is limited in time and size."
    },
    {
      "question": "The GAS results in: ___________ heart rate; increased respiration rate; increased muscle tension; __________ production of saliva; loss of appetite; high level of alertness; increased energy levels.",
      "choices": [
        "increased; reduced",
        "reduced; reduced",
        "reduced; increased",
        "increased; increased"
      ],
      "answer": "increased; reduced"
    },
    {
      "question": "A conflict between people is an example of:",
      "choices": [
        "Interpersonal conflict.",
        "Implicit communication.",
        "Intrapersonal conflict.",
        "Explicit communication."
      ],
      "answer": "Interpersonal conflict."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the main advantages that the human possesses over those of a machine in the decision making process?",
      "choices": [
        "Creativity, innovation and adaptability.",
        "The ability to analyse and memorise.",
        "The ability to analyse and compare.",
        "The ability to reach the most advantageous option from a number of choices."
      ],
      "answer": "Creativity, innovation and adaptability."
    },
    {
      "question": "Side-by-side seating on the flight deck __________ the quality of interpersonal communication.",
      "choices": [
        "Has no effect on",
        "Improves",
        "reduces",
        "increases"
      ],
      "answer": "reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "A permanent or temporary inability to recall or even recognise events that were previously firmly stored in memory is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Spatial disorientation.",
        "Modelling.",
        "Semantic memory.",
        "Amnesia."
      ],
      "answer": "Amnesia."
    },
    {
      "question": "A helpful process in which the crew members communicate with each other and share information and tasks, is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Conformity.",
        "Cooperation.",
        "Groupthink.",
        "Co-action."
      ],
      "answer": "Cooperation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Misinterpreting the size of human figures in an 'Ames Room' is an example of the brain trying to maintain __________ constancy.",
      "choices": [
        "size",
        "sensory",
        "shape",
        "accurate"
      ],
      "answer": "size"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a symptom of human overload on a flight deck?",
      "choices": [
        "During the cruise stage of flight and in good weather, making an error when executing a normal procedure.",
        "During the cruise stage of a long flight, in VMC, missing out one or more steps when executing a normal procedure.",
        "During an emergency procedure, concentrating on one task and ignoring other information.",
        "Inadequate system knowledge."
      ],
      "answer": "During an emergency procedure, concentrating on one task and ignoring other information."
    },
    {
      "question": "The best countermeasure against illusions in IMC is to use your __________ to help you to correct your mental model.",
      "choices": [
        "Mental model",
        "Visual Cues",
        "seat of the pants sense",
        "instruments"
      ],
      "answer": "instruments"
    },
    {
      "question": "The faulty interaction between a pilot and a procedure, for example incorrectly reading from a checklist, is a type of:",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft handling error.",
        "Communication error.",
        "Procedural error.",
        "Latent threat."
      ],
      "answer": "Procedural error."
    },
    {
      "question": "The physiological response to stress (the 'fight or flight' response) is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Arousal.",
        "The general adaption syndrome.",
        "A stimulus.",
        "Underload."
      ],
      "answer": "The general adaption syndrome."
    },
    {
      "question": "Physical Stress takes place when:",
      "choices": [
        "outside conditions put a strain upon the homeostatic mechanisms of the body.",
        "the brain can no longer cope due to either quantitative or qualitative overload.",
        "overload of the neurones in the nervous system.",
        "the perceived demand is greater than the perceived ability."
      ],
      "answer": "outside conditions put a strain upon the homeostatic mechanisms of the body."
    },
    {
      "question": "It __________ possible to maintain at least straight, level and unaccelerated flight in cloud using just the seat of the pant's sense.",
      "choices": [
        "is always",
        "is not",
        "is",
        "may be"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    },
    {
      "question": "Having interrupted the Captain for a sound reason, the co-pilot should:",
      "choices": [
        "Never interrupt his/her Captain at a critical stage of flight.",
        "Ensure there is no ATC traffic on the radio that may be causing a possible distraction before continuing.",
        "Repeat the interruption twice so that the Captain's attention is focussed on the new information.",
        "Remind him/her of his/her last action before the interruption."
      ],
      "answer": "Remind him/her of his/her last action before the interruption."
    },
    {
      "question": "A conspiracy of silence in which mishaps aren\u2019t publicised and so individuals can\u2019t learn from the mistakes of others, is a central characteristic of:",
      "choices": [
        "Disciplinary cultures.",
        "Closed cultures.",
        "Open cultures.",
        "Safety first cultures."
      ],
      "answer": "Closed cultures."
    },
    {
      "question": "A human error associated with automation includes: Loss of __________ awareness caused by being out of the loop.",
      "choices": [
        "situational",
        "cognitive",
        "passive",
        "mode"
      ],
      "answer": "situational"
    },
    {
      "question": "To ensure that the aircraft is operated in accordance with the manufacturer\u2019s recommendations; to reduce the risk of omissions; to correctly sequence actions and to encourage cooperation and cross-checking is the ultimate purpose of:",
      "choices": [
        "Standard Operating Preparations.",
        "Checklists.",
        "Automation.",
        "Call-outs."
      ],
      "answer": "Checklists."
    },
    {
      "question": "When the risk of a decision is assessed as __________ and/or the time pressure is very __________, the individual is likely to make a quick decision based on past experience.",
      "choices": [
        "low; low",
        "high; high",
        "low; high",
        "high; low"
      ],
      "answer": "low; high"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ describes the brain's ability to interpret (for example) multiple perspectives of a person's face as all belonging to the same person.",
      "choices": [
        "Size constancy",
        "Shape constancy",
        "Bottom up processing",
        "Top down processing"
      ],
      "answer": "Shape constancy"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a lesson in a disorientation trainer with no external vision, a student is told to move the head up and down while the training device rotates about the vertical axis. Why, during this manoeuvre, does the student suddenly feel dizzy and disoriented?",
      "choices": [
        "The head movements disturb the processing of sensory inputs in the cerebral cortex areas of the student's brain, and subsequently, spatial orientation is lost.",
        "Because the training device is rotating, and without outside vision, the interaction between the senses is disturbed when the head is moved.",
        "The head movement itself has no effect on the disorientation; the rotation of the student about the vertical axis in combination with no outside vision alone account for the disorientation.",
        "The head movements disturb the equilibrium between all sensory inputs, and after a certain period of time, the human brain is no longer able to compensate for this."
      ],
      "answer": "Because the training device is rotating, and without outside vision, the interaction between the senses is disturbed when the head is moved."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ errors are very difficult to detect and often come to light only when an accident chain of events is examined.",
      "choices": [
        "Internal",
        "External",
        "Active",
        "Latent"
      ],
      "answer": "Latent"
    },
    {
      "question": "What strategy should be put in place when faced with an anticipated period of stress?",
      "choices": [
        "A non-sequenced strategy",
        "A strategy of preparing decisions",
        "A strategy of no commitment",
        "A Laissez-faire strategy"
      ],
      "answer": "A strategy of preparing decisions"
    },
    {
      "question": "Our mental model of the world is based",
      "choices": [
        "entirely on past experiences",
        "on both our past experiences and the sensory information we receive",
        "entirely on the sensory information we receive",
        "on both our past experiences and our motor programmes"
      ],
      "answer": "on both our past experiences and the sensory information we receive"
    },
    {
      "question": "In __________ workload situations, there is less opportunity to listen and discuss matters because both pilots must concentrate on the task. In such situations there is a __________ amount of non-verbal communication.",
      "choices": [
        "high; increased",
        "low; increased",
        "high; reduced",
        "low; reduced"
      ],
      "answer": "high; reduced"
    },
    {
      "question": "The basis of the perceptual process is receiving __________ information and constructing mental models to make sense of it.",
      "choices": [
        "biological",
        "physical",
        "sensory",
        "mental"
      ],
      "answer": "sensory"
    },
    {
      "question": "A culture which allows mistakes to be reported without undue risk of sanctions, and thus enables people to benefit from the knowledge of others' mistakes is a:",
      "choices": [
        "National cultural norm.",
        "Closed culture.",
        "Open culture.",
        "Safety first culture."
      ],
      "answer": "Open culture."
    },
    {
      "question": "Active errors/failures are committed at:",
      "choices": [
        "the system/system interface and have a delayed effect.",
        "the human/system interface and have an immediate effect.",
        "the human/system interface and have a delayed effect.",
        "the system/system interface and have an immediate effect."
      ],
      "answer": "the human/system interface and have an immediate effect."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ attention results in processing one set of information to the exclusion (almost) of all others.",
      "choices": [
        "Cognitive",
        "Selective",
        "Reflective",
        "Divided"
      ],
      "answer": "Selective"
    },
    {
      "question": "Valid stress coping strategies include: ___________ seeking in which you seek to understand and thus predict the stressor. This is a short or long-term solution.",
      "choices": [
        "Emotional",
        "Inhibition",
        "Information",
        "Direct"
      ],
      "answer": "Information"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ in thinking causes an individual to unjustifiably favour one strand of reasoning over another leading sometimes to a faulty decision.",
      "choices": [
        "Error",
        "Violation",
        "Bias",
        "Tolerance"
      ],
      "answer": "Bias"
    },
    {
      "question": "Stress increases arousal, which increases ___________.",
      "choices": [
        "Performance",
        "vigilance",
        "clarity",
        "calmness"
      ],
      "answer": "vigilance"
    },
    {
      "question": "A store of autobiographical information such as memories of places you have been to, people you know and life experiences you\u2019ve had, is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Episodic memory.",
        "Modelling.",
        "Semantic memory.",
        "Amnesia."
      ],
      "answer": "Episodic memory."
    },
    {
      "question": "False horizons caused by gently sloping terrain or gently sloping cloud tops can create __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Spatial disorientation",
        "a very powerful illusion",
        "mild air sickness",
        "the leans"
      ],
      "answer": "a very powerful illusion"
    },
    {
      "question": "Acute stress results in ___________ in the body's blood sugar level.",
      "choices": [
        "Rapid fluctuation",
        "No change",
        "an increase",
        "a decrease"
      ],
      "answer": "an increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "Valid stress coping strategies include: Inhibition, in which you do nothing, and just 'suck it up'. This is effective for ___________ stressors.",
      "choices": [
        "acute",
        "all",
        "short-term",
        "long-term"
      ],
      "answer": "short-term"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mental models, can pose a threat because they can be very __________.",
      "choices": [
        "False",
        "sensory",
        "alarming",
        "persuasive"
      ],
      "answer": "persuasive"
    },
    {
      "question": "Very high ambition and need for achievement",
      "choices": [
        "fulfil the requirements of stress resistance",
        "always promote teamwork",
        "improves the coping process with personal failures",
        "disturb the climate of cooperation"
      ],
      "answer": "disturb the climate of cooperation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fundamental philosophies for automation: __________: automated systems can correct erroneous pilot action.",
      "choices": [
        "McDonnell Douglas",
        "Lockheed",
        "Boeing",
        "Airbus"
      ],
      "answer": "Airbus"
    },
    {
      "question": "An unmotivated individual __________ learn a skill as fast as a motivated one.",
      "choices": [
        "Should",
        "may",
        "will not",
        "will"
      ],
      "answer": "will not"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is a generalised dizziness which is not necessarily accompanied by spatial disorientation.",
      "choices": [
        "Leans",
        "Coriolis",
        "Vertigo",
        "visual"
      ],
      "answer": "Vertigo"
    },
    {
      "question": "Faulty __________ models are the prime cause of cognitive illusions.",
      "choices": [
        "sensory",
        "biological",
        "mental",
        "physical"
      ],
      "answer": "mental"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Swiss Cheese model, what do holes represent?",
      "choices": [
        "Errors in the system or process.",
        "Systems or processes designed to prevent harm",
        "Systems or processes put in place to reduce risk.",
        "Missing data in the risk management system."
      ],
      "answer": "Errors in the system or process."
    },
    {
      "question": "Complementing leadership to ensure the optimal functioning and effectiveness of the group, is a description of good:",
      "choices": [
        "Trans-cockpit authority gradient.",
        "Groupthink.",
        "Followership.",
        "Leadership."
      ],
      "answer": "Followership."
    },
    {
      "question": "Motor programmes are susceptible to: __________ in which the right intention is wrongly executed.",
      "choices": [
        "Omission",
        "Environmental capture",
        "Action slips",
        "Violation"
      ],
      "answer": "Action slips"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode Error is associated with:",
      "choices": [
        "Hardware",
        "Vertigo",
        "Check lists",
        "Automation"
      ],
      "answer": "Automation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The phases of learning a Motor Programme are:",
      "choices": [
        "Induction, Simulation and Practice phases",
        "Initial, Interim and Final phases",
        "1st, 2nd and 3rd phases",
        "Cognitive, Associative and Automatic phases"
      ],
      "answer": "Cognitive, Associative and Automatic phases"
    },
    {
      "question": "A hypothesis is made and then information is sought to confirm it, is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Perception.",
        "Mental model.",
        "Bottom up processing.",
        "Top down processing."
      ],
      "answer": "Top down processing."
    },
    {
      "question": "A false sensation of pitching up when accelerating (e.g. take-off at night) or pitching down when decelerating (e.g. configuring the aircraft for landing in IMC) is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Coriolis",
        "The leans.",
        "The somatogyral illusion.",
        "The somatogravic illusion."
      ],
      "answer": "The somatogravic illusion."
    },
    {
      "question": "Falsely sensing an angular acceleration, or falsely sensing no angular acceleration when one is present, is an example of:",
      "choices": [
        "Coriolis.",
        "The somatogyral illusion.",
        "The somatogravic illusion.",
        "Air sickness."
      ],
      "answer": "The somatogyral illusion."
    },
    {
      "question": "How may haze effect perception?",
      "choices": [
        "Objects seem to be further away than in reality.",
        "Objects seem to be closer than in reality.",
        "Haze makes the eyes to focus at infinity",
        "There will be better contrast between objects"
      ],
      "answer": "Objects seem to be further away than in reality."
    },
    {
      "question": "A false or misinterpreted perception of a sensory experience is called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "a sensory fault",
        "a hallucination",
        "a mental model",
        "an illusion"
      ],
      "answer": "an illusion"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 3 components of the TEM model are:",
      "choices": [
        "Conditions, omissions, undesired aircraft states.",
        "Threats, errors, undesired aircraft states.",
        "Conditions, omissions, desired aircraft states.",
        "Threats, situations, undesired aircraft states."
      ],
      "answer": "Threats, errors, undesired aircraft states."
    },
    {
      "question": "Between which components, with reference to the SHELL Concept, covers pilot misinterpretation of the old three-point altimeter?",
      "choices": [
        "Liveware - Liveware",
        "Liveware - Software",
        "Liveware - Environment",
        "Liveware - Hardware"
      ],
      "answer": "Liveware - Hardware"
    },
    {
      "question": "Valid stress coping strategies include: Obtaining emotional support from others. This ___________ practicable on the flight deck.",
      "choices": [
        "Will always be",
        "is not",
        "will be",
        "is"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    },
    {
      "question": "A typical example of an undesired aircraft state according to the TEM model would be:",
      "choices": [
        "Flying too fast and/or too high during an approach.",
        "Missing readback clearances between flight crew and ATC.",
        "Using an incorrect communication frequency.",
        "Approaching a runway with a crosswind component."
      ],
      "answer": "Flying too fast and/or too high during an approach."
    },
    {
      "question": "The fundamental restrictions of auto-flight systems are: a lack of __________ in unknown situations and a lack of motivation with regard to personal safety.",
      "choices": [
        "decision making",
        "originality",
        "clarity",
        "creativity"
      ],
      "answer": "creativity"
    },
    {
      "question": "A standard behavioural response to a familiar situation, which may or may not be appropriate given the circumstances, is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "A reflex.",
        "Personality.",
        "A habit.",
        "An attitude."
      ],
      "answer": "A habit."
    },
    {
      "question": "The 'ironies of automation' are that design errors can leave tasks to the pilot that are too complex to automate, while causing loss of the pilot's manual and __________ skills.",
      "choices": [
        "Decision making",
        "creativity",
        "originality",
        "cognitive"
      ],
      "answer": "cognitive"
    },
    {
      "question": "A false sensation of tumbling, usually when you move your head while the aircraft is turning in IMC, is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "The leans.",
        "The somatogravic illusion.",
        "Vertigo.",
        "Coriolis."
      ],
      "answer": "Coriolis."
    },
    {
      "question": "Learning from pieces of knowledge and extrapolating them to new untried situations is an example of:",
      "choices": [
        "Insight (cognitive learning).",
        "Operant conditioning.",
        "Modelling.",
        "Classical conditioning."
      ],
      "answer": "Insight (cognitive learning)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Choose the correct option regarding environmental threats (TEM model):",
      "choices": [
        "Some environmental threats can be planned for and some will arise spontaneously, but they all have to be managed by flight crews in real time.",
        "Environmental threats are usually latent in nature.",
        "Environmental threats can be controlled (for example removed or, at least, minimised) at source by aviation organisations.",
        "Environmental threats refer to weather and terrain only."
      ],
      "answer": "Some environmental threats can be planned for and some will arise spontaneously, but they all have to be managed by flight crews in real time."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statements describes the act of decision making:",
      "choices": [
        "Actively and consciously choosing between 2 or more options.",
        "Following an instruction from ATC.",
        "Accepting advice from a more senior crew member.",
        "Following a course of action."
      ],
      "answer": "Actively and consciously choosing between 2 or more options."
    },
    {
      "question": "Considering the Threat and Error Management (TEM) model, which of the following situations is considered an error?",
      "choices": [
        "Take-off with less than the legally required amount of fuel on board due to an erroneous calculation by the dispatch crew.",
        "inadequate control inputs resulting in a hard landing and the collapse of the landing gear.",
        "A descent below the glide path in wind shear.",
        "A lateral offset from the cleared track as a result of a drifting IRS."
      ],
      "answer": "inadequate control inputs resulting in a hard landing and the collapse of the landing gear."
    },
    {
      "question": "Imitating and reproducing behaviours is an example of:",
      "choices": [
        "Classical conditioning.",
        "Modelling.",
        "Operant conditioning.",
        "Insight (cognitive learning)."
      ],
      "answer": "Modelling."
    },
    {
      "question": "Very high traffic density in the circuit, or windshear on the final approach, are examples of __________ threats.",
      "choices": [
        "unexpected",
        "latent",
        "environmental",
        "active"
      ],
      "answer": "environmental"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mnemonics are a useful way of improving __________ recall.",
      "choices": [
        "Working",
        "Sensory",
        "short-term",
        "long-term"
      ],
      "answer": "long-term"
    },
    {
      "question": "A group of pilots are currently undergoing the same type rating training at the same time. The stress associated with the course will:",
      "choices": [
        "Vary from pilot to pilot, depending on the amount of training completed.",
        "Be the same for each pilot, provided they are all given the same reading material to study.",
        "Vary from pilot to pilot, depending on each pilot's perception of the difficulty of the course.",
        "Be the same for each pilot, since they have all started the course at the same time."
      ],
      "answer": "Vary from pilot to pilot, depending on each pilot's perception of the difficulty of the course."
    },
    {
      "question": "Lack of textural cues can cause difficulty __________.",
      "choices": [
        "In cruise",
        "in the climb",
        "when levelling off",
        "in the flare when landing"
      ],
      "answer": "in the flare when landing"
    },
    {
      "question": "Published procedures designed to reduce ambiguity and unexpected or unanticipated actions are known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Call-outs.",
        "Crew briefings.",
        "Standard operating preparations.",
        "Standard operating procedures."
      ],
      "answer": "Standard operating procedures."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the option which is not a Procedural Error (TEM model):",
      "choices": [
        "Documentation: wrong weight and balance, fuel information, ATIS, or clearance information recorded, misinterpreted items on paperwork; incorrect logbook entries or incorrect application of MEL procedures.",
        "Callouts: omitted/incorrect callouts.",
        "Ground navigation: attempting to turn down wrong taxiway or runway, taxi too fast, failure to hold short or missed taxiway or runway.",
        "Checklists: wrong challenge and response; items missed, checklist performed late or at the wrong time."
      ],
      "answer": "Ground navigation: attempting to turn down wrong taxiway or runway, taxi too fast, failure to hold short or missed taxiway or runway."
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1972, a psychologist named Edwards presented a concept of the interface between flight crew and other parts of the airspace environment. What is this concept called and the names of those elements involved ?",
      "choices": [
        "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, environment, and liveware",
        "The SHELL Concept. Software, harmony, environment, and location",
        "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, environment and location",
        "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, economy and liveware"
      ],
      "answer": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, environment, and liveware"
    },
    {
      "question": "Stimuli which register attention are drawn into memory in sequence: __________ memory which has a large capacity and can hold information for very long periods.",
      "choices": [
        "Short term",
        "Working",
        "Long term",
        "Sensory store"
      ],
      "answer": "Long term"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct statement regarding decision making and biases:",
      "choices": [
        "Confirmation bias is a tendency to give undue weight to information supporting the current mental picture.",
        "Biases tend to differ among crew members and thus can help finding more probable solutions to a problem and improve the quality of the final decision if managed wisely.",
        "Attentional bias occurs when the entire crew simultaneously focuses on one particular aspect while at the same time ignoring other important details.",
        "Routine bias can help crews to find the most adequate solution quickly in conditions of high workload."
      ],
      "answer": "Confirmation bias is a tendency to give undue weight to information supporting the current mental picture."
    },
    {
      "question": "The \"Break Point\" is that point after which, if stress continues to rise:",
      "choices": [
        "performance peaks and remains at this level.",
        "performance is initially degraded and is then enhanced.",
        "performance is enhanced.",
        "performance is degraded."
      ],
      "answer": "performance is degraded."
    },
    {
      "question": "An __________ leader is a rigid thinker, often excessively obedient to \"superiors\" and excessively strict with \u2018inferiors\u2019 and unreceptive to their inputs.",
      "choices": [
        "Democratic",
        "paternalistic",
        "authoritarian",
        "interactive"
      ],
      "answer": "authoritarian"
    },
    {
      "question": "A component of the SHELL model is: __________. Aircraft systems.",
      "choices": [
        "Environment",
        "Software",
        "Hardware",
        "Liveware"
      ],
      "answer": "Hardware"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is synergy in a crew?",
      "choices": [
        "The coordinated action of unrelated individual performances in achieving a non-standard task",
        "The coordinated action of all members towards a common objective, in which collective performance is proving to be more than the sum of the individual performances",
        "The uncoordinated action of the crewmembers towards a common objective",
        "A behavioural expedient associated with the desynchronisation of the coordinated actions"
      ],
      "answer": "The coordinated action of all members towards a common objective, in which collective performance is proving to be more than the sum of the individual performances"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ culture is seen by all to appropriately punish deliberate transgression. This is distinct from a non-punitive culture where deliberate transgressions go unpunished.",
      "choices": [
        "open",
        "punitive",
        "learning",
        "just"
      ],
      "answer": "just"
    },
    {
      "question": "The role of a \"learning culture\" within a good safety culture is that:",
      "choices": [
        "Safety relevant information is given to all employees concerned.",
        "Dangerous violations must have appropriate consequences for the violator.",
        "Human errors must be documented and discussed on an anonymous basis.",
        "Processes and procedures must be adjusted to detect threats and errors."
      ],
      "answer": "Processes and procedures must be adjusted to detect threats and errors."
    },
    {
      "question": "The right amount of arousal optimises your ability to respond to events.",
      "choices": [
        "What the fuck",
        "MAYBE",
        "False",
        "True"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "Very low workload situations can lead to less than optimal performance.",
      "choices": [
        "What the fuck",
        "MAYBE",
        "False",
        "True"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "Error __________ describes a design philosophy in which the design of a system or process reduces the seriousness of the consequences of an error.",
      "choices": [
        "limitation",
        "bias",
        "tolerance",
        "violation"
      ],
      "answer": "tolerance"
    },
    {
      "question": "One possible countermeasure to the ironies of automation is regular __________.",
      "choices": [
        "overload exercises",
        "Checks",
        "training flights",
        "examination flights"
      ],
      "answer": "training flights"
    },
    {
      "question": "Valid stress coping strategies include: Palliative coping, in which you reduce the symptoms using, for example, relaxation techniques. This is a ___________ solution.",
      "choices": [
        "Temporary",
        "Permanent",
        "long-term",
        "short-term"
      ],
      "answer": "short-term"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is an environmental threat according to the TEM (Threat and Error Management) model?",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft hardware design.",
        "A maintenance error.",
        "A contaminated runway.",
        "A crew-scheduling error."
      ],
      "answer": "A contaminated runway."
    },
    {
      "question": "A sense of satisfaction resulting from, or causing, a general lack of critical analysis of the circumstances, is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Concentration.",
        "Monitoring",
        "Complacency.",
        "Hypovigilance."
      ],
      "answer": "Complacency."
    },
    {
      "question": "The combination of interactions between, vision, equilibrium, proprioception and hearing provide pilots with:",
      "choices": [
        "An illusion",
        "Spatial orientation.",
        "Size constancy.",
        "Perception."
      ],
      "answer": "Spatial orientation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Flickering light from strobes, or sunlight through rotors or propellers, can induce __________ and vertigo.",
      "choices": [
        "A headache",
        "an illusion",
        "vomiting",
        "dizziness"
      ],
      "answer": "dizziness"
    },
    {
      "question": "An inability to visually detect other aircraft in daylight, at high altitude and in clear skies, is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "The black hole effect.",
        "The leans.",
        "Empty field myopia.",
        "Coriolis."
      ],
      "answer": "Empty field myopia."
    },
    {
      "question": "Performance ___________ rapidly beyond the break point.",
      "choices": [
        "stagnates",
        "deteriorates",
        "is constant",
        "improves"
      ],
      "answer": "deteriorates"
    },
    {
      "question": "Safety culture is:",
      "choices": [
        "NOT a sub-set of national culture.",
        "considered to be a sub-set of national culture.",
        "considered to be independent of national culture.",
        "NOT a product of national culture."
      ],
      "answer": "considered to be a sub-set of national culture."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does Murphy's Law state?",
      "choices": [
        "An opportunity to engage in more probable behaviours (or activities) will reinforce less probable behaviours (or activities).",
        "Safety measures are offset by increased risk taking.",
        "Anything that can go wrong, will go wrong.",
        "In order to understand what someone is telling you, it is necessary for you to assume the person is being truthful, then imagine what could be true about it."
      ],
      "answer": "Anything that can go wrong, will go wrong."
    },
    {
      "question": "The operator of an aircraft takes disciplinary action against the captain of a flight, claiming that he/she violated established operating procedures by landing with insufficient fuel on board. The captain can plausibly demonstrate that he/she has only made a mistake when documenting the fuel mass in the technical logbook after the flight, while the actual fuel on board after landing was well within the operational limits. The operator decides to suspend the pilot from work for 10 days. Which of the following statements is correct with regard to the operator's safety culture?",
      "choices": [
        "In a \"just culture\" environment, the punishment of an employee for making an error is an example of bad management; errors and violations should not be punished in order to promote an atmosphere of trust.",
        "The operator demonstrates an adequate concern towards safety and considers negligent behaviour as unacceptable. Negligence displays a lack of awareness of risks and hazards, probably reducing the safety margin in flight.",
        "The operator efficiently applies the principle of \"just culture\", fairly punishing negligent behaviour as a form of positive control. This can motivate employees to be more careful before taking action and promote risk awareness.",
        "The operator does not apply the principle of \"just culture\" to foster trust and collaboration. Such an unintended slip should be reported and discussed to prevent their future re-occurrence, it should not be punished."
      ],
      "answer": "The operator does not apply the principle of \"just culture\" to foster trust and collaboration. Such an unintended slip should be reported and discussed to prevent their future re-occurrence, it should not be punished."
    },
    {
      "question": "During training the instructor suddenly cuts power to simulate an engine failure. Initially the student freezes, but then responds quickly and executes a perfect landing. Later, when discussing the event, the student feels tired but excited by the situation. What does he exhibit?",
      "choices": [
        "Exhaustion phase, associated with elimination of toxins produced by the stress, like adrenaline and cortisol.",
        "Fight-or-flight response, associated with adrenaline secretion for a rapid response to a stressor.",
        "Alarm phase, which is associated with coping with sustained stress.",
        "Resistance phase, which is associated with instantaneous arousal and reaction."
      ],
      "answer": "Fight-or-flight response, associated with adrenaline secretion for a rapid response to a stressor."
    },
    {
      "question": "As stress increases, the individual eventually reaches the ___________ point where he becomes overloaded.",
      "choices": [
        "tipping",
        "Maximum",
        "break",
        "pivot"
      ],
      "answer": "break"
    },
    {
      "question": "An up-sloping runway can give the illusion that you are __________ on the approach.",
      "choices": [
        "Slow",
        "Fast",
        "high",
        "low"
      ],
      "answer": "high"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ergonomics are associated with:",
      "choices": [
        "cognition",
        "the human/workplace interface",
        "communications",
        "information processing"
      ],
      "answer": "the human/workplace interface"
    },
    {
      "question": "The advantage of mental models is that they __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "let you develop situation awareness with few or no external cues",
        "help you to defend against illusions",
        "enable the brain to deal quickly with very large amounts of information",
        "are a way of selecting what is relevant from what is irrelevant"
      ],
      "answer": "enable the brain to deal quickly with very large amounts of information"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are two types of attention ?",
      "choices": [
        "Selective and divided",
        "Intuitive and behavioural",
        "Divided and behavioural",
        "Cognitive and intuitive"
      ],
      "answer": "Selective and divided"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sensed information is used to slowly construct a useful perception of the world. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Bottom up processing.",
        "Size constancy.",
        "Top down processing.",
        "Perception."
      ],
      "answer": "Bottom up processing."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a company, a safety culture is established where a person is not legally prosecuted when committing an error without intent, but where intentional violation or negligent behaviour are not tolerated. This safety culture is called:",
      "choices": [
        "Just culture",
        "Non-punitive culture",
        "Open culture",
        "Flexible culture"
      ],
      "answer": "Just culture"
    },
    {
      "question": "The recognition schema is based on __________ and the outcome.",
      "choices": [
        "predicted result",
        "actions",
        "sensory actions",
        "initial conditions"
      ],
      "answer": "sensory actions"
    },
    {
      "question": "In terms of decision-making, the intention to become integrated into the team, to be recognised as the leader or to avoid conflicts may lead to:",
      "choices": [
        "the improvement of internal risk assessment capabilities.",
        "a fast and decisive option.",
        "the attempt to agree on decisions made by other crew members.",
        "an authoritarian approach thus demonstrating ones own ability to lead."
      ],
      "answer": "the attempt to agree on decisions made by other crew members."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Rasmussen\u2019s SRK model: The __________ mode involves smooth execution of highly practiced physical actions in which there is virtually no __________ monitoring.",
      "choices": [
        "Skill; conscious",
        "Skill; unconscious",
        "Rule; unconscious",
        "Rule; conscious"
      ],
      "answer": "Skill; conscious"
    },
    {
      "question": "A human error associated with automation includes: __________ monitoring: the error of looking at but not really taking-in information.",
      "choices": [
        "Blinkered",
        "Mode",
        "Passive",
        "Situational"
      ],
      "answer": "Passive"
    },
    {
      "question": "The intention was correct but there was a failure of execution is an example of an __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Commission",
        "action slip",
        "environmental capture",
        "omission"
      ],
      "answer": "action slip"
    },
    {
      "question": "Stimuli which register attention are drawn into memory in sequence: Sensory store, one for each sense, which holds unprocessed information for __________ periods.",
      "choices": [
        "indefinite",
        "Extended",
        "short",
        "long"
      ],
      "answer": "short"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following list of stressors, which are psychological? 1 - noise 2 - loss of spouse or partner 3 - heat 4 - loss of job 5 - vibrations 6 - credit card debt",
      "choices": [
        "1, 3, and 5 only.",
        "2, 4, and 6 only.",
        "3, 5, and 6 only",
        "2, 4, and 5 only"
      ],
      "answer": "2, 4, and 6 only."
    },
    {
      "question": "A false sensation of increasing or decreasing aircraft bank or attitude (caused by gentle or unintentional control inputs in IMC) is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Coriolis.",
        "The leans.",
        "The somatogravic illusion.",
        "The somatogyral illusion."
      ],
      "answer": "The leans."
    },
    {
      "question": "1 of the 3 stages of the general adaption syndrome is: Stage 2: ___________ in which corticosteroids are released, blood flow increases and body fat becomes available for conversion to sugar.",
      "choices": [
        "Alarm",
        "Flight",
        "Resistance",
        "Exhaustion"
      ],
      "answer": "Resistance"
    },
    {
      "question": "The best countermeasure against approach path deviations is to use the __________ in VMC and the ILS indications in IMC.",
      "choices": [
        "Runway Width",
        "Runway slope",
        "runway texture",
        "PAPIs or VASIs"
      ],
      "answer": "PAPIs or VASIs"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a crew operating an aircraft, a culture of organisational indiscipline, a general lack of oversight or supervision by the organisation, and commercial pressure are all examples of organisational __________.",
      "choices": [
        "actions",
        "errors",
        "process",
        "threats"
      ],
      "answer": "threats"
    },
    {
      "question": "A store of accumulated knowledge and language, which is highly structured and organised is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Semantic memory.",
        "Episodic memory.",
        "Amnesia.",
        "Modelling."
      ],
      "answer": "Semantic memory."
    },
    {
      "question": "An internal conflict, in which you doubt and question your own ability and performance, is an example of:",
      "choices": [
        "Explicit communication.",
        "Interpersonal conflict.",
        "Implicit communication.",
        "Intrapersonal conflict."
      ],
      "answer": "Intrapersonal conflict."
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot becomes skilled when he/she: 1. trains or practises regularly 2. knows how to manage himself /herself 3. possesses all the knowledge associated with the aircraft 4. knows how to keep resources in reserve for coping with the unexpected.",
      "choices": [
        "2, 3, and 4",
        "1 and 2 only",
        "1, 2, and 4",
        "1, 3, and 4"
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, and 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "An SOP which contains a procedural mistake is an example of:",
      "choices": [
        "A memory error.",
        "An active error.",
        "A latent error.",
        "An internal error."
      ],
      "answer": "A latent error."
    },
    {
      "question": "Failure to maintain level flight when manually flying a turn is a type of:",
      "choices": [
        "Communication error.",
        "Procedural error.",
        "Aircraft handling error.",
        "Latent threat."
      ],
      "answer": "Aircraft handling error."
    },
    {
      "question": "The part that the organisation expects the individual to play within a group, which serves to provide clarity about what is expected from each group member is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Group norms.",
        "Roles.",
        "Groupthink.",
        "Status."
      ],
      "answer": "Roles."
    },
    {
      "question": "A commercial organisation invests heavily in new technology solely to reduce a hazard that has a safety risk index of \"acceptable\". According to ICAO Doc 9859, what is the probable outcome?",
      "choices": [
        "The organisation will significantly increase its safety level, attracting more customers, and could increase profits.",
        "The cost can reduce profits with minimal safety improvements, and could lead to bankruptcy.",
        "The \"safety space\" of the organisation will be significantly improved.",
        "The risk index for this individual hazard will rise."
      ],
      "answer": "The cost can reduce profits with minimal safety improvements, and could lead to bankruptcy."
    },
    {
      "question": "The errors resulting from an illogical indexing system in an operations manual are related, according to the SHELL mode 1, to a conflict between:",
      "choices": [
        "Liveware - Environment.",
        "Liveware - Hardware.",
        "Liveware - Liveware.",
        "Liveware - Software."
      ],
      "answer": "Liveware - Software."
    },
    {
      "question": "While flying VFR \"wings level\" on top of clouds at 10000 feet, your artificial horizon indicates a 20 degree bank.",
      "choices": [
        "No attitude correction is needed since you know that your vision is more reliable than the instrument with regards to spatial orientation.",
        "You trust the instrument and level off according to the instrument read-out.",
        "You take the proper action by \"leaning\" toward the lower end of the artificial horizon, thus compensating for the perceptional illusion.",
        "You pull the circuit breaker to the artificial horizon knowing that perceptional illusions called \"leans\" might severely impair your control of the aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "You trust the instrument and level off according to the instrument read-out."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the cockpit there is the captain, first officer and a student pilot who has been invited to the observer seat. Prior to take-off, the first officer completes checkpoints in the checklist, which the captain accepts with ease. What are the behaviours in this situation?",
      "choices": [
        "Captain - cognitive, first officer - associative, student pilot - autonomous.",
        "Captain - autonomous, first officer - associative, student pilot - cognitive.",
        "Captain - autonomous, first officer - cognitive, student pilot - associative.",
        "Captain - associative, first officer - autonomous, student pilot - cognitive."
      ],
      "answer": "Captain - autonomous, first officer - associative, student pilot - cognitive."
    },
    {
      "question": "High altitude hazards include: High intensity __________ light, which can eventually cause cataracts.",
      "choices": [
        "X-Ray",
        "Visible Light",
        "UV",
        "infra-red"
      ],
      "answer": "UV"
    },
    {
      "question": "When travelling to tropical and developing countries, what are the two diseases that can lead to incapacitation and death within a short time period when exposed?",
      "choices": [
        "TB and dengue.",
        "AIDS and gonorrhoea.",
        "Heat stroke and a chlamydia.",
        "Cholera and dysentery."
      ],
      "answer": "Cholera and dysentery."
    },
    {
      "question": "Incapacitation is most dangerous when its onset is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Not serious",
        "painful",
        "insidious",
        "sudden"
      ],
      "answer": "insidious"
    },
    {
      "question": "More than __________ mg per day of caffeine produces over-stimulation of the central nervous system and degrades performance.",
      "choices": [
        "600",
        "400",
        "250",
        "150"
      ],
      "answer": "250"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ binds readily to red blood cells, preventing oxygen from being absorbed and transported to tissues and organs.",
      "choices": [
        "Oxygen",
        "Nitrogen",
        "Carbon monoxide",
        "Carbon dioxide"
      ],
      "answer": "Carbon monoxide"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following materials in aviation may cause health problems, when uncontained? 1. Fuel 2. Oxygen 3. Engine oil 4. Hydraulic fluid",
      "choices": [
        "2 and 3.",
        "1, 3 and 4.",
        "1 and 4.",
        "2, 3 and 4."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3 and 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "High altitude hazards include: A greater concentration of __________ gas.",
      "choices": [
        "Oxygen",
        "Nitrogen",
        "carbon dioxide",
        "ozone"
      ],
      "answer": "ozone"
    },
    {
      "question": "The cause of decompression sickness is __________ gas dissolved in the blood coming out of solution in conditions of low ambient pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "carbon monoxide",
        "carbon dioxide",
        "oxygen",
        "nitrogen"
      ],
      "answer": "nitrogen"
    },
    {
      "question": "Trapped gas in the stomach or bowel causes intense abdominal pain. This is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Aerodontalgia.",
        "Otic barotrauma.",
        "Gastrointestinal barotrauma.",
        "Sinus barotrauma."
      ],
      "answer": "Gastrointestinal barotrauma."
    },
    {
      "question": "Blocked sinuses cause pressure build-up in the sinus passages. This causes intense pain in the face and forehead and possible nose bleeds. This is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Sinus barotrauma.",
        "Gastrointestinal barotrauma.",
        "Otic barotrauma.",
        "Aerodontalgia."
      ],
      "answer": "Sinus barotrauma."
    },
    {
      "question": "You must seek medical advice from an aeromedical examiner (AME) or aeromedical centre (AeMC) if you: Are admitted to a hospital or clinic for more than __________ hours.",
      "choices": [
        "24",
        "6",
        "8",
        "12"
      ],
      "answer": "12"
    },
    {
      "question": "If noxious fumes are detected, make __________ descent.",
      "choices": [
        "A controlled",
        "an emergency",
        "a normal",
        "a glide"
      ],
      "answer": "an emergency"
    },
    {
      "question": "A blocked eustachian tube, which causes a difference between the middle ear and ambient pressure, can result in:",
      "choices": [
        "Aerodontalgia.",
        "Gastrointestinal barotrauma.",
        "Sinus barotrauma.",
        "Otic barotrauma."
      ],
      "answer": "Otic barotrauma."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ __________ __________ system is a data-driven means of continuously monitoring and managing fatigue-related safety risks. It is based upon scientific principles and operational experience that aims to ensure personnel are performing at adequate levels of alertness.",
      "choices": [
        "Flight time limitation",
        "Alertness Management System",
        "fatigue risk management",
        "flight safety data"
      ],
      "answer": "fatigue risk management"
    },
    {
      "question": "The symptoms of decompression sickness are:",
      "choices": [
        "The creeps and the leans.",
        "The bends, the leans and the chokes.",
        "The leans.",
        "The bends, the chokes and the creeps."
      ],
      "answer": "The bends, the chokes and the creeps."
    },
    {
      "question": "In tropical countries possible sources of incapacitation include: __________ worms.",
      "choices": [
        "Intestinal",
        "Waterborne",
        "Parasitic",
        "Topical"
      ],
      "answer": "Parasitic"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum EASA blood/alcohol limit for flight and cabin crew is:",
      "choices": [
        "20 milligrams per 100 millilitres of blood.",
        "10 milligrams per 100 millilitres of blood.",
        "40 milligrams per 100 millilitres of blood.",
        "0 milligrams per 100 millilitres of blood."
      ],
      "answer": "20 milligrams per 100 millilitres of blood."
    },
    {
      "question": "The most common cause of in-flight incapacitation is.",
      "choices": [
        "Aerodontalgia.",
        "Otic barotrauma.",
        "Sinus barotrauma.",
        "Gastrointestinal upsets."
      ],
      "answer": "Gastrointestinal upsets."
    },
    {
      "question": "You must seek medical advice from an aeromedical examiner (AME) or aeromedical centre (AeMC) if you: __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Get a headache",
        "Use E-Cigarettes",
        "undergo a surgical operation or invasive procedure",
        "take a medication"
      ],
      "answer": "undergo a surgical operation or invasive procedure"
    },
    {
      "question": "Because of the design of the air conditioning system, noxious fumes or smoke can spread rapidly from their source throughout the cabin. They can quickly degrade your performance and lead to incapacitation. You immediate actions are to: Don oxygen masks and select __________ as soon as you suspect the presence of fumes.",
      "choices": [
        "Pressurised.",
        "Emergency.",
        "Normal.",
        "100 percent."
      ],
      "answer": "100 percent."
    },
    {
      "question": "Positive g can cause a progressive loss of __________, a sense of fatigue and drowsiness and difficulty breathing. Very high g can cause __________.",
      "choices": [
        "vision; syncope",
        "hearing; loss of consciousness",
        "hearing; syncope",
        "vision; loss of consciousness"
      ],
      "answer": "vision; loss of consciousness"
    },
    {
      "question": "In aviation, the term used to describe temporary mental tiredness is:",
      "choices": [
        "Short-term exhaustion.",
        "Fatigue.",
        "Incapacitation.",
        "Chronic fatigue."
      ],
      "answer": "Fatigue."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary cause of stomach upsets in most of the developing world is __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "Viruses",
        "Parasites",
        "exposure to heat and sun",
        "bacterially contaminated water and food"
      ],
      "answer": "bacterially contaminated water and food"
    },
    {
      "question": "Major causes of incapacitation in flight could be:",
      "choices": [
        "gastrointestinal upset, stress, hypoxia and fatigue.",
        "decompression sickness, high cabin temperature and fever.",
        "drunkenness, fatigue, poor diet and headache.",
        "smoking, acute medical condition, lack of sleep and stress."
      ],
      "answer": "gastrointestinal upset, stress, hypoxia and fatigue."
    },
    {
      "question": "During flight, a pilot may get sensory illusions about the pitch and bank angle. This is caused by the misinterpretation of signals from the vestibular apparatus. Which of the following is an element of the vestibular apparatus?",
      "choices": [
        "The cochlea in the inner ear.",
        "The anterior semi-circular canal.",
        "The eardrum in the ear canal.",
        "The ossicles."
      ],
      "answer": "The anterior semi-circular canal."
    },
    {
      "question": "Trapped gas under dental fillings causes intense toothache. This is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Gastrointestinal barotrauma.",
        "Aerodontalgia.",
        "Sinus barotrauma.",
        "Otic barotrauma."
      ],
      "answer": "Aerodontalgia."
    },
    {
      "question": "The in-flight environment may __________ the severity of symptoms which seem minor while on the ground.",
      "choices": [
        "Make dissapear",
        "Maintain",
        "reduce",
        "increase"
      ],
      "answer": "increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "Major infectious diseases associated with developing and/or tropical areas include:",
      "choices": [
        "Malaria, yellow fever, tuberculosis, diabetes, rabies.",
        "Malaria, yellow fever, coronary disease, polio, rabies.",
        "Malaria, yellow fever, tuberculosis, polio, rabies.",
        "Malaria, parasitic worms, tuberculosis, polio, rabies."
      ],
      "answer": "Malaria, yellow fever, tuberculosis, polio, rabies."
    },
    {
      "question": "If you feel so unwell that you require medication, then you should consider yourself unfit to fly.",
      "choices": [
        "Never",
        "Sometimes",
        "False",
        "True"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ significantly increases the risk of decompression sickness because __________ forces more nitrogen into the blood stream.",
      "choices": [
        "Snorkelling; lower breathing rate",
        "Snorkelling; higher breathing pressure",
        "Scuba diving; higher breathing pressure",
        "Scuba diving; lower breathing rate"
      ],
      "answer": "Scuba diving; higher breathing pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "The EASA legal limit for alcohol is __________ mg per 100 ml.",
      "choices": [
        "80",
        "375",
        "20",
        "0"
      ],
      "answer": "20"
    },
    {
      "question": "Stimuli must be of a certain strength for the receptors to pick them up. This is called:",
      "choices": [
        "Sensory strength",
        "Sensory threshold",
        "Sensory volume",
        "Sensory filter"
      ],
      "answer": "Sensory threshold"
    },
    {
      "question": "The incomplete combustion of fuel produces:",
      "choices": [
        "Carbon monoxide.",
        "Oxygen.",
        "Nitrogen.",
        "Carbon dioxide."
      ],
      "answer": "Carbon monoxide."
    },
    {
      "question": "What may the impacts of excessive exposure to radiation (such as solar radiation) be?",
      "choices": [
        "It increases the temperature in the flight crew compartment, causing an increase in stress levels, and resulting in decreased performance.",
        "It increases radiation absorption by the skin, stimulating the release of melatonin and darken your skin colour permanently.",
        "It may have a detrimental effect on your central nervous system, damage your internal organs, and cause skin cancer.",
        "It may disrupt your circadian rhythm, thus disrupting your sleep pattern, leading to excessive fatigue during the flight."
      ],
      "answer": "It may have a detrimental effect on your central nervous system, damage your internal organs, and cause skin cancer."
    },
    {
      "question": "Decompression sickness can be avoided by ensuring that the cabin altitude never exceeds __________ ft or that you avoid prolonged flight where the cabin altitude exceeds 18 000 ft.",
      "choices": [
        "18000",
        "24 500",
        "8000",
        "14 000"
      ],
      "answer": "14 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "The body eliminates alcohol at the rate of about __________ unit(s) per hour.",
      "choices": [
        "1.5",
        "1",
        "2",
        "0.5"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the four sleep-related processes that affect the level of performance?",
      "choices": [
        "Sleep lnertia, Sleep Latency, Sleep Regulation, and Sleep Apnoea.",
        "Sleep Regulation, Elevated Sleep Drive, Desynchronisation, and Sleep lnertia.",
        "Sleep Regulation, Sleep Apnoea, Diurnal Synchronisation, and Sleep Drive.",
        "Circadian Rhythm, Homeostatic Sleep Drive, insomnia, and Sleepiness."
      ],
      "answer": "Sleep Regulation, Elevated Sleep Drive, Desynchronisation, and Sleep lnertia."
    },
    {
      "question": "The most important issue with an incapacitated pilot is to recognise the situation quickly and ensure that __________.",
      "choices": [
        "The other crewmembers are aware",
        "no part of his/her body is interfering with the controls",
        "the victim is immediately laid flat",
        "ATC is made aware of the problem"
      ],
      "answer": "no part of his/her body is interfering with the controls"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the major symptoms of gastrointestinal upsets causing incapacitation in flight?",
      "choices": [
        "Heartburn and acid regurgitation",
        "Vomiting, nausea, pain in the stomach.",
        "Constipation and ileus.",
        "Diarrhoea, dizziness, fatigue"
      ],
      "answer": "Vomiting, nausea, pain in the stomach."
    },
    {
      "question": "One unit of alcohol is equivalent to __________ ml of pure alcohol.",
      "choices": [
        "25",
        "10",
        "15",
        "20"
      ],
      "answer": "10"
    },
    {
      "question": "You must seek medical advice from an aeromedical examiner (AME) or aeromedical centre (AeMC) if you: Regularly use __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Painkillers",
        "medication",
        "e-cigarettes",
        "alcohol"
      ],
      "answer": "medication"
    },
    {
      "question": "Low relative humidity causes: thirst, dry eyes; dry skin and dry mucus membranes. As a countermeasure, drink plenty of __________ and use eye drops and aqueous cream.",
      "choices": [
        "water",
        "coffee",
        "electrolytes",
        "alcohol"
      ],
      "answer": "water"
    },
    {
      "question": "If noxious fumes are detected, when safe to do so consider depressurising and opening the direct vision window. Land______ ______ .",
      "choices": [
        "When possible",
        "as soon as convenient",
        "as soon as practicable",
        "as soon as possible"
      ],
      "answer": "as soon as possible"
    },
    {
      "question": "You must seek medical advice from an aeromedical examiner (AME) or aeromedical centre (AeMC) if you:  Are admitted to a hospital or clinic for more than __________ hours.",
      "choices": [
        "24",
        "12",
        "6",
        "8"
      ],
      "answer": "12"
    },
    {
      "question": "The slightly hypoxic conditions of flight __________ the effects of medications",
      "choices": [
        "have no effect on",
        "don't change",
        "increase",
        "decrease"
      ],
      "answer": "increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "Eat meals at regular times to avoid __________.",
      "choices": [
        "overhydration",
        "dehydration",
        "hypoglycaemia",
        "hyperglycaemia"
      ],
      "answer": "hypoglycaemia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Angular acceleration during a pitch-up manoeuvre __________ blood circulation to the brain and __________ blood volume in the lower legs.",
      "choices": [
        "reduces; increases",
        "increases; reduces",
        "increases; increases",
        "reduces; reduces"
      ],
      "answer": "reduces; increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a night flight a pilot returns from the cabin and takes their seat in the flight deck, allowing their eyes to adapt to the dark. Which term is relevant to describe the change in the rods and the cones?",
      "choices": [
        "Binocular cue",
        "Sensitivity",
        "Peripheral vision",
        "Grey-out"
      ],
      "answer": "Sensitivity"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ accelerations are experienced when an aircraft increases or decreases its air speed.",
      "choices": [
        "Transverse",
        "Radial",
        "Linear",
        "Angular"
      ],
      "answer": "Linear"
    },
    {
      "question": "If you suspect such poisoning: immediately close __________ air vents; turn __________ the cabin heating; open cabin windows and land asap.",
      "choices": [
        "hot; off",
        "cold; on",
        "cold; off",
        "hot; on"
      ],
      "answer": "hot; off"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mild decompression symptoms disappear when you __________.",
      "choices": [
        "increase speed",
        "stay at the same altitude",
        "ascend",
        "descend"
      ],
      "answer": "descend"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct? 1. A state of hyperventilation can occur in response to psychological stress. 2. Physiological stress, e.g. through intense exercise, can cause hyperventilation.",
      "choices": [
        "1 is correct, 2 is incorrect.",
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct.",
        "Both 1 and 2 are correct.",
        "Both 1 and 2 are incorrect."
      ],
      "answer": "Both 1 and 2 are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "The pressure in the middle ear is equalised with ambient pressure by the:",
      "choices": [
        "Tympanic membrane.",
        "Ossicles.",
        "Eustachian tube.",
        "Semi-circular canals."
      ],
      "answer": "Eustachian tube."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary sources of health risks in tropical climates are insects and __________.",
      "choices": [
        "food",
        "animals",
        "airborne",
        "waterborne"
      ],
      "answer": "waterborne"
    },
    {
      "question": "Analysis of accidents involving the human factor in aviation shows that:",
      "choices": [
        "only front-line operators are involved.",
        "failure of the human factor is always connected with technical breakdowns.",
        "only pilot training will make it possible to improve the situation.",
        "there is hardly ever a single cause responsible."
      ],
      "answer": "there is hardly ever a single cause responsible."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do not fly within __________ hrs of shallow diving using compressed air or __________ hrs if diving deeper than 30 ft using compressed air.",
      "choices": [
        "12; 48",
        "12; 24",
        "6; 24",
        "8; 12"
      ],
      "answer": "12; 24"
    },
    {
      "question": "The relative humidity in a pressurised jet aircraft is usually much __________ than ambient.",
      "choices": [
        "stronger",
        "lower",
        "the same",
        "higher"
      ],
      "answer": "lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "During flight, carbon monoxide poisoning is a threat that may be the result of:",
      "choices": [
        "Exhaust gases from other aircraft ahead entering the cabin.",
        "Unfettered recirculated bleed air entering the cabin.",
        "Ineffective filtering by the air conditioning system of turbine engine bleed air.",
        "A defective cabin heating system allowing exhaust gases to enter the cabin."
      ],
      "answer": "A defective cabin heating system allowing exhaust gases to enter the cabin."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum units of alcohol that can be consumed per day, without causing damage to organs, is __________ units for men and __________ units for women.",
      "choices": [
        "4-5; 3-4",
        "2-3; 3-4",
        "3-4; 2-3",
        "3-4; 1-2"
      ],
      "answer": "3-4; 2-3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Physical exercise in high temperatures or tropical climates may:",
      "choices": [
        "cause painful muscle and abdominal cramps.",
        "increase a pilot's resistance to decompression sickness.",
        "cause the pilot to collapse, due to an excess of fluid in the body.",
        "cause dysentery."
      ],
      "answer": "cause painful muscle and abdominal cramps."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following types of radiation can be blocked by a sheet of paper?",
      "choices": [
        "Gamma radiation",
        "X rays",
        "Alpha radiation",
        "Beta radiation"
      ],
      "answer": "Alpha radiation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of the photosensitive cells is not impaired by:",
      "choices": [
        "High speed.",
        "Oxygen deficiency.",
        "Positive acceleration.",
        "Toxic influence (alcohol, medication)."
      ],
      "answer": "High speed."
    },
    {
      "question": "Relative humidity in the atmosphere is mostly associated with __________ ambient temperature.",
      "choices": [
        "fluctuating",
        "constant",
        "low",
        "high"
      ],
      "answer": "high"
    },
    {
      "question": "What can pilots do to reduce the probability of suffering from noise-induced hearing loss?",
      "choices": [
        "Use hearing protection equipment, like earplugs, or active noise-reduction headsets.",
        "Avoid any kind of artificial blockage of the ear canal, including unusual earwax build-up.",
        "Use the Valsalva manoeuvre when experiencing a ringing or buzzing of the ears due to noise.",
        "Limit the duration of exposure to high-frequency noise (above 20 kHz) to less than 5 hours."
      ],
      "answer": "Use hearing protection equipment, like earplugs, or active noise-reduction headsets."
    },
    {
      "question": "High altitude hazards include: __________ which can damage DNA.",
      "choices": [
        "X-Rays",
        "UV-Radiation",
        "Cosmic radiation",
        "Solar winds"
      ],
      "answer": "Cosmic radiation"
    },
    {
      "question": "If you have not used a particular drug before __________.",
      "choices": [
        "do not self-medicate before flight",
        "use only half the recommended dose",
        "it will not effect you",
        "increase the time interval between doses"
      ],
      "answer": "do not self-medicate before flight"
    },
    {
      "question": "Diabetes __________ a licence disqualifier.",
      "choices": [
        "is never",
        "may be",
        "is",
        "is not"
      ],
      "answer": "is"
    },
    {
      "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness",
      "choices": [
        "are only relevant when diving",
        "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT",
        "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms",
        "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear"
      ],
      "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ accelerations (g) are experienced when the aircraft is pitching nose-up or nose-down.",
      "choices": [
        "Transverse",
        "Radial",
        "Linear",
        "Angular"
      ],
      "answer": "Angular"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot who is trying to pick up a fallen abject from the cockpit floor during a tight turn may experience :",
      "choices": [
        "barotrauma.",
        "pressure vertigo.",
        "an autokinetic illusion.",
        "a Coriolis illusion."
      ],
      "answer": "a Coriolis illusion."
    },
    {
      "question": "Antihistamine medicines may cause __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Increased alertness",
        "depression",
        "drowsiness",
        "euphoria"
      ],
      "answer": "drowsiness"
    },
    {
      "question": "Injury caused by air pressure is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Barotrauma.",
        "The bends.",
        "The leans.",
        "The creeps."
      ],
      "answer": "Barotrauma."
    },
    {
      "question": "You are flying above a fog layer. What's the danger in spotting traffic?",
      "choices": [
        "An aircraft can come through the layer of fog in front of you.",
        "You look at the fog instead of in front of you.",
        "Your eyes focus some meters in front of you. The pilot is looking without seeing, which is dangerous.",
        "There is no danger associated with it."
      ],
      "answer": "Your eyes focus some meters in front of you. The pilot is looking without seeing, which is dangerous."
    },
    {
      "question": "Otic barotrauma can be worse in the __________ because relatively __________ pressure at the entrance to the eustachian tube causes it to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "ascent; high; close",
        "descent; low; open",
        "descent; high; close",
        "descent; high; open"
      ],
      "answer": "descent; high; close"
    }
  ],
  "GNAV": [
    {
      "question": "From a navigational perspective, \u2018visibility\u2019 is defined as:",
      "choices": [
        "The minimum required visual acuity permitted to undertaken visual navigation flight.",
        "The ability to be able to see through the air.",
        "The distance, measured in metres up to 5000 m and kilometres thereafter, at which it is possible to see an object.",
        "The clarity of the lower atmosphere, in which commercial air transportation takes place."
      ],
      "answer": "The ability to be able to see through the air."
    },
    {
      "question": "The change of latitude between N72\u00b000\u2032 E035\u00b000\u2032 and N54\u00b000\u2032 E035\u00b000\u2032 is ________",
      "choices": [
        "16\u00b000\u2032",
        "18\u00b000\u2032",
        "20\u00b000\u2032",
        "17\u00b060\u2032"
      ],
      "answer": "18\u00b000\u2032"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying a magnetic heading of 170\u00b0M at a TAS of 220 kt. The forecast W/V is 210\u00b0/30. Magnetic variation = 10\u00b0E.\nWhat is the true track and the groundspeed?",
      "choices": [
        "176\u00b0T - 195 kt",
        "183\u00b0T - 247 kt",
        "184\u00b0T - 185 kt",
        "176\u00b0T - 246 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "176\u00b0T - 195 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What will be the revised ETA (to the nearest minute) overhead turning point B in the following situation? Assume that all other conditions remain unchanged.\nPlanned ETA over turning point B: 14:14.\nPlanned distance from turning A to turning point B: 43 NM.\nPlanned distance from turning A to check feature X: 10 NM.\nActual time overhead check feature X: 1 minute 15 seconds late",
      "choices": [
        "14:19",
        "14:26",
        "14:18",
        "14:15"
      ],
      "answer": "14:19"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given magnetic variation = 22\u00b0E, what is the wind angle for an aircraft flying a heading of 168\u00b0M when W/V = 240\u00b0T/60 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "46\u00b0 Right.",
        "50\u00b0 Right.",
        "50\u00b0 Left.",
        "39\u00b0 Right."
      ],
      "answer": "50\u00b0 Right."
    },
    {
      "question": "Using mental dead reckoning techniques, what is the speed factor for an aircraft maintaining a TAS of 150 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "2.5",
        "2.3",
        "2",
        "2.7"
      ],
      "answer": "2.5"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the horizontal length of 1 nm in feet, based on an approximation (rule of thumb)?",
      "choices": [
        "5000",
        "6080",
        "6000",
        "5500"
      ],
      "answer": "6000"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft commences to descent from a Top of Descent at 35 000 ft and 75 NM from the Initial Approach Fix, at which it has to level-off at 7500 feet altitude.\nWhat descent gradient is required to achieve the aforementioned requirements?",
      "choices": [
        "3.7%",
        "4.6%",
        "7.6%",
        "6.1%"
      ],
      "answer": "6.1%"
    },
    {
      "question": "Estimate the descent rate of an aircraft established on a standard 3\u00b0 approach when TAS = 100 kt and headwind component = 15 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "425 fpm",
        "800 fpm",
        "480 fpm",
        "700 fpm"
      ],
      "answer": "425 fpm"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the approximate gradient, expressed as a percentage, for an aircraft descending 8000 ft over a distance of 25 nm?",
      "choices": [
        "3.1%",
        "5.3%",
        "4.8%",
        "2.5%"
      ],
      "answer": "5.3%"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are flying a low level VFR flight over a snowy area with no visual checkpoints and you get lost. What should you do?",
      "choices": [
        "Proceed and turn at the next checkpoint based on time.",
        "Start flying larger concentric circles.",
        "Climb to a higher level and initiate the lost procedure.",
        "Climb to avoid blowing snow."
      ],
      "answer": "Climb to a higher level and initiate the lost procedure."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is 650 lb of fuel expressed in kilograms?",
      "choices": [
        "350 kg",
        "143 kg",
        "295 kg",
        "172 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "295 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying a distance of 50 NM from A to B. After 15 minutes of flying with the planned TAS and TH the aircraft is 3 NM South of the intended track and 2.5 NM ahead of the dead reckoning position. Determine the approximate correction angle on the heading to reach destination B from this position, given:\nTrue course in the flight log: 090\u00b0\nForecast wind: 225\u00b0 (T) / 15 kt\nTAS: 120 kt",
      "choices": [
        "17\u00b0",
        "12\u00b0",
        "15\u00b0",
        "5\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "17\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying from SALCO to BERRY HEAD on Magnetic Track 007\u00b0, TAS 445 kt. The wind is 50\u00b0 (T) / 40 kt. Variation 5\u00b0W, deviation +2\u00b0. At 10:00 UTC the RB of locator PY is 311\u00b0. At 10:03 UTC the RB of locator PY is 266\u00b0. Calculate the distance of the aircraft from locator PY at 10:03 UTC.",
      "choices": [
        "22 NM",
        "23 NM",
        "24 NM",
        "21 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "21 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Track can be calculated by applying calculated drift to heading: TRK = HDG + DR (__________). TRK = HDG - DR (__________).",
      "choices": [
        "North; Left",
        "Right; Left",
        "Left; Right",
        "North; South"
      ],
      "answer": "Right; Left"
    },
    {
      "question": "The main reason to keep the VFR chart lined up with the current track is that:",
      "choices": [
        "It is easier to distinguish the required track in case of diversion.",
        "It is easier to recognise landmarks and terrain.",
        "It stores the chart more easily.",
        "It saves space in the cockpit."
      ],
      "answer": "It is easier to recognise landmarks and terrain."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft overflies waypoint FLOBA at 10.45 UTC, on a direct track to waypoint ANGUS at a TAS of 385 kt, with an ETO of 11.25 UTC. NGM = 232 nm. What is the aircraft’s approximate groundspeed?",
      "choices": [
        "350 kt",
        "406 kt",
        "425 kt",
        "361 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "350 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "HWC = Wind Speed x __________ of Wind Angle.",
      "choices": [
        "Cosine",
        "Sine",
        "Secant",
        "Tangent"
      ],
      "answer": "Cosine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)12 (Ignore chart altitude limitations)\nAn aircraft is flying across open sea with 10\u00b0 of left drift between RODOS (RDS - N36\u00b021' E028\u00b004') VOR/DME and IRAKLION (IRA - N35\u00b024' E025\u00b012') VOR/DME following the UV57 airway, at an altitude of 3000 ft amsl and at a planned GS of 100 kt.\nIRAKLION Approach is expecting position reports from you. You depart overhead RDS at 15:55 UTC.\n25 nm from RDS, passing LOKNA at 16:11 UTC your DME equipment fails and no distance information is available.\nA clear signal is being received on the ADF from the KARPATHOS (KRC - N35\u00b026' E027\u00b009') NDB.\nWhat approximate relative bearings to KRC identify your position along track and at what times can position reports be confirmed at TIPAS and LABUX?",
      "choices": [
        "16:39 UTC (RB to KRC = 249\u00b0) and 17:10 UTC (RB to KRC = 201\u00b0)",
        "16:38 UTC (RB to KRC = 239\u00b0) and 17:11 UTC (RB to KRC = 199\u00b0)",
        "16:36 UTC (RB to KRC = 249\u00b0) and 17:05 UTC (RB to KRC = 201\u00b0)",
        "16:39 UTC (RB to KRC = 144\u00b0) and 17:10 UTC (RB to KRC = 096\u00b0)"
      ],
      "answer": "16:39 UTC (RB to KRC = 249\u00b0) and 17:10 UTC (RB to KRC = 201\u00b0)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the true bearing of the aircraft's position line from the NDB plotted on a Polar Stereographic chart?\nAircraft position: 70\u00b0N, 035\u00b0E\nNDB position: 70\u00b0N, 050\u00b0E\nVariation at the aircraft: 32\u00b0E\nVariation at the NDB: 60\u00b0E\nDeviation: +2\u00b0",
      "choices": [
        "083\u00b0",
        "278\u00b0",
        "049\u00b0",
        "229\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "278\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ - Magnetic bearing from the navaid to the aircrafts position, measured at the navaid.",
      "choices": [
        "Radial",
        "Range",
        "Line of Position",
        "Bearing"
      ],
      "answer": "Radial"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the TAS of an aircraft cruising at FL380 (OAT: ISA +20°C) at M 0.84?",
      "choices": [
        "503 kt",
        "599 kt",
        "432 kt",
        "498 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "503 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Position lines are plotted from an aircrafts position fix to a VOR/DME (265°T), and from the aircraft to the destination aerodrome (085°T). Magnetic variation at the aircraft is 3°W and 5°W at the VOR. Ignoring convergency, what radial will the aircraft follow from its position fix to the aerodrome?",
      "choices": [
        "R-088",
        "R-082",
        "R-080",
        "R-090"
      ],
      "answer": "R-090"
    },
    {
     "question": "Refer to Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2\nAn aircraft is flying due north in nil wind on a heading of 005\u00b0M along the west course of the Republic of Ireland at a GS of 90 kt. The ADF indicates the following bearings to the FOY NDB (N52\u00b034' W009\u00b012'):\n11:10 UTC - 065\u00b0M\n11:20 UTC - 095\u00b0M\nWhat is the aircraft's position at 11:20 UTC?",
     "choices": [
       "N52\u00b018' W009\u00b055'",
       "N52\u00b034' W009\u00b035'",
       "N52\u00b050' W009\u00b054'",
       "N52\u00b034' W009\u00b056'"
     ],
     "answer": "N52\u00b034' W009\u00b056'"
    },
    {
      "question": "Apart from meridians and the Equator, how are great circles depicted on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
       "Straight lines.",
       "Curved lines, concave to the origin.",
       "Complex curves.",
       "Curved lines, convex to the origin."
      ],
      "answer": "Curved lines, concave to the origin."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements, regarding scale on a polar stereographic chart, is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Scale contracts with decreasing latitude, away from the pole.",
        "Scale expands with decreasing latitude, away from the pole.",
        "Scale expands with increasing latitude, towards the pole.",
        "Scale expands with increasing latitude, away from the pole."
      ],
      "answer": "Scale expands with decreasing latitude, away from the pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies from (A) N50\u00b000' W134\u00b000' to (B) N55\u00b000' x\u00b0 following a great circle route. The initial direction at point A is 083\u00b0T and at B is 089\u00b0T. What is the approximate longitude of (B)?",
      "choices": [
        "W126\u00b030'",
        "W137\u00b045'",
        "W141\u00b030'",
        "W130\u00b015'"
      ],
      "answer": "W126\u00b030'"
    }, 
    {
      "question": "Conversion angle can be found between the great circle track bearing and the rhumb line track bearing at __________ end of the route.",
      "choices": [
        "either departure or arrival",
        "mid-point",
        "only departure",
        "only arrival"
      ],
      "answer": "either departure or arrival"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Estimated Time of Departure A 15\u00b015.0'N, 072\u00b006.0'W on 12 March is 01:00 ST\nST = UTC -5 hr\nEstimated Time of Arrival B 55\u00b018.0'N, 005\u00b045.0'E 16:15 ST on the same date\nST = UTC +1 hr\nAccording to the Air Almanac tables sunset at B takes place at 18:20.\nCalculate the flight time from A to B and the time between arrival and sunset at B.",
      "choices": [
        "09h15m and 03h28m.",
        "21h15m and 03h28m.",
        "09h15m and 02h42m.",
        "21h15m and 02h42m."
      ],
     "answer": "09h15m and 02h42m."
    },
    {
     "question": "The standard time at Dubai International Airport, Dubai, UAE (25\u00b015'N 055\u00b020'E) is 17:35 ST on 15 March 2017.\nWhat is the ST at Ninoy Aquino International Airport, Manila, Philippines (14\u00b030'N 121\u00b000'E)?",
      "choices": [
        "17:58 ST on 15 March 2017",
        "21:35 ST on 15 March 2017",
        "13:35 ST on 15 March 2017",
        "17:35 ST on 15 March 2017"
     ],
       "answer": "21:35 ST on 15 March 2017"
    },
    {
     "question": "Date changes, whilst travelling across the International Date Line (IDL):\nEast = date goes _________.\nWest = date goes _________.",
      "choices": [
        "forwards; forwards.",
        "forwards; backwards.",
        "backwards; forwards.",
        "backwards; backwards."
     ],
      "answer": "backwards; forwards."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a low level flight two parallel roads are crossed at right angles by an aircraft. What can the time taken between the road crossing be used to check?",
      "choices": [
        "drift",
        "position",
        "track",
        "groundspeed"
      ],
      "answer": "groundspeed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Date changes, whilst travelling across the midnight boundary:\nEast = date goes _________.\nWest = date goes _________.",
      "choices": [
        "backwards; backwards.",
        "forwards; backwards.",
        "forwards; forwards.",
        "backwards; forwards."
      ],
      "answer": "forwards; backwards."
    },
    {
      "question": "If a straight line is drawn on an aeronautical chart between any two positions, what will determine the true track change along that line between the two positions?",
      "choices": [
        "The chart convergence between the two meridians.",
        "The Earth convergence between the two meridians and the sine of the mean latitude.",
        "The chart convergence between the two meridians and the sine of the parallel of origin.",
        "The Earth convergence between the two meridians."
      ],
      "answer": "The chart convergence between the two meridians."
    },
    {
      "question": "Generally speaking, which of the following will be more difficult to see when flying at high level?",
      "choices": [
        "Power stations in built up areas.",
        "Roads and railways.",
        "Rivers and canals.",
        "Out-of-town shopping complexes with large car parks."
      ],
      "answer": "Power stations in built up areas."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a general consideration when selecting en-route navigational visual check points during flight planning?",
      "choices": [
        "Working from large features to small features.",
        "Terrain.",
        "In-flight visibility.",
        "Proximity to leg."
      ],
      "answer": "In-flight visibility."
    },
    {
      "question": "Some states implement daylight saving time (sometimes referred to as summer time) by advancing the clocks 1 hour in spring. Which of the following options is an effect of this?",
      "choices": [
        "The daylight is shifted towards later in the day.",
        "The daylight is shifted towards earlier in the day.",
        "There is 1 hour of reduced daylight per day.",
        "There is 1 hour of additional daylight per day."
      ],
      "answer": "The daylight is shifted towards later in the day."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following, from a navigational perspective, are recognised as causes of reduced in-flight visibility?",
      "choices": [
        "Precipitation, Fog / Mist, Sea Spray.",
        "Solar storms, Night flight, Haze.",
        "Haze, Smoke / Smog, High altitude flight.",
        "Heavy rain, Insomnia, Haze."
      ],
      "answer": "Precipitation, Fog / Mist, Sea Spray."
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot is flying VFR and is about to conduct an approach to an unfamiliar airfield just after the sunrise. What should he/she pay extra attention to?",
      "choices": [
        "The position of the sun.",
        "The position of the moon.",
        "The aerodrome reference point.",
        "The duration of the morning civil twilight."
      ],
      "answer": "The position of the sun."
    },
    {
      "question": "You are flying a low level VFR flight over a snowy area with no visual checkpoints. What should you do?",
      "choices": [
        "Climb to a higher level and initiate the lost procedure .",
        "Start flying larger concentric circles.",
        "Turn at DR point to next leg.",
        "Climb to avoid blowing snow"
      ],
      "answer": "Turn at DR point to next leg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Illumination by the sun or the moon does not alter visibility, nor does it alter the range at which objects can be seen.",
        "Illumination by the sun or the moon alters visibility, but does not alter the range at which objects can be seen.",
        "Illumination by the sun or the moon does alter visibility, and alters the range at which objects can be seen.",
        "Illumination by the sun or the moon does not alter visibility; however, it does alter the range at which objects can be seen."
      ],
      "answer": "Illumination by the sun or the moon does not alter visibility; however, it does alter the range at which objects can be seen."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft at FL160, IAS 195 kt, OAT -25\u00b0C and WC -25 kt, is required to reduce speed in order to cross a reporting point 5 min later than planned. Assuming that flight conditions do not change, when 121 NM from the reporting point the aircraft should reduce IAS by what amount?",
      "choices": [
        "35 kt",
        "25 kt",
        "10 kt",
        "15 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "25 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "While proceeding en-route, after half the distance between two waypoints, the aircraft's position is 3 NM left of the desired track. The total distance between the two waypoints ls 120 NM. Using the 1 sin 60 rule and for the purpose of reaching the active waypoint, the heading should be changed by:",
      "choices": [
        "6\u00b0 to the right.",
        "3\u00b0 to the left.",
        "6\u00b0 to the left.",
        "3\u00b0 to the right."
      ],
      "answer": "6\u00b0 to the right."
    },
    {
      "question": "The time difference in Local Mean Time between sunset at positions A 50\u00b0N, 120\u00b0E and B 50\u00b0S, 120\u00b0E on the 21st of November is:",
      "choices": [
        "some hours and the Sun rises earlier in B than in A.",
        "some hours and the Sun rises earlier in A than in B.",
        "negligibly small because A and B are located at the same meridian.",
        "negligibly small because A and B are located symmetrically to the Equator."
      ],
      "answer": "some hours and the Sun rises earlier in B than in A."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a Mercator's projection the distance between (17\u00b0N, 035\u00b0E) and (17\u00b0N, 040\u00b0 E) is 5 cm. The scale at 57\u00b0 N is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "1 :18 658 470",
        "1 :6 052 030",
        "1 :5 556 000",
        "1 :10 626 460"
      ],
      "answer": "1 :6 052 030"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft overflies waypoint 1 at 10:37 UTC and is overhead waypoint 2 at 10:49 UTC. The measured distance on the chart between the two waypoints is 11.4 cm. If 1 cm on the chart represents 3.2 NM on the Earth, what Ground Speed has been flown between the two waypoints?",
      "choices": [
        "171 kt",
        "192 kt",
        "177 kt",
        "182 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "182 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where is the International Dateline located?",
      "choices": [
        "To the east of the 180\u00b0E/W meridian only.",
        "To the west of the 180\u00b0E/W meridian.",
        "Exactly on the 180\u00b0E/W meridian.",
        "In the vicinity of the 180\u00b0E/W meridian."
      ],
      "answer": "In the vicinity of the 180\u00b0E/W meridian."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: DTK = 055\u00b0M, forecast drift = 15\u00b0 left, planned heading = 065\u00b0M. At a fix 36 nm along the leg the aircraft was determined to be 3 nm left of track. What is the track error angle and what heading should be flown to parallel track?",
      "choices": [
        "5\u00b0 Right - 060\u00b0M",
        "5\u00b0 Left - 060\u00b0M",
        "5\u00b0 Right - 070\u00b0M",
        "5\u00b0 Left - 070\u00b0M"
      ],
      "answer": "5\u00b0 Left - 070\u00b0M"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft follows a radial to a VOR/DME station. At 10:00 the DME reads 120 NM. At 10:03 the DME reads 105 NM. The estimated time overhead the VOR/DME station is:",
      "choices": [
        "10:27:00",
        "10:18:00",
        "10:24:00",
        "10:21:00"
      ],
      "answer": "10:24:00"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the approximate scale, expressed as a ratio, of a low altitude en-route chart with a quoted scale of 1 inch = 15 NM?",
      "choices": [
        "1 :2 057 235",
        "1 :2 778 000",
        "1:7 056 120",
        "1 :1 094 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1 :1 094 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying a leg of 105 nm distance on a heading of 220\u00b0M. At the first planned DR Fix 45 nm along track, the actual Position Fix is found to be 3 nm right of track. What approximate heading is required to overfly the end of the leg?",
      "choices": [
        "213\u00b0M",
        "216\u00b0M",
        "224\u00b0M",
        "227\u00b0M"
      ],
      "answer": "213\u00b0M"
    },
    {
      "question": "When navigating by following a line feature, where should the line feature be kept?",
      "choices": [
        "Do not follow line features.",
        "Either side.",
        "Left.",
        "Right."
      ],
      "answer": "Left."
    },
    {
      "question": "In general, which of the following is not a problem associated with night VFR navigation?",
      "choices": [
        "Black-hole conditions.",
        "Night flight illusions.",
        "Collisions on the ground.",
        "Tracking errors."
      ],
      "answer": "Tracking errors."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for solving off track errors?",
      "choices": [
        "TEA (DOT x DAT) \u00f7 60",
        "DOT = (TEA \u00f7 DAT) x 60",
        "TEA = (DOT \u00f7 DAT) x 60",
        "DAT = 60 x ( TEA \u00f7 DOT)"
      ],
      "answer": "TEA = (DOT \u00f7 DAT) x 60"
    },
    {
      "question": "Having regard to the 1-in-60 rule, which of the following statements is incorrect?",
      "choices": [
        "4 nm of Cross Track Error after 40 nm of distance flown is equal to 6\u00b0 of Track Error Angle.",
        "3\u00b0 of Track Error Angle produces 4.5 nm of Cross Track Error per 90 nm of distance flown.",
        "2 nm of Cross Track Error after 30 nm of distance flown is equal to 4\u00b0 of Track Error Angle.",
        "4\u00b0 of Track Error Angle produces 2 nm of Cross Track Error after a flight of 120 nm."
      ],
      "answer": "4\u00b0 of Track Error Angle produces 2 nm of Cross Track Error after a flight of 120 nm."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for solving closing angle errors?",
      "choices": [
        "DRAT = 60 x ( CA \u00f7 DOT)",
        "CA = (DOT x DRAT) \u00f7 60",
        "CA = (DOT \u00f7 DRAT) x 60",
        "DOT = (CA \u00f7 DRAT) x 60"
      ],
      "answer": "CA = (DOT \u00f7 DRAT) x 60"
    },
    {
      "question": "When planning a VFR flight, the selection of the navigation features that are suitable for transferring from map to ground is required. What ground features are particularly important for VFR navigation? 1. Large water features, 2. Agricultural farm land, 3. Exceptionally high obstacles, 4. Telephone lines, 5. Isolated towns.",
      "choices": [
        "2, 3 and 4.",
        "2, 4 and 5.",
        "1, 2 and 4 .",
        "1, 3 and 5."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3 and 5."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following will be easier to see when flying at low level?",
      "choices": [
        "Power stations with large cooling towers.",
        "Shopping complexes with car parks.",
        "Rivers and canals.",
        "Roads and railways."
      ],
      "answer": "Power stations with large cooling towers."
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the approximate rate of descent required to maintain a 3\u00b0 glide path at a groundspeed of 120 kt:",
      "choices": [
        "600 ft/min",
        "550 ft/min",
        "950 ft/min",
        "800 ft/min"
      ],
      "answer": "600 ft/min"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is in Tokyo (35\u00b039'N, 139\u00b050'E) and plans to fly Anchorage (61\u00b013'N, 149\u00b052'W). What is the arc-to-time difference between Tokyo and Anchorage?",
      "choices": [
        "4 hours 41 minutes",
        "9 hours 19 minutes",
        "9 hours 59 minutes",
        "4 hours 15 minutes"
      ],
      "answer": "4 hours 41 minutes"
    },
    {
      "question": "The position A (75\u00b0N, 34\u00b0E) of an aircraft and the position B (75\u00b0N, 50\u00b0E) of an NDB station are plotted on a polar stereographic chart projection and are connected with a straight line. Determine the true bearing from position B to position A, given: Magnetic variation at position A: 32\u00b0W Magnetic variation at position B: 60\u00b0W",
      "choices": [
        "278\u00b0",
        "310\u00b0",
        "082\u00b0",
        "050\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "278\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the best ground feature to check the track deviation for a north-south flight?",
      "choices": [
        "A river in a north-south direction.",
        "A railroad running from east to west.",
        "4 windmills spaced east-west .",
        "An east to west power line."
      ],
      "answer": "A river in a north-south direction."
    },
    {
      "question": "If a VCP is not visible at the end of the leg being flown, what action should be taken by the pilot?",
      "choices": [
        "Continue flight until the ETO and turn onto the planned heading for the next leg.",
        "Turn back to the previous VCP.",
        "Fly around in a circle looking for the VCP.",
        "Head for the nearest line feature and follow it to a known ground feature."
      ],
      "answer": "Continue flight until the ETO and turn onto the planned heading for the next leg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the factors listed below should be considered by the pilot when selecting landmarks as visual reference points? 1. Possibility of identification 2. Transmitted frequency 3. Visibility 4. Closeness to the track",
      "choices": [
        "2, 3 and 4",
        "1, 2 and 3",
        "1, 3 and 4",
        "2 and 3 only"
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3 and 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following features are the most useful for VFR navigation by day: 1. Tall masts 2. Large lakes 3. Streets in a large town 4. Area with several small woods 5. Active power station",
      "choices": [
        "1, 3 and 4.",
        "1, 2 and 5.",
        "2 and 4 .",
        "2, 3 and 5."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2 and 5."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: TAS = 155 kt, HDG (T) = 216\u00b0, W/V = 090/60 kt. Calculate the Track (\u00b0T) and GS.",
      "choices": [
        "231 - 196 kt",
        "222 - 181 kt",
        "226 - 186 kt",
        "224 - 175 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "231 - 196 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft departs points A (50\u00b0N, 006\u00b0 50'W) on a southerly track of 300 NM to point B. From point B, the aircraft flies on a westerly track for 300 NM to point C. What is the aircraft's final position?",
      "choices": [
        "45\u00b0N 013\u00b054'W",
        "45\u00b0N 000\u00b014'E",
        "45\u00b0N 001\u00b025'W",
        "56\u00b0N 003\u00b0W"
      ],
      "answer": "45\u00b0N 013\u00b054'W"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following aircraft is most likely to obtain clear VHF communications with an air traffic service unit?",
      "choices": [
        "Commercial aircraft at 25 000 ft amsl communicating with an ATSU 1200 ft amsl at a range of 65 nm over flat land.",
        "Commercial aircraft at 25 000 ft amsl communicating with an ATSU 1200 ft amsl at a range of 128 nm over mountainous terrain up to 21 000 ft amsl.",
        "Light aircraft at 1000 ft amsl communicating with an ATSU at sea level at a range of 40 nm over sea.",
        "Light aircraft at 2000 ft amsl communicating with an ATSU 300 ft amsl at a range of 70 nm over flat land."
      ],
      "answer": "Commercial aircraft at 25 000 ft amsl communicating with an ATSU 1200 ft amsl at a range of 65 nm over flat land."
    },
    {
      "question": "Two positions lie at the same geographical latitude. Position A is at 076\u00b0E, Position B at 126\u00b0E. Sunrise occurs at 07:29 ST at Position B. Provided that both positions are within the same time zone, what is the ST of sunrise at Position A?",
      "choices": [
        "04:09 ST",
        "10:49 ST",
        "07:29 ST",
        "06:39 ST"
      ],
      "answer": "10:49 ST"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a visual checkpoint?",
      "choices": [
        "A position on the ground chosen to identify an on-track navigation feature.",
        "A position established by an aerodrome as a feature to be flown by or over as part of a VFR departure or arrival procedure.",
        "A unique feature, or combination of features, used to positively identify a position on the surface of the Earth from an aircraft in flight.",
        "A waypoint, aerodrome or navigation aid clearly identifiable on a chart."
      ],
      "answer": "A unique feature, or combination of features, used to positively identify a position on the surface of the Earth from an aircraft in flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: DTK = 165\u00b0T, forecast drift = 10\u00b0 left. At a fix 40 nm along the leg between two positions 90 nm apart, the aircraft was determined to be 4 nm right of track. Magnetic variation = 10\u00b0W. Without using a CRP-5 or calculator, what is the track error angle and what revised heading should be flown to fly to the end of the leg?",
      "choices": [
        "11\u00b0 Right - 154\u00b0M",
        "6\u00b0 Right - 174\u00b0M",
        "6\u00b0 Right - 164\u00b0M",
        "11\u00b0 Right - 164\u00b0M"
      ],
      "answer": "6\u00b0 Right - 174\u00b0M"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for resolving heading errors? REV HDG - Revised Heading OR HDG - Original Heading CORR - Correction",
      "choices": [
        "REV HDG = OR HDG + CORR (Right)",
        "REV HDG = OR HDG + CORR (Left)",
        "REV HDG = OR HDG \u00f7 CORR (Right)",
        "REV HDG = OR HDG - CORR (Right)"
      ],
      "answer": "REV HDG = OR HDG + CORR (Right)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following describes the appearance of rhumb lines, except meridians, on a Polar Stereographic chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Ellipses around the Pole.",
        "Curves convex to the Pole.",
        "Curves concave to the Pole.",
        "Straight lines."
      ],
      "answer": "Curves concave to the Pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a polar stereographic chart, what is the initial straight track from A (75\u00b0N 060\u00b0E) to B (75\u00b0N 060\u00b0W)?",
      "choices": [
        "360\u00b0",
        "030\u00b0",
        "060\u00b0",
        "330\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "330\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the purpose of fan lines on a VFR chart used for in-flight navigation?",
      "choices": [
        "Assist with working from large features to small features.",
        "They permit the rapid assessment of track error angles.",
        "They allow the pilot to see what terrain will be flown over from an off-track position fix to the next checkpoint.",
        "They allow the pilot to see what features are within a pre-determined angular distance from the track line over the length of the fan line."
      ],
      "answer": "They permit the rapid assessment of track error angles."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the UTC and date when it is 23:00 LMT on the 21st August at position A(11\u00b000'N, 067\u00b030'W)?",
      "choices": [
        "03:30 UTC 21st August",
        "18:30 UTC 22nd August",
        "18:30 UTC 21st August",
        "03:30 UTC 22nd August"
      ],
      "answer": "03:30 UTC 22nd August"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft, flying at a TAS of 230 kt, is tracking inbound to the ABN VOR/DME along the R-240 radial on a heading of 052\u00b0M. At the VOR/DME it turns outbound along the R-045 radial on a heading of 036\u00b0M. Magnetic variation = 15\u00b0E. What is the approximate true wind velocity?",
      "choices": [
        "115\u00b0 / 55",
        "280\u00b0 / 40",
        "310\u00b0 / 40",
        "295\u00b0 / 40"
      ],
      "answer": "310\u00b0 / 40"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the true wind velocity being experienced by an aircraft flying on a track of 267\u00b0T whilst maintaining a heading of 280\u00b0T at a TAS of 190 kt and GS of 210 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "025\u00b0 / 50",
        "160\u00b0 / 60",
        "205\u00b0 / 50",
        "340\u00b0 / 50"
      ],
      "answer": "025\u00b0 / 50"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot flying a VFR flight got lost while in contact with ATC and with enough fuel in tanks. What are the recommended actions in this case?",
      "choices": [
        "Continue the flight with the same heading until the position can be established.",
        "Turn back to the last confirmed position.",
        "Note the actual time and ask ATC for help.",
        "Make an urgency call (PAN PAN) on frequency 121.5 MHz."
      ],
      "answer": "Note the actual time and ask ATC for help."
    },
    {
      "question": "The clock method is used to establish the amount of wind component used, from the wind angle: __________\u00b0 = 1/4 (25%) of wind speed. __________\u00b0 = 1/2 (50%) of wind speed. __________\u00b0 = 3/4 (75%) of wind speed. __________\u00b0 = ALL (100%) of wind speed.",
      "choices": [
        "15; 20; 30; 45",
        "30; 60; 90; 120",
        "10; 20; 30; 45",
        "15; 30; 45; 60"
      ],
      "answer": "15; 30; 45; 60"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies between 2 waypoints 48 nm apart in 16 minutes. In the same time, the aircraft flies an air distance of 55 nm. What is the TAS of the aircraft and what is the wind component experienced?",
      "choices": [
        "206 kt - 26 kt TWC.",
        "206 kt - 26 kt HWC.",
        "157 kt - 23 kt TWC.",
        "194 kt - 14 kt TWC."
      ],
      "answer": "206 kt - 26 kt HWC."
    },
    {
      "question": "Using mental dead reckoning techniques, what is the maximum drift experienced by an SEP aircraft maintaining a TAS of 180 kt, with W/V = 330\u00b0/30?",
      "choices": [
        "10\u00b0",
        "12\u00b0",
        "15\u00b0",
        "8\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "10\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following ground features should allow a pilot flying along a VFR track to best check for any time deviation?",
      "choices": [
        "A double-lane road crossing a lake close to your intended track.",
        "A single-lane road crossing a lake close to your intended track.",
        "A double-lane road crossing your intended track.",
        "A double-lane road crossing a railway close to your intended track."
      ],
      "answer": "A double-lane road crossing your intended track."
    },
    {
      "question": "265 US-GAL equals? (Specific gravity 0.80)",
      "choices": [
        "895 kg",
        "803 kg",
        "940 kg",
        "862 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "803 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies from (A) latitude 40\u00b0 W005\u00b0 to (B) latitude 50\u00b0 E008\u00b0 following a great circle route. The initial direction at point A is 282\u00b0T and at B is 287\u00b0T. In which hemisphere is the route?",
      "choices": [
        "Western hemisphere.",
        "Southern hemisphere.",
        "Eastern hemisphere.",
        "Northern hemisphere."
      ],
      "answer": "Northern hemisphere."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a low level VFR flight at 600 ft AGL, which one of the following challenges may be faced by the pilot?",
      "choices": [
        "It might NOT be easy to recognise visual waypoints, so he/she could fly past them .",
        "Terrain contours are more difficult to spot compared to when flying at a high altitude.",
        "Open areas are much easier to identify than built-up areas.",
        "Vertical features disappear in the surrounding environment and are difficult to spot."
      ],
      "answer": "It might NOT be easy to recognise visual waypoints, so he/she could fly past them ."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is using 160 Imperial Gallons of fuel (SG = 0.78) per hour. How many pounds of fuel will it use in 40 minutes?",
      "choices": [
        "475 lb",
        "1040 lb",
        "380 lb",
        "830 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "830 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "GS can be calculated as: TAS __________ HWC TAS __________ TWC",
      "choices": [
        "minus; minus",
        "minus; plus",
        "plus; plus",
        "plus; minus"
      ],
      "answer": "minus; plus"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is using 200 US Gallons of fuel (SG = 0.72) per hour. How many kilograms of fuel will it use in 15 minutes?",
      "choices": [
        "308 kg",
        "136 kg",
        "380 kg",
        "163 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "136 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "TAS can be calculated as: GS __________ HWC GS __________ TWC",
      "choices": [
        "minus; plus",
        "plus; plus",
        "plus; minus",
        "minus; minus"
      ],
      "answer": "plus; minus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using both the Mental Dead Reckoning (MDR) technique, calculate the tailwind component for the following information given: Runway 33 Surface wind (from the tower): 190\u00b0/15 kt, Variation: 20\u00b0W",
      "choices": [
        "11.5 kt",
        "15 kt",
        "7.5 kt",
        "10 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "11.5 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Wind correction angle (WCA) can be calculated using the following formula: WCA = __________ \u00f7 SF",
      "choices": [
        "DA",
        "TWC",
        "HWC",
        "XWC"
      ],
      "answer": "XWC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to the winds aloft data below: An aircraft passes overhead RAG VOR/DME at FL320 and immediately descends at 1000 fpm to FL160 along Airway XY15 to DINKY at a constant CAS of 210 kt and a wind component of +60 kt. What is the approximate distance from RAG to DINKY?",
      "choices": [
        "88 nm",
        "96 nm",
        "92 nm",
        "76 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "96 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft takes off from an aerodrome 1250 ft amsl and climbs to an initial cruise pressure altitude of FL 140. Regional QNH = 998 hPa. Rate of Climb = 1000 fpm and average GS = 140 kt. What is the approximate distance to top of climb?",
      "choices": [
        "31 nm",
        "33 nm",
        "27 nm",
        "29 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "29 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ = Difference between aircraft heading and wind direction.",
      "choices": [
        "Drift Angle",
        "Track Correction Angle",
        "Wind Angle",
        "Wind Correction Angle"
      ],
      "answer": "Wind Angle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given magnetic variation = 10\u00b0W and compass deviation = 3\u00b0E, what is the true wind velocity being experienced by an aircraft flying on a track of 073\u00b0T, whilst maintaining a heading of 102\u00b0C at a TAS of 320 kt and GS of 290 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "190\u00b0 / 155",
        "160\u00b0 / 120",
        "340\u00b0 / 120",
        "010\u00b0 / 120"
      ],
      "answer": "160\u00b0 / 120"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the primary advantage of using line features during a VFR flight?",
      "choices": [
        "Line features should normally be free of the other VFR navigation traffic.",
        "Following line features, particularly If they are distinctive, removes the need for dead reckoning navigation.",
        "Overflying an area containing several railway lines and roads, the correct line features can still be reliably identified.",
        "Line features can be followed towards a significant position."
      ],
      "answer": "Line features can be followed towards a significant position."
    },
    {
      "question": "For climbing and descending problems, at which point in the descent are average values calculated?",
      "choices": [
        "2/3 x change of altitude",
        "1/2 x change of altitude",
        "1/4 x change of altitude",
        "1/2 x cruise altitude"
      ],
      "answer": "1/2 x change of altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft at FL330 is required to commence descent when 65 NM from a VOR and to cross the VOR at FL100. The mean GS during the descent is 330 kt. What is the minimum rate of descent required?",
      "choices": [
        "1950 ft/min",
        "1650 ft/min",
        "1850 ft/min",
        "1750 ft/min"
      ],
      "answer": "1950 ft/min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Winds at higher altitudes are normally __________ than those at lower altitudes, and have a __________ effect on the air distance.",
      "choices": [
        "weaker; lesser",
        "weaker; greater",
        "stronger; greater",
        "stronger; lesser"
      ],
      "answer": "stronger; greater"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: TAS = 250 kt, NGM = 140 NGM, GS = 280 kt. What is the air distance travelled?",
      "choices": [
        "175 nm",
        "500 nm",
        "157 nm",
        "125 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "125 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft has to descend from FL 300 to FL 120 over a distance of 80 nm. The aircraft\u2019s average GS in the descent is 265 kt. What aproximate rate of descent is required?",
      "choices": [
        "1200 fpm",
        "1300 fpm",
        "1000 fpm",
        "1100 fpm"
      ],
      "answer": "1000 fpm"
    },
    {
      "question": "As WCA increases, the difference between TAS and GS __________.",
      "choices": [
        "expands",
        "remains constant",
        "increases",
        "reduces"
      ],
      "answer": "reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft on a heading of 158\u00b0T is experiencing a wind of 205\u00b0/40. Using mental dead reckoning techniques, what is the crosswind component?",
      "choices": [
        "28 kt",
        "29 kt",
        "30 kt",
        "32 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "30 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is maintaining a track of 315\u00b0T at a TAS of 490 kt. The forecast W/V is 350\u00b0/100. Magnetic variation = 15\u00b0W, Compass deviation = 4\u00b0E. What is the compass heading and groundspeed?",
      "choices": [
        "306\u00b0C - 425 kt",
        "311\u00b0C - 405 kt",
        "333\u00b0C - 405 kt",
        "309\u00b0C - 412 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "333\u00b0C - 405 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ - wind coming from ahead of the aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Crosswind component",
        "Headwind component",
        "Tailwind component",
        "Downwind component"
      ],
      "answer": "Headwind component"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying a heading of 022\u00b0T at a TAS of 130 kt. The forecast W/V is 270\u00b0/20. Magnetic variation = 15\u00b0E. What is the true track and the groundspeed?",
      "choices": [
        "014\u00b0T - 139 kt",
        "029\u00b0T - 136 kt",
        "030\u00b0T - 139 kt",
        "014\u00b0T - 136 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "030\u00b0T - 139 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following VFR navigation techniques provides to a pilot the maximum amount of time to check for other traffic and also maintain a good situational awareness?",
      "choices": [
        "Keep a continuous update of the position by looking within a short distance of the aircraft.",
        "Identify a feature to be used for guidance as far as possible down the planned track.",
        "Delay any aircraft system checks until the aircraft is turned onto a new heading.",
        "Plan to fly from point to point as identified on the map and then on the ground."
      ],
      "answer": "Identify a feature to be used for guidance as far as possible down the planned track."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the simplified formula for calculating the rate of descent on a glidepath, measured as a percentage gradient?",
      "choices": [
        "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) \u00f7 Gradient (%) x 100",
        "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) x Gradient (%) x 60",
        "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) x Gradient (%)",
        "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) \u00f7 Gradient (%)"
      ],
      "answer": "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) x Gradient (%)"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ - wind coming from behind the aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Crosswind component",
        "Tailwind component",
        "Downwind component",
        "Headwind component"
      ],
      "answer": "Tailwind component"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, calculate the average TAS during the descent: Cruising altitude: FL 130 Target level: FL60 Average CAS during descent: 130 kt Temperature Conditions: ISA",
      "choices": [
        "143 kt",
        "115 kt",
        "150 kt",
        "161 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "150 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the general formula (as per the ATPL syllabus) for calculating the rate of descent on a glidepath, measured in ft/nm?",
      "choices": [
        "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) x Gradient (ft/nm)",
        "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) \u00f7 Gradient (ft/nm) x 100",
        "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) x Gradient (ft/nm) \u00f7 60",
        "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) x Gradient (ft/nm) x 60"
      ],
      "answer": "Rate of Descent = Groundspeed (kt) x Gradient (ft/nm) \u00f7 60"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft takes off from an aerodrome 1450 ft amsl and climbs to an initial cruise pressure altitude of FL 80. Regional QNH = 1028 hPa. Rate of Climb = 1000 fpm and average GS = 80 kt. What is the approximate distance to top of climb?",
      "choices": [
        "9.5 nm",
        "10.7 nm",
        "6.5 nm",
        "12.0 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "9.5 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ - wind coming from the left or right side of the aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Headwind component",
        "Tailwind component",
        "Downwind component",
        "Crosswind component"
      ],
      "answer": "Crosswind component"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft travels 240 NAM in 45 minutes with a wind component of +25 kt. How many NGM will it travel?",
      "choices": [
        "460 nm",
        "259 nm",
        "222 nm",
        "215 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "259 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that the earth distance between two meridians of longitude shown on a Direct Mercator chart at N20\u00b0 is 160 nm, what is the approximate earth distance between the same two meridians at N50\u00b0?",
      "choices": [
        "265 nm",
        "103 nm",
        "109 nm",
        "234 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "109 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying from A (60\u00b0S, 165\u00b0W) to B (60\u00b0S, 177\u00b0E). The true great circle track, when passing 172\u00b0E will be:",
      "choices": [
        "098\u00b0 T",
        "278\u00b0 T",
        "082\u00b0 T",
        "262\u00b0 T"
      ],
      "answer": "262\u00b0 T"
    },
    {
      "question": "The convergence factor of a southern hemisphere Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart is stated as being 0.66913. At which latitude is chart convergency equal to earth convergency?",
      "choices": [
        "S35\u00b000\u2019",
        "S30\u00b030\u2019",
        "S38\u00b000\u2019",
        "S55\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "S35\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to IFR Chart E(LO)2, calculate the average magnetic track from KILKENNY (EIKK - N52\u00b039\u2032 W007\u00b017\u2032) to KERRY (EIKY - N52\u00b011\u2032 W009\u00b031\u2032)?",
      "choices": [
        "075\u00b0M",
        "247\u00b0M",
        "251\u00b0M",
        "255\u00b0M"
      ],
      "answer": "255\u00b0M"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that magnetic variation = 16\u00b0W and compass deviation = 2\u00b0W, planned track = 328\u00b0T and planned heading = 316\u00b0M, what is the wind correction angle?",
      "choices": [
        "030\u00b0 Left.",
        "028\u00b0 Left.",
        "012\u00b0 Right.",
        "030\u00b0 Right."
      ],
      "answer": "028\u00b0 Left."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following describes the planned direction of aircraft movement relative to the surface of the Earth?",
      "choices": [
        "DTK",
        "HDG",
        "TMC",
        "TRK"
      ],
      "answer": "DTK"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the CTM graph, an aircraft is descending from FL 340 to FL165 at a reducing MN. What is happening to TAS and CAS?",
      "choices": [
        "TAS = decreasing, CAS = constant.",
        "TAS = decreasing, CAS = increasing.",
        "TAS = constant, CAS = decreasing.",
        "TAS = constant, CAS = constant."
      ],
      "answer": "TAS = decreasing, CAS = constant."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following terms defines the planned path of an aircraft over the ground?",
      "choices": [
        "Track Made Good (TMG).",
        "Planned Heading (HDG).",
        "Desired Track (DTK).",
        "Proposed Track (PTK)."
      ],
      "answer": "Desired Track (DTK)."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft with a constant TAS of 180 kt, initially follows a magnetic track of 250\u00b0M, because of a drift 8\u00b0L. After turning, it follows a magnetic track of 340\u00b0M, because of a drift 8\u00b0R. What is the wind velocity and direction (T\u00b0), if magnetic variation is 10\u00b0 East?",
      "choices": [
        "305\u00b0/36 kt",
        "295\u00b0/36 kt",
        "305\u00b0/32 kt",
        "295\u00b0 /32 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "305\u00b0/36 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ - Magnetic bearing from the navaid to the aircraft\u2019s position, measured at the navaid.",
      "choices": [
        "Range",
        "Line of Position",
        "Bearing",
        "Radial"
      ],
      "answer": "Radial"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the CTM graph, an aircraft is descending from FL 200 to FL140 at a constant TAS. What is happening to CAS and MN?",
      "choices": [
        "CAS = decreasing, MN = increasing.",
        "CAS = increasing, MN = decreasing.",
        "CAS = increasing, MN = increasing.",
        "CAS = decreasing, MN = decreasing."
      ],
      "answer": "CAS = increasing, MN = decreasing."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the TAS of an aircraft cruising at FL100 (OAT: +10\u00b0C) at a CAS of 145 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "122 kt",
        "174 kt",
        "125 kt",
        "168 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "174 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following speeds describes the speed of the aircraft relative to the air mass through which is flying?",
      "choices": [
        "TAS",
        "MN",
        "CAS",
        "IAS"
      ],
      "answer": "TAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the MN of an aircraft cruising at FL250 (OAT: ISA -5\u00b0C) at a TAS of 445 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "M 0.72",
        "M 0.26",
        "M 0.75",
        "M 0.65"
      ],
      "answer": "M 0.75"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: TAS = 485 kt, OAT = ISA +10\u00b0C, FL 410. Calculate the Mach Number?",
      "choices": [
        "0.85",
        "0.9",
        "0.87",
        "0.825"
      ],
      "answer": "0.825"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to IFR Chart E(LO)2, what is the approximate the aircraft position, given the following 2 radials: SHANNON VOR/DME (SHA - N52\u00b043\u2032 W008\u00b053\u2032) - R-102\u00b0 and CORK VOR/DME (CRK - N51\u00b050\u2032 W008\u00b029\u2032) - R-025\u00b0.",
      "choices": [
        "N52\u00b040\u2032 W008\u00b000\u2032",
        "N52\u00b030\u2032 W008\u00b010\u2032",
        "N52\u00b040\u2032 W008\u00b010\u2032",
        "N52\u00b050\u2032 W007\u00b050\u2032"
      ],
      "answer": "N52\u00b040\u2032 W008\u00b000\u2032"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is mach number?",
      "choices": [
        "Ratio of CAS to TAS x \u221a38.94",
        "Ratio of TAS to Local Speed of Sound.",
        "TAS x \u221a38.94",
        "1"
      ],
      "answer": "Ratio of TAS to Local Speed of Sound."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a QDR of 246\u00b0M from an NDB. Magnetic variation at the aircraft is 22\u00b0W and at the NDB is 18\u00b0W. What is the true bearing from the aircraft to the NDB?",
      "choices": [
        "044\u00b0T",
        "050\u00b0T",
        "218\u00b0T",
        "038\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "044\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the convergency factor on a Direct Mercator projection?",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "It varies as it is dependent on the latitude.",
        "The convergency factor ls infinite.",
        "0"
      ],
      "answer": "0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, calculate the heading (T) and groundspeed: TAS: 465 kt Track: 007\u00b0T Wind velocity: 300\u00b0T /80 kt",
      "choices": [
        "Heading: 358\u00b0T, groundspeed: 428 kt",
        "Heading: 017\u00b0T, groundspeed: 490 kt",
        "Heading: 357\u00b0T, groundspeed: 502 kt",
        "Heading: 001\u00b0T, groundspeed: 435 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "Heading: 358\u00b0T, groundspeed: 428 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The nominal scale of a Lambert conformal conic chart is the:",
      "choices": [
        "mean scale between pole and equator",
        "mean scale between the parallels of the secant cone",
        "scale at the equator",
        "scale at the standard parallels"
      ],
      "answer": "scale at the standard parallels"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following may be used to obtain an unambiguous position fix?",
      "choices": [
        "2 x lines of position from 1 x landmark",
        "2 x lines of position from 2 x landmarks",
        "2 x reciprocal radials from 2 x VORs",
        "2 x DME ranges"
      ],
      "answer": "2 x lines of position from 2 x landmarks"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from point A to B: 420 NM Ground speed: 140 knots TAS: 120 knots Calculate the flight time from position A to B.",
      "choices": [
        "1 hr 37 mins",
        "3 hr 30 mins",
        "3 hr",
        "2 hr 40 mins"
      ],
      "answer": "3 hr"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using a rule-of-thumb, what is the TAS of an aircraft cruising at FL100 at a CAS of 150 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "153 kt",
        "180 kt",
        "170 kt",
        "110 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "180 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is correct as regards the properties of a Great Circle?",
      "choices": [
        "Both vertices of a great circle are positioned at the same latitude and 180\u00b0 apart in longitude on the same hemisphere.",
        "Both vertices of a great circle are situated at the same distance respectively North and South of the Equator and 180\u00b0 apart in longitude.",
        "The intersection point of a great circle and the Equator are named \"the vertices\", which are positioned 180\u00b0 apart in longitude.",
        "The latitudes of both vertices are of different values, the longitudes are equal although respectively East and West."
      ],
      "answer": "Both vertices of a great circle are situated at the same distance respectively North and South of the Equator and 180\u00b0 apart in longitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the velocity vectors commonly used in navigation?",
      "choices": [
        "Air, Ground, Wind",
        "Air, Heading, Drift",
        "Ground. Heading, Drift",
        "Wind, Air, Earth"
      ],
      "answer": "Air, Ground, Wind"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rhumb line on a Direct Mercator chart appears as a:",
      "choices": [
        "small circle concave to the nearer pole.",
        "curve convex to the nearer pole.",
        "complex curve.",
        "straight line."
      ],
      "answer": "straight line."
    },
    {
      "question": "How many position lines must be transferred in order to obtain a position fix?",
      "choices": [
        "2",
        "1",
        "0",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is located on the R-115 radial from a VOR/DME. Local magnetic variation is 12\u00b0E. Ignoring convergency, what is the QDM to the VOR/DME?",
      "choices": [
        "283\u00b0M",
        "103\u00b0M",
        "307\u00b0M",
        "295\u00b0M"
      ],
      "answer": "295\u00b0M"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Q Code for magnetic bearing from a navaid or feature?",
      "choices": [
        "QTE",
        "QUJ",
        "QDM",
        "QDR"
      ],
      "answer": "QDR"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2 An aircraft is flying in an easterly direction on a heading of 089\u00b0M to the south of Sligo (EISG - N) in the Republic of Ireland at a GS of 120 kt. The RBI indicates the following relative bearings to the SLG NDB (N54\u00b043' W008\u00b035'): 15.30 UTC - 343\u00b0 15.45 UTC - 328\u00b0 What is the aircraft's position at 15.45 UTC?",
      "choices": [
        "IBATU",
        "ENULA",
        "NAVEM",
        "MOPOM"
      ],
      "answer": "NAVEM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: GS = 480 kt. Distance from A to B = 5360 NM. What is the time from A to B?",
      "choices": [
        "11 HR 07 MIN",
        "11 HR 06 MIN",
        "11 HR 15 MIN",
        "11 HR 10 MIN"
      ],
      "answer": "11 HR 10 MIN"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which bearings are measured from the local meridian of longitude to the line of direction?",
      "choices": [
        "Compass bearings",
        "Meridian bearings",
        "Magnetic bearings",
        "True bearings"
      ],
      "answer": "True bearings"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is located on the R-352 radial from a VOR/DME. Local magnetic variation is 5\u00b0W. Ignoring convergency, what is the QDM to the VOR/DME?",
      "choices": [
        "352\u00b0M",
        "172\u00b0M",
        "167\u00b0M",
        "177\u00b0M"
      ],
      "answer": "172\u00b0M"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using a rule-of-thumb, what is the TAS of an aircraft cruising at FL50 at a CAS of 100 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "102 kt",
        "101 kt",
        "110 kt",
        "120 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "110 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the formula for calculating the Local Speed of Sound?",
      "choices": [
        "LSS = 38.94 x \u221aTemp (K).",
        "LSS = \u221a38.94 x Temp (K).",
        "LSS = \u221a38.94 x Temp (\u00b0F).",
        "LSS = 38.94 x \u221aTemp (\u00b0C)."
      ],
      "answer": "LSS = 38.94 x \u221aTemp (K)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a magnetic bearing from the station?",
      "choices": [
        "QDR",
        "QDM",
        "QTE",
        "QUJ"
      ],
      "answer": "QDR"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is track error angle calculated?",
      "choices": [
        "TEA = (Distance Off Track \u00f7 Distance Along Track) x 60",
        "TEA = (Distance Along Track x Distance Off Track) \u00f7 60",
        "TEA = (Distance Along Track \u00f7 Distance Off Track) x 60",
        "TEA = (Distance Off Track x Distance Along Track) \u00f7 60"
      ],
      "answer": "TEA = (Distance Off Track \u00f7 Distance Along Track) x 60"
    },
    {
      "question": "How may the difference between a dead reckoning position and a position fix be used to refine navigation solutions?",
      "choices": [
        "Using the Direct To feature on your GNSS receiver (or Sky Demon) to provide an accurate updated track and heading from your present position to your destination and using this information to calculate an accurate updated wind vector",
        "Requesting updated position fixes plus actual wind vectors for each leg of flight from ATC",
        "Measuring planned and actual heading together with planned and actual TAS over a pre-determined period of time",
        "Measuring planned track and track made good together with actual TAS and distance flown over a pre-determined period of time to calculate an accurate wind vector"
      ],
      "answer": "Measuring planned track and track made good together with actual TAS and distance flown over a pre-determined period of time to calculate an accurate wind vector"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying due west between 2 waypoints, A and B, over a distance of 90 nm. At the planned ETO for B, the aircraft\u2019s position is fixed as being 3 nm north of B. What is the TEA?",
      "choices": [
        "2\u00b0",
        "3\u00b0",
        "4\u00b0",
        "1\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "2\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following describes the actual direction of aircraft movement relative to surface of the Earth?",
      "choices": [
        "TRK",
        "TMG",
        "DTK",
        "HDG"
      ],
      "answer": "TMG"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the CTM graph, an aircraft is climbing from FL 100 to FL220 at a constant CAS. What is happening to TAS and MN?",
      "choices": [
        "TAS = increasing, MN = increasing.",
        "TAS = decreasing, MN = increasing.",
        "TAS = increasing, MN = decreasing.",
        "TAS = decreasing, MN = decreasing."
      ],
      "answer": "TAS = increasing, MN = increasing."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a true bearing to the station?",
      "choices": [
        "QDM",
        "QTE",
        "QUJ",
        "QDR"
      ],
      "answer": "QUJ"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where on a Direct Mercator projection is the chart convergency correct compared to the earth convergency?",
      "choices": [
        "At the equator.",
        "At the poles.",
        "All over the chart.",
        "At the two parallels of tangency."
      ],
      "answer": "At the equator."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the 1-in-60 rule?",
      "choices": [
        "For every 1\u00b0 of TEA, an aircraft will be 1 km off track over a distance of 60 nm along track.",
        "For every 1\u00b0 of TEA, an aircraft will be 2 nm off track over a distance of 30 nm along track.",
        "For every 1\u00b0 of TEA, an aircraft will be 1 nm off track over a distance of 60 nm along track.",
        "For every 1\u00b0 of TEA, an aircraft will be 1 nm off track over a distance of 60 km along track."
      ],
      "answer": "For every 1\u00b0 of TEA, an aircraft will be 1 nm off track over a distance of 60 nm along track."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following may be used to calculate the actual GS during flight?",
      "choices": [
        "Time taken to fly between two positively identified line features perpendicular to your planned track",
        "Taking the average of change of relative bearing to two features, following a change of heading at an intermediate checkpoint",
        "(Time to fly between waypoints x 60) \u00f7 Distance between waypoints",
        "Time taken to fly overhead two possibly identified features along your planned track"
      ],
      "answer": "Time taken to fly between two positively identified line features perpendicular to your planned track"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a line of position on an aeronautical chart?",
      "choices": [
        "A QDM from a navaid or feature to an aircraft position.",
        "A great circle from a navaid or feature to an aircraft position.",
        "A rhumb line from an aircraft to a navaid.",
        "A rhumb line from a navaid or feature to an aircraft position."
      ],
      "answer": "A great circle from a navaid or feature to an aircraft position."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the TAS of an aircraft cruising at FL80 (OAT: 00\u00b0C) at a CAS of 130 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "170 kt",
        "147 kt",
        "130 kt",
        "151 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "147 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft\u2019s estimated ground speed is 180 kt. At 13.40 UTC an NDB is on a relative bearing of 030\u00b0 and at 13.55 UTC on a relative bearing of 060\u00b0. What is the range to the NDB at 13.55 UTC?",
      "choices": [
        "55 nm",
        "25 nm",
        "35 nm",
        "45 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "45 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "With which of the following radio navigation aids is magnetic variation applied at the ground station (select all that apply)?",
      "choices": [
        "NDB",
        "DME",
        "VDF",
        "AWR"
      ],
      "answer": "VDF"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following describes the angle applied to the track to calculate the heading?",
      "choices": [
        "TMG",
        "DA",
        "Desired Track",
        "WCA"
      ],
      "answer": "WCA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following radio navigation aids provides distance information?",
      "choices": [
        "NDB",
        "VDF",
        "DME",
        "VOR"
      ],
      "answer": "DME"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the TAS of an aircraft cruising at FL340 (OAT: -50\u00b0C) at a CAS of 320 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "529 kt",
        "555 kt",
        "575 kt",
        "610 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "529 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a QDR of 004\u00b0M from an NDB. Magnetic variation at the aircraft is 12\u00b0E and at the NDB is 10\u00b0E. What is the true bearing from the aircraft to the NDB?",
      "choices": [
        "014\u00b0T",
        "016\u00b0T",
        "194\u00b0T",
        "196\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "196\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "What datum is used for the measurement of average true bearings between two positions on aeronautical charts?",
      "choices": [
        "The observer's local meridian of longitude, at the mid-point",
        "The observer's magnetic meridian, at the mid-point",
        "The Greenwich Meridian, transferred parallel to the observer's location, at the mid-point",
        "Any meridian of longitude"
      ],
      "answer": "The observer's local meridian of longitude, at the mid-point"
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the wind direction/velocity (\u00b0T), given: TAS:135 kt Magnetic track: 144\u00b0 Variation: 12\u00b0W Drift angle: 6\u00b0L Headwind: 15 kt",
      "choices": [
        "189\u00b0/20 kt",
        "200\u00b0/20 kt",
        "087\u00b0/20 kt",
        "177\u00b0/20 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "177\u00b0/20 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is formula for calculating MN?",
      "choices": [
        "MN = TAS x \u221aLSS",
        "MN = TAS x LSS",
        "MN = TAS \u00f7 LSS",
        "MN = TAS \u00f7 \u221aLSS"
      ],
      "answer": "MN = TAS \u00f7 LSS"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a Lambert conformal conic projection with two standard parallels:",
      "choices": [
        "the lines of longitude are shown as parallel straight lines.",
        "the scale is only correct at the parallel of origin.",
        "ail great circles are shown as straight lines.",
        "the scale is only correct along the standard parallels ."
      ],
      "answer": "the scale is only correct along the standard parallels ."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the primary factor affecting mach numbers?",
      "choices": [
        "Pressure.",
        "Humidity.",
        "Temperature.",
        "Density."
      ],
      "answer": "Temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "At what airspeed does compressibility correction need to be taken into account?",
      "choices": [
        "TAS = 300 kt",
        "CAS = 300 kt",
        "TAS = 200 kt",
        "TAS = 350 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "TAS = 300 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the TAS of an aircraft cruising at FL140 (OAT: -10\u00b0C) at a CAS of 200 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "258 kt",
        "248 kt",
        "242 kt",
        "160 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "248 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a Polar Stereographic chart showing the South Pole, a straight line joins position A 70\u00b0S, 065\u00b0E to position B 70\u00b0S, 025\u00b0W. What is the approximate true track on departure from position A?",
      "choices": [
        "315\u00b0",
        "225\u00b0",
        "135\u00b0",
        "250\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "225\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following terms defines the planned direction of an aircraft in flight?",
      "choices": [
        "Track Made Good (TMG).",
        "Relative Bearing (RB).",
        "Heading (HDG).",
        "Track (TK)."
      ],
      "answer": "Heading (HDG)."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a Lambert conformal conic chart the convergence of the meridians:",
      "choices": [
        "is the same as earth convergency at the parallel of origin.",
        "equals earth convergency at the standard parallels.",
        "is zero throughout the chart.",
        "varies as the secant of the latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "is the same as earth convergency at the parallel of origin."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL70 at an OAT of +25\u00b0C. Determine the change in TAS when the CAS is reduced from 130 kt to 105 kt:",
      "choices": [
        "26 kt.",
        "29 kt.",
        "27 kt.",
        "22 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "29 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following radio navigation aids are used to establish a Rho/Theta position fix?",
      "choices": [
        "VOR and DME",
        "VOR and VOR",
        "NDB and DME",
        "VDF and VOR"
      ],
      "answer": "VOR and DME"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the relationship between Wind Correction Angle and Drift?",
      "choices": [
        "Equal magnitude, opposite sign",
        "Opposite magnitude, opposite sign",
        "Equal sign, equal magnitude",
        "Equal sign, opposite magnitude"
      ],
      "answer": "Equal magnitude, opposite sign"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying due west between 2 waypoints, A and B, over a distance of 140 nm. At the planned ETO for B, the aircraft\u2019s position is fixed as being 3.5 nm north of B. What is the TEA?",
      "choices": [
        "2.5\u00b0",
        "3.0\u00b0",
        "1.5\u00b0",
        "1.0\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "1.5\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "The sighting angle to a feature at sea level is estimated as being 10\u00b0. The aircraft is currently at FL 200. What is the approximate distance to the feature?",
      "choices": [
        "15 nm",
        "25 nm",
        "20 nm",
        "10 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "20 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "What datum is used for the measurement of average magnetic bearings between two positions on aeronautical charts?",
      "choices": [
        "The observer's magnetic meridian, at the mid-point",
        "The Greenwich Meridian, transferred parallel to the observer's location, at the mid-point",
        "Any meridian of longitude",
        "The observer's local meridian of longitude, at the mid-point"
      ],
      "answer": "The observer's local meridian of longitude, at the mid-point"
    },
    {
      "question": "How would a great circle between 80\u00b000'N, 010\u00b000'W and 80\u00b000'N, 020\u00b000'W appear on a Polar Stereographic chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Aligned with a parallel of latitude.",
        "A curve concave to the North Pole.",
        "A curve convex to the North Pole.",
        "A straight line along the parallel ."
      ],
      "answer": "A curve concave to the North Pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which radio navigation aids are used for a rho/rho position fix?",
      "choices": [
        "DME/DME",
        "VOR/VOR",
        "NDB/NDB",
        "VDF/VDF"
      ],
      "answer": "DME/DME"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum difference in distance when proceeding along the great circle between two positions, instead of the rhumb line, will occur",
      "choices": [
        "on North-South tracks at high latitudes.",
        "on North-South tracks at low latitudes.",
        "on East-West tracks at high latitudes.",
        "on East-West tracks at low latitudes."
      ],
      "answer": "on East-West tracks at high latitudes."
    },
    {
      "question": "Two places are situated on the same parallel in the Southern Hemisphere. The great circle, rhumb line and the straight line between these places are drawn on a Polar Stereographic Projection. Which statement is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "The correct sequence from North to South is: Great circle, straight line, rhumb line.",
        "The great circle is situated between the parallel and the straight line, because the concave side of the great circle is always pointed towards the pole.",
        "The rhumb line is situated between the great circle and the straight line because the shortest distance between to places on Earth is the great circle.",
        "The great circle is situated between the parallel and the straight line, because the concave side of the great circle is always pointed towards the equator."
      ],
      "answer": "The great circle is situated between the parallel and the straight line, because the concave side of the great circle is always pointed towards the pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Earth convergency for a straight line between position A (37\u00b045'S, 170\u00b025'W) and position B (37\u00b045'S 168\u00b035'E)?",
      "choices": [
        "32.31\u00b0",
        "24.79\u00b0",
        "12.86\u00b0",
        "64.62\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "12.86\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is located on the R-153 radial from a VOR/DME. Local magnetic variation is 12\u00b0E. Ignoring convergency, what is the QUJ to the VOR/DME?",
      "choices": [
        "357\u00b0T",
        "333\u00b0T",
        "345\u00b0T",
        "165\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "345\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "How are CAS and TAS related on the CRP-5?",
      "choices": [
        "AIRSPEED window for Pressure Altitude and OAT - CAS on inner scale and TAS on outer scale",
        "AIRSPEED window for Pressure Altitude and OAT - CAS on outer scale and TAS on inner scale",
        "ALTITUDE window for Pressure Altitude and OAT - CAS on outer scale and TAS on inner scale",
        "AIRSPEED window for Pressure Altitude and ISA Temperature - CAS on inner scale and TAS on outer scale"
      ],
      "answer": "AIRSPEED window for Pressure Altitude and OAT - CAS on inner scale and TAS on outer scale"
    },
    {
      "question": "From which of the following radio navigation aids is bearing established by the calculation of the phase difference between the reference and variable phase signals?",
      "choices": [
        "NDB",
        "VDF",
        "DME",
        "VOR"
      ],
      "answer": "VOR"
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Polar Stereographic Projection are: __________, stereographic projection.",
      "choices": [
        "Conical",
        "Cylindrical",
        "Conformic",
        "Azimuthal"
      ],
      "answer": "Azimuthal"
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Lambert Conformal Conical Projection are: Scale is __________ along a parallel of latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "varying proprotionally to the secant of the latitude",
        "Constant",
        "Decreasing",
        "Increasing"
      ],
      "answer": "Constant"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the Jeppesen GSPRM, IFR Chart E(HI)5, EUROPE-CANARY ISLANDS INSET, what is the constant of the cone for this chart?",
      "choices": [
        "0.54464",
        "0.91355",
        "0.64941",
        "0.83867"
      ],
      "answer": "0.54464"
    },
    {
      "question": "\u2018Chart Convergency\u2019 = Difference in __________ between 2 positions on great circle track, drawn on chart.",
      "choices": [
        "Relative Bearing",
        "Latitude",
        "Longitude",
        "Bearing"
      ],
      "answer": "Bearing"
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Direct Mercator projection are: (Parallel of) Origin = ________",
      "choices": [
        "Standard Meridian of Tangency",
        "Great Meridian of Tangency",
        "Equator",
        "Standard Parallel of Tangency"
      ],
      "answer": "Equator"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a Mercator chart at the latitude of 30\u00b0N, a distance of 8.3 cm on the chart equals to 40 NM on the ground. What is the same distance on the ground at a latitude of 45\u00b0N?",
      "choices": [
        "91 km",
        "74 km",
        "49 km",
        "60 km"
      ],
      "answer": "60 km"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that the circumference of the Earth at S08\u00b0 is represented by a straight line on the chart, 145 cm long, what is the approximate scale of the chart at N15\u00b0?",
      "choices": [
        "1:36 350 000",
        "1:27 035 000",
        "1:26 650 000",
        "1:27 320 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1:26 650 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is the ABBA formula used to solve distance problems on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Distance \u03d5 A x Cosine \u03d5 B = Distance \u03d5 B \u00f7 Cosine \u03d5 A",
        "Distance \u03d5 A x Secant \u03d5 B = Distance \u03d5 B x Secant \u03d5 A",
        "Distance \u03d5 A x Cosine \u03d5 B = Distance \u03d5 B x Cosine \u03d5 A",
        "Distance \u03d5 A \u00f7 Cosine \u03d5 B = Distance \u03d5 B x Cosine \u03d5 A"
      ],
      "answer": "Distance \u03d5 A x Cosine \u03d5 B = Distance \u03d5 B x Cosine \u03d5 A"
    },
    {
      "question": "The cone of projection, from which a Lamberts conformal conical chart has been derived, circumscribes an angle of 285\u00b0. What is the parallel of origin of the projection (degrees and minutes only)?",
      "choices": [
        "52\u00b020\u2019",
        "37\u00b066\u2019",
        "52\u00b034'",
        "37\u00b040\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "52\u00b020\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line is drawn on a polar stereographic chart from A (S75\u00b0 W050\u00b0) to B (S75\u00b0x\u00b0). The great circle track measured at A = 130\u00b0T and at B = 050\u00b0T. What is the longitude of B?",
      "choices": [
        "E050\u00b0",
        "E030\u00b0",
        "W130\u00b0",
        "E010\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "E030\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that the earth distance between two meridians of longitude shown on a Direct Mercator chart at S60\u00b0 is 300 nm, what is the approximate earth distance (nm) between the same two meridians at the Equator?",
      "choices": [
        "900 nm",
        "150 nm",
        "300 nm",
        "600 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "600 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line, representing a great circle track, is drawn on a Lambert\u2019s Conformal Conical Chart with standard parallels at S22\u00ba and S38\u00ba from A (S32\u00ba30\u2019 E008\u00ba45\u2019) to B (S32\u00ba30\u2019 E020\u00ba45\u2019). What is the great circle track bearing on departing A?",
      "choices": [
        "093\u00b0T",
        "096\u00b0T",
        "084\u00b0T",
        "087\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "093\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Polar Stereographic Projection are: (Parallel of) Origin = __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Standard Parallel",
        "Equator",
        "Azimuth",
        "Pole"
      ],
      "answer": "Pole"
    },
    {
      "question": "The scale on a Direct Mercator chart is 1:1 500 000 at S30\u00b0, the approximate scale of the chart at N60\u00b0 is:",
      "choices": [
        "1:250 000",
        "1:500 000",
        "1:1 000 000",
        "1:865 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1:865 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying from A(60\u00b0N, 060\u00b0W) to B(60\u00b0N,070\u00b0W). The true great circle track, when passing 064\u00b0W will be:",
      "choices": [
        "265.7\u00b0",
        "270.8\u00b0",
        "277.8\u00b0",
        "270.0\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "270.8\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Lambert Conformal Conical Projection are: Usable area = __________\u00b0 north and __________\u00b0 south of Parallel of Origin.",
      "choices": [
        "12; 24.",
        "12; 12.",
        "24; 12.",
        "12; 06."
      ],
      "answer": "12; 12."
    },
    {
      "question": "How are rhumb lines depicted on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Straight lines.",
        "Curved lines, concave to the nearer pole.",
        "Curved lines, convex to the nearer pole.",
        "Complex curves."
      ],
      "answer": "Straight lines."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which point on the surface of the Earth can never be projected onto a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "The poles.",
        "The Equator.",
        "The standard parallels.",
        "The parallel of origin."
      ],
      "answer": "The poles."
    },
    {
      "question": "Conversion angle = \u00bd x __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Convergency",
        "Change of latitude",
        "Conversion",
        "Change of longitude"
      ],
      "answer": "Convergency"
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Lambert Conformal Conical Projection are: Scale __________ north and south of Parallel of Origin.",
      "choices": [
        "increases",
        "decreases",
        "varies proprotionally to the secant of the latitude",
        "remains constant"
      ],
      "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that the circumference of the Earth at N52\u00b0 is represented by a straight line on the chart, 110 cm long, what is the approximate scale of the chart at S30\u00b0?",
      "choices": [
        "1:27 320 000",
        "1:31 500 000",
        "1:27 035 000",
        "1:26 650 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1:31 500 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "Aeronautical charts are required to be __________, which requires: A right-angled graticule. Constant scale in all directions.",
      "choices": [
        "Divergent",
        "Confirmative",
        "Conformal",
        "Constant"
      ],
      "answer": "Conformal"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the formula, in simplest terms, for calculating convergency on a Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Convergency = Change of Longitude.",
        "Convergency = Change of Longitude x n.",
        "Convergency = Change of Latitude x sine Mean Longitude.",
        "Convergency = Change of Longitude x sine Mean Latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Convergency = Change of Longitude x n."
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line passing through the pole is a...?",
      "choices": [
        "Straight line only.",
        "Great circle and a rhumb line.",
        "Great circle only.",
        "Rhumb line only."
      ],
      "answer": "Great circle and a rhumb line."
    },
    {
      "question": "A Polar Stereographic chart is used for navigation. The straight line between A 75\u00b0 00'.0N, 166\u00b0 00'.0E and B 78\u00b0 00'.0N, 154\u00b0 00'.0E is drawn on this chart. The True Track angle of the Rhumb line is 317\u00b0. Calculate the direction T of the straight line in position A .",
      "choices": [
        "305\u00b0",
        "323\u00b0",
        "329\u00b0",
        "311\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "323\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Applying a ratio of __________, when presented with a scale or distance at one latitude (\u03a6), the ABBA formulae can be used to calculate scales and distances at any other latitudes:",
      "choices": [
        "Sines",
        "Logarithms",
        "Tangents",
        "Cosines"
      ],
      "answer": "Cosines"
    },
    {
      "question": "How does scale vary on a Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Scale contracts outside and expands inside the standard parallels.",
        "Scale expands outside and contracts inside the standard parallels.",
        "Scale expands outside and contracts inside the Parallel of Origin.",
        "Scale has an absolute value and does not vary across the chart."
      ],
      "answer": "Scale expands outside and contracts inside the standard parallels."
    },
    {
      "question": "Scale is constant on a Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart ...?",
      "choices": [
        "Across the whole chart.",
        "Along a parallel of latitude.",
        "Along a meridian of longitude.",
        "At the standard parallels only."
      ],
      "answer": "Along a parallel of latitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Polar Stereographic Projection are: Parallels of latitude = parallel, __________ lines, __________ to nearer pole.",
      "choices": [
        "curved; converging",
        "curved; concave",
        "straight; concave",
        "straight; converging"
      ],
      "answer": "curved; concave"
    },
    {
      "question": "Great circles (apart from the Equator and meridians) = Curved lines, ________ to origin (Equator).",
      "choices": [
        "proportionate",
        "concave",
        "convex",
        "parallel"
      ],
      "answer": "concave"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line, representing a great circle track, is drawn on a Lambert\u2019s Conformal Conical Chart with standard parallels at N42\u00b0 and N66\u00b0 from A (N42\u00b030\u2019 E022\u00b045\u2019) to B (N47\u00b030\u2019 X\u00b0). The great circle track measured at A = 085\u00b0T and at B = 099\u00b0T. What is the approximate longitude of B?",
      "choices": [
        "E040\u00b000\u2019",
        "E031\u00b030\u2019",
        "E005\u00b030\u2019",
        "E014\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "E040\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "The convergence factor of a southern hemisphere Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart is stated as being 0.66913. What are the possible standard parallels on this chart?",
      "choices": [
        "S29\u00b000\u2019 & S47\u00b000\u2019",
        "S39\u00b000\u2019 & S47\u00b000\u2019",
        "S30\u00b000\u2019 & S44\u00b000\u2019",
        "S35\u00b000\u2019 & S49\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "S35\u00b000\u2019 & S49\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying from A (24\u00b032'N, 166\u00b036'W) to B (32\u00b046'N, 173\u00b020'E).The rhumb line track is 295\u00b0 (T). Determine the initial great circle track ('T):",
      "choices": [
        "285.4\u00b0",
        "304.6\u00b0",
        "290.2\u00b0",
        "299.8\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "299.8\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of projection is a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Stereographic.",
        "Azimuthal.",
        "Conical.",
        "Cylindrical."
      ],
      "answer": "Cylindrical."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the parallel of origin on a Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart?",
      "choices": [
        "The average of the standard parallels.",
        "It is equal to the standard parallel.",
        "The difference between the standard parallels.",
        "The sum of the standard parallels."
      ],
      "answer": "The average of the standard parallels."
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Lambert Conformal Conical Projection are: Defined by __________ x Standard Parallels (intersections of \u2018internal\u2019 secant cone with Earth surface).",
      "choices": [
        "5",
        "2",
        "10",
        "4"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that the earth distance between two meridians of longitude shown on a Direct Mercator chart at N00\u00b0 is 300 nm, what is the approximate earth distance (nm) between the same two meridians at N60\u00b0?",
      "choices": [
        "300 nm",
        "15 nm",
        "600 nm",
        "150 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "150 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the Jeppesen GSPRM Radar Vectoring Chart for Alicante, Spain (10-1R), what is the highest elevation shown on the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "6631 m amsl",
        "6000 ft amsl",
        "6631 ft agl",
        "6631 ft amsl"
      ],
      "answer": "6631 ft amsl"
    },
    {
      "question": "The convergence factor of a southern hemisphere Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart is stated as being 0.57357. At which latitude is chart convergency equal to earth convergency?",
      "choices": [
        "S35\u00b000\u2019",
        "S42\u00b000\u2019",
        "N38\u00b000\u2019",
        "S55\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "S42\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that the chart distance between S20\u00b0 E170\u00b0 and S20\u00b0 W160\u00b0 on a Direct Mercator chart is 40 cm, what is the scale of the chart at N40\u00b0?",
      "choices": [
        "1:7 810 000",
        "1:6 385 000",
        "1:1 065 000",
        "1:7 215 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1:6 385 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "When proceeding along a great circle track between 2 points on the same parallel of latitude, the position nearest the pole is known as the...?",
      "choices": [
        "Vertex.",
        "Vortex.",
        "Cervix.",
        "Cortex."
      ],
      "answer": "Vertex."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that the nominal scale of a Direct Mercator chart is defined as being 1:1 000 000, what is the scale of the chart at N60\u00b0?",
      "choices": [
        "1:500 000",
        "1:1 000 000",
        "1:250 000",
        "1:2 000 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1:500 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the origin on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "The pole of the hemisphere being covered by the chart.",
        "It is equal to the standard parallel.",
        "The average of the standard parallels.",
        "The Equator."
      ],
      "answer": "The Equator."
    },
    {
      "question": "This question is designed to test several areas of knowledge: A pilot has a Direct Mercator chart of Equatorial Africa, with a nominal scale of 1:4 000 000. A straight line, 44.5 cm long, is drawn on a bearing of 090\u00b0T from the departure aerodrome at N09\u00b030\u2019 W006\u00b030\u2019 to the destination aerodrome. Given a departure time of 13.45 UTC on 15th April 2018 and an average groundspeed of 340 kt, what is the approximate location of and ETA at the destination aerodrome?",
      "choices": [
        "Nigeria - N09\u00b030\u2019 E006\u00b030\u2019 - 16.32 UTC on 15th April 2018",
        "Nigeria - N09\u00b030\u2019 E003\u00b020\u2019 - 15.29 UTC on 15th April 2018",
        "Nigeria - N09\u00b030\u2019 E009\u00b045\u2019 - 16.35 UTC on 15th April 2018",
        "Chad - N09\u00b030\u2019 E016\u00b030\u2019 - 07.06 UTC on 16th April 2018"
      ],
      "answer": "Nigeria - N09\u00b030\u2019 E009\u00b045\u2019 - 16.35 UTC on 15th April 2018"
    },
    {
      "question": "Chart Convergency = Change of __________ x n",
      "choices": [
        "Longitude",
        "Heading",
        "Latitude",
        "Relative Bearing"
      ],
      "answer": "Longitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is depicted by contour lines on a chart, which are closely spaced together?",
      "choices": [
        "Flat terrain.",
        "Uneven surface.",
        "Steep terrain.",
        "The edge of a significant water feature."
      ],
      "answer": "Steep terrain."
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line is drawn on a polar stereographic chart from A to B (S80\u00b0 W010\u00b0). The initial track measured at A = 103\u00b0T and at B = 060\u00b0T. What is the longitude of A?",
      "choices": [
        "033\u00b0E",
        "053\u00b0W",
        "012\u00b0E",
        "032\u00b0W"
      ],
      "answer": "053\u00b0W"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where, in general terms, is chart convergency equal to Earth convergency on a chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Pole.",
        "Meridian of longitude.",
        "Origin.",
        "Equator."
      ],
      "answer": "Origin."
    },
    {
      "question": "Scale expands with increasing latitude, away from the Equator, proportional to the secant (1 / cosine) of the latitude. As scale ________, the denominator of the scale fraction reduces. As scale ________, the denominator of the scale fraction increases.",
      "choices": [
        "contracts; contracts",
        "contracts; expands",
        "expands; contracts",
        "expands; expands"
      ],
      "answer": "expands; contracts"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line is drawn on a Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart, having standard parallels at S30\u00b0 and S40\u00b0, between A (S33\u00b0 E010\u00b0) and B (S37\u00b0 E012\u00b0). If anything, how will the great circle followed by the aircraft differ from the straight line on the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "It will follow a slight curve, towards the Equator, concave to the pole.",
        "It will follow the path of the straight line.",
        "It will follow a slight curve, away from the Equator, convex to the pole.",
        "It will follow a slight curve, concave to the pole, until it reaches S35\u00b0, where it will curve in the opposite direction, convex to the pole."
      ],
      "answer": "It will follow a slight curve, concave to the pole, until it reaches S35\u00b0, where it will curve in the opposite direction, convex to the pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the origin of a polar stereographic chart?",
      "choices": [
        "The opposite pole",
        "The Equator",
        "The pole",
        "Arctic Circle"
      ],
      "answer": "The pole"
    },
    {
      "question": "A chart has a scale of 1:500 000. On a chart, the distance between points A and B is measured as 38 cm. What is the approximate distance between A and B?",
      "choices": [
        "102 km",
        "190 nm",
        "190 sm",
        "103 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "103 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line is drawn on a Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart, having standard parallels at N68\u00b0 and N78\u00b0, between A (N69\u00b0 W125\u00b0) and B (N72\u00b0 W135\u00b0). If anything, how will the great circle followed by the aircraft differ from the straight line on the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "It will follow the path of the straight line.",
        "It will follow a slight curve, concave to the pole, until it reaches the mid-point, where it will curve in the opposite direction, convex to the pole.",
        "It will follow a slight curve, towards the Equator, concave to the pole.",
        "It will follow a slight curve, away from the Equator, convex to the pole."
      ],
      "answer": "It will follow a slight curve, towards the Equator, concave to the pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Lambert Conformal Conical Projection are: Meridians of longitude = vertical, straight lines, converging towards nearer pole. Parallels of latitude = __________, curved lines, concave to nearer pole.",
      "choices": [
        "Complex",
        "Parallel",
        "Diverging",
        "Converging"
      ],
      "answer": "Parallel"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the approximate usable area of a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "The Equator to N70\u00b0.",
        "12\u00b0 either side of the parallel of origin.",
        "500 nm either side of the great circle of tangency",
        "N20\u00b0 - S20\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "500 nm either side of the great circle of tangency"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the Jeppesen GSPRM VFR +GPS Chart ED-4, what are the features at (N48\u00b039\u2019 E014\u00b048\u2019)?",
      "choices": [
        "Spot height 3055 ft amsl, lit obstacle <1000 ft agl.",
        "Spot height 3055 m amsl, lit obstacle >1000 ft agl.",
        "Spot height 3055 m amsl, lit obstacle <1000 ft agl.",
        "Spot height 3055 ft amsl, lit obstacle >1000 ft agl."
      ],
      "answer": "Spot height 3055 ft amsl, lit obstacle <1000 ft agl."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the approximate scale of a chart where a line 420 mm long represents an earth distance of 539 nm?",
      "choices": [
        "1:237 500",
        "1:23 750",
        "1:23 750 000",
        "1:2 375 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1:2 375 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a Mercator chart, at latitude 60\u00b0N, the distance measured between W002\u00b0 and E008\u00b0 is 20 cm. The scale of this chart at latitude 60\u00b0N is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "1: 278 000",
        "1: 556 000",
        "1: 5 560 000",
        "1: 2 780 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1: 2 780 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "The convergence factor of a northern hemisphere Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart is stated as being 0.79335. At which latitude is chart convergency equal to earth convergency?",
      "choices": [
        "N38\u00b025\u2019",
        "S52\u00b030\u2019",
        "N52\u00b030\u2019",
        "N37\u00b030\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "N52\u00b030\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a Direct Mercator projection chart, the scale at 23\u00b0N is 1 : 2 761 515. What is the scale of the same chart at 56\u00b0N?",
      "choices": [
        "1 : 1 544 220",
        "1 : 1 421 462",
        "1 : 1 677 579",
        "1 : 2 541 988"
      ],
      "answer": "1 : 1 677 579"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where \u2018Scale\u2019 is expressed without the numerator \u20181\u2019, and simply in terms of the denominator of the fraction, the formula to solve scale problems can be transposed. Which of the following is NOT a transposition of that formula?",
      "choices": [
        "Earth Distance = Scale x Chart Distance.",
        "Chart Distance = Earth Distance \u00f7 Scale.",
        "Scale = Earth Distance \u00f7 Chart Distance.",
        "Scale = Chart Distance x Earth Distance."
      ],
      "answer": "Scale = Chart Distance x Earth Distance."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the approximate scale of a chart where a line 15 cm long represents an earth distance of 28 nm?",
      "choices": [
        "1:3 450 000",
        "1:345 000",
        "1900-01-02 10:30:00",
        "1:34 500"
      ],
      "answer": "1:345 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Polar Stereographic Projection are: Scale errors <1%. Usable area = __________\u00b0 - __________\u00b0 latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "50; 70",
        "10; 30",
        "70; 90",
        "20; 40"
      ],
      "answer": "70; 90"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is normally used to describe scale?",
      "choices": [
        "Scale is a ratio of chart distance, in metric units, to earth distance, in imperial units.",
        "Scale is the ratio of earth distance to chart distance, in unequal units.",
        "Scale is a ratio of chart distance, always in centimetres, to earth distance, always in nautical miles.",
        "Scale is a ratio of chart distance to earth distance, in equal units."
      ],
      "answer": "Scale is a ratio of chart distance to earth distance, in equal units."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are contour lines on a chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Lines joining points of equal importance.",
        "Lines joining points of unequal elevation.",
        "Lines joining points of equal elevation.",
        "Lines joining points of equal geographic interest."
      ],
      "answer": "Lines joining points of equal elevation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which famous Swedish musical artists will assist you in calculating scales and distances at different latitudes on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "ACE OF BASE",
        "ABBA",
        "ROXETTE",
        "AH HA"
      ],
      "answer": "ABBA"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the limit of distortion of scale, shapes and lines of latitude and longitude on aeronautical charts used for navigation?",
      "choices": [
        "0.02",
        "0.1",
        "0.01",
        "0.05"
      ],
      "answer": "0.01"
    },
    {
      "question": "A chart has a scale of 1:1 000 000. The distance between positions A and B is known to be 225 nm. What is the approximate length of a line drawn on the chart between A and B?",
      "choices": [
        "41.7 mm",
        "416.7 cm",
        "4.2 m",
        "41.7 cm"
      ],
      "answer": "41.7 cm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Scale is defined on a Direct Mercator chart at the ________.",
      "choices": [
        "Vertex",
        "Standard Parallels",
        "Pole",
        "Equator"
      ],
      "answer": "Equator"
    },
    {
      "question": "In simple terms, how does scale vary on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Scale has an absolute value and does not vary across the chart.",
        "Scale expands towards the Equator.",
        "Scale contracts away from the Equator.",
        "Scale expands away from the Equator."
      ],
      "answer": "Scale expands away from the Equator."
    },
    {
      "question": "How are meridians of longitude depicted on aeronautical charts?",
      "choices": [
        "Straight lines, converging to the nearer pole.",
        "Curved lines, concave to the nearer pole.",
        "Curved lines, convex to the nearer pole.",
        "Straight lines."
      ],
      "answer": "Straight lines."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that the earth distance between N45\u00b0 W100\u00b0 and N45\u00b0 W080\u00b0 on a Direct Mercator chart is 848.5 nm, what is the approximate earth distance between the same 2 meridians at N10\u00b0?",
      "choices": [
        "1182 nm",
        "591 nm",
        "609 nm",
        "208 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "1182 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the formula, in simplest terms, for calculating convergency on a polar stereographic chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Convergency = Change of Latitude.",
        "Convergency = Change of Longitude",
        "Convergency = \u00bd x Change of Longitude.",
        "Convergency = \u00bd x Change of Longitude x n."
      ],
      "answer": "Convergency = Change of Longitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "In mathematical terms, how does scale vary on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Scale expands proportional to the secant of the latitude, north and south of the Equator.",
        "Scale has an absolute value and does not vary across the chart.",
        "Scale expands inversely proportional to the secant of the latitude, north and south of the Equator.",
        "Scale expands proportional to the cosine of the latitude, north and south of the Equator."
      ],
      "answer": "Scale expands proportional to the secant of the latitude, north and south of the Equator."
    },
    {
      "question": "A line, 22 cm long, is drawn on a chart between S35\u00b0 E120\u00b0 and S38\u00b0 E120\u00b0. What is the approximate scale of the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "1: 750 000",
        "1: 900 000",
        "1: 1 500 000",
        "1: 6 000 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1: 1 500 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the Jeppesen GSPRM, IFR Chart E(LO)1, what is the constant of the cone for this chart?",
      "choices": [
        "0.97815",
        "0.62932",
        "1.2349",
        "0.77715"
      ],
      "answer": "0.77715"
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of aeronautical chart is projected from a point on the Earth, directly opposite the chart origin?",
      "choices": [
        "Polar Stereographic.",
        "Mercator's Non-azimuthal.",
        "Lambert's Orthographic.",
        "Lambert's Gnomonic."
      ],
      "answer": "Polar Stereographic."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is layer tinting used to define elevation on a chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Different colours indicate specific steepness of elevation.",
        "Different colours indicate points of equal elevation.",
        "Different colours indicate the change from land to water features.",
        "Different colours indicate ranges of elevation, between defined limits."
      ],
      "answer": "Different colours indicate ranges of elevation, between defined limits."
    },
    {
      "question": "Relief is usually portrayed by combinations of: 1) contour lines 2) shading 3) frequencies 4) colours 5) spot heights 6) graduated scale",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 4, 5 and 6.",
        "1, 2, 3, 4 and 5.",
        "2, 3, 4 and 5.",
        "1, 2, 4 and 5."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 4 and 5."
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the Jeppesen GSPRM, IFR Chart E(LO)3, a straight line is drawn between CORK VOR/DME (CRK) (N51\u00b050\u2019 W008\u00b030\u2019) and BROOKMANS PARK VOR/DME (BPK) (N51\u00b045\u2019 W000\u00b005\u2019). Referring to the BRECON VOR/DME (BCN) (N51\u00b045\u2019 W003\u00b015\u2019), where will the great circle pass, relative to BCN?",
      "choices": [
        "It will follow a slight curve, away from the Equator, convex to the pole, to the north of BCN",
        "It will follow a slight curve, away from the Equator, convex to the pole, to the south of BCN",
        "It will follow the path of the straight line, straight over the top of BCN",
        "It will follow a slight curve, towards the Equator, concave to the pole, to the south of BCN"
      ],
      "answer": "It will follow a slight curve, away from the Equator, convex to the pole, to the north of BCN"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a line of position drawn on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "As a curved line, convex to the parallel of origin, from the feature or navaid to the aircraft.",
        "As a straight line from the aircraft to the feature or navaid.",
        "As a straight line from the feature or navaid to the aircraft.",
        "As a curved line, concave to the parallel of origin, from the feature or navaid to the aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "As a straight line from the feature or navaid to the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "The scale on a Direct Mercator chart is 1:2 000 000 at S45\u00b0, the approximate scale of the chart at N45\u00b0 is:",
      "choices": [
        "1:250 000",
        "1:500 000",
        "1:2 000 000",
        "1:1 000 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1:2 000 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line, representing a great circle track, is drawn from A (N40\u00ba00\u2019 W010\u00ba00\u2019) to B (N50\u00ba00\u2019 E010\u00ba30\u2019) on a Lambert\u2019s Conformal Conical Chart with standard parallels at N36\u00ba and N50\u00ba. Flying from A to B, the aircraft crosses A on a track bearing of 048\u00baT. What is the great circle track when passing B?",
      "choices": [
        "041\u00b0T",
        "055\u00b0T",
        "034\u00b0T",
        "062\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "062\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "What, in general terms, is the name of the point where a chart makes contact with the reduced Earth?",
      "choices": [
        "Origin.",
        "Meridian of longitude.",
        "Pole.",
        "Equator."
      ],
      "answer": "Origin."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a representation of scale on an aeronautical chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Fraction.",
        "Ratio.",
        "Numerical relationship of coordinates.",
        "Relationship of distance units."
      ],
      "answer": "Numerical relationship of coordinates."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is following the 45\u00b0N parallel of latitude. The track followed is a:",
      "choices": [
        "constant-heading track",
        "rhumb line",
        "constant-drift track",
        "great circle"
      ],
      "answer": "rhumb line"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line is drawn on a Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart, having standard parallels at S48\u00b0 and S62\u00b0, between A (S57\u00b0 E013\u00b0) and B (S61\u00b0 E018\u00b0). If anything, how will the great circle followed by the aircraft differ from the straight line on the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "It will follow a slight curve, towards the Equator, concave to the pole.",
        "It will follow a slight curve, away from the Equator, convex to the pole.",
        "It will follow a slight curve, concave to the pole, until it reaches the mid-point, where it will curve in the opposite direction, convex to the pole.",
        "It will follow the path of the straight line."
      ],
      "answer": "It will follow a slight curve, away from the Equator, convex to the pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is scale shown on charts?",
      "choices": [
        "Distance rule.",
        "Using isoscalic lines, to depict areas of common scale.",
        "Relationship of distance units.",
        "Ratio."
      ],
      "answer": "Using layer tinting, to depict areas of common scale."
    },
    {
      "question": "Two locations A and B have the same latitude and are located on a meridian and anti-meridian. On a Lambert conical projection map, the angle between these two meridians is 156\u00b0. What is the parallel of the origin of this map?",
      "choices": [
        "30\u00b0 N or S.",
        "55\u00b0 N or S.",
        "60\u00b0 N or S.",
        "35\u00b0 N or S."
      ],
      "answer": "60\u00b0 N or S."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a Lambert conformal projection the chart convergency between two positions depends on:",
      "choices": [
        "the difference in longitude of the two positions only.",
        "the latitude of the parallel of origin only.",
        "the difference in longitude and the mean latitude of the two positions.",
        "the difference in longitude of the two positions and the latitude of the parallel of origin ."
      ],
      "answer": "the difference in longitude of the two positions and the latitude of the parallel of origin ."
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2, what is the Grid MORA for Kerry aerodrome (N52\u00b011\u2019 W009\u00b032\u2019)?",
      "choices": [
        "4400 ft amsl",
        "4400 ft agl",
        "44 000 ft amsl",
        "4400 m amsl"
      ],
      "answer": "4400 ft amsl"
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Polar Stereographic Projection are: Scale __________ with decreasing latitude, away from the pole. Scale is __________ along a parallel of latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "reduces; variable",
        "reduces; constant",
        "expands; variable",
        "expands; constant"
      ],
      "answer": "expands; constant"
    },
    {
      "question": "The famous Swedish pop group of the 1970\u2019s and 1980\u2019s who will assist you in calculating scales and distances at different latitudes on a Direct Mercator chart is ________.",
      "choices": [
        "AABB",
        "BABA",
        "ABBA",
        "BBAA"
      ],
      "answer": "ABBA"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line, representing a great circle track, is drawn from A (S34\u00ba30\u2019 W140\u00ba15\u2019) to B (S42\u00ba45\u2019 W148\u00ba45\u2019) on a Lambert\u2019s Conformal Conical Chart with standard parallels at S38\u00ba and S52\u00ba. Flying from A to B, the aircraft crosses A on a track bearing of 262\u00baT. What is the great circle track when passing B?",
      "choices": [
        "268\u00b0T",
        "265\u00b0T",
        "256\u00b0T",
        "259\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "268\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "A line, 29.5 cm long, is drawn on a chart between N72\u00b0 E019\u00b0 and N77\u00b0 W161\u00b0. What is the approximate scale of the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "1: 11 675 000",
        "1: 900 000",
        "1: 56 000 000",
        "1: 3 125 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1: 11 675 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Lambert Conformal Conical Projection are: Scale is defined at the Standard Parallels, __________ outside Standard Parallels, __________ inside Standard Parallels.",
      "choices": [
        "expands; contracts",
        "contract; contracts",
        "expands; expands",
        "contract; expands"
      ],
      "answer": "expands; contracts"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a Lambert conformal chart, the given scale differs from the scale at latitudes between the standard parallels. The limitation for this difference ls a maximum of:",
      "choices": [
        "1% of the scale at the standard parallels.",
        "0.1% of the scale at the parallel of origin.",
        "0.01% of the scale of the globe.",
        "0.01% of the given scale in the index."
      ],
      "answer": "1% of the scale at the standard parallels."
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the Jeppesen GSPRM VFR +GPS Chart ED-4, what is the height of the elevation at Kohout (N48\u00b046\u2019 E014\u00b034\u2019)?",
      "choices": [
        "2854 ft amsl",
        "2854 m amsl",
        "2041 ft amsl",
        "2854 ft agl"
      ],
      "answer": "2854 ft amsl"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rhumb line, 35 cm long, is drawn on a chart between N60\u00b0 W030\u00b0 and N60\u00b0 W040\u00b0. What is the approximate scale of the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "1: 26 500",
        "1: 1 585 000",
        "1: 6 000 000",
        "1: 5 880 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1: 1 585 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the Jeppesen GSPRM VFR +GPS Chart ED-4, what is the elevation of Salzburg Airport (N47\u00b047\u2019 E013\u00b000\u2019)?",
      "choices": [
        "2750 m amsl",
        "3120 ft agl",
        "1411 ft amsl",
        "1181 amsl"
      ],
      "answer": "1411 ft amsl"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is correct about large/small scale maps?",
      "choices": [
        "A large scale map shows more area represented with more detail.",
        "A large scale map shows more area represented with less detail.",
        "A small scale map shows more area represented with more detail.",
        "A small scale map shows more area represented and less detail."
      ],
      "answer": "A small scale map shows more area represented and less detail."
    },
    {
      "question": "What colour are contour lines on a chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Green",
        "Brown",
        "Red",
        "Blue"
      ],
      "answer": "Brown"
    },
    {
      "question": "Precise locations, marked on a chart with a small black dot, usually the summit of a hill or a small, sudden rise (or dip), too small to be illustrated with a contour line, are known as...?",
      "choices": [
        "Summits.",
        "Crests.",
        "Spot heights.",
        "High points."
      ],
      "answer": "Spot heights."
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Polar Stereographic Projection are: Meridians of longitude = __________ lines, __________ to pole.",
      "choices": [
        "straight; converging",
        "curved; concave",
        "curved; converging",
        "straight; concave"
      ],
      "answer": "straight; converging"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the value of the constant of the cone for a Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart with standard parallels of S32\u00b0 and S44\u00b0?",
      "choices": [
        "0.78801",
        "0.61556",
        "0.78129",
        "0.97029"
      ],
      "answer": "0.61556"
    },
    {
      "question": "A chart has a scale of 1:5 000 000. On a chart, the distance between points A and B is measured as 42 cm. What is the approximate distance between A and B?",
      "choices": [
        "1852 km",
        "1135 nm",
        "1300 km",
        "1135 sm"
      ],
      "answer": "1135 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "A chart has a scale of 1:1 000 000. On a chart, the distance between points A and B is measured as 25 cm. What is the approximate distance between A and B?",
      "choices": [
        "135 km",
        "135 sm",
        "135 dm",
        "135 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "135 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Convergence Factor  = __________ Parallel of Origin. Pole = __________\u00b0 latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "cosine; 180",
        "sine; 180",
        "cosine; 90",
        "sine; 90"
      ],
      "answer": "sine; 90"
    },
    {
      "question": "\u2018Conversion Angle\u2019 = Difference between great circle track bearing and rhumb line track bearing at __________ of the route.",
      "choices": [
        "either end",
        "the mid-point",
        "end",
        "start"
      ],
      "answer": "either end"
    },
    {
      "question": "How are meridians of longitude represented on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "As horizontal, straight, converging, equidistant lines.",
        "As horizontal, straight, parallel, unequally spaced lines.",
        "As vertical, straight, converging, equidistant lines.",
        "As vertical, straight, parallel, equidistant lines."
      ],
      "answer": "As vertical, straight, parallel, equidistant lines."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is normally used to solve scale problems?",
      "choices": [
        "1 / Scale = Chart Distance / Earth Distance.",
        "1 / Chart Distance = Earth Distance / Scale.",
        "1 / Scale = Earth Distance / Chart Distance.",
        "Scale / 1 = Chart Distance / Earth Distance."
      ],
      "answer": "1 / Scale = Chart Distance / Earth Distance."
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a Direct Mercator projection are: ________ of longitude = parallel, equally spaced, vertical straight lines.",
      "choices": [
        "Parallels",
        "Vertices",
        "Meridians",
        "Tangents"
      ],
      "answer": "Meridians"
    },
    {
      "question": "Parallels of latitude are shown on a Lambert\u2019s conformal conical chart as:",
      "choices": [
        "Parallel, curved lines, concave to nearer pole.",
        "Parallel, curved lines, convex to nearer pole.",
        "Vertical straight lines, converging to nearer pole.",
        "Vertical straight lines, converging towards Equator."
      ],
      "answer": "Parallel, curved lines, concave to nearer pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Chart scale is 1: 1 850 000. The chart distance between two points is 4 centimetres. Earth distance is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "100 NM",
        "74 NM",
        "40 NM",
        "4 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "40 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is the ABBA formula used to solve scale problems on a Direct Mercator chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Scale \u03d5 A \u00f7 Cosine \u03d5 B = Scale \u03d5 B x Cosine \u03d5 A",
        "Scale \u03d5 A x Cosine \u03d5 B = Scale \u03d5 B x Cosine \u03d5 A",
        "Scale \u03d5 A x Secant \u03d5 B = Scale \u03d5 B x Secant \u03d5 A",
        "Scale \u03d5 A x Cosine \u03d5 B = Scale \u03d5 B \u00f7 Cosine \u03d5 A"
      ],
      "answer": "Scale \u03d5 A x Cosine \u03d5 B = Scale \u03d5 B x Cosine \u03d5 A"
    },
    {
      "question": "When the contour lines are closer together, the slope is:",
      "choices": [
        "The terrain is fiat.",
        "Shallow.",
        "Steep.",
        "a narrow mountain bowl."
      ],
      "answer": "Steep."
    },
    {
      "question": "A line, 78 mm long, is drawn on a chart between S30\u00b0 E120\u00b0 and S30\u00b0 E128\u00b0. What is the approximate scale of the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "1: 9 850 000",
        "1: 11 400 000",
        "1: 6 600 000",
        "1: 6 000 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1: 9 850 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "With the exception of meridians of longitude and the Equator, straight lines drawn on a Direct Mercator chart are examples of _________ lines.",
      "choices": [
        "Great circle",
        "Rhumb",
        "Small circle",
        "Tangent"
      ],
      "answer": "Rhumb"
    },
    {
      "question": "The change in bearing of a great circle track along a route is known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Convergency",
        "Conversion Angle",
        "Conversion",
        "Complacency"
      ],
      "answer": "Convergency"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies along a great circle route between 2 positions, separated by meridians 20\u00b0 apart, on the same parallel of latitude. The initial great circle at point A is 096\u00b0T. What is the approximate latitude of the parallel?",
      "choices": [
        "E005\u00b040\u2019",
        "N36\u00b050\u2019",
        "S17\u00b030\u2019",
        "S36\u00b050\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "S36\u00b050\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rhumb line track is drawn between N50\u00b0 W020\u00b0 and N60\u00b0 W030\u00b0 on an initial track bearing of 278\u00b0T. What is the final rhumb line track bearing?",
      "choices": [
        "270\u00b0T",
        "274\u00b0T",
        "278\u00b0T",
        "282\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "278\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies along a rhumb line track from (A) S28\u00b0 E089\u00b0 to (B) S32\u00b0 E073\u00b0. The initial direction at point A is 266\u00b0T. What is the approximate direction of the track at (B)?",
      "choices": [
        "270\u00b0T",
        "274\u00b0T",
        "262\u00b0T",
        "266\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "266\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies along a great circle route between 2 positions, separated by meridians 16\u00b030\u2019 apart, on the same parallel of latitude. The initial great circle at point A is 272\u00b0T. What is the approximate latitude of the parallel?",
      "choices": [
        "N07\u00b000\u2019",
        "N14\u00b000\u2019",
        "S14\u00b000\u2019",
        "E016\u00b030\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "N14\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies from (A) N20\u00b0 W070\u00b0 to (B) N40\u00b0 W100\u00b0 following a great circle route. The initial direction at point A is 282\u00b0T. What is the approximate direction of the route at (B)?",
      "choices": [
        "290\u00b0T",
        "297\u00b0T",
        "267\u00b0T",
        "274\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "267\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "Great circle and rhumb line tracks are drawn between S45\u00b0 E110\u00b0 and S45\u00b0 E115\u00b0. Which will follow the shorter path over the ground?",
      "choices": [
        "The great circle.",
        "The rhumb line.",
        "Impossible to calculate.",
        "Both have the same distance."
      ],
      "answer": "The great circle."
    },
    {
      "question": "A rhumb line is a line of constant bearing. A rhumb-line route __________ the shortest distance between any 2 positions on the Earth (excluding meridians and Equator).",
      "choices": [
        "is",
        "is not",
        "intersects",
        "is parallel to"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies along a rhumb line track from (A) N41\u00b0 E145\u00b0 to (B) N55\u00b0 E169\u00b0. The initial direction at point A is 073\u00b0T. What is the approximate direction of the track at (B)?",
      "choices": [
        "079\u00b0T",
        "073\u00b0T",
        "067\u00b0T",
        "085\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "073\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is magnetic variation?",
      "choices": [
        "The difference in bearing between the directions from an observer to True North and Magnetic North.",
        "The difference in magnetic bearing between the directions from the True and Magnetic North Poles to an observer.",
        "The difference in bearing between the directions from an observer to Compass North and Magnetic North.",
        "The difference in true bearing between the directions from the True and Magnetic North Poles to an observer."
      ],
      "answer": "The difference in bearing between the directions from an observer to True North and Magnetic North."
    },
    {
      "question": "The proportional difference in distance between the great circle and rhumb-line routes between any 2 positions increases with: An __________ change in longitude and/or increasing latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "constant",
        "decreasing",
        "variable",
        "increasing"
      ],
      "answer": "increasing"
    },
    {
      "question": "The value of convergency between 2 points along a great circle track, which is also a rhumb line track is _____.",
      "choices": [
        "270",
        "180",
        "90",
        "0"
      ],
      "answer": "0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is an example of a great circle?",
      "choices": [
        "S45\u00b0",
        "The Greenwich Meridian plus its anti-meridian.",
        "N60\u00b0",
        "W015\u00b0 + E155\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "The Greenwich Meridian plus its anti-meridian."
    },
    {
      "question": "The great circle is always on the __________ side of the rhumb line.",
      "choices": [
        "co-latitude",
        "Equatorial",
        "Polar",
        "anti-meridian"
      ],
      "answer": "Polar"
    },
    {
      "question": "Application of WCA and DR to track or heading, as appropriate: TRK +/- WCA = __________.",
      "choices": [
        "REL BRG",
        "TRK",
        "HDG",
        "BRG"
      ],
      "answer": "HDG"
    },
    {
      "question": "Examples of rhumb lines are: The Equator. All __________ of longitude.",
      "choices": [
        "Parallels",
        "Co-latitudes",
        "Oblique tracks",
        "Meridians"
      ],
      "answer": "Meridians"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the formulae used to approximate the value of conversion angle, up to 30\u00b0 difference of longitude?",
      "choices": [
        "Conversion angle = Change of longitude x Cosine mean latitude.",
        "Conversion angle = \u00bd x Change of longitude x Sine mean latitude.",
        "Conversion angle = Change of longitude x Sine mean latitude.",
        "Conversion angle = \u00bd x Change of longitude x Cosine mean latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Conversion angle = \u00bd x Change of longitude x Sine mean latitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "Compass deviation is applied to a magnetic bearing to calculate a compass bearing: Deviation __________ - Compass Best Deviation __________ - Compass Least",
      "choices": [
        "East; West",
        "East; East",
        "West; West",
        "West; East"
      ],
      "answer": "West; East"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a correct derivative of the earth convergency formulae, used to approximate the mean latitude?",
      "choices": [
        "Mean latitude = Sine\u207b\u00b9(Convergency x Change of longitude).",
        "Mean latitude = Sine (Convergency x Change of longitude).",
        "Mean latitude = Sine\u207b\u00b9(Convergency \u00f7 Change of longitude).",
        "Mean latitude = Sine (Change of longitude \u00f7 Convergency)."
      ],
      "answer": "Mean latitude = Sine\u207b\u00b9(Convergency \u00f7 Change of longitude)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a great circle?",
      "choices": [
        "N/S00\u00b0",
        "The Equator.",
        "N/S45\u00b0",
        "The Greenwich Meridian plus its anti-meridian."
      ],
      "answer": "N/S45\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Magnetic variation is applied to a true bearing to calculate a magnetic bearing: Variation __________ - Magnetic Best Variation __________ - Magnetic Least",
      "choices": [
        "East; East",
        "West; West",
        "East; West",
        "West; East"
      ],
      "answer": "West; East"
    },
    {
      "question": "Compass deviation changes with: 1- Alignment of Earth and aircraft magnetic fields. 2- Aircraft heading. 3- __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Deviation",
        "Longitude",
        "Declination",
        "Latitude"
      ],
      "answer": "Latitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a correct derivative of the earth convergency formulae, used to approximate the change of longitude?",
      "choices": [
        "Change of longitude = Convergency x \u00bd x Sine mean latitude.",
        "Change of longitude = Convergency \u00f7 Sine mean latitude.",
        "Change of longitude = Convergency x \u00bd x Cosine mean latitude.",
        "\u00bd x Change of latitude = Convergency x Cosine mean latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Change of longitude = Convergency \u00f7 Sine mean latitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "A great circle track crosses the Equator at W160\u00b0 on a bearing of 030\u00b0T. What are the coordinates of the highest point reached?",
      "choices": [
        "S60\u00b000\u2019 W070\u00b000\u2019",
        "S60\u00b000\u2019 E250\u00b000\u2019",
        "N60\u00b000\u2019 W070\u00b000\u2019",
        "N60\u00b000\u2019 E110\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "N60\u00b000\u2019 W070\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the initial bearing at (A) of the rhumb line track from (A) N52\u00b000\u2019 E001\u00b030\u2019 to (B) N48\u00b000\u2019 E001\u00b030\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "178\u00b0T",
        "180\u00b0T",
        "181\u00b0T",
        "179\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "180\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line track is drawn from N30\u00b0 W020\u00b0 to N30\u00b0 W028\u00b0. What is the latitude of the vertex?",
      "choices": [
        "N29\u00b046\u2019",
        "N30\u00b000\u2019",
        "N29\u00b053\u2019",
        "N30\u00b007\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "N30\u00b007\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "This question is designed to test several areas of knowledge: An aircraft passes overhead (A) at 15.19 UTC as it flies along a rhumb line track at an average groundspeed of 380 kt, between 2 positions, (A) and (B), separated by meridians 28\u00b000\u2019 apart, located on the same parallel of latitude. Given that the initial great circle bearing at point (A) is 266\u00b0T, what is the estimated time of overflight (ETO) at point (B)?",
      "choices": [
        "16.35 UTC",
        "19.41 UTC",
        "19.33 UTC",
        "15.57 UTC"
      ],
      "answer": "19.33 UTC"
    },
    {
      "question": "The rhumb line is __________ to the nearer pole.",
      "choices": [
        "concave",
        "horizontal",
        "convex",
        "vertical"
      ],
      "answer": "concave"
    },
    {
      "question": "Positive Variation and Deviation = __________ (+5\u00b0 = 5\u00b0__________)",
      "choices": [
        "Westerly; E",
        "Westerly; W",
        "Easterly; E",
        "Easterly; W"
      ],
      "answer": "Easterly; E"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a small circle?",
      "choices": [
        "S45\u00b0",
        "N30\u00b0",
        "S60\u00b0",
        "The Equator."
      ],
      "answer": "The Equator."
    },
    {
      "question": "A circle which does not have its plane passing through the centre of the earth is known as a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "North Pole",
        "small circle",
        "Vertex",
        "great circle"
      ],
      "answer": "small circle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Negative Variation and Deviation = __________ (-5\u00b0 = 5\u00b0__________)",
      "choices": [
        "Westerly; E",
        "Westerly; W",
        "Easterly; E",
        "Easterly; W"
      ],
      "answer": "Westerly; W"
    },
    {
      "question": "Drift - the effect of prevailing wind on the flight path of the aircraft (from __________ to __________).",
      "choices": [
        "track; track",
        "heading; heading",
        "heading; track",
        "track; heading"
      ],
      "answer": "heading; track"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 033\u00b0M, and a land feature is visible on a relative bearing of 090\u00b0 from the aircraft. Magnetic variation at the aircraft = 5\u00b0W and at the land feature = 3\u00b0W. What is the true bearing from the land feature to the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "298\u00b0T",
        "128\u00b0T",
        "308\u00b0T",
        "300\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "298\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a Polar Stereographic chart, the initial great circle course from A 70\u00b0N 060\u00b0W to B 70\u00b0N 060\u00b0E is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "150\u00b0 (T)",
        "030\u00b0 (T)",
        "210\u00b0 (T)",
        "330\u00b0 (T)"
      ],
      "answer": "030\u00b0 (T)"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line track is drawn from N30\u00b0 W020\u00b0 to N30\u00b0 W028\u00b0. What is the longitude of the vertex?",
      "choices": [
        "W048\u00b000\u2019",
        "W024\u00b000\u2019",
        "W008\u00b000\u2019",
        "W022\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "W024\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "2 possible direct paths between 2 points are: A great circle track. A __________ __________ track.",
      "choices": [
        "Radian line",
        "Rum line",
        "Reverse line",
        "Rhumb Line"
      ],
      "answer": "Rhumb Line"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bearing TO +/- 180\u00b0 = Bearing __________.",
      "choices": [
        "TO",
        "RELATIVE",
        "FROM",
        "MAGNETIC"
      ],
      "answer": "FROM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Relative bearings are measured in a : __________ direction.",
      "choices": [
        "Anti-clockwise",
        "Vertical",
        "Horizontal",
        "Clockwise"
      ],
      "answer": "Clockwise"
    },
    {
      "question": "The angle between True North and Magnetic North is called:",
      "choices": [
        "variation",
        "compass error",
        "deviation",
        "drift"
      ],
      "answer": "variation"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies from (A) latitude 40\u00b0 W005\u00b0 to (B) latitude 50\u00b0 E008\u00b0 following a great circle route. The initial direction at point A is 084\u00b0T and at B is 093\u00b0T. In which hemisphere is the route?",
      "choices": [
        "Western hemisphere.",
        "Southern hemisphere.",
        "Eastern hemisphere.",
        "Northern hemisphere."
      ],
      "answer": "Northern hemisphere."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ of a great circle is: The point where the great circle bearing measures 090\u00b0/270\u00b0T. At the highest latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "Vortex",
        "Vertex",
        "Simplex",
        "Vertices"
      ],
      "answer": "Vertex"
    },
    {
      "question": "To perform relative bearing calculations: __________ + Relative Bearing = Bearing __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Relative Bearing; FROM",
        "Heading; FROM",
        "Relative Bearing; TO",
        "Heading; TO"
      ],
      "answer": "Heading; TO"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a line drawn on a chart which joins all points where the value of magnetic variation is zero?",
      "choices": [
        "An aclinic line.",
        "An isotach.",
        "An agonic line.",
        "An isogonal line ."
      ],
      "answer": "An agonic line."
    },
    {
      "question": "If an aircraft flies along a VOR radial it will follow a:",
      "choices": [
        "great circle track.",
        "line of constant bearing.",
        "constant magnetic track.",
        "rhumb line track."
      ],
      "answer": "great circle track."
    },
    {
      "question": "By what term is the difference between Compass North and Magnetic North known?",
      "choices": [
        "Compensation.",
        "Variation.",
        "Deviation.",
        "Convergency."
      ],
      "answer": "Deviation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is an example of a small circle?",
      "choices": [
        "The Greenwich Meridian plus its anti-meridian.",
        "Any parallel of latitude, except the Equator.",
        "Any meridian of longitude.",
        "The Equator."
      ],
      "answer": "Any parallel of latitude, except the Equator."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a chart a straight line is drawn between two points and has a length of 4.63 cm. What is the chart scale if the line represents 150 NM?",
      "choices": [
        "1 : 3 000 000",
        "1 : 1 000 000",
        "1 : 5 000 000",
        "1 : 6 000 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1 : 6 000 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "The formulae used to approximate the value of conversion angle, up to 30\u00b0 difference of longitude, is: Conversion Angle = \u00bd x __________. This can also be used to calculate an unknown longitude from a known longitude.",
      "choices": [
        "Conversion",
        "Change of latitude",
        "Change of longitude",
        "Convergency"
      ],
      "answer": "Convergency"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is calculated when magnetic variation is applied to a magnetic bearing?",
      "choices": [
        "A true bearing.",
        "A compass bearing.",
        "A drift bearing.",
        "A grid bearing."
      ],
      "answer": "A true bearing."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the northerly rhumb line track bearing along a meridian of longitude?",
      "choices": [
        "180\u00b0T",
        "000\u00b0T",
        "270\u00b0T",
        "090\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "000\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "Wind Correction Angle - the correction to track to calculate heading (from __________ to __________).",
      "choices": [
        "heading; heading",
        "track; heading",
        "heading; track",
        "track; track"
      ],
      "answer": "track; heading"
    },
    {
      "question": "Between which 2 positions will the difference in distance between the great circle and rhumb line tracks be the least?",
      "choices": [
        "S30\u00b0 E090\u00b0 and N30\u00b0 E120\u00b0",
        "S80\u00b0 E172\u00b0 and S60\u00b0 E172\u00b0",
        "N10\u00b0 W170\u00b0 and N10\u00b0 E160\u00b0",
        "N45\u00b0 W030\u00b0 and N45\u00b0 W060\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "S80\u00b0 E172\u00b0 and S60\u00b0 E172\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the formula used to calculate convergency between two positions relatively close to each other? Convergency = Difference in:",
      "choices": [
        "latitude x sin (mean longitude)",
        "longitude x cos (mean latitude)",
        "longitude x sin (mean latitude)",
        "latitude x cos (mean longitude)"
      ],
      "answer": "longitude x sin (mean latitude)"
    },
    {
      "question": "The rhumb line is always on the __________ side of the great circle.",
      "choices": [
        "anti-meridian",
        "co-latitude",
        "Polar",
        "Equatorial"
      ],
      "answer": "Equatorial"
    },
    {
      "question": "Great circle and rhumb line tracks are drawn between N/S00\u00b0 E005\u00b0 and N/S00\u00b0 W015\u00b0. Which will follow the shorter path over the ground?",
      "choices": [
        "Impossible to calculate.",
        "The rhumb line.",
        "Both have the same distance.",
        "The great circle."
      ],
      "answer": "Both have the same distance."
    },
    {
      "question": "All bearings are measured in degrees, __________ , from a datum, being the __________ point for measurement of the bearing.",
      "choices": [
        "anti-clockwise; zero",
        "anti-clockwise; 180 degree",
        "clockwise; zero",
        "clockwise; 180 degree"
      ],
      "answer": "clockwise; zero"
    },
    {
      "question": "Any great circle route, other than a meridian of longitude or the Equator, intersects converging meridians at changing angles, and as such, its true __________ changes.",
      "choices": [
        "convergency",
        "relative bearing",
        "bearing",
        "conversion angle"
      ],
      "answer": "bearing"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the westerly bearing of a track at the vertex.",
      "choices": [
        "000\u00b0T",
        "090\u00b0T",
        "270\u00b0T",
        "180\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "270\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ __________ - the alignment of a magnetic compass with the local magnetic meridian, at any given point, in the absence of any external influences.",
      "choices": [
        "Compass South",
        "Compass West",
        "Compass North",
        "Compass East"
      ],
      "answer": "Compass North"
    },
    {
      "question": "The change of great circle track bearing between 2 points, measured across the surface of the Earth, is a definition of __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Chart conversion angle",
        "Earth convergency",
        "Earth conversion angle",
        "Chart Convergency"
      ],
      "answer": "Earth convergency"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of a great circle?",
      "choices": [
        "Forms a straight line between any 2 positions on the Earth.",
        "Has its plane passing through the centre of the Earth.",
        "Forms the shortest distance between any 2 positions on the Earth.",
        "Forms a diameter of the Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "Forms a diameter of the Earth."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies from (A) latitude 20\u00b0 E005\u00b0 to (B) latitude 40\u00b0 W005\u00b0 following a great circle route. The initial direction at point A is 282\u00b0T and at B is 287\u00b0T. In which hemisphere is the route?",
      "choices": [
        "Western hemisphere.",
        "Southern hemisphere.",
        "Northern hemisphere.",
        "Eastern hemisphere."
      ],
      "answer": "Southern hemisphere."
    },
    {
      "question": "To perform relative bearing calculations: HDG (\u00b0M) + __________ = BRG TO (\u00b0__________)",
      "choices": [
        "Relative Bearing; Magnetic",
        "Heading; Magnetic",
        "Relative Bearing; True",
        "Heading; True"
      ],
      "answer": "Relative Bearing; Magnetic"
    },
    {
      "question": "A great circle track crosses the Equator at W010\u00b0 on a bearing of 203\u00bd\u00b0T. At which longitudes will the track line reach the Polar Circles?",
      "choices": [
        "E080\u00b000\u2019 and W100\u00b000\u2019",
        "S66\u00b030\u2019 and N66\u00b030\u2019",
        "W080\u00b000\u2019 and E100\u00b000\u2019",
        "W080\u00b000\u2019 and E080\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "E080\u00b000\u2019 and W100\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "A great circle track crosses the Equator at E030\u00b0 on a bearing of 120\u00b0T. What are the coordinates of the highest point reached?",
      "choices": [
        "S30\u00b000\u2019 E060\u00b000\u2019",
        "N30\u00b000\u2019 E120\u00b000\u2019",
        "S30\u00b000\u2019 W120\u00b000\u2019",
        "S30\u00b000\u2019 E120\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "S30\u00b000\u2019 E120\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "To perform relative bearing calculations: HDG (\u00b0T) + __________ = BRG TO (\u00b0__________)",
      "choices": [
        "Relative Bearing; True",
        "Relative Bearing; Magnetic",
        "Heading; True",
        "Heading; Magnetic"
      ],
      "answer": "Relative Bearing; True"
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens to the position of the Magnetic North Pole?",
      "choices": [
        "It moves in an elliptical shape on a daily basis but always returns to the same position over time.",
        "It changes over time in a linear and predictable manner.",
        "It changes over time in a seemingly random manner.",
        "It remains constant."
      ],
      "answer": "It changes over time in a seemingly random manner."
    },
    {
      "question": "Great circle and rhumb line tracks are drawn between N60\u00b0 W020\u00b0 and N60\u00b0 W030\u00b0. Which will follow the longer path over the ground?",
      "choices": [
        "Both have the same distance.",
        "The great circle.",
        "Impossible to calculate.",
        "The rhumb line."
      ],
      "answer": "The rhumb line."
    },
    {
      "question": "The formulae used to approximate the value of earth convergency, up to 30\u00b0 difference of longitude, is: (Earth) Convergency = Change of longitude x __________ latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "Sine",
        "Cosine mean",
        "Tangent",
        "Sine mean"
      ],
      "answer": "Sine mean"
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the value of the Earth Convergency, to the nearest whole degree, between positions A (53\u00b045'N, 177\u00b005'W) and B (65\u00b005'N, 161\u00b010'E).",
      "choices": [
        "14\u00b0",
        "09\u00b0",
        "19\u00b0",
        "25\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "19\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ - the direction in which the aircraft is pointing.",
      "choices": [
        "Track",
        "Direction",
        "Heading",
        "Bearing"
      ],
      "answer": "Heading"
    },
    {
      "question": "Contour lines on aeronautical maps and charts connect points:",
      "choices": [
        "with the same variation.",
        "having the same elevation.",
        "having the same longitude.",
        "of equal latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "having the same elevation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Application of WCA and DR to track or heading, as appropriate: HDG +/- DR = __________.",
      "choices": [
        "REL BRG",
        "HDG",
        "BRG",
        "TRK"
      ],
      "answer": "TRK"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the formulae used to approximate the value of earth convergency, up to 30\u00b0 difference of longitude?",
      "choices": [
        "Convergency = Change of longitude x Cosine mean latitude.",
        "\u00bd x Change of longitude x Cosine mean latitude.",
        "\u00bd x Change of longitude x Sine mean latitude.",
        "Convergency = Change of longitude x Sine mean latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Convergency = Change of longitude x Sine mean latitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "The difference between the directions from an observer along the local true and magnetic meridians is known as __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "magnetic deviation",
        "magnetic pole",
        "magnetic variation",
        "ecliptic"
      ],
      "answer": "magnetic variation"
    },
    {
      "question": "A small circle: Does not have its __________ passing through the centre of the Earth.",
      "choices": [
        "Plane",
        "Vortex",
        "Plain",
        "Vertex"
      ],
      "answer": "Plane"
    },
    {
      "question": "An Island is observed to be 30\u00b0 to the right of the aircraft's longitudinal axis. The aircraft heading is 290\u00b0M, variation 10\u00b0E. The bearing from the aircraft to the Island is:",
      "choices": [
        "310\u00b0T",
        "330\u00b0T",
        "250\u00b0T",
        "270\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "330\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "The rhumb line track from A 53\u00b0 50'N, 006\u00b0 55'E to B 53\u00b0 00'N, 015\u00b0 40'E is 099\u00b0. Calculate the initial True Track along the great circle.",
      "choices": [
        "096\u00b0",
        "92\u00b0",
        "103\u00b0",
        "106\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "096\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "A great circle track crosses the Equator at E050\u00b0 on a bearing of 040\u00b0T. What are the coordinates of the highest point reached?",
      "choices": [
        "N50\u00b000\u2019 W040\u00b000\u2019",
        "N50\u00b000\u2019 E140\u00b000\u2019",
        "N40\u00b000\u2019 E140\u00b000\u2019",
        "S50\u00b000\u2019 W320\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "N50\u00b000\u2019 E140\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "A straight line route ls drawn on a Direct Mercator chart from position A 45\u00b030'N, 013\u00b025'W to position B 41\u00b042'N, 003\u00b0S57'E. The rhumb line track measured at A ls 129\u00b0 T. What is approximately the great circle track from A to B, measured at position A?",
      "choices": [
        "123\u00b0 T",
        "126\u00b0 T",
        "135\u00b0 T",
        "117\u00b0 T"
      ],
      "answer": "123\u00b0 T"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rhumb line track is a track of constant bearing. The difference between the rhumb line track and the great circle track is known as __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Conversion angle",
        "Convergency angle",
        "Divergency bearing",
        "Conversion bearing"
      ],
      "answer": "Conversion angle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Earth convergency __________ with increasing: Change of longitude. Latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "varies neagtively",
        "remains constant",
        "decreases",
        "increases"
      ],
      "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "The name given to the largest circle that can be drawn on the surface of a sphere is a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Vertex",
        "small circle",
        "North Pole",
        "great circle"
      ],
      "answer": "great circle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider any two positions with a difference in Longitude of 7\u00b0. The proportional difference between the rhumb line distance and the great circle distance between the two positions increases with:",
      "choices": [
        "decreasing Latitude.",
        "increasing Latitude.",
        "decreasing convergence.",
        "increasing altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "increasing Latitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "Deviation applied to magnetic heading gives:",
      "choices": [
        "magnetic track",
        "magnetic course",
        "compass heading",
        "true heading"
      ],
      "answer": "compass heading"
    },
    {
      "question": "Relative bearings are measured in: __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Degrees Magnetic",
        "Degrees True",
        "Degrees Compass",
        "Degrees"
      ],
      "answer": "Degrees"
    },
    {
      "question": "Magnetic North (MN) may be defined as:",
      "choices": [
        "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local magnetic meridian to the Magnetic North Pole.",
        "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude to the Magnetic North Pole.",
        "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local parallel of latitude to the Magnetic North Pole.",
        "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local parallel of longitude to the Magnetic North Pole."
      ],
      "answer": "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local magnetic meridian to the Magnetic North Pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "Great circle and rhumb line tracks are drawn between S30\u00b0 E005\u00b0 and S40\u00b0 E005\u00b0. Which will follow the shorter path over the ground?",
      "choices": [
        "The rhumb line.",
        "Both have the same distance.",
        "Impossible to calculate.",
        "The great circle."
      ],
      "answer": "Both have the same distance."
    },
    {
      "question": "At 10:00 UTC an aircraft departs position A 51\u00b030'N, 001\u00b059'W and flies on a track of 270\u00b0 at a groundspeed of 390 kt. What is the aircraft's position at 11:30 UTC?",
      "choices": [
        "51\u00b030'N, 017\u00b039'W",
        "51\u00b030'N, 008\u00b003'W",
        "51\u00b030'N, 011\u00b044'W",
        "51\u00b030'N, 014\u00b027'W"
      ],
      "answer": "51\u00b030'N, 017\u00b039'W"
    },
    {
      "question": "A great-circle route which follows the path of a meridian of longitude or the Equator is also a rhumb line, and __________ change bearing.",
      "choices": [
        "always",
        "does not",
        "does",
        "sometimes"
      ],
      "answer": "does not"
    },
    {
      "question": "True North (TN) is defined as:",
      "choices": [
        "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local parallel of longitude to the True North Pole.",
        "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local parallel of latitude to the True North Pole.",
        "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude to the True North Pole.",
        "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local meridian of latitude to the True North Pole."
      ],
      "answer": "The direction measured along the observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude to the True North Pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "Compass deviations are recorded on a compass calibration card, which usually reads: For course __________. Steer __________.",
      "choices": [
        "magnetic; compass.",
        "magnetic; magnetic.",
        "compass; compass.",
        "compass; magnetic."
      ],
      "answer": "magnetic; compass."
    },
    {
      "question": "A great circle track crosses the Equator at W025\u00b0 on a bearing of 315\u00b0T. What are the coordinates of the highest northerly point reached?",
      "choices": [
        "N45\u00b000\u2019 W115\u00b000\u2019",
        "S45\u00b000\u2019 W115\u00b000\u2019",
        "S45\u00b000\u2019 E065\u00b000\u2019",
        "N45\u00b000\u2019 E065\u00b000\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "N45\u00b000\u2019 W115\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ __________ is the result of external influences on the magnetic compass, causing it to deviate from Magnetic North.",
      "choices": [
        "Compass deviation",
        "Compass variation",
        "Compass North",
        "Compass inclination"
      ],
      "answer": "Compass deviation"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 050\u00b0M, with an NDB on a relative bearing of 140\u00b0 from the aircraft. What is the magnetic bearing from the aircraft to the NDB?",
      "choices": [
        "190\u00b0M",
        "140\u00b0M",
        "010\u00b0M",
        "090\u00b0M"
      ],
      "answer": "190\u00b0M"
    },
    {
      "question": "Between which 2 positions will the difference in distance between the great circle and rhumb line tracks be the greatest?",
      "choices": [
        "S30\u00b0 E090\u00b0 and N30\u00b0 E120\u00b0",
        "N60\u00b0 W150\u00b0 and N60\u00b0 E160\u00b0",
        "S60\u00b0 E162\u00b0 and S60\u00b0 E122\u00b0",
        "N45\u00b0 W030\u00b0 and N45\u00b0 W060\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "N60\u00b0 W150\u00b0 and N60\u00b0 E160\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot is flying from A 60\u00b0S, 165\u00b0W to B 60\u00b0S, 177\u00b0E. What is the angle between the initial true great circle track and the true rhumb line track?",
      "choices": [
        "7.8\u00b0",
        "9\u00b0",
        "5.2\u00b0",
        "15.6\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "7.8\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the zero datum for true bearings?",
      "choices": [
        "The observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude, towards the South Pole.",
        "The direction in which the aircraft is pointing.",
        "The observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude, towards the North Pole.",
        "The observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude, away from the North Pole."
      ],
      "answer": "The observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude, towards the North Pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that the rhumb line track between (A) N22\u00b000\u2019 W010\u00b000\u2019 and (B) N28\u00b000\u2019 W024\u00b000\u2019 is 281\u00b0T, what is the final bearing at (B) of the great circle track between the same 2 points?",
      "choices": [
        "287\u00b0T",
        "278\u00b0T",
        "275\u00b0T",
        "284\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "278\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "The local mean time at Suvanarbhumi International Airport, Bangkok, Thailand (N13\u00b040\u2019 E100\u00b045\u2019 ) is 21.30 LMT. What is the local mean time at Ministro Pistarini International Airport, Buenos Aires, Argentina (S34\u00b050\u2032 W58\u00b030\u2019)?",
      "choices": [
        "09.30 LMT",
        "08.30 ST",
        "08.07 LMT",
        "10.53 LMT"
      ],
      "answer": "10.53 LMT"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying from Position A (53\u00b0N, 10\u00b035'W) to Position B (53\u00b0N, 51\u00b045'E). Its average ground speed is equal to 375 kt. The time difference to UTC is 1 hour for Position A and 4 hours for Position B. Assuming the aircraft arrives at Position B on August 5th, 15:00 ST, what is its time of departure from Position A?",
      "choices": [
        "August 5th, 04:00 ST",
        "August 4th, 16:00 ST",
        "August 5th, 14:00 ST",
        "August 4th, 06:00 ST"
      ],
      "answer": "August 5th, 04:00 ST"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the time of sunrise at Dubai International Airport, Dubai, UAE (N25\u00b015\u2032 E055\u00b020\u2032) on 20th April 2017?",
      "choices": [
        "01.52 LMT",
        "05.33 UTC",
        "05.33 LMT",
        "04.52 ST"
      ],
      "answer": "05.33 LMT"
    },
    {
      "question": "The local mean time at The Royal Observatory, Greenwich, London, UK (N51\u00b029\u2019 E000\u00b000\u2019 ) is 13.40 LMT. What is UTC at Sydney Kingsford Airport, New South Wales, Australia (S33\u00b057\u2032 E151\u00b000\u2032)?",
      "choices": [
        "13.40 LMT",
        "23.44 LMT",
        "23.44 UTC",
        "13.40 UTC"
      ],
      "answer": "13.40 UTC"
    },
    {
      "question": "At which of the following does the duration of daylight change at the slowest rate?",
      "choices": [
        "Summer Solstice.",
        "Aphelion.",
        "Spring Equinox.",
        "Perihelion."
      ],
      "answer": "Summer Solstice."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is departing Ataturk International Airport, Istanbul, Turkey (N40\u00b058\u2032 E028\u00b045\u2032) for Tokyo International Airport, Tokyo, Japan (N35\u00b033\u2032 E139\u00b045\u2019) via Beijing Capital International Airport, Beijing, China (N40\u00b004\u2032 E116\u00b030\u2032). Time off blocks at Istanbul is 22.20 ST on 22nd June 2017. Taxi time at Istanbul is 20 min and the flight time to Beijing is 9 hr 15 min. Taxi time to and from the gate at Beijing is 45 min and the transfer time at the gate at Beijing is 6 hr 50 min. Flight time from Beijing to Tokyo is 3 hr 10 min and taxi time at Tokyo is 25 min. What is the ST and date of arrival at the gate at Tokyo?",
      "choices": [
        "04.05 ST on 24th June 2017",
        "08.05 ST on 24th June 2017",
        "02.29 ST on 24th June 2017",
        "01.05 ST on 24th June 2017"
      ],
      "answer": "01.05 ST on 24th June 2017"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information from an Air Almanac, what is the Standard Time (ST) and date in country A, if in country B, it is 15:00 ST 15th July? Standard time in country A is UTC +4 hours. Standard time in country B is UTC -7 hours.",
      "choices": [
        "02:00 ST 16th July",
        "04:00 ST 15th July",
        "18:00 ST 15th July",
        "22:00 ST 16th July"
      ],
      "answer": "02:00 ST 16th July"
    },
    {
      "question": "A distinct point at the start of a day is: Sunrise - Upper limb of Sun ascends above the _________ in the _________.",
      "choices": [
        "horizon; West",
        "Equator; East",
        "Equator; West",
        "horizon; East"
      ],
      "answer": "horizon; East"
    },
    {
      "question": "The duration of daylight changes at the _________ rate at the Spring and Autumn Equinoxes and at the _________ rate at the Summer and Winter Solstices.",
      "choices": [
        "lowest; fastest",
        "highest; fastest",
        "lowest; slowest",
        "highest; slowest"
      ],
      "answer": "highest; slowest"
    },
    {
      "question": "At which of the following does the duration of daylight change at the highest rate?",
      "choices": [
        "Winter Solstice.",
        "Spring Equinox.",
        "Summer Solstice.",
        "Perihelion."
      ],
      "answer": "Spring Equinox."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft departs Incheon International Airport, Seoul, South Korea (N37\u00b030\u2019 E126\u00b030\u2032) at sunset on 16th December 2017 for a non-stop 13 hr 55 min flight to JFK Airport, Queens, New York, USA (N40\u00b038\u2032 W073\u00b045\u2019)? What is the ST and date of landing at JFK?",
      "choices": [
        "17.12 ST on 16th December 2017",
        "17.12 ST on 17th December 2017",
        "17.17 ST on 16th December 2017",
        "16.38 ST on 16th December 2017"
      ],
      "answer": "17.12 ST on 16th December 2017"
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the ETA at the destination, given: An aircraft departing from the western hemisphere, flying along the equator to the eastern hemisphere, crossing the date line on a westerly heading. The difference between the location and the destination is 15\u00b0 of longitude. Date and time of departure ls 12:00 LMT on the 14th of August. Aircraft travels at an average ground speed of 300 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "14:00 LMT, 15th of August",
        "10:00 LMT, 14th of August",
        "10:00 LMT, 15th of August",
        "14:00 LMT, 14th of August"
      ],
      "answer": "14:00 LMT, 15th of August"
    },
    {
      "question": "A distinct point at the start of a day is: Morning Civil Twilight - Centre disk of ascending Sun is _________ the horizon.",
      "choices": [
        "5\u00b0 below",
        "6\u00b0 below",
        "6\u00b0 above",
        "5\u00b0 above"
      ],
      "answer": "6\u00b0 below"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft departs Cairo International Airport, Cairo, Egypt (N30\u00b005\u2032E031\u00b015\u2032) at 12.15 ST on 11th February 2017 for a non-stop, direct flight to King Shaka International Airport, Durban, South Africa (S29\u00b040\u2032 E031\u00b015\u2032E). The average groundspeed of the flight is 890 km/hr. What is the ST and date of landing at Durban?",
      "choices": [
        "19.43 ST on 11th February 2017",
        "16.38 ST on 11th February 2017",
        "17.12 ST on 11th February 2017",
        "20.17 ST on 11th February 2017"
      ],
      "answer": "19.43 ST on 11th February 2017"
    },
    {
      "question": "Daylight Saving Time (DST) is an adjustment to ST, usually of one hour duration and used in most countries, but with exceptions, both in duration and location. Clocks go: _________ in Spring. _________ in Autumn.",
      "choices": [
        "forwards; backwards.",
        "backwards; backwards.",
        "backwards; forwards.",
        "forwards; forwards."
      ],
      "answer": "forwards; backwards."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the duration of morning civil twilight at McClarren International Airport, Nevada, USA (N36\u00b000\u2032 115\u00b015\u2019) on 20th May 2017?",
      "choices": [
        "0.35",
        "0.29",
        "4.5",
        "4.21"
      ],
      "answer": "0.29"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the time of sunset at Keflavik International Airport, Iceland (N64\u00b000\u2032 W022\u00b030\u2032) on 26th July 2017? Apply Daylight Savings Time, if applicable.",
      "choices": [
        "22.51 LMT",
        "23.51 ST",
        "22.51 ST",
        "21.21 UTC"
      ],
      "answer": "22.51 ST"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft departs Toulouse International Airport, France (43\u00b030\u2032 E001\u00b022\u2032) at 18.30 ST on 25th July 2017 for a non-stop flight, along a constant track, to Toronto, Ontario, Canada (N43\u00b030\u2032 W079\u00b038\u2032). The average groundspeed of the flight is 508 kt. How long before or after sunset will the flight land at Toronto?",
      "choices": [
        "6 min after sunset.",
        "24 min before sunset.",
        "At sunset.",
        "2 hr 23 min after sunset."
      ],
      "answer": "24 min before sunset."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which document will you be most likely to find Standard Time conversion tables?",
      "choices": [
        "Air Almanac",
        "AIP",
        "AIRAC",
        "AIS"
      ],
      "answer": "Air Almanac"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is the mean solar day best defined?",
      "choices": [
        "24 hours, being the time it takes a fictitious Sun, traveling at uniform speed along the celestial Equator, to make two transits overhead the observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude.",
        "Of variable length, being the time it takes the actual Sun, traveling at varying speed along the ecliptic, to make two transits overhead the observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude.",
        "24 hours, being the time it takes the actual Sun, traveling at varying speed along the celestial Equator, to make two transits overhead the observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude.",
        "24 hours, being the time it takes a fictitious Sun, traveling at constant speed along the ecliptic, to make two transits overhead the observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude."
      ],
      "answer": "24 hours, being the time it takes a fictitious Sun, traveling at uniform speed along the celestial Equator, to make two transits overhead the observer\u2019s local meridian of longitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "Maintaining a ground speed of 180 kt, an aircraft leaves position A 30\u00b0S, 010\u00b0W and flies the rhumb line tracks listed below. What are the coordinates of point E? A to B: 090\u00b0 for 25 minutes B to C: 180\u00b0 for 32 minutes C to D: 270\u00b0 for 28 minutes D to E: 360\u00b0 for 24 minutes",
      "choices": [
        "31\u00b000'S, 010\u00b003'W",
        "30\u00b024'S, 010\u00b010'W",
        "30\u00b024'S, 010\u00b009'W",
        "30\u00b024'S, 010\u00b012'W"
      ],
      "answer": "30\u00b024'S, 010\u00b012'W"
    },
    {
      "question": "At which of the following does evening civil twilight end?",
      "choices": [
        "Upper limb of the descending Sun 6\u00b0 below the horizon to the west.",
        "Centre disk of the descending Sun 6\u00b0 below the horizon to the west.",
        "Centre disk of the descending Sun 12\u00b0 below the horizon to the east.",
        "Centre disk of the ascending Sun 6\u00b0 below the horizon to the east."
      ],
      "answer": "Centre disk of the descending Sun 6\u00b0 below the horizon to the west."
    },
    {
      "question": "_________ and _________ are often used interchangeably within this syllabus.",
      "choices": [
        "LMT; UTC",
        "DST; ST",
        "GMT; UTC",
        "GMT; LMT"
      ],
      "answer": "GMT; UTC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the Standard Time (ST) and date of arrival in Chile, given the following Information: Route: New Zealand to Chile, crossing the international date line on an easterly course Departure time and date: 03:00 UTC, 19th November Flight time: 12 hours 30 minutes New Zealand ST: UTC + 12 hours Chile ST: UTC - 4 hours",
      "choices": [
        "11:30, 18th November",
        "23:30, 18th November",
        "15:30, 19th November",
        "11:30, 19th November"
      ],
      "answer": "11:30, 19th November"
    },
    {
      "question": "A distinct point at the end of a day is: Sunset - Upper limb of Sun descends below the _________ in the _________.",
      "choices": [
        "Equator; West",
        "horizon; East",
        "Equator; East",
        "horizon; West"
      ],
      "answer": "horizon; West"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name given to the orbital path taken by the Earth around the Sun?",
      "choices": [
        "Ecliptic",
        "Elliptical",
        "Ellipsoid",
        "Eclipse"
      ],
      "answer": "Ecliptic"
    },
    {
      "question": "In relation to the easterly rotational direction of the Earth on its vertical axis, which direction does the Earth orbit the Sun?",
      "choices": [
        "Easterly",
        "Southerly",
        "Northerly",
        "Westerly"
      ],
      "answer": "Easterly"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the antipodes of N55\u00b0 30' W130\u00b0 25'?",
      "choices": [
        "S44\u00b0 30' E049\u00b0 35'",
        "S44\u00b0 30' E130\u00b0 25",
        "S55\u00b0 30' E130\u00b0 25'",
        "S55\u00b0 30' E049\u00b0 35'"
      ],
      "answer": "S55\u00b0 30' E049\u00b0 35'"
    },
    {
      "question": "Changing insolation throughout the year is the cumulative result of: The __________ position of the Sun, relative to the surface of the Earth.",
      "choices": [
        "deviation",
        "variation",
        "changing",
        "inclination"
      ],
      "answer": "changing"
    },
    {
      "question": "What name is given to lines on the surface of the Earth, north and south of the Equator, which join points of equal geodetic latitude?",
      "choices": [
        "A meridian of longitude.",
        "A parallel of latitude.",
        "A meridian of latitude.",
        "A co-latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "A parallel of latitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "Geodetic __________ is the angle between the plane of the Greenwich Meridian and a line joining the centre of the Earth\u2019s __________ axis to a specified point on the Earth's surface.",
      "choices": [
        "longitude; horizontal.",
        "longitude; vertical.",
        "latitude; horizontal.",
        "latitude; vertical."
      ],
      "answer": "longitude; vertical."
    },
    {
      "question": "A car is driving along a motorway at a constant 135 km/hr. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how long does it take to travel 56 sm?",
      "choices": [
        "25 min",
        "2 hr 6 min",
        "40 min",
        "1 hr 16 min"
      ],
      "answer": "40 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Parallels of latitude are __________ lines on the surface of the Earth, north and south of the Equator, which join points of equal geographic latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "imaginary.",
        "vertical.",
        "physical.",
        "variable"
      ],
      "answer": "imaginary."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the antipodes of S72 42' E115\u00b0 37'?",
      "choices": [
        "N72 42' W064\u00b0 23'",
        "S72 42 W115\u00b0 37'",
        "N17 18' W064\u00b0 23'",
        "N17 18' E115\u00b0 37'"
      ],
      "answer": "N72 42' W064\u00b0 23'"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many nautical miles are equal to 10 statute miles?",
      "choices": [
        "11.5 nm",
        "16 nm",
        "18.52 nm",
        "8.7 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "8.7 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the ratio of nautical miles to centimetres?",
      "choices": [
        "1 nm = 18520 cm",
        "1 nm = 1 852 000 cm",
        "1 nm = 1.852 cm",
        "1 nm = 185 200 cm"
      ],
      "answer": "1 nm = 185 200 cm"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a constant east-west distance: Change of longitude __________ with increasing latitude Change of longitude __________ with decreasing latitude",
      "choices": [
        "increases; decreases.",
        "decreases; increases.",
        "decreases; decreases.",
        "increases; increases."
      ],
      "answer": "increases; decreases."
    },
    {
      "question": "Geodetic latitude is the angle between the plane of the Earth's Equator and a line, __________ to the surface of the Earth at a specified point on the Earth's surface, joining that point to the __________ of the Equator.",
      "choices": [
        "parallel; meridian.",
        "meridian; parallel.",
        "plane; perpendicular.",
        "perpendicular; plane."
      ],
      "answer": "perpendicular; plane."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying at a constant 110 knots. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how long does it take to travel 145 sm?",
      "choices": [
        "2 hr 18 min",
        "1 hr 9 min",
        "39 min",
        "1 hr 12 min"
      ],
      "answer": "1 hr 9 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "The antipodal geodetic longitude is calculated by __________ the original longitude __________, but in the opposite hemisphere.",
      "choices": [
        "subtracting; to 180\u00b0.",
        "adding; :from 180\u00b0.",
        "subtracting; from 180\u00b0.",
        "adding; to 180\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "subtracting; from 180\u00b0."
    },
    {
      "question": "A bicycle is travelling at a constant 8 mph. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how long does it take to travel 56 sm?",
      "choices": [
        "7.5 hrs",
        "8 hrs",
        "7 hrs",
        "6.5 hrs"
      ],
      "answer": "7 hrs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Distance =",
      "choices": [
        "Time \u00f7 Speed",
        "Speed \u00f7 Time.",
        "Speed x Time.",
        "Speed + time"
      ],
      "answer": "Speed x Time."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name given to a line joining points of equal longitude?",
      "choices": [
        "A meridian of longitude.",
        "A co-latitude.",
        "A meridian of latitude.",
        "A parallel of latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "A meridian of longitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name given to the mathematical shape, which defines the Earth?",
      "choices": [
        "Ellipsoid",
        "Oblate spheroid",
        "WGS-84 ellipsoid",
        "Geoid"
      ],
      "answer": "WGS-84 ellipsoid"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a co-latitude?",
      "choices": [
        "A complementary angle to the latitude, calculated as 180\u00b0 - the latitude",
        "A complementary angle to the latitude, calculated as 90\u00b0 - the latitude",
        "A complementary angle to the latitude, calculated as 90\u00b0 + the latitude",
        "A complementary angle to the latitude, calculated as 180\u00b0 + the latitude"
      ],
      "answer": "A complementary angle to the latitude, calculated as 90\u00b0 - the latitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the international standard ellipsoid, used to reference geographical coordinates?",
      "choices": [
        "Oblate spheroid",
        "Ellipsoid",
        "WGS-84 ellipsoid",
        "Geoid"
      ],
      "answer": "WGS-84 ellipsoid"
    },
    {
      "question": "The change of longitude between N60\u00b000\u2019 E082\u00b030\u2019 and N30\u00b000\u2019 W031\u00b000\u2019 is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "113\u00b000\u2019",
        "114\u00b030\u2019",
        "112\u00b030\u2019",
        "113\u00b030\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "113\u00b030\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the distance, via the North Pole, between N49\u00b020\u2019 E005\u00b000\u2019 and N59\u00b020\u2019 W170\u00b000\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "4280 sm",
        "6920 km",
        "2480 nm",
        "4280 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "4280 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name given to the angle between the plane of the Greenwich Meridian and a line joining the centre of the Earth\u2019s vertical axis to a specified point on the Earth's surface.",
      "choices": [
        "Meridian.",
        "Co-latitude.",
        "Latitude.",
        "Longitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Longitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name given to the irregular shape of the Earth, which is based on the surface of the oceans, and influenced only by gravity and centrifugal force?",
      "choices": [
        "Oblate spheroid",
        "Geoid",
        "Ellipsoid",
        "WGS-84 ellipsoid"
      ],
      "answer": "Geoid"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Earth\u2019s equatorial axis is inclined at an angle of __________ from the ecliptic.",
      "choices": [
        "22\u00bd\u00b0",
        "23\u00bd\u00b0",
        "45\u00bd\u00b0",
        "25\u00bd"
      ],
      "answer": "23\u00bd\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Coordinates are defined as the point of intersection between...?",
      "choices": [
        "A meridian of longitude and a co-latitude.",
        "A meridian of longitude and a parallel of latitude.",
        "A meridian of longitude and its anti-meridian.",
        "A meridian of latitude and a parallel of longitude."
      ],
      "answer": "A meridian of longitude and a parallel of latitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "Time =",
      "choices": [
        "Distance x Speed",
        "Distance \u00f7 Speed",
        "Speed \u00f7 Distance",
        "Speed x Distance"
      ],
      "answer": "Distance \u00f7 Speed"
    },
    {
      "question": "1\u00b0 Change of Latitude = __________ nm and 1\u2019 Change of Latitude = __________ nm.",
      "choices": [
        "360; 1",
        "60; 1",
        "1; 60",
        "60; 10"
      ],
      "answer": "60; 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the ratio of nautical miles to metres?",
      "choices": [
        "1 nm = 1609 m",
        "1 nm = 1000 m",
        "1 nm = 1852 m",
        "1 nm = 1760 m"
      ],
      "answer": "1 nm = 1852 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying at a constant 240 knots. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how far would it have travelled after 45 minutes?",
      "choices": [
        "120 nm",
        "180 nm",
        "240 nm",
        "300 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "180 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "A train is travelling at a constant 120 mph. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how long does it take to travel 40 sm?",
      "choices": [
        "48 min",
        "40 min",
        "15 min",
        "20 min"
      ],
      "answer": "20 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Earth rotates around a __________ axis, located between the South and North Poles, in an __________ direction.",
      "choices": [
        "horizontal; easterly",
        "vertical; westerly",
        "horizontal; westerly",
        "vertical; easterly"
      ],
      "answer": "vertical; easterly"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are parallels of latitude parallel to?",
      "choices": [
        "Geodetics",
        "Geodesics",
        "Meridians",
        "Equator"
      ],
      "answer": "Equator"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the correct formula for solving distance?",
      "choices": [
        "Distance = 1.23 x \u221aTime x Speed",
        "Distance = Speed x Time",
        "Distance = Time \u00f7 Speed",
        "Distance = \u221aSpeed\u00b2 \u00f7 Time\u00b2"
      ],
      "answer": "Distance = Speed x Time"
    },
    {
      "question": "Speed =",
      "choices": [
        "Distance x Time.",
        "Time \u00f7 Speed.",
        "Distance \u00f7 Time",
        "Time + distance"
      ],
      "answer": "Distance \u00f7 Time"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a constant change of longitude: Departure __________ with increasing latitude. Departure __________ with decreasing latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "increases; decreases.",
        "decreases; increases.",
        "increases; increases.",
        "decreases; decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "decreases; increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the shortest change of longitude between N36\u00b000\u2019 E155\u00b000\u2019 and N42\u00b000\u2019 W148\u00b000\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "57\u00b000\u2019",
        "303\u00b000\u2019",
        "39\u00b000\u2019",
        "151\u00b030\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "57\u00b000\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "Across Pole: Change of latitude = __________\u00b0 - (Latitude 1 + Latitude 2)",
      "choices": [
        "90",
        "45",
        "360",
        "180"
      ],
      "answer": "180"
    },
    {
      "question": "What units are used to define coordinates on the surface of the Earth?",
      "choices": [
        "Hours, minutes and seconds.",
        "Radians and Mils.",
        "Positive and negative declination.",
        "Degrees, minutes and seconds."
      ],
      "answer": "Degrees, minutes and seconds."
    },
    {
      "question": "1\u2019 change of longitude, along a parallel of latitude = __________ nm along a parallel of latitude \u00f7 __________ of the latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "1; sine",
        "60; cosine",
        "60; sine",
        "1; cosine"
      ],
      "answer": "1; cosine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Changing insolation throughout the year is partly due to: The changing distance of the Earth from the Sun, owing to the __________ orbit of the Earth around the Sun.",
      "choices": [
        "variation",
        "deviation",
        "declination",
        "elliptical"
      ],
      "answer": "elliptical"
    },
    {
      "question": "How are positions on the surface of the Earth defined?",
      "choices": [
        "Equatorial and polar distances.",
        "East and west coordinates.",
        "Latitude and longitude coordinates.",
        "North and south coordinates."
      ],
      "answer": "Latitude and longitude coordinates."
    },
    {
      "question": "How many metres are equal to 4 nm?",
      "choices": [
        "7480 m",
        "7408 m",
        "6436 m",
        "5542 m"
      ],
      "answer": "7408 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "To calculate new latitude and or longitude: Opposite hemispheres (east/west or north/south) = __________. Same hemisphere, e.g. east/east, = __________.",
      "choices": [
        "ADD; ADD",
        "SUBTRACT; ADD",
        "SUBTRACT; SUBTRACT",
        "ADD; SUBTRACT"
      ],
      "answer": "ADD; SUBTRACT"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the shortest distance between N65\u00b000\u2019 E142\u00b000\u2019 and N58\u00b000\u2019 W038\u00b000\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "1632 nm",
        "3420 nm",
        "3005 nm",
        "2241 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "3420 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Positions on the surface of the Earth and the WGS-84 ellipsoid are defined as the point of intersection of a geodetic __________ and a geodetic __________.",
      "choices": [
        "meridian; parallel.",
        "parallel; meridian.",
        "longitude; latitude.",
        "latitude; longitude."
      ],
      "answer": "latitude; longitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "1\u2019 change of latitude along a meridian of longitude = __________ nm. Change of latitude (degrees) = Distance (nm) \u00f7 __________.",
      "choices": [
        "1; 30",
        "360; 1",
        "60; 1",
        "1; 60"
      ],
      "answer": "1; 60"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the distance between N28\u00b030\u2019 W020\u00b000\u2019 and N15\u00b000\u2019 W020\u00b000\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "810 km",
        "810 nm",
        "810 sm",
        "2610 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "810 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The change of longitude between S45\u00b000\u2019 E030\u00b000\u2019 and N60\u00b000\u2019 E015\u00b000\u2019 is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "05\u00b000'",
        "16\u00b000'",
        "15\u00b000'",
        "25\u00b000'"
      ],
      "answer": "15\u00b000'"
    },
    {
      "question": "A train is travelling at a constant 120 mph. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how far would it have travelled after 22 minutes?",
      "choices": [
        "44 sm",
        "36 sm",
        "48 sm",
        "40 sm"
      ],
      "answer": "44 sm"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the distance between S30\u00b000\u2019 W142\u00b000\u2019 and S30\u00b000\u2019 E115\u00b000\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "1620 nm",
        "6155 nm",
        "5352 nm",
        "4421 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "5352 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The change of latitude between S38\u00b000\u2019 E120\u00b000\u2019 and N41\u00b000\u2019 E120\u00b000\u2019 is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "78\u00b000'",
        "81\u00b000'",
        "78\u00b060'",
        "79\u00b000'"
      ],
      "answer": "79\u00b000'"
    },
    {
      "question": "A racing car is driving at a constant 360 km/hr. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how far would it have travelled after 1 hr 30 min?",
      "choices": [
        "315 sm",
        "285 sm",
        "335 sm",
        "415 sm"
      ],
      "answer": "335 sm"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft must fly a distance of 225 nm in no more than 1 hr 55 min. Using a mechanical flight computer, what is the minimum speed it must maintain?",
      "choices": [
        "110 kt",
        "115 kt",
        "125 kt",
        "120 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "120 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The change of latitude between N72\u00b000\u2019 E035\u00b000\u2019 and N54\u00b000\u2019 E035\u00b000\u2019 is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "17\u00b060'",
        "18\u00b000'",
        "20\u00b000'",
        "16\u00b000'"
      ],
      "answer": "18\u00b000'"
    },
    {
      "question": "Meridians of longitude are imaginary lines on the surface of the Earth, west and east of the __________ Meridian, which join points of equal geodetic __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Equator; longitude.",
        "Greenwich; latitude.",
        "Greenwich; longitude.",
        "Equator; latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Greenwich; longitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "A car is driving at a constant 96 km/hr. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how far would it have travelled after 1 hr 30 min?",
      "choices": [
        "99.5 sm",
        "93 sm",
        "240 km",
        "144 sm"
      ],
      "answer": "99.5 sm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The antipodal geodetic latitude of any position has the __________ numerical value as the original position, but in the opposite hemisphere.",
      "choices": [
        "equal",
        "the same",
        "opposite",
        "different"
      ],
      "answer": "the same"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft travels due north from N33\u00b025\u2019 W107\u00b030\u2019 for 660 nm. What is its final position?",
      "choices": [
        "N44\u00b025\u2019 W107\u00b030\u2019",
        "N22\u00b025\u2019 W107\u00b030\u2019",
        "N39\u00b020\u2019 W107\u00b030\u2019",
        "S22\u00b025\u2019 W107\u00b030\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "N44\u00b025\u2019 W107\u00b030\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft travels due south from N03\u00b030\u2019 W045\u00b030\u2019 for 1666.8 km. What is its final position?",
      "choices": [
        "N11\u00b030\u2019 W045\u00b030\u2019",
        "S24\u00b018\u2019 W045\u00b030\u2019",
        "S11\u00b030\u2019 W045\u00b030\u2019",
        "N18\u00b030\u2019 W045\u00b030\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "S11\u00b030\u2019 W045\u00b030\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many centimetres are equal to 25 nm?",
      "choices": [
        "23 150 m",
        "92 600 m",
        "46 300 m",
        "52 000 m"
      ],
      "answer": "46 300 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the antipodes of a position on the surface of the Earth?",
      "choices": [
        "The position on the opposite side of the Earth, in terms of longitude only",
        "The position on the direct opposite side of the Earth, in terms of both latitude and longitude",
        "The position in the same hemisphere of the Earth, in terms of latitude, and opposite in longitude",
        "The position on the opposite side of the Earth, in terms of latitude only"
      ],
      "answer": "The position on the direct opposite side of the Earth, in terms of both latitude and longitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the distance between N60\u00b000\u2019 E075\u00b000\u2019 and N60\u00b000\u2019 E015\u00b000\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "1800 nm",
        "2910 km",
        "3600 nm",
        "3118 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "1800 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The distance, expressed in nautical miles, between positions on the same meridian of longitude is calculated as a change of __________, measured in minutes of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "longitude; arc.",
        "latitude; arc.",
        "longitude; latitude.",
        "latitude; latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "latitude; arc."
    },
    {
      "question": "The circumference of the Earth is approximately __________ km.",
      "choices": [
        "4000",
        "21 600",
        "26 100",
        "40 000"
      ],
      "answer": "40 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many nautical miles are equal to 19 631 200 cm?",
      "choices": [
        "98 nm",
        "112 nm",
        "106 nm",
        "76 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "106 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "A train is travelling at a constant 150 mph. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how far would it have travelled after 22 minutes?",
      "choices": [
        "55 sm",
        "40 sm",
        "50 sm",
        "27 sm"
      ],
      "answer": "55 sm"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the approximate circumference of the Earth at the Equator?",
      "choices": [
        "40 000 sm",
        "21 600 nm",
        "40 000 nm",
        "21 600 km"
      ],
      "answer": "21 600 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a geodetic latitude defined?",
      "choices": [
        "The angle (measured at the plane of the Equator) between a line, perpendicular to the surface of the Earth, joining a position north or south of the Equator to the centre of the Earth",
        "The angle (measured at the plane of the Earth's vertical axis) between a line, perpendicular to the surface of the Earth, joining a position north or south of the Equator to the plane of the axis",
        "The angle (measured at the plane of the Equator) between a line, perpendicular to the surface of the Earth, joining a position north or south of the Equator to the plane of the Equator",
        "The angle (measured at the plane of the Equator) between a line, perpendicular to the Equator, joining a position north or south of the Equator to the plane of the Equator"
      ],
      "answer": "The angle (measured at the plane of the Equator) between a line, perpendicular to the surface of the Earth, joining a position north or south of the Equator to the plane of the Equator"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the distance between S57\u00b045\u2019 W077\u00b030\u2019 and N36\u00b030\u2019 W077\u00b030\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "5655 km",
        "5655 sm",
        "10 473 km",
        "10 473 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "10 473 km"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the general direction of a meridian of longitude?",
      "choices": [
        "North, from the North Pole to the South Pole.",
        "North, from the South Pole to the North Pole.",
        "South, from the South Pole to the North Pole.",
        "South, from the North Pole to the South Pole."
      ],
      "answer": "North, from the South Pole to the North Pole."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying at a constant 240 knots. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how long does it take to travel 380 nm?",
      "choices": [
        "9 hr 30 min",
        "1 hr 31 min",
        "1 hr 52 min",
        "1 hr 35 min"
      ],
      "answer": "1 hr 35 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying at a constant 300 knots. Using a mechanical flight computer, approximately how far would it have travelled after 45 minutes?",
      "choices": [
        "225 nm",
        "250 nm",
        "200 nm",
        "185 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "225 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Departure (nm) = Change of __________ (min) x __________ latitude",
      "choices": [
        "longitude; sine",
        "latitude; cosine",
        "latitude; sine",
        "longitude; cosine"
      ],
      "answer": "longitude; cosine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the distance between S60\u00b000\u2019 W092\u00b000\u2019 and S60\u00b000\u2019 E089\u00b000\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "5370 nm",
        "5370 km",
        "5370 sm",
        "9301 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "5370 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Earth orbits the Sun along the plane of the __________ (orbital path) in the same direction that it rotates on its __________ axis.",
      "choices": [
        "insolation; horizontal",
        "insolation; vertical",
        "ecliptic; vertical",
        "ecliptic; horizonal"
      ],
      "answer": "ecliptic; vertical"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the correct formula for solving speed?",
      "choices": [
        "Speed = 1.23 x \u221aDistance x Time",
        "Speed = Distance x Time",
        "Speed = \u221aDistance x Time",
        "Speed = Distance \u00f7 Time"
      ],
      "answer": "Speed = Distance \u00f7 Time"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which direction does the Earth rotate around its vertical axis?",
      "choices": [
        "Westerly",
        "Southerly",
        "Easterly",
        "Northerly"
      ],
      "answer": "Easterly"
    },
    {
      "question": "Changing insolation throughout the year is the cumulative result of: The __________ of the Earth from the ecliptic.",
      "choices": [
        "variation",
        "declination",
        "deviation",
        "inclination"
      ],
      "answer": "inclination"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the shortest distance between S70\u00b000\u2019 W075\u00b000\u2019 and S80\u00b000\u2019 E105\u00b000\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "466 nm",
        "2910 nm",
        "1800 nm",
        "1739 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "1800 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ is the complementary angle to the latitude measured from the polar axis to the latitude.",
      "choices": [
        "Equator",
        "longitude",
        "co-longitude",
        "co-latitude"
      ],
      "answer": "co-latitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the angle of inclination between the Earth\u2019s horizontal, equatorial axis and the Ecliptic?",
      "choices": [
        "90\u00b0",
        "23\u00bd\u00b0",
        "66\u00bd\u00b0",
        "00\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "23\u00bd\u00b0"
    }
  ],
  "RNAV": [
    {
      "question": "What determines the arc radius of the Fixed Radius Transition?",
      "choices": [
        "Speed.",
        "Performance capability.",
        "Navaid.",
        "Altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Altitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a VFR cross-country flight, a landmark is spotted on a relative bearing of 315\u00b0. Three minutes later the same landmark is observed on a relative bearing of 270\u00b0. If the TAS is 90 kt and there is a tailwind of 30 kt, what is the distance to the landmark at the time of the second bearing?",
      "choices": [
        "4.5 NM",
        "3 NM",
        "6 NM",
        "2 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "6 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 309\u00b0M, with an NDB on a relative bearing of 320\u00b0 from the aircraft? Magnetic variation at the aircraft = 35\u00b0W and at the NDB = 40\u00b0W. What is the true bearing from the NDB to the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "234\u00b0T",
        "054\u00b0T",
        "049\u00b0T",
        "059\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "054\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ - the path over the ground the aircraft follows.",
      "choices": [
        "Direction",
        "Track",
        "Bearing",
        "Heading"
      ],
      "answer": "Track"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 235\u00b0M, with an NDB on a relative bearing of 080\u00b0 from the aircraft. What is the magnetic bearing from the NDB to the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "315\u00b0M",
        "135\u00b0M",
        "335\u00b0M",
        "155\u00b0M"
      ],
      "answer": "135\u00b0M"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 315\u00b0M, with an NDB on a relative bearing of 120\u00b0 from the aircraft? Magnetic variation at the aircraft = 10\u00b0W and at the NDB = 20\u00b0W. What is the true bearing from the NDB to the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "225\u00b0T",
        "045\u00b0T",
        "265\u00b0T",
        "245\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "245\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "What process is used to minimise the amount of residual error in a direct reading magnetic compass?",
      "choices": [
        "Compass magnetism reduction.",
        "Compass calibration swing.",
        "Compass alignment swing.",
        "Compass variation swing."
      ],
      "answer": "Compass calibration swing."
    },
    {
      "question": "The true bearing being followed by an aircraft is 145\u00b0T. Local magnetic variation = 15\u00b0W. Compass deviation = 5\u00b0E. What is the magnetic bearing?",
      "choices": [
        "130\u00b0M",
        "135\u00b0M",
        "160\u00b0M",
        "125\u00b0M"
      ],
      "answer": "160\u00b0M"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft\u2019s EFIS Navigation Display shows the aircraft to be on a heading of 271\u00b0M, with an island 45\u00b0 right of the centreline. Magnetic variation = 26\u00b0E. What is the true bearing from the island to the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "162\u00b0T",
        "290\u00b0T",
        "110\u00b0T",
        "342\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "162\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft\u2019s EFIS Navigation Display shows the aircraft to be on a heading of 303\u00b0M, with an island 30\u00b0 left of the centreline. Magnetic variation = 12\u00b0E. What is the true bearing from the island to the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "321\u00b0T",
        "105\u00b0T",
        "141\u00b0T",
        "285\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "105\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 205\u00b0M, with an island on a relative bearing of 270\u00b0 from the aircraft. Magnetic variation = 45\u00b0E. What is the true bearing from the island to the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "070\u00b0T",
        "160\u00b0T",
        "340\u00b0T",
        "250\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "340\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft\u2019s EFIS Navigation Display shows the aircraft to be on a heading of 008\u00b0M, with an island 45\u00b0 left of the centreline. Magnetic variation = 22\u00b0E. What is the true bearing from the island to the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "119\u00b0T",
        "299\u00b0T",
        "345\u00b0T",
        "165\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "165\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 353\u00b0M, and a land feature is visible 45\u00b0 left of the aircraft\u2019s nose. Magnetic variation at the aircraft = 22\u00b0E and at the land feature = 20\u00b0E. What is the true bearing of the aircraft from the land feature?",
      "choices": [
        "330\u00b0T",
        "148\u00b0T",
        "106\u00b0T",
        "150\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "150\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 212\u00b0M, and a land feature is visible 60\u00b0 left of the aircraft\u2019s nose. Magnetic variation at the aircraft = 14\u00b0E and at the land feature = 11\u00b0E. What is the true bearing of the aircraft from the land feature?",
      "choices": [
        "346\u00b0T",
        "318\u00b0T",
        "163\u00b0T",
        "343\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "346\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 212\u00b0M, and a land feature is visible 60\u00b0 left of the aircraft\u2019s nose.  Magnetic variation at the aircraft = 14\u00b0E and at the land feature = 11\u00b0E. What is the true bearing of the aircraft from the land feature?",
      "choices": [
        "346\u00b0T",
        "318\u00b0T",
        "343\u00b0T",
        "163\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "346\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "The magnetic bearing being followed by an aircraft is 303\u00b0M. Local magnetic variation = 8\u00b0E. Compass deviation = 2\u00b0E. What is the true bearing?",
      "choices": [
        "309\u00b0T",
        "295\u00b0T",
        "313\u00b0T",
        "311\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "311\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 100\u00b0T, with an island on a relative bearing of 060\u00b0 from the aircraft. What is the true bearing from the aircraft to the island?",
      "choices": [
        "160\u00b0T",
        "340\u00b0T",
        "040\u00b0T",
        "280\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "160\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 085\u00b0M, with an island on a relative bearing of 110\u00b0 from the aircraft. Magnetic variation = 15\u00b0W. What is the true bearing from the aircraft to the island?",
      "choices": [
        "140\u00b0T",
        "320\u00b0T",
        "180\u00b0T",
        "360\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "180\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a heading of 320\u00b0T, with an island on a relative bearing of 010\u00b0 from the aircraft. What is the true bearing from the island to the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "130\u00b0T",
        "330\u00b0T",
        "150\u00b0T",
        "310\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "150\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "How are bearings measured?",
      "choices": [
        "In degrees, counter-clockwise from a datum.",
        "In degrees, from a datum, in either direction.",
        "In radians, clockwise from a datum.",
        "In degrees, clockwise from a datum."
      ],
      "answer": "In degrees, clockwise from a datum."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the abbreviation DME stand for?",
      "choices": [
        "Direct Measuring Equipment",
        "Direct Monitoring Equipment",
        "Distance Monitoring Equipment",
        "Distance Measuring Equipment"
      ],
      "answer": "Distance Measuring Equipment"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on a QDR of 165\u00b0M from an NDB. Magnetic variation at the aircraft is 10\u00b0E and at the NDB is 12\u00b0E. What is the true bearing from the aircraft to the NDB?",
      "choices": [
        "335\u00b0T",
        "345\u00b0T",
        "175\u00b0T",
        "355\u00b0T"
      ],
      "answer": "355\u00b0T"
    },
    {
      "question": "What clocks are used in a Galileo satellite timing section?",
      "answers": [
        "3 types of clock are used; Caesium, Rubidium and Hydrogen Passive Maser clocks.",
        "2 types of clocks are used; Caesium Frequency Standard Clock and a Passive Hydrogen Maser Clock.",
        "2 types of clocks are used; a Rubidium Frequency Standard clock and a more accurate Passive Hydrogen Maser clock.",
        "They use 2 of the same type of clock; the very accurate Passive Hydrogen Maser clock."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "2 types of clocks are used; a Rubidium Frequency Standard clock and a more accurate Passive Hydrogen Maser clock."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following operating codes are used by which modes of operation?",
      "choices": [
        "C\/A and P \u2013 SPS and PPS.",
        "C\/A \u2013 SPS only, P \u2013 PPS only.",
        "C\/A \u2013 SPS and PPS, P \u2013 PPS only.",
        "C\/A \u2013 PPS only, P \u2013 SPS only."
      ],
      "answer": "C\/A \u2013 SPS only, P \u2013 PPS only."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the accuracy of Mode S altitude reporting?",
      "choices": [
        "50 ft",
        "25 ft",
        "200 ft",
        "100 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "25 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to a 5 dot HSI, in which of the following cases may an aircraft descend on the GP?",
      "choices": [
        "LOC deviation bar 3 dots right of centre and GP deviation bar centred.",
        "LOC deviation bar 2 dots right of centre and GP deviation bar 3 dots below centre.",
        "LOC deviation bar 2 dots left of centre and GP deviation 1 dot above centre.",
        "LOC deviation bar centred and GP deviation bar 3 dots above centre."
      ],
      "answer": "LOC deviation bar 2 dots left of centre and GP deviation 1 dot above centre."
    },
    {
      "question": "Assume that one of the GPS\/NAVSTAR satellites used by the receiver is faulty and that the PDOP has relatively low value when receiving signals from GPS satellites (including faulty). When signals from 6 satellites are received, the RAIM software in the receiver:",
      "choices": [
        "Is unable to identify the faulty satellite.",
        "Is not active, software needs 8 satellites to function correctly.",
        "Is able to detect the 1 satellite that is faulty, but is unable to identify it.",
        "Is able to detect the 1 satellite that is faulty and identify which one."
      ],
      "answer": "Is able to detect the 1 satellite that is faulty and identify which one."
    },
    {
      "question": "On which bearing do errors caused by the shoreline\/coastal effect reach their maximum?",
      "choices": [
        "Bearing 30 to 60 degrees to the coastline.",
        "Bearings 000-030 degrees to the coastline.",
        "Any bearing in HF band.",
        "Bearings perpendicular to the coastline."
      ],
      "answer": "Bearings 000-030 degrees to the coastline."
    },
    {
      "question": "Why should the tilt of an Airborne Weather Radar system (without auto tilt) be changed to a higher setting when descending over terrain?",
      "choices": [
        "If the beam\u2019s tilt remains at the setting used during cruise, the scanning range will be reduced and the strength of the reflected signals will be weaker.",
        "The higher tilt setting will keep the beam above the aircraft\u2019s flight path.",
        "The lower tilt setting will keep the beam above the aircraft\u2019s flight path.",
        "If the beam\u2019s tilt remains at the setting used during cruise, the scanning range will be reduced and significant ground clutter may be displayed."
      ],
      "answer": "If the beam\u2019s tilt remains at the setting used during cruise, the scanning range will be reduced and significant ground clutter may be displayed."
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot is requested by an ATC controller\u2019s to \u201cSquawk Ident\u201d. Which action should be taken by the pilot and what result will be shown to the controller?",
      "choices": [
        "The pilot should press the transponder IDENT button, which will cause the aircraft\u2019s data block on the ATC display to flash on and off repeatedly for 10 seconds.",
        "The pilot should turn the transponder off, re-select the previously entered Mode A transponder code and turn the transponder to Standby, which will cause the aircraft\u2019s data block on the ATC display to illuminate briefly.",
        "The pilot should press the transponder IDENT button, which will cause the aircraft\u2019s data block on the ATC display to illuminate briefly.",
        "The pilot should turn the transponder off, re-select the previously entered Mode A transponder code and turn the transponder to Mode C, which will cause the aircraft\u2019s data block on the ATC display to flash on and off repeatedly for 10 seconds."
      ],
      "answer": "The pilot should press the transponder IDENT button, which will cause the aircraft\u2019s data block on the ATC display to illuminate briefly."
    },
    {
      "question": "During ILS Category II and III operations, the pre take-off runway holding point is different to the holding point used in Category I operations in order to:",
      "choices": [
        "Move the holding point out of the ILS critical area as the holding is positioned within the ILS critical area during category I operations.",
        "Increase the distance from the runway of taxiing aircraft during low visibility, precision approach operations.",
        "Increase aircraft separation in very reduced visibility conditions.",
        "Prevent unacceptable interference of the ILS signal due to aircraft coming too near to the runway."
      ],
      "answer": "Prevent unacceptable interference of the ILS signal due to aircraft coming too near to the runway."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is required to approach a VOR station via the 244\u00b0 radial. In order to obtain correct sense indications the deviation indicator should be set to:",
      "choices": [
        "244\u00b0 with the TO flag showing.",
        "064\u00b0 with the FROM flag showing.",
        "244\u00b0 with the FROM flag showing.",
        "064\u00b0 with the TO flag showing."
      ],
      "answer": "064\u00b0 with the TO flag showing."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum range that an aircraft at FL80 could expect to detect a signal from a VOR at an elevation of 313 m above sea level is:",
      "choices": [
        "158 NM",
        "149 NM",
        "100 NM",
        "122 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "149 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is correct about the SBAS (Satellite-Based Augmentation Systems)?",
      "choices": [
        "In an SBAS the pseudo range correction are determined by geostationary satellites and sent to the users by a network of ground stations.",
        "In an SBAS the pseudo range correction are sent to the users by the satellite of the satellite systems (e.g. by GPS satellites for GPS).",
        "In an SBAS the pseudo range corrections are sent to the users by geostationary satellites.",
        "In an SBAS the pseudo range corrections are determined by geostationary satellites and sent to the users by the satellite of the satellite systems (e.g. by GPS satellites for GPS)."
      ],
      "answer": "In an SBAS the pseudo range corrections are sent to the users by geostationary satellites."
    },
    {
      "question": "Regarding the monitoring system of the VOR - which statement is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Failure of the VOR stations to stay within required limits will trigger VOR caution annunciator in the cockpit.",
        "Failure of the VOR station to stay within required limits can cause removal of identification and the navigation components from the carrier wave to cease.",
        "System monitors directly the phase of the reference signal and the phase of the variable signal.",
        "The monitoring system detects a change in the measured radial and the transmission power will be reduced and consequently only aircraft in the Terminal Area can use the VOR."
      ],
      "answer": "Failure of the VOR station to stay within required limits can cause removal of identification and the navigation components from the carrier wave to cease."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following additional aircraft parameters can be downloaded by the Mode S transponder?",
      "choices": [
        "TAS, Pitch angle, Vertical rate.",
        "Pitch angle, vertical rate, TAS.",
        "Vertical rate, pitch angle, TAS.",
        "Vertical rate, True Track angle and IAS"
      ],
      "answer": "Vertical rate, True Track angle and IAS"
    },
  
    {
      "question": "The direct track from an aircraft\u2019s position to an NDB is 050\u00b0T. W/V = 000\u00b0/30. TAS = 120 kt. What relative bearing to the NDB must be maintained for the aircraft to navigate to the NDB via the procedure known as homing?",
      "choices": [
        "000\u00b0",
        "050\u00b0",
        "230\u00b0",
        "310\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "000\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "A frequency of 117.25 MHz is entered into a DME airborne interrogator. What frequencies will be used by the interrogator for interrogation and reply?",
      "choices": [
        "1143 MHz and 1080 MHz",
        "114.3 MHz and 108.00 MHz",
        "117.25 MHz for both",
       "114.3 MHz and 108.00 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "1143 MHz and 1080 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name of the process used to fix an aircraft\u2019s position using VDF lines of position?",
      "choices": [
        "Trilateration.",
        "Ambulation.",
        "Progression.",
        "Triangulation."
      ],
      "answer": "Triangulation."
    },
    {
      "question": "The direct track from an aircraft\u2019s position to an NDB is 050\u00b0T. W/V = 000\u00b0/30. TAS = 120 kt. What relative bearing to the NDB must be maintained for the aircraft to navigate directly to the NDB via the procedure known as tracking?",
      "choices": [
        "349\u00b0",
        "011\u00b0",
        "191\u00b0",
        "169\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "011\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "A communications signal is being transmitted over a maximum range of 40 nm, using a 25 watt transmitter. What minimum power is required to increase the range to 60 nm?",
      "choices": [
        "60 watts",
        "40 watts",
        "25 watts",
        "55 watts"
      ],
      "answer": "60 watts"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum theoretical range that a VDF ground station, elevation 855 ft amsl, can receive a signal from an aircraft, in level flight at 4000 ft amsl?",
      "choices": [
        "211 km",
        "114 km",
        "182 km",
        "345 km"
      ],
      "answer": "211 km"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum permissible mean course line shift for a CAT III ILS localiser?",
      "choices": [
        "15 ft.",
        "25 ft.",
        "35 ft.",
        "10 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "10 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "RNP __________ requires special authorisation.",
      "choices": [
        "RNAV 2",
        "RNAV 5",
        "AR APCH",
        "RNAV/RNP 1"
      ],
      "answer": "AR APCH"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is correct about fly-by and fly-over waypoints and turns?",
      "choices": [
        "A fly-over waypoint is a waypoint that requires turn anticipation to allow tangential interception of the next segment of a route or procedure.",
        "A fly-by waypoint is a waypoint that requires turn anticipation to allow tangential interception of the next segment of a route or procedure.",
        "Turn via fly-over is always shorter than fly-by.",
        "Fly-by waypoints require turning in the overhead."
      ],
      "answer": "A fly-by waypoint is a waypoint that requires turn anticipation to allow tangential interception of the next segment of a route or procedure."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not one of the principal benefits of Area Navigation?",
      "choices": [
        "Allows direct straight-line paths between departure and destination airports in all cases.",
        "Instrument approaches at airports, which have no landing aids.",
        "Pre-programmed arrival and departure paths.",
        "Shorter routes."
      ],
      "answer": "Allows direct straight-line paths between departure and destination airports in all cases."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the correct acronym for an approach procedure based on area navigation?",
      "choices": [
        "RNAV APPCH",
        "RNAV APP",
        "RNP APCH",
        "ANAV APCH"
      ],
      "answer": "RNP APCH"
    },
    {
      "question": "When preparing your aircraft to commence a descent the ATS unit requests you to arrive at a level overhead the waypoint at a specified time. Which RNAV system would be required for this?",
      "choices": [
        "3D RNAV",
        "4D RNAV",
        "2D Precision RNAV",
        "2D Basic RNAV"
      ],
      "answer": "4D RNAV"
    },
    {
      "question": "PBN path terminator DF means:",
      "choices": [
        "Doppler Fix",
        "Destination Fix",
        "Direct to a Fix",
        "Designated Fix"
      ],
      "answer": "Direct to a Fix"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a visual flight, a useful method for a pilot to resolve any uncertainty in the aircraft's position is to maintain visual contact with the ground and:",
      "choices": [
        "fly reverse headings and associated timings until the point of departure is regained.",
        "fly the reverse of the heading being flown prior to becoming uncertain until a pinpoint is obtained.",
        "fly expanding circles until a pinpoint is obtained.",
        "set the heading towards a line feature such as a coastline, motorway, river or railway."
      ],
      "answer": "set the heading towards a line feature such as a coastline, motorway, river or railway."
    },
    {
      "question": "For climbing and descending problems, at which point in the climb are average values calculated?",
      "choices": [
        "1/2 x change of altitude",
        "2/3 x change of altitude",
        "1/4 x change of altitude",
        "1/2 x cruise altitude"
      ],
      "answer": "2/3 x change of altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following terms refers to a fixed radius path for en-route sections using Performance Based Navigation (PBN)?",
      "choices": [
        "RF leg type",
        "FRT leg type",
        "TMA leg type",
        "ABC leg type"
      ],
      "answer": "FRT leg type"
    },
    {
      "question": "RNAV or RNP system performance requirements are defined in terms of:",
      "choices": [
        "Accuracy, integrity, complexity.",
        "Accuracy, integrity.",
        "Accuracy, continuity.",
        "Accuracy, integrity, continuity."
      ],
      "answer": "Accuracy, integrity, continuity."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is true about Performance Based Navigation (PBN)?",
      "choices": [
        "As with conventional navigation it requires a ground-based infrastructure.",
        "It requires the development of sensor-specific procedures and routes.",
        "It is not sensor specific.",
        "It is based on sensor-specific navigation specifications."
      ],
      "answer": "It is not sensor specific."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the components of Total System Error?",
      "choices": [
        "MPE, NSE, FET",
        "PEM, ETE, FTA",
        "PDE, NSE, FTE",
        "PDA, NSE, FET"
      ],
      "answer": "PDE, NSE, FTE"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following navigation specifications requires 2 x Long Range Navigation Systems (LRNS), one of which may be IRS?",
      "choices": [
        "RNP 0.3",
        "RNP 1",
        "RNP 10",
        "RNP 4"
      ],
      "answer": "RNP 10"
    },
    {
      "question": "Can operators with aircraft equipped with a single IRS or INS extend their RNAV 10 capability time?",
      "choices": [
        "No, this is not possible.",
        "Yes, they can extend their time by updating.",
        "Yes, they can extend their time by applying to the State of Registration.",
        "Yes they can extend their time by fitting 2 IRS systems."
      ],
      "answer": "Yes, they can extend their time by updating."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following gives the best information about the progress of a flight between 2 en-route waypoints from a RNAV equipment?",
      "choices": [
        "ATA.",
        "Elapsed time on route.",
        "ETD.",
        "ETO."
      ],
      "answer": "ETO."
    },
    {
      "question": "PBN path terminator FA means:",
      "choices": [
        "Final Approach",
        "Fix to Approach",
        "Fix to Altitude",
        "Final Altitude"
      ],
      "answer": "Fix to Altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which RNP can be used in all phases of flight except for en-route oceanic/remote and final approach phases and is intended primarily for helicopters?",
      "choices": [
        "RNP AR APCH",
        "RNP 0.3",
        "RNP 5",
        "RNP 10"
      ],
      "answer": "RNP 0.3"
    },
    {
      "question": "An error during PBN operations in determining actual aircraft coordinates is a:",
      "choices": [
        "Flight Technical Error (FTE)",
        "Crew Coordination Error",
        "Navigation System Error (NSE)",
        "Path Definition Error (PDE)"
      ],
      "answer": "Navigation System Error (NSE)"
    },
    {
      "question": "What forms of vertical guidance are permissible for a RNP APCH LPV?",
      "choices": [
        "Barometric",
        "SBAS",
        "Barometric or SBAS",
        "Geometrically adjusted barometric"
      ],
      "answer": "SBAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the definition of a Radius to Fix flight path?",
      "choices": [
        "Path defined by radius and arc length, centred on a fix.",
        "Path to a position fix, based on a fixed radius from a point.",
        "Path between 2 VOR radials, along an arc, at a fixed radius from one of the VORs.",
        "Path along an arc at a fixed radius, commencing at a position fix."
      ],
      "answer": "Path defined by radius and arc length, centred on a fix."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the validity of the Navigation Database, under the normal AIRAC cycle?",
      "choices": [
        "56 days.",
        "30 days.",
        "28 Days",
        "1 calendar month"
      ],
      "answer": "28 Days"
    },
    {
      "question": "PBN Path terminator CA means:",
      "choices": [
        "Course to Altitude",
        "Certified Altitude",
        "Centre Altitude",
        "Centre Approach"
      ],
      "answer": "Course to Altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "An error during PBN operations arising from the RNAV system and its inability to accurately specify the desired path is a:",
      "choices": [
        "Crew Error (CE)",
        "Flight Technical Error (FTE)",
        "Path Definition Error (PDE)",
        "Navigation System Error (NSE)"
      ],
      "answer": "Path Definition Error (PDE)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following groups the components of PBN?",
      "choices": [
        "Navaid infrastructure, navigation specification, navigation application.",
        "Navaid specification, navigation application, navigation equipment.",
        "Navigation specification, navigation application, navigation equipment.",
        "Navaid infrastructure, navigation technical information, navigation application."
      ],
      "answer": "Navaid infrastructure, navigation specification, navigation application."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following best defines continuity?",
      "choices": [
        "The permanent conformance of the true position and the required position.",
        "A measure of the permanent accuracy of the system.",
        "The capability of the system to perform its function without interruption.",
        "The capability of the aircraft to always arrive at the correct time and position at any given waypoint."
      ],
      "answer": "The capability of the system to perform its function without interruption."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following best describes Area Navigation?",
      "choices": [
        "Area Navigation is defined as a means of navigation along any path, using station referenced navigation signals or a self-contained navigation system.",
        "Area Navigation is defined as a means of navigation by the most direct route, using station referenced navigation signals or a self-contained navigation system.",
        "Area Navigation is defined as a means of navigation along any chosen path, using GNSS wherever possible.",
        "Area Navigation is defined as a means of navigation along any path, using station referenced navigation signals."
      ],
      "answer": "Area Navigation is defined as a means of navigation along any path, using station referenced navigation signals or a self-contained navigation system."
    },
    {
      "question": "Precision RNAV (P-RNAV) requires a track-keeping accuracy of:",
      "choices": [
        "\u00b1 5.0 NM for 95% of the flight time.",
        "\u00b1 10.0 NM for 95% of the flight time.",
        "\u00b1 1.0 NM for 95% of the flight time.",
        "\u00b1 8.0 NM for 95% of the flight time."
      ],
      "answer": "\u00b1 1.0 NM for 95% of the flight time."
    },
    {
      "question": "RNP AR APCH is used:",
      "choices": [
        "In the arrival, approach and en-route phases of flight",
        "In the approach phase of flight.",
        "In all phases of flight except remote phases.",
        "In all phases of flight except approach phases."
      ],
      "answer": "In the approach phase of flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not an RNAV approach?",
      "choices": [
        "LNAV/VNAV",
        "LPV",
        "L/VNAV",
        "LNAV"
      ],
      "answer": "L/VNAV"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is true regarding an offset flight path?",
      "choices": [
        "An offset flight path is used for holding.",
        "It allows the crew to specify a vertical offset from a defined route.",
        "It allows the crew to specify a lateral offset from a defined route.",
        "An offset flight path is used for parallel approaches in terminal areas."
      ],
      "answer": "It allows the crew to specify a lateral offset from a defined route."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is Estimated Position Error (EPE) defined?",
      "choices": [
        "Comparison by system of probable amount of current error against margin of error allowable; variable by statistical analysis of all available sensors.",
        "Comparison by flight crew of probable amount of current error against margin of error allowable; variable by sensor used.",
        "Comparison by system of probable amount of current error against margin of error allowable; variable by sensor used.",
        "Comparison by system of actual amount of current error against margin of potential error allowable; variable by statistical analysis of all available sensors."
      ],
      "answer": "Comparison by system of probable amount of current error against margin of error allowable; variable by sensor used."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a 3D RNAV precision approach?",
      "choices": [
        "RNP APCH \u2013 LNAV",
        "RNP APCH - VNAV",
        "RNP APCH \u2013 LNAV/VNAV",
        "RNP APCH - LPV"
      ],
      "answer": "RNP APCH - LPV"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a navigation specification?",
      "choices": [
        "RNP 0.3",
        "RNP 1.3",
        "RNAV 10",
        "RNP 1"
      ],
      "answer": "RNP 1.3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the components of Total System Error is considered negligible and not factored into the mathematical solution for TSE?",
      "choices": [
        "Path Definition Error.",
        "Minimal Position Error.",
        "Navigation Systems Error.",
        "Flight Technical Error."
      ],
      "answer": "Path Definition Error."
    },
    {
      "question": "What form of lateral guidance is permissible for a 3D LNAV/VNAV non-precision approach?",
      "choices": [
        "GNSS",
        "VOR/DME",
        "ILS",
        "DME/DME"
      ],
      "answer": "GNSS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following best defines accuracy?",
      "choices": [
        "The accuracy of the aircraft in relation to its time and position at any given waypoint.",
        "The conformance of the true position and the required position.",
        "A measure of the accuracy of the system.",
        "The capability of the system to perform accurately without interruption."
      ],
      "answer": "The conformance of the true position and the required position."
    },
    {
      "question": "How can the RNAV 10 time limit be updated?",
      "choices": [
        "By cross-checking and updating the position in the FMC using DME/DME.",
        "By aligning the aircraft clocks to GNSS time.",
        "By resetting the aircraft clocks to the correct UTC parameters.",
        "By updating the position on the LRNS in use."
      ],
      "answer": "By updating the position on the LRNS in use."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which of the following navigation specifications may manual data entry be permitted in certain circumstances?",
      "choices": [
        "RNP 1",
        "RNAV 5",
        "RNAV 1",
        "PRNAV"
      ],
      "answer": "RNAV 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "PBN guidance may be either:",
      "choices": [
        "Horizontal or lateral.",
        "Angular or Lateral.",
        "Linear or angular.",
        "Linear or lateral."
      ],
      "answer": "Linear or angular."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Total System Error assumed in PBN operations encompasses:",
      "choices": [
        "Path Definition Error (PDE), Flight Technical Error (FTE), Navigation System Error (NSE)",
        "Path Terminator Error (PTE), Path Calculation Error (PCE), Flight Technical Error (FTE)",
        "Flight Technical Error (FTE), Navigation System Error (NSE), Path Calculation Error (PCE)",
        "Path Calculation Error (PCE), Navigation System Error (NSE), Flight Crew Error (FCE)"
      ],
      "answer": "Path Definition Error (PDE), Flight Technical Error (FTE), Navigation System Error (NSE)"
    },
    {
      "question": "3D RNAV fixing gives you:",
      "choices": [
        "Horizontal, vertical profile and time guidance.",
        "2D RNAV plus speed control.",
        "2D RNAV plus time guidance.",
        "Horizontal and vertical profile guidance."
      ],
      "answer": "Horizontal and vertical profile guidance."
    },
    {
      "question": "Concerning FMC databases:",
      "choices": [
        "company database and FMC databases can not be used at the same time.",
        "the navigation database may be customised for the specific airline operations.",
        "only the performance database may be customised by the company.",
        "only the navigation database may be customised by the company's cost index strategy."
      ],
      "answer": "the navigation database may be customised for the specific airline operations."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a 2D RNAV non-precision approach?",
      "choices": [
        "RNP APCH - LPV",
        "RNP AR APCH \u2013 LNAV/VNAV",
        "RNP APCH - LNAV",
        "RNP APCH - LNAV/VNAV"
      ],
      "answer": "RNP APCH - LNAV"
    },
    {
      "question": "The minimum equipment requirement for RNP 4 operation is:",
      "choices": [
        "1 LRNS plus twin GNSS",
        "2 LRNS, both of which must be GNSS",
        "2 LRNS, 1 of which must be GNSS",
        "1 LRNS"
      ],
      "answer": "2 LRNS, both of which must be GNSS"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is meant by RNAV 5?",
      "choices": [
        "The defined required accuracy of the navigation system, whereby the aircraft\u2019s actual position must be within 5 nm laterally and horizontally of its stated position, for 95% of the total flight time within RNAV 5 airspace.",
        "The containment limit of the aircraft is no more than 5 nm and the aircraft must be within 5 nm of its stated position throughout its flight time.",
        "The defined required accuracy of the navigation system, whereby the aircraft\u2019s actual position must be within 5 nm laterally and horizontally of its stated position, for 100% of the total flight time within RNAV 5 airspace.",
        "The preferred accuracy of the navigation system, whereby the aircraft\u2019s actual position must be within 5 nm laterally and horizontally of its stated position, for 90% of the total flight time within RNAV 5 airspace."
      ],
      "answer": "The defined required accuracy of the navigation system, whereby the aircraft\u2019s actual position must be within 5 nm laterally and horizontally of its stated position, for 95% of the total flight time within RNAV 5 airspace."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which navigation specifications are included in Advanced RNP (A-RNP)?",
      "choices": [
        "RNAV 2, RNAV/RNP 1 and RNP 0.3",
        "RNAV 5, RNAV/RNP 2, RNAV/RNP 1 and RNP APCH",
        "RNAV 10, RNAV/RNP 4, RNAV/RNP 1 and RNP APCH",
        "RNAV 2, RNAV/RNP 1 and RNP 0.3"
      ],
      "answer": "RNAV 5, RNAV/RNP 2, RNAV/RNP 1 and RNP APCH"
    },
    {
      "question": "PBN path terminator 'TF' means:",
      "choices": [
        "Terminal Fix",
        "Tower Fix",
        "Track to Fix",
        "Time to Fix"
      ],
      "answer": "Track to Fix"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is true with regard to RNP/RNAV navigation specifications?",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft approved to more stringent accuracy requirements automatically meet the functional requirements of a navigation specification with a less stringent accuracy requirement.",
        "Aircraft approved to more stringent accuracy requirements may not necessarily meet some of the functional requirements of a navigation specification with a less stringent accuracy requirement.",
        "Accuracy requirements are always similar to functional requirements.",
        "Aircraft approved to more stringent accuracy requirements will never meet the functional requirements of a navigation specification with a less stringent accuracy requirement."
      ],
      "answer": "Aircraft approved to more stringent accuracy requirements may not necessarily meet some of the functional requirements of a navigation specification with a less stringent accuracy requirement."
    },
    {
      "question": "An error in PBN operations relating to the execution of a flight along a defined path is a:",
      "choices": [
        "Flight Path Error (FPE)",
        "Path Definition Error (PDE)",
        "Navigation System Error (NSE)",
        "Flight Technical Error (FTE)"
      ],
      "answer": "Flight Technical Error (FTE)"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to Performance Based Navigation (PBN) what is the name of a curved terminal or approach section defined by radius, arc length and fix?",
      "choices": [
        "Radius approach.",
        "Fixed arc approach.",
        "Radius to fix.",
        "Curved terminal approach."
      ],
      "answer": "Radius to fix."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following lists all the stages of flight when it is possible to change the route in the active flight plan on an FMS equipped aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "Only before the flight plan is activated.",
        "Only once the aircraft is airborne.",
        "Only before take-off.",
        "At any time before take-off and throughout the flight."
      ],
      "answer": "At any time before take-off and throughout the flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "ICAO Annex 11 defines Area Navigation (RNAV) as a method of navigation which permits aircraft operation on any desired flight path:",
      "choices": [
        "Within the coverage of station-referenced navigation aids or within the limits of the capability of self-contained navigation system, or a combination of these.",
        "Outside the coverage of station-referenced navigation aids provided that it is equipped with a minimum of two serviceable self-contained navigation aids.",
        "Outside the coverage of station-referenced navigation aids provided that it is equipped with a minimum of one serviceable self-contained navigation aid.",
        "Within the coverage of station-referenced navigation aids provided that it is equipped with a minimum of one serviceable self-contained navigation aid."
      ],
      "answer": "Within the coverage of station-referenced navigation aids or within the limits of the capability of self-contained navigation system, or a combination of these."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following best defines integrity?",
      "choices": [
        "The belief in the aircraft navigation system, in relation to its time and position at all given waypoints.",
        "The functional ability of the system to perform its function without interruption.",
        "The measure of the trust that can be placed in the system.",
        "The capability of the system to provide accurate information continuously."
      ],
      "answer": "The measure of the trust that can be placed in the system."
    },
    {
      "question": "Fly-By Turn - __________ the waypoint to intercept new track without delay.",
      "choices": [
        "turn after",
        "turn before",
        "overfly",
        "underfly"
      ],
      "answer": "turn before"
    },
    {
      "question": "What sets standards for the coding of flight procedures?",
      "choices": [
        "ARINC 424",
        "ICAO Annex 10",
        "The PBN Manual",
        "ICAO Doc 8168"
      ],
      "answer": "ARINC 424"
    },
    {
      "question": "The navigation database in a PBN approved receiver is usually valid for?",
      "choices": [
        "30 days.",
        "56 days.",
        "28 days.",
        "One calendar month."
      ],
      "answer": "28 days."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the AR acronym of RNP AR APCH denote?",
      "choices": [
        "Authorisation Restricted.",
        "Special Authorisation Required.",
        "Approach Restricted (to certain licence holders).",
        "Approach Regulated."
      ],
      "answer": "Special Authorisation Required."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is correct, regarding PBN?",
      "choices": [
        "PBN is not sensor specific, like conventional navigation.",
        "PBN is navaid specific, like conventional navigation.",
        "PBN is not sensor specific, unlike conventional navigation.",
        "PBN is sensor specific, unlike conventional navigation."
      ],
      "answer": "PBN is not sensor specific, unlike conventional navigation."
    },
    {
      "question": "\"Accuracy of navigation system\" is a description of what navigation accuracy?.",
      "choices": [
        "Navigation Systems Error",
        "Flight Technical Error",
        "Path Definition Error",
        "Absolute Navigation Accuracy"
      ],
      "answer": "Navigation Systems Error"
    },
    {
      "question": "\"Error following prescribed path, by pilot or autopilot\" is a description of what navigation accuracy?",
      "choices": [
        "Flight Technical Error",
        "Navigation Systems Error",
        "Path Definition Error",
        "Special Authorisation Error"  
      ],
      "answer": "Flight Technical Error"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following navigation specification is used in all phases of flight, except oceanic / remote regions and final approach?",
      "choices": [
        "RNAV 0.5",
        "RNAV 1",
        "RNP 1",
        "RNP 0.3"
      ],
      "answer": "RNP 0.3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Advanced RNP incorporates RNAV __________ , RNAV/RNP 2, RNAV/RNP 1 and RNP APCH.",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "0",
        "5",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "question": "\"Error following prescribed path, by pilot or autopilot\" is a description of what navigation accuracy?",
      "choices": [
        "Navigation Systems Error",
        "Path Definition Error",
        "Flight Technical Error",
        "Absolute Flight Error"
      ],
      "answer": "Flight Technical Error"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "RNP APCH procedures can only be flown by commercial pilots holding a current, valid instrument rating for a multi-pilot aircraft.",
        "RNP APCH procedures must be retrievable by name from the navigation database and conform to the published chart, which does not have to be carried if a moving map display is available in the pilot\u2019s primary field of view.",
        "RNP APCH procedures must be retrievable by name from the navigation database and conform to the published chart.",
        "RNP APCH procedures must be stored in the current navigation database and index by airport name, runway and approach type."
      ],
      "answer": "RNP APCH procedures must be retrievable by name from the navigation database and conform to the published chart."
    },
    {
      "question": "Concerning an RNP AR APCH, what does AR stand for?",
      "choices": [
        "Angular Resolution",
        "Airborne Radar",
        "Approach Resolution",
        "Authorisation Required"
      ],
      "answer": "Authorisation Required"
    },
    {
      "question": "\"Managed by gross reasonableness checks of navigation data during procedure design, and usually negligible\" is a description of what navigation accuracy?",
      "choices": [
        "Flight Technical Error",
        "Navigation Systems Error",
        "Path Definition Error",
        "System Definition Error"
      ],
      "answer": "Path Definition Error"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the usual order of priority for navigation equipment in the RNAV hierarchy?",
      "choices": [
        "DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR, IRS, GNSS",
        "GNSS, IRS, DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR",
        "GNSS, DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR, IRS",
        "IRS, GNSS, DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR"
      ],
      "answer": "GNSS, IRS, DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR"
    },
    {
      "question": "Basic RNAV requires a track-keeping accuracy of:",
      "choices": [
        "+/- 5NM or better for 95% of the flight time.",
        "+/- 3NM or better for 90% of the flight time.",
        "+/- 2NM or better for 75% of the flight time.",
        "+/- 5NM or better throughout the flight."
      ],
      "answer": "+/- 5NM or better for 95% of the flight time."
    },
    {
      "question": "In terms of \u2018X\u2019, what is meant by RNAV \u2018X\u2019 and RNP \u2018X\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "The lateral system accuracy requirement where \u2018X\u2019 indicates required LNAV accuracy in nautical miles, for 90% of the flight time, with an added requirement for RNP to have an alerting and monitoring function.",
        "The lateral system accuracy requirement where \u2018X\u2019 indicates required LNAV accuracy in nautical miles, for 95% of the flight time, with an added requirement for RNAV to have an alerting and monitoring function.",
        "The lateral system accuracy requirement where \u2018X\u2019 indicates required LNAV accuracy in nautical miles, for 100% of the flight time, with an added requirement for RNP to have an alerting and monitoring function.",
        "The lateral system accuracy requirement where \u2018X\u2019 indicates required VNAV accuracy in nautical miles, for 95% of the flight time, with an added requirement for RNP to have an alerting function."
      ],
      "answer": "The lateral system accuracy requirement where \u2018X\u2019 indicates required LNAV accuracy in nautical miles, for 95% of the flight time, with an added requirement for RNAV to have an alerting and monitoring function."
    },
    {
      "question": "RNAV/RNP system performance requirements are defined in terms of which of the following?",
      "choices": [
        "Accuracy, Integrity and Continuity.",
        "Cooperation, Integrity and Reliability.",
        "Integrity, Consistency and Reliability.",
        "Precision, Accuracy and Reliability."
      ],
      "answer": "Accuracy, Integrity and Continuity."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a self-contained navigation system?",
      "choices": [
        "IRS/INS",
        "DME",
        "VOR",
        "GNSS"
      ],
      "answer": "IRS/INS"
    },
    {
      "question": "RNAV 10 and RNP 4 are used:",
      "choices": [
        "In the oceanic and remote phase of flight.",
        "In all phases of flight except in the en-route, approach and departure phases.",
        "In the approach phase of flight.",
        "In the en-route, approach and departure phases of flight."
      ],
      "answer": "In the oceanic and remote phase of flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Fly Over - __________ the waypoint before turning onto the new course.",
      "choices": [
        "turn after",
        "turn before",
        "overfly",
        "intercept"
      ],
      "answer": "overfly"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the required tracking accuracy for en-route NDB tracking?",
      "choices": [
        "+/-10\u00b0",
        "+/-2.5\u00b0",
        "+/-0.7\u00b0",
        "+/-5\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/-5\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following navigation aids will provide an RNAV system with position?",
      "choices": [
        "NDB",
        "VOR/DME",
        "VDF",
        "ADF"
      ],
      "answer": "VOR/DME"
    },
    {
      "question": "On modern passenger aircraft, the navigation data base usually contains:",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft performance data.",
        "Obstacle altitudes.",
        "Airport reference data.",
        "ATC frequencies."
      ],
      "answer": "Airport reference data."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are permitted by the use of offset flight paths?",
      "choices": [
        "They allow the RNAV computer to automatically select any route, off the defined route, at a fixed distance from a navaid.",
        "They allow the crew to fly a route, offset from a defined airway between two VORs, at a fixed distance from airway.",
        "They allow the crew to fly any route, entered into the RNAV computer off the defined route, at a fixed distance from a navaid.",
        "They allow the crew to fly a parallel route, entered into the RNAV computer, at a fixed distance from defined route."
      ],
      "answer": "They allow the crew to fly a parallel route, entered into the RNAV computer, at a fixed distance from defined route."
    },
    {
      "question": "The selection of code 7500 on an aircraft SSR transponder indicates:",
      "choices": [
        "unlawful interference with the planned operation of the flight",
        "an emergency",
        "radio communication failure",
        "transponder malfunction"
      ],
      "answer": "unlawful interference with the planned operation of the flight"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode S transponders can provide vertical tracking by using a _____ altitude increment.",
      "choices": [
        "100 ft",
        "25 ft",
        "50 ft",
        "35 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "25 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The minimum number of ground stations required to give range and bearing information using Direction Finding alone is:",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "3",
        "1",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following SSR modes provides altitude information to +/-25 ft of accuracy?",
      "choices": [
        "Mode S",
        "Mode C",
        "Mode B",
        "Mode A"
      ],
      "answer": "Mode S"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement with respect to the transponder interrogation modes A, C and S is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Mode S Only all-call will trigger transponder replies of all mode A/C/S transponders.",
        "Mode S Selective will trigger replies of all mode S transponders. Mode A/C transponders are suppressed.",
        "Intermode A/C/S all call and Intermode A/C only all call, differ in the pulse spacing used between the P1 and P3 pulses.",
        "Mode S All-Call will transmit information to all mode S transponders."
      ],
      "answer": "Mode S All-Call will transmit information to all mode S transponders."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which increments of altitude is a Mode C pressure altitude transmitted?",
      "choices": [
        "250 ft",
        "500 ft",
        "100 ft",
        "1000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "100 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which is the most significant difference between GBAS and SBAS?",
      "choices": [
        "SBAS uses an intermediate satellite to relay correction factors to the aircraft, GBAS transmits correction factors information directly to the aircraft.",
        "SBAS uses an intermediate satellite to relay correction factors to the aircraft, GBAS transmits error data directly to the aircraft.",
        "SBAS uses an intermediate satellite to relay error data to the aircraft, GBAS transmits correction factors directly to the aircraft.",
        "GBAS uses an intermediate satellite to relay correction factors to the aircraft, SBAS transmits error data directly to the aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "SBAS uses an intermediate satellite to relay correction factors to the aircraft, GBAS transmits error data directly to the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is lateral position determined on an ILS LOC?",
      "choices": [
        "Phase difference, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 150 Hz and 90 Hz respectively.",
        "Difference in depth of modulation, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 150 Hz and 90 Hz respectively.",
        "Phase difference, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz respectively.",
        "Difference in depth of modulation, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz respectively."
      ],
      "answer": "Difference in depth of modulation, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz respectively."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is being indicated by a flashing reply lamp or illuminated letter \u201cR\u201d?",
      "choices": [
        "The transponder is in reply mode and can only reply to ground based interrogations and not respond to TCAS interrogations.",
        "The transponder is being interrogated by a ground station and is replying to that interrogation",
        "The transponder is receiving replies from a ground station it is interrogating.",
        "The transponder is relaying Mode S / TCAS interrogations from another aircraft to the controlling ATC facility."
      ],
      "answer": "The transponder is being interrogated by a ground station and is replying to that interrogation"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the worldwide SBAS in use is: _________ - India.",
      "choices": [
        "EGNOS",
        "MSAS",
        "WAAS",
        "GAGAN"
      ],
      "answer": "GAGAN"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many satellites are required for a 3D position fix?",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "5",
        "6",
        "4"
      ],
      "answer": "4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Within which time period must SBAS alert users of GNSS malfunctions?",
      "choices": [
        "10 seconds",
        "6 seconds",
        "8 seconds",
        "2 seconds"
      ],
      "answer": "6 seconds"
    },
    {
      "question": "Frequency band of the SBAS data link is:",
      "choices": [
        "962 to 1213 MHz.",
        "VHF band of ILS and VOR systems.",
        "A signal with the same frequency as GPS.",
        "VHF band 108.0 to 111.975 MHz."
      ],
      "answer": "A signal with the same frequency as GPS."
    },
    {
      "question": "What frequencies are used by SSR?",
      "choices": [
        "Different Interrogation (UHF) and Reply (UHF) frequencies.",
        "Same Interrogation (UHF) and Reply (UHF) frequencies.",
        "Same Interrogation (VHF) and Reply (VHF) frequencies.",
        "Different Interrogation (UHF) and Reply (VHF) frequencies."
      ],
      "answer": "Different Interrogation (UHF) and Reply (UHF) frequencies."
    },
    {
      "question": "Marker beacons are identified visually (cockpit lights) and audibly (Morse identification) as follows: Outer marker - __________ coloured - __________ dashes per second at __________frequency.",
      "choices": [
        "Amber; continuous; medium",
        "White; 6; high",
        "Blue; 4; low",
        "Blue; 2; low"
      ],
      "answer": "Blue; 2; low"
    },
    {
      "question": "What information is provided in a satellite 3D position fix?",
      "choices": [
        "Latitude, longitude, distance and time.",
        "Latitude, longitude, altitude and satellite ID.",
        "Latitude, longitude, altitude and time.",
        "Latitude, longitude, bearing, and time"
      ],
      "answer": "Latitude, longitude, altitude and time."
    },
    {
      "question": "When Mode C is selected on the aircraft SSR transponder the additional information transmitted is:",
      "choices": [
        "Altitude based on regional QNH.",
        "Height based on QFE.",
        "Pressure altitude based on 1013.25 hPa.",
        "Aircraft height based on sub-scale setting."
      ],
      "answer": "Pressure altitude based on 1013.25 hPa."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is approaching the MLS extended centre-line from the left. How will the cockpit indications present themselves?",
      "choices": [
        "The horizontal guidance deviation bar will move towards the centre from the right side of the EHSI.",
        "The horizontal guidance deviation bar will be in the centre of the EHSI and the aircraft indicator will move from the left towards the centre.",
        "The horizontal guidance deviation bar will move towards the centre from the left side of the EHSI.",
        "The horizontal guidance deviation bar will be in the centre of the EHSI and the aircraft indicator will move from the right towards the centre."
      ],
      "answer": "The horizontal guidance deviation bar will move towards the centre from the right side of the EHSI."
    },
    {
      "question": "As a flight progresses you observe that what you saw as one return on your AWR screen has now turned into two separate echoes.",
      "choices": [
        "The AWR is malfunctioning and the information cannot be trusted.",
        "It is a function that shows areas of CAT.",
        "It is normal since with decreasing range the beam width azimuth will also decrease.",
        "It is due to unwanted returns from contamination on the radome."
      ],
      "answer": "It is normal since with decreasing range the beam width azimuth will also decrease."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which transponder mode results in interrogations being received and aircraft identification plus altitude being returned?",
      "choices": [
        "Mode C",
        "Mode B",
        "Mode D",
        "Mode A"
      ],
      "answer": "Mode C"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following phenomena is least likely to be detected by radar?",
      "choices": [
        "Wet snow and turbulence in cloud that has precipitation.",
        "Clear air turbulence.",
        "Precipitation.",
        "Turbulence in cloud that has precipitation."
      ],
      "answer": "Clear air turbulence."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is shown on the ATC RADAR screen when the pilot pushes the Special Position Identification (SPI) button on the transponder?",
      "choices": [
        "The removal of that aircraft from the RADAR display.",
        "A flashing indication of all the aircraft which are not \"squawking ident\".",
        "A flashing indication of the aircraft which is \"squawking ident\".",
        "A flashing indication of all the aircraft on the RADAR display."
      ],
      "answer": "A flashing indication of the aircraft which is \"squawking ident\"."
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode __________ interrogation contains either: Specific aircraft address. All-call. Selective surveillance calling (Roll-call).",
      "choices": [
        "C",
        "S",
        "A",
        "O"
      ],
      "answer": "S"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the largest source of error with NDB/ADF systems?",
      "choices": [
        "Thunderstorm activity.",
        "Skywave interference.",
        "Quadrantal error.",
        "Coastal effect."
      ],
      "answer": "Thunderstorm activity."
    },
    {
      "question": "A RAIM system has excluded a satellite. How many satellites are required to maintain a 3D Position fix with RAIM capability?",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "6",
        "5",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the worldwide SBAS in use is: _________ - USA.",
      "choices": [
        "WAAS",
        "MSAS",
        "GAGAN",
        "EGNOS"
      ],
      "answer": "WAAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the wavebands of the ILS components?",
      "choices": [
        "LOC \u2013 VHF, GP \u2013 VHF, DME \u2013 VHF",
        "LOC \u2013 VHF, GP \u2013 UHF, DME \u2013 UHF",
        "LOC \u2013 UHF, GP \u2013 UHF, DME \u2013 VHF",
        "LOC \u2013 VHF, GP \u2013 UHF, DME \u2013 VHF"
      ],
      "answer": "LOC \u2013 VHF, GP \u2013 UHF, DME \u2013 UHF"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is defined by a pseudo-range?",
      "choices": [
        "A circular line of position on the surface of the Earth with the receiver at the centre of the circle and the pseudo-range forming the distance from the satellite to the receiver.",
        "A sphere with the receiver at the centre and the pseudo-range forming the distance from the satellite to the receiver.",
        "A sphere with the satellite at the centre and the pseudo-range forming the circumference of the receiver.",
        "A sphere with the satellite at the centre and the pseudo-range forming the distance from the satellite to the receiver."
      ],
      "answer": "A sphere with the satellite at the centre and the pseudo-range forming the distance from the satellite to the receiver."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the most significant factor when calculating UERE?",
      "choices": [
        "Satellite clock error.",
        "Ionospheric propagation delay.",
        "Dilution of position.",
        "Satellite orbital variations."
      ],
      "answer": "Ionospheric propagation delay."
    },
    {
      "question": "During preparation for an MLS curved approach the DME/P is found to be inoperative. What type of approach must be flown?",
      "choices": [
        "Standard ILS-type approach with a straight-in final approach segment.",
        "The curved approach may be flown using DME/N but using higher approach minima at a greater range.",
        "There are no restrictions to the curved MLS approach, which is dependent on horizontal and vertical guidance only.",
        "The curved approach may be flown using DME/N but using higher approach minima."
      ],
      "answer": "Standard ILS-type approach with a straight-in final approach segment."
    },
    {
      "question": "SSR modes of operation are determined by the time spacing between pulse pairs, and are: Mode __________ - addressing and flight data.",
      "choices": [
        "C",
        "A",
        "O",
        "S"
      ],
      "answer": "S"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the worldwide SBAS in use is: _________ - Japan.",
      "choices": [
        "MSAS",
        "EGNOS",
        "GAGAN",
        "WAAS"
      ],
      "answer": "MSAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "What would be the approximate range over the sea of an NDB transmitting at 250 watts?",
      "choices": [
        "70 NM",
        "50 NM",
        "60 NM",
        "80 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "50 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is defined by \u201can area around LOC and GP antennas where operations are prohibited during ILS operations\u201d?",
      "choices": [
        "ILS prohibited area.",
        "ILS maintenance area.",
        "ILS sensitive area.",
        "ILS critical area."
      ],
      "answer": "ILS critical area."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a GNSS, commercially used for aircraft navigation?",
      "choices": [
        "GLONASS",
        "SKYNET",
        "NAVSTAR",
        "GALILEO"
      ],
      "answer": "SKYNET"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the minimum coverage area of the final approach path (FAP) for a ground-based augmentation system (GBAS) augmented approach?",
      "choices": [
        "10\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance between 15 and 20 NM, and 35\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 15 NM.",
        "10\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance of 25 NM, and 35\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 17 NM.",
        "35\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance of 20 NM, and 20\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 10 NM.",
        "10\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance between 17 NM and 22 NM, and 30\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 17 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "10\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance between 15 and 20 NM, and 35\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 15 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "What can be calculated by the receiver by using Doppler effect or change of calculated position?",
      "choices": [
        "Ground speed.",
        "Heading.",
        "Calibrated Airspeed.",
        "New position information data."
      ],
      "answer": "Ground speed."
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the worldwide SBAS in use is: _________ - Western Europe and the Mediterranean.",
      "choices": [
        "MSAS",
        "GAGAN",
        "EGNOS",
        "WAAS"
      ],
      "answer": "EGNOS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement relating to the stabilisation of airborne weather radar antennas is true?",
      "choices": [
        "They are stabilised with respect to the pitch, roll, and yaw-axis.",
        "They are stabilised with respect to the pitch and roll axis but not with respect to the yaw-axis.",
        "The pilot can choose the axes of stabilisation with the systems stabilisation selector switch.",
        "They are stabilised with respect to the yaw-axis, but not with respect to the pitch and roll axis."
      ],
      "answer": "They are stabilised with respect to the pitch and roll axis but not with respect to the yaw-axis."
    },
    {
      "question": "How many Mode A addresses are available to transponders?",
      "choices": [
        "4096",
        "7777",
        "16.7 million",
        "Infinite"
      ],
      "answer": "4096"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the area of coverage of a GBAS protected zone, with reference to the extended centerline of any approach?",
      "choices": [
        "+/- 8\u00b0 to 20 nm and +/- 35\u00b0 to 17 nm",
        "+/- 10\u00b0 to 25 nm and +/- 35\u00b0 to 17 nm",
        "+/- 10\u00b0 to 20 nm and +/- 35\u00b0 to 15 nm",
        "+/- 15\u00b0 to 20 nm and +/- 40\u00b0 to 20 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "+/- 10\u00b0 to 20 nm and +/- 35\u00b0 to 15 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which transponder mode setting is selected in order to provide aircraft identification and altitude information to an interrogating station?",
      "choices": [
        "ALT",
        "SBY",
        "ON",
        "TEST"
      ],
      "answer": "ALT"
    },
    {
      "question": "in which frequency band does an ILS GP transmit?",
      "choices": [
        "UHF",
        "SHF",
        "VHF",
        "EHF"
      ],
      "answer": "UHF"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the maximum LOC and GP deviations on an ILS cockpit indicator?",
      "choices": [
        "LOC +/- 2.5\u00b0 and GP +/- 1\u00b0",
        "LOC +/- 10\u00b0 and GP +/- 2.5\u00b0",
        "LOC +/- 5\u00b0 and GP +/- 2\u00b0",
        "LOC +/- 2.5\u00b0 and GP +/- 0.7\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "LOC +/- 2.5\u00b0 and GP +/- 0.7\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Multipath interference in ground-based radar systems is the result of:",
      "choices": [
        "multiple echo paths, and enables targets to be accurately identified.",
        "ionospheric reflection, which amplifies the echoes from targets.",
        "echoes from targets caused, for example, by ground reflection.",
        "line-of-sight echoes being repeated multiple times."
      ],
      "answer": "echoes from targets caused, for example, by ground reflection."
    },
    {
      "question": "What information, additional to primary radar, is obtained by SSR Modes A and C?",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft ID and pressure altitude.",
        "Aircraft bearing, range, airframe 24-bit ID and pressure altitude.",
        "Aircraft airframe 24-bit ID and pressure altitude.",
        "Aircraft type and pressure altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Aircraft ID and pressure altitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "When may an MLS curved approach be flown?",
      "choices": [
        "Published approach procedure, with DME/P functional, with an authorised flight crew using an automatic flight control system.",
        "Published approach procedure, with DME/P functional, with an authorised flight crew.",
        "Published approach procedure, with DME/P functional, and using an automatic flight control system.",
        "Published approach procedure and using an automatic flight control system."
      ],
      "answer": "Published approach procedure, with DME/P functional, with an authorised flight crew using an automatic flight control system."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the acronym RAIM stand for?",
      "choices": [
        "Receiver Autonomous Identity Monitoring",
        "Receiver Application Integrity Monitoring",
        "Receiver Altitude Information Monitoring",
        "Receiver Autonomous Integrity Monitoring"
      ],
      "answer": "Receiver Autonomous Integrity Monitoring"
    },
    {
      "question": "GBAS ground subsystems provide two services, the precision approach service and the GBAS positioning service. The precision approach service provides:",
      "choices": [
        "Horizontal position information to support RNAV operations.",
        "Horizontal position information on the ground.",
        "Deviation guidance for Going Around Segments.",
        "Deviation guidance for Final Approach Segments."
      ],
      "answer": "Deviation guidance for Final Approach Segments."
    },
     {
      "question": "A GPS satellite is marked unhealthy by:",
      "choices": [
        "An independent international body controlling the functioning of GPS.",
        "The GPS control segment.",
        "The space division of the Department of Transportation of the USA.",
        "The GPS space segment."
      ],
      "answer": "The GPS control segment."
    },
    {
      "question": "SSR modes of operation are determined by the time spacing between pulse pairs, and are: Mode __________ - identification.",
      "choices": [
        "O",
        "C",
        "A",
        "S"
      ],
      "answer": "A"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the primary modes of operation used in NAVSTAR/GPS?",
      "choices": [
        "SPS, PPS and EPS.",
        "PPS and EPS.",
        "SPS, PPS, EPS and RPS.",
        "SPS and PPS."
      ],
      "answer": "SPS and PPS."
    },
    {
      "question": "Marker beacons are identified visually (cockpit lights) and audibly (Morse identification) as follows: Inner marker - __________ coloured - __________ dots per second at __________ frequency.",
      "choices": [
        "White; 6; high",
        "White; 2; high",
        "Amber; continuous; medium",
        "Blue; 2; low"
      ],
      "answer": "White; 6; high"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the main components of SSR?",
      "choices": [
        "Ground-based interrogator and airborne transponder.",
        "Airborne interrogator and ground-based transponder.",
        "ATC radar system and squawk box.",
        "Ground-based transmitter with remote receiving antenna for capturing reply echoes from aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "Ground-based interrogator and airborne transponder."
    },
    {
      "question": "A Mode C-transponder is able to report the pressure altitude in:",
      "choices": [
        "100 ft increments.",
        "25 ft increments.",
        "50 m increments.",
        "100 m increments."
      ],
      "answer": "100 ft increments."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is on the 120\u00b0 radial from a VOR station. Course 340\u00b0 is selected on the HSI (Horizontal Situation Indicator). If the Magnetic Heading is 070\u00b0, the deviation bar relative to the aeroplane model, will be:",
      "choices": [
        "Right.",
        "Behind.",
        "Left.",
        "In front."
      ],
      "answer": "Behind."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is the DME frequency selected for a MLS approach?",
      "choices": [
        "It is frequency paired to the MLS SHF frequency, which is automatically selected by the MMR on entering the DME channel number.",
        "Using a separate standard DME interrogator and DME frequency.",
        "It is frequency paired to the MLS SHF frequency, which is automatically selected by the MMR on entering the DME frequency.",
        "It is frequency paired to the MLS SHF frequency and automatically selected by the MMR on entering the MLS frequency and/or channel number."
      ],
      "answer": "It is frequency paired to the MLS SHF frequency and automatically selected by the MMR on entering the MLS frequency and/or channel number."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is distance information obtained for MLS approaches?",
      "choices": [
        "DME/N",
        "Micro DME",
        "MLS DME",
        "DME/P"
      ],
      "answer": "DME/P"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a Mode S interrogation type?",
      "choices": [
        "All-call.",
        "Selective calling.",
        "Responsive selection.",
        "Aircraft addressing."
      ],
      "answer": "Responsive selection."
    },
    {
      "question": "The 3 main components of an ILS are?",
      "choices": [
        "VOR, Glidepath, Range information.",
        "Localiser, Glidepath, Glideslope.",
        "Localiser, Glidepath, Range information.",
        "Azimuth, Elevation, DME/P."
      ],
      "answer": "Localiser, Glidepath, Range information."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the recommended nominal GP angle?",
      "choices": [
        "3.2\u00b0",
        "3.5\u00b0",
        "4\u00b0",
        "3\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "3\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "The quadrantal error of an ADF:",
      "choices": [
        "May be caused by the interference of VORs within range of the ADF receiver and cannot be compensated for.",
        "Is caused by aircraft magnetism and varies with the deviation as shown on the deviation table.",
        "Is caused by interference from the sky wave.",
        "Is compounded by an electro-magnetic force induced in the receiver aerial by the signal re-radiating from the aircrafts metallic surfaces, causing multi-path signals."
      ],
      "answer": "Is compounded by an electro-magnetic force induced in the receiver aerial by the signal re-radiating from the aircrafts metallic surfaces, causing multi-path signals."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following contain the principle elements of a GNSS?",
      "choices": [
        "Satellite, User and Ground segments.",
        "Space, Receiver, Ground and Control segments.",
        "Satellite, Receiver and Ground segments.",
        "Space, User and Control segments."
      ],
      "answer": "Space, User and Control segments."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the principle of operation in an ILS, the glide path indicator needle is centred when the Difference in Depth of Modulation (DDM) is:",
      "choices": [
        "More than 150 Hz",
        "Maximum",
        "Zero",
        "Less than 90 Hz"
      ],
      "answer": "Zero"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is vertical position determined on an ILS GP?",
      "choices": [
        "Difference in depth of modulation, calculated from 2 overlapping upper and lower lobes of energy, modulated at 150 Hz and 90 Hz respectively.",
        "Phase difference, calculated from 2 overlapping upper and lower lobes of energy, modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz respectively.",
        "Difference in depth of modulation, calculated from 2 overlapping upper and lower lobes of energy, modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz respectively.",
        "Phase difference, calculated from 2 overlapping upper and lower lobes of energy, modulated at 150 Hz and 90 Hz respectively."
      ],
      "answer": "Difference in depth of modulation, calculated from 2 overlapping upper and lower lobes of energy, modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz respectively."
    },
    {
      "question": "What frequency band does MLS operate in?",
      "choices": [
        "UHF",
        "SHF",
        "VHF",
        "MHF"
      ],
      "answer": "SHF"
    },
    {
      "question": "SPS uses the _________frequency only.",
      "choices": [
        "L2",
        "L1",
        "L3",
        "L4"
      ],
      "answer": "L1"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a consequence of LOC and GP lateral (side) lobes?",
      "choices": [
        "False LOC and GP beams, which causes reverse sensing on the cockpit display indications.",
        "Additional LOC and GP beams, which can be used to provide alternative approaches to landing for suitably equipped aircraft.",
        "False LOC and GP beams, which causes excessive indications on the cockpit display indications, outside normal indications.",
        "Interference with the ILS cockpit display equipment, which may cause erratic indications."
      ],
      "answer": "False LOC and GP beams, which causes reverse sensing on the cockpit display indications."
    },
    {
      "question": "The frequency range for ILS is?",
      "choices": [
        "118.00 \u2013 111.975 MHz",
        "108.00 \u2013 111.975 MHz",
        "111.975 \u2013 117.975 MHz",
        "108.00 \u2013 117.975 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "108.00 \u2013 111.975 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Q code for a magnetic bearing from a VDF station?",
      "choices": [
        "QTE",
        "QNH",
        "QDM",
        "QDR"
      ],
      "answer": "QDR"
    },
    {
      "question": "SSR modes of operation are determined by the time spacing between pulse pairs, and are: Mode __________ - altitude.",
      "choices": [
        "S",
        "A",
        "O",
        "C"
      ],
      "answer": "C"
    },
    {
      "question": "How could a pilot counter the effects of reverse sensing when flying a LOC BC approach?",
      "choices": [
        "By using an OBI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the ILS front course .",
        "By using a HSI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the ILS front course.",
        "By using an OBI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the LOC back-course .",
        "By using a HSI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the LOC back-course."
      ],
      "answer": "By using a HSI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the ILS front course."
    },
    {
      "question": "A back beam from the LOC antenna can be used as what type of approach?",
      "choices": [
        "Precision back-course approach with glide path information.",
        "Non-precision back-course approach with glide path information.",
        "Non-precision back-course approach with no glide path information.",
        "Precision back-course approach with no glide path information."
      ],
      "answer": "Non-precision back-course approach with no glide path information."
    },
    {
      "question": "By what term is Mode S Selective Surveillance Call more commonly known?",
      "choices": [
        "Mode S Select.",
        "Addressing Call.",
        "All Call.",
        "Roll Call."
      ],
      "answer": "Roll Call."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a primary radar using pulse technique, pulse length determines:",
      "choices": [
        "target discrimination",
        "minimum measurable range",
        "beam width",
        "maximum measurable range"
      ],
      "answer": "minimum measurable range"
    },
    {
      "question": "The interrogator transmits its interrogation signal as a series of __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "flight levels",
        "pressure altitudes",
        "pulse pairs",
        "frequencies"
      ],
      "answer": "pulse pairs"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is an advantage of an SSR with a selective addressing mode over primary radar?",
      "choices": [
        "It is independent from airborne and space based systems.",
        "Its range is unrelated to its transmitting power.",
        "It allows for unambiguous aircraft identification.",
        "In case of a transponder malfunction, the SSR can be used as a primary radar."
      ],
      "answer": "It allows for unambiguous aircraft identification."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a satellite identified to a GNSS receiver?",
      "choices": [
        "The satellite transmits a unique Pseudo-Random Noise (PRN) code to the receiver, containing the satellite ID and time of transmission.",
        "The receiver interrogates the satellite, which responds with its unique ID number in the form of a Pseudo-Random Noise (PRN) code.",
        "Each satellite transmits an Almanac which contains all of the approximate positions of each satellite, which is then compared to the on-board Almanac at the receiver, to check the integrity of pseudo-ranges.",
        "Each satellite transmits a database of all Pseudo-Random Noise (PRN) codes, which are received at the receiver, and compared to the positions of each satellite in its on-board Ephemeris."
      ],
      "answer": "The satellite transmits a unique Pseudo-Random Noise (PRN) code to the receiver, containing the satellite ID and time of transmission."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following affects VDF range?",
      "choices": [
        "The height of the transmitter and of the receiver.",
        "Sky wave propagation.",
        "Coastal refraction.",
        "Strength of the pilot's voice when transmitting."
      ],
      "answer": "The height of the transmitter and of the receiver."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following frequencies are used by which modes of operation?",
      "choices": [
        "L1 \u2013 PPS, L2 \u2013 SPS",
        "L1 \u2013 SPS, L2 \u2013 PPS",
        "L1 and L2 \u2013 SPS and PPS",
        "L1 \u2013 SPS and PPS, L2 \u2013 PPS"
      ],
      "answer": "L1 \u2013 SPS and PPS, L2 \u2013 PPS"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the MLS protected zone coverage, in relation to the runway extended centreline?",
      "choices": [
        "+/- 40\u00b0 out to 20 nm",
        "+/- 35\u00b0 out to 15 nm",
        "+/- 10\u00b0 out to 25 nm",
        "+/- 35\u00b0 out to 17 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "+/- 40\u00b0 out to 20 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Marker beacons are identified visually (cockpit lights) and audibly (Morse identification) as follows: Middle marker - __________ coloured - __________ alternating dots and dashes at __________ frequency.",
      "choices": [
        "White; 6; high",
        "Amber; 4; medium",
        "Amber; continuous; medium",
        "Blue; 2; low"
      ],
      "answer": "Amber; continuous; medium"
    },
    {
      "question": "For what reason is a mask angle set-up in a GPS-receiver?",
      "choices": [
        "To select from all visible GPS-satellites the satellite-configuration which results in the smallest GDOP.",
        "To make the receiver select GPS-satellites with a certain optimum elevation which is about equal to the mask angle.",
        "To deny the receiver the use of GPS-satellites with an elevation less than the mask angle.",
        "To eliminate the reception of the signal from GPS-satellites with an elevation of about 90\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "To deny the receiver the use of GPS-satellites with an elevation less than the mask angle."
    },
    {
      "question": "In what increments does Mode S carry out enhanced vertical tracking?",
      "choices": [
        "75 ft",
        "50 ft",
        "25 ft",
        "100 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "25 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the coverage of the ILS LOC protected zone, in relation to the runway extended centreline?",
      "choices": [
        "+/- 10\u00b0 to 17 nm and +/- 35\u00b0 to 25 nm",
        "+/- 10\u00b0 to 15 nm and +/- 35\u00b0 to 20 nm",
        "+/- 10\u00b0 to 20 nm and +/- 35\u00b0 to 15 nm",
        "+/- 10\u00b0 to 25 nm and +/- 35\u00b0 to 17 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "+/- 10\u00b0 to 25 nm and +/- 35\u00b0 to 17 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The interrogator and transponder use different __________.",
      "choices": [
        "frequencies",
        "pressure altitudes",
        "flight levels",
        "signals"
      ],
      "answer": "frequencies"
    },
    {
      "question": "What guidance is provided during an MLS approach?",
      "choices": [
        "Horizontal, vertical and distance guidance during the approach and horizontal guidance during a missed approach.",
        "Horizontal, vertical and distance guidance during all approach and missed approach phases.",
        "Horizontal and vertical guidance during the approach only.",
        "Horizontal, vertical and distance guidance during the approach only."
      ],
      "answer": "Horizontal, vertical and distance guidance during the approach and horizontal guidance during a missed approach."
    },
    {
      "question": "An ILS warning flag will appear on either the localiser or the glideslope display when:",
      "choices": [
        "Only when both the 90 Hz and the 150 Hz signals are lost by one of the aircraft receivers.",
        "When the ILS ground station detects a fault in the aircraft receiver.",
        "Either the 90 Hz or the 150 Hz signal is lost by one of the aircraft receivers.",
        "Only when valid signals for both localiser and glideslope are lost."
      ],
      "answer": "Either the 90 Hz or the 150 Hz signal is lost by one of the aircraft receivers."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following ILS approaches will provide guidance down to and along the surface of the runway?",
      "choices": [
        "LNAV + VNAV",
        "CAT III",
        "CAT I",
        "CAT II"
      ],
      "answer": "CAT III"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the plan coverage of the ILS GP protected zone, in relation to the runway extended centreline?",
      "choices": [
        "+/- 8\u00b0 to 10 nm",
        "+/- 8\u00b0 to 17 nm",
        "+/- 10\u00b0 to 8 nm",
        "+/- 10\u00b0 to 17 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "+/- 8\u00b0 to 10 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Each satellite transmits timing and ranging signals on 2 frequencies, L_________ and L_________.",
      "choices": [
        "A; B",
        "Alpha; Beta",
        "1; 2",
        "X,Y"
      ],
      "answer": "1; 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many different MLS frequencies are available?",
      "choices": [
        "250",
        "200",
        "300",
        "100"
      ],
      "answer": "200"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum time to alert (TTA) if the signal is lost when using SBAS augmentation during RNP APCH procedures?",
      "choices": [
        "0.3 seconds",
        "15 seconds",
        "6 seconds",
        "10 seconds"
      ],
      "answer": "6 seconds"
    },
    {
      "question": "What equipment is required by an aircraft to fly an MLS approach?",
      "choices": [
        "Multi-mode receiver in MLS mode plus specific MLS display equipment.",
        "Multi-mode receiver in GLS mode.",
        "VHF NAV receiver, DME interrogator plus OBI.",
        "Multi-mode receiver in MLS mode plus standard display equipment."
      ],
      "answer": "Multi-mode receiver in MLS mode plus standard display equipment."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the meaning of the transponder special code 7600?",
      "choices": [
        "Emergency.",
        "Unlawful interference with the safe conduct of a flight.",
        "Mode S airspace.",
        "Loss of communications."
      ],
      "answer": "Loss of communications."
    },
    {
      "question": "How many Mode S aircraft addresses are currently in use?",
      "choices": [
        "7777",
        "4096",
        "16.7 million",
        "Infinite"
      ],
      "answer": "16.7 million"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which transponder mode results in interrogations being received but only aircraft identification being returned?",
      "choices": [
        "Mode C",
        "Mode D",
        "Mode B",
        "Mode A"
      ],
      "answer": "Mode A"
    },
    {
      "question": "With thunderstorms reported in the vicinity, when lining up on the runway what would you do with the weather radar?",
      "choices": [
        "Select map mode to get a wider coverage during the take-off period.",
        "Turn the Ground clutter switch to off.",
        "Increase the gain to get a better image.",
        "After scanning upwards to look for weather, set the tilt a few degrees up."
      ],
      "answer": "After scanning upwards to look for weather, set the tilt a few degrees up."
    },
    {
      "question": "RAIM is a type of _________ using GNSS information only.",
      "choices": [
        "SBAS",
        "ABAS",
        "GBAS",
        "RBAS"
      ],
      "answer": "ABAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "What, typically, are the additional on-board sensors forming constituent parts of an AAIM system?",
      "choices": [
        "VHF NAV and DME.",
        "VHF NAV and IRS.",
        "Barometric altimetry and VHF NAV equipment.",
        "Barometric altimetry and IRS."
      ],
      "answer": "Barometric altimetry and IRS."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the acronym NDB stand for?",
      "choices": [
        "Non-Directional Beacon",
        "Node-Debugging Beacon",
        "Navigation Database",
        "Near Deflective Beacon"
      ],
      "answer": "Non-Directional Beacon"
    },
    {
      "question": "What part of the ICAO frequency range of VORs is shared with ILS?",
      "choices": [
        "108.00 \u2013 111.975 MHz",
        "95.00 \u2013 111.975 MHz",
        "108.00 \u2013 117.975 MHz",
        "111.975 \u2013 117.975 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "108.00 \u2013 111.975 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ : a complete series of values of a periodical process.",
      "choices": [
        "Amplitude",
        "Wavelength",
        "Frequency",
        "Cycle"
      ],
      "answer": "Cycle"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is correct regarding antenna shadowing?",
      "choices": [
        "Terrain blocking the path between the transmitter and receiver/aircraft antenna.",
        "Poor reception of GPS signals due to very weak signals compared to the background noise at that frequency.",
        "Reduced reception by an antenna when part of the airframe blocks the signal to the antenna.",
        "Protection of a radar-reception antenna from the strong signals produced by a nearby transmission antenna."
      ],
      "answer": "Reduced reception by an antenna when part of the airframe blocks the signal to the antenna."
    },
    {
      "question": "VHF, UHF, SHF and EHF propagate as direct line-of-sight __________ wave.",
      "choices": [
        "Sky",
        "Ground",
        "Space",
        "Multi-path"
      ],
      "answer": "Space"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a VOR frequency differentiated from an ILS frequency?",
      "choices": [
        "VOR \u2013 even number after the decimal, ILS \u2013 odd number after the decimal.",
        "VOR \u2013 odd number before the decimal, ILS \u2013 even number before the decimal.",
        "VOR \u2013 even number before the decimal, ILS \u2013 odd number before the decimal.",
        "VOR \u2013 odd number after the decimal, ILS \u2013 even number after the decimal."
      ],
      "answer": "VOR \u2013 even number after the decimal, ILS \u2013 odd number after the decimal."
    },
    {
      "question": "When homing to an NDB with a wind from the left, what change, if any, can be expected to the aircraft heading?",
      "choices": [
        "A decrease in heading with right drift.",
        "A decrease in heading with left drift.",
        "Constant heading.",
        "An increase in heading with left drift."
      ],
      "answer": "A decrease in heading with right drift."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which mode of propagation is most likely to be the primary means of propagation for a signal being transmitted on a frequency of 116.45 MHz?",
      "choices": [
        "Mexican wave",
        "Space wave",
        "Surface wave",
        "Sky wave"
      ],
      "answer": "Space wave"
    },
    {
      "question": "The skip distance of HF-transmission will increase with:",
      "choices": [
        "higher frequency and higher level of the refracting ionospheric layer.",
        "higher frequency and lower level of the refracting ionospheric layer.",
        "lower frequency and lower level of the refracting ionospheric layer.",
        "lower frequency and higher level of the refracting ionospheric layer."
      ],
      "answer": "higher frequency and higher level of the refracting ionospheric layer."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the International Telecommunication Union (ITU} code, a radio signal may be classified by three symbols. The abbreviation A3E is used for the type of transmission in which the carrier wave is:",
      "choices": [
        "A continuous wave interrupted with a keyed Morse code ident as used by an NDB.",
        "A double sideband carrier wave, frequency modulated for speech, such as is used for VHF-COM.",
        "Amplitude modulated to transmit the Morse code ident, as is used by a VOR.",
        "Amplitude modulated by a speech signal, such as is used for VHF-COM."
      ],
      "answer": "Amplitude modulated by a speech signal, such as is used for VHF-COM."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the ICAO frequency range for NDB transmitters?",
      "choices": [
        "190 \u2013 1750 KHz",
        "108.00 \u2013 117.95 MHz",
        "30 \u2013 300 MHz",
        "300 KHz \u2013 3 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "190 \u2013 1750 KHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ propagation: signal reflected from surfaces near the receiver arrives at the receiver from several directions almost simultaneously.",
      "choices": [
        "Space",
        "Sky",
        "Ground",
        "Multi-path"
      ],
      "answer": "Multi-path"
    },
    {
      "question": "Doppler Effect: the __________ of a wave increases or decreases if there is relative motion between the transmitter and the receiver.",
      "choices": [
        "frequency",
        "amplitude",
        "wavelength",
        "cycle"
      ],
      "answer": "frequency"
    },
    {
      "question": "How are radio waves in MF propagated?",
      "choices": [
        "At daytime as ground wave and sky wave, during night only as ground wave.",
        "At daytime and during night only as ground wave.",
        "At daytime as ground wave, during night as ground wave and sky wave.",
        "At daytime as ground wave, during night only as sky wave."
      ],
      "answer": "At daytime as ground wave, during night as ground wave and sky wave."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a VOR radial converted into a true bearing?",
      "choices": [
        "+/- magnetic inclination.",
        "+/- compass deviation.",
        "+/- magnetic deviation.",
        "+/- magnetic variation."
      ],
      "answer": "+/- magnetic variation."
    },
    {
      "question": "The AWR system may not be able to detect anything behind __________ rain, owing to the total beam energy being __________ by the rain.",
      "choices": [
        "light; reflected",
        "heavy; reflected",
        "heavy; absorbed",
        "heavy; attenuated"
      ],
      "answer": "heavy; reflected"
    },
    {
      "question": "A radio signal may be classified by three symbols in accordance with the ITU radio regulation e.g. A 1 A. Which statement is true?",
      "choices": [
        "The second symbol indicates the nature of information to be transmitted.",
        "The three symbols together indicate which device is transmitting on the carrier.",
        "The third symbol indicates the nature of the signal modulating the main carrier.",
        "The first symbol indicates the type of modulation of the main carrier."
      ],
      "answer": "The first symbol indicates the type of modulation of the main carrier."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a Radio Magnetic Indicator (RMI) used to indicate the bearing to/from a VOR?",
      "choices": [
        "The needle indicates true bearing TO the VOR at the point of the needle.",
        "The needle indicates true bearing TO the VOR at the tail of the needle.",
        "The needle indicates magnetic bearing TO the VOR at the point of the needle.",
        "The needle indicates magnetic bearing FROM the VOR at the point of the needle."
      ],
      "answer": "The needle indicates magnetic bearing TO the VOR at the point of the needle."
    },
    {
      "question": "Using which mode of propagation is it possible for a signal to be transmitted over long ranges on a frequency of 289 KHz, at 06.30 UTC in the USA?",
      "choices": [
        "Reflection",
        "Direct line-of-sight",
        "Refraction",
        "Diffraction"
      ],
      "answer": "Refraction"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which mode of propagation is most likely to be the primary means of propagation for a signal being transmitted on a frequency of 388.5 KHz, at 14.30 UTC in Western Europe?",
      "choices": [
        "Mexican wave",
        "Ground wave",
        "Space wave",
        "Sky wave"
      ],
      "answer": "Ground wave"
    },
    {
      "question": "Phase __________ : the angular difference in phase angle between the corresponding points of 2 cycles of equal frequency/wavelength, measured in degrees.",
      "choices": [
        "amplitude",
        "frequency",
        "difference",
        "angle"
      ],
      "answer": "difference"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refraction from ionospheric layers is used in which of the following radio frequencies:",
      "choices": [
        "HF",
        "VHF",
        "UHF",
        "VLF"
      ],
      "answer": "HF"
    },
    {
      "question": "RMI Radial __________ (QDM) - at the point of the needle.",
      "choices": [
        "TO",
        "FROM",
        "Waypoint",
        "Bearing"
      ],
      "answer": "TO"
    },
    {
      "question": "DME operates in the __________ frequency band, using __________ frequencies for interrogation and reply.",
      "choices": [
        "VHF; same",
        "UHF; different",
        "UHF; same",
        "VHF; different"
      ],
      "answer": "UHF; different"
    },
    {
      "question": "International Telecommunication Union (ITU) classification abbreviations used in aviation include the (1) ____ _ abbreviation. This designates carrier wave emissions amplitude modulated with Morse code which is used by (2) _____ .",
      "choices": [
        "(1) A3E; (2) NDBs",
        "(1) A2A; (2) VORs",
        "(1) A3E; (2) VORs",
        "(1) A2A; (2) NDBs"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) A2A; (2) NDBs"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the receiver aerial location of a GNSS system?",
      "choices": [
        "Left wing tip.",
        "Bottom of the fuselage.",
        "Top of the tail.",
        "Top of the fuselage."
      ],
      "answer": "Top of the fuselage."
    },
    {
      "question": "How many navigational signals are transmitted by a VOR transmitter?",
      "choices": [
        "2 \u2013 radial and identification.",
        "2 \u2013 reference phase and variable phase.",
        "4 \u2013 reference phase, variable phase, identification and ATIS.",
        "3 - reference phase, variable phase and identification."
      ],
      "answer": "2 \u2013 reference phase and variable phase."
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio signal frequency: the frequency of the __________ wave.",
      "choices": [
        "modulated",
        "carrier",
        "radio",
        "amplified"
      ],
      "answer": "carrier"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name of the process used to fix an aircraft\u2019s position using VDF lines of position?",
      "choices": [
        "Ambulation.",
        "Trilateration.",
        "Progression.",
        "Triangulation."
      ],
      "answer": "Triangulation."
    },
    {
      "question": "AWR may be used to detect turbulence and __________ indirectly by analysing the movement of water droplets.",
      "choices": [
        "thunder",
        "wind shear",
        "lightning",
        "rain"
      ],
      "answer": "wind shear"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which mode of propagation is most likely to be the primary means of propagation for a signal being transmitted on a frequency of 315 KHz, at 11.30 UTC in the Republic of Ireland?",
      "choices": [
        "Direct line-of-sight",
        "Refraction",
        "Diffraction",
        "Reflection"
      ],
      "answer": "Diffraction"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the order of colours, with increasing intensity of precipitation, on a modern airborne weather radar system?",
      "choices": [
        "Black, White, Amber, Red",
        "Green, Amber, Red, Magenta",
        "Amber, Red, Magenta, Green",
        "Black, Amber, Red, Green"
      ],
      "answer": "Green, Amber, Red, Magenta"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the approximate speed of light?",
      "choices": [
        "3 x 10\u2078 nm/s",
        "162 x 10\u00b3 km/s",
        "3 x 10\u2078 km/s",
        "3 x 10\u2078 m/s"
      ],
      "answer": "3 x 10\u2078 m/s"
    },
    {
      "question": "The cockpit displays indicate compass bearing to and from an NDB: __________ - at the tail of the needle.",
      "choices": [
        "FROM",
        "TO",
        "Bearing",
        "Heading"
      ],
      "answer": "FROM"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the beam width normally used by modern radar systems for the detection of weather systems?",
      "choices": [
        "3 \u2013 5\u00b0",
        "10\u00b0",
        "1\u00b0",
        "85\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "3 \u2013 5\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "When raising the frequency of an electromagnetic wave, the:",
      "choices": [
        "Wavelength and amplitude increases",
        "Wavelength remains the same.",
        "Wavelength decreases.",
        "Wavelength increases."
      ],
      "answer": "Wavelength decreases."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying away from a ground station, whilst transmitting a signal at a frequency of 134.975 MHz. What is the approximate frequency being received at the ground station?",
      "choices": [
        "Slightly less than 134.975 MHz.",
        "More than 134.975 MHz.",
        "Significantly more than 134.975 MHz.",
        "134.975 MHz."
      ],
      "answer": "Slightly less than 134.975 MHz."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum deviation that can be shown by the deviation bar on a standard omni-bearing indicator in VOR mode?",
      "choices": [
        "+/-5\u00b0",
        "+/-2.5\u00b0",
        "+/-15\u00b0",
        "+/-10\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/-10\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ space: the gap between the end of the ground wave and the first returning sky wave. Also known as the skip zone.",
      "choices": [
        "Space",
        "Carrier",
        "Dead",
        "Empty"
      ],
      "answer": "Dead"
    },
    {
      "question": "What Q code refers to the magnetic bearing from the ground station?",
      "choices": [
        "QTE",
        "QUJ",
        "QDR",
        "QDM"
      ],
      "answer": "QDR"
    },
    {
      "question": "DME groundspeed is calculated by rate of change of __________, and reads 0 when flying a DME arc at a constant range.",
      "choices": [
        "angle",
        "height",
        "range",
        "bearing"
      ],
      "answer": "range"
    },
    {
      "question": "The super position of two EM-waves of the same or nearly the same frequency is called:",
      "choices": [
        "Refraction.",
        "Diffraction.",
        "Reflection.",
        "Interference."
      ],
      "answer": "Interference."
    },
    {
      "question": "At what speed do radio waves travel?",
      "choices": [
        "30 000 m/s",
        "300 000 000 km/s",
        "300 000 000 m/s",
        "300 000 m/s"
      ],
      "answer": "300 000 000 m/s"
    },
    {
      "question": "What techniques do primary surveillance radar systems use to obtain information?",
      "choices": [
        "Doppler shift.",
        "Interrogation and reply.",
        "Inverse square process.",
        "Pulse and echo."
      ],
      "answer": "Pulse and echo."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the term \"antenna shadowing\" mean?",
      "choices": [
        "The antenna is placed under a dome.",
        "Antenna shadowing occurs when the incoming line-of-sight signal from the source is partially or fully blocked by another antenna in front of it.",
        "Terrain deflects the signal transmitted by the aircraft's transmitter.",
        "The antenna is shielded from the sun in order to reduce the influence of the ionosphere."
      ],
      "answer": "Antenna shadowing occurs when the incoming line-of-sight signal from the source is partially or fully blocked by another antenna in front of it."
    },
    {
      "question": "The cockpit displays indicate compass bearing to and from an NDB: __________ - at the point of the needle.",
      "choices": [
        "FROM",
        "TO",
        "Position",
        "Location"
      ],
      "answer": "TO"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the range of an NDB locator beacon?",
      "choices": [
        "20 \u2013 35 nm",
        "25 \u2013 50 nm",
        "10 \u2013 25 nm",
        "15 \u2013 30 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "10 \u2013 25 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "An AWR display uses __________ and range marker lines to indicate bearing and range to targets.",
      "choices": [
        "azimuth",
        "frequency control",
        "beam width",
        "radar"
      ],
      "answer": "azimuth"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the 2 items of active equipment used in distance measurement?",
      "choices": [
        "Airborne transponder and ground-based interrogator/responder.",
        "Airborne interrogator and ground-based transponder.",
        "Ground-based interrogator and airborne transponder.",
        "Airborne interrogator/responder and ground-based calculator."
      ],
      "answer": "Airborne interrogator and ground-based transponder."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is meant by keying in A 1 A modulation:",
      "choices": [
        "adding information on the carrier wave by use of a modulating signal.",
        "changing the amplitude of the carrier wave to add information.",
        "interrupting the carrier wave to break it into dots and dashes.",
        "interrupting the modulating signal to break it into dots and dashes."
      ],
      "answer": "interrupting the carrier wave to break it into dots and dashes."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ : the physical distance travelled by one complete wave in one cycle.",
      "choices": [
        "Cycle",
        "Amplitude",
        "Frequency",
        "Wavelength"
      ],
      "answer": "Wavelength"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum permissible tracking error when tracking to or from an NDB?",
      "choices": [
        "+/- 10\u00b0",
        "+/- 2\u00b0",
        "+/- 1\u00b0",
        "+/- 5\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/- 5\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which aircraft would a DME transponder preferentially respond to?",
      "choices": [
        "The 100 aircraft with the strongest signals.",
        "The 100 aircraft at the lowest altitudes.",
        "The 100 aircraft at the highest altitudes.",
        "The 100 closest aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "The 100 aircraft with the strongest signals."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which frequency band may fading occur during the twilight period?",
      "choices": [
        "VHF",
        "UHF",
        "HF",
        "MF"
      ],
      "answer": "MF"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the approximate wavelength of an airborne weather radar system?",
      "choices": [
        "30 cm",
        "3 cm",
        "0.3 m",
        "0.3 cm"
      ],
      "answer": "3 cm"
    },
    {
      "question": "When homing: __________ crosswind = __________ drift = heading increasing.",
      "choices": [
        "Left; left",
        "Right; left",
        "Right; right",
        "Left; right"
      ],
      "answer": "Right; left"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following forms of modulation maintains a constant frequency?",
      "choices": [
        "Deciduous",
        "Frequency",
        "Volumetric",
        "Amplitude"
      ],
      "answer": "Amplitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "What waveband do airborne weather radars typically operate in?",
      "choices": [
        "Metric",
        "Centimetric",
        "Millimetric",
        "Decimetric"
      ],
      "answer": "Centimetric"
    },
    {
      "question": "The phase angle of a wave is:",
      "choices": [
        "The deflection on a wave expressed in degrees from 000\u00b0 to 360\u00b0.",
        "The angle of the modulation on a wavelength expressed in degrees from 000\u00b0 to 360\u00b0.",
        "The fraction of one wavelength expressed in degrees from 000\u00b0 to 360\u00b0.",
        "The position of a modulation on a wavelength expressed in degrees from 000\u00b0 to 360\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "The fraction of one wavelength expressed in degrees from 000\u00b0 to 360\u00b0."
    },
    {
      "question": "Scalloping is a fluctuation of the navigation signal and occurs when signals are __________ by terrain, buildings or vehicles.",
      "choices": [
        "absorbed",
        "attenuated",
        "reflected",
        "amplified"
      ],
      "answer": "reflected"
    },
    {
      "question": "The process by which EM-energy is taken up by the atmosphere is called:",
      "choices": [
        "Interference.",
        "Absorption.",
        "Diffraction.",
        "Refraction."
      ],
      "answer": "Absorption."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the acronym VDF stand for?",
      "choices": [
        "Vertical Direction Finding",
        "Visual Direction Finding",
        "VHF Distance Finder",
        "VHF Direction Finding"
      ],
      "answer": "VHF Direction Finding"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the 2 main functions of an airborne weather radar system?",
      "choices": [
        "Detection of thunderstorms and in-flight icing.",
        "Detection of cumulonimbus clouds and turbulence.",
        "Detection of turbulence and rain.",
        "Detection of adverse weather and ground navigation."
      ],
      "answer": "Detection of adverse weather and ground navigation."
    },
    {
      "question": "The line-of-sight range is limited by the __________ of the Earth.",
      "choices": [
        "curvature",
        "density",
        "atmosphere",
        "temperature"
      ],
      "answer": "curvature"
    },
    {
      "question": "By what angle should a 4\u00b0 beam be tilted to determine whether distant clouds are above the flight path of an aircraft in level flight?",
      "choices": [
        "Tilt down by 4\u00b0",
        "Tilt up by 2\u00b0",
        "The tilt angle should be maintained at 0\u00b0 and the gain increased",
        "Tilt up by 4\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "Tilt up by 2\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What ionospheric phenomena is responsible for the propagation of NDB signals at night?",
      "choices": [
        "Diffracted space wave.",
        "Reflected ground wave.",
        "Refracted sky wave.",
        "Diffracted sky wave."
      ],
      "answer": "Refracted sky wave."
    },
    {
      "question": "The ionosphere is divided into which layers by day and by night?",
      "choices": [
        "They are the same by day and by night.",
        "E and F by day and D, E and F by night.",
        "D and E by day and F by night.",
        "D, E, F1, F2 by day and E and F by night."
      ],
      "answer": "D, E, F1, F2 by day and E and F by night."
    },
    {
      "question": "The wavelength of a non-directional beacon (NDB) with a frequency of 300 kHz is:",
      "choices": [
        "10 metres.",
        "100 metres.",
        "1000 metres.",
        "1 metre."
      ],
      "answer": "1000 metres."
    },
    {
      "question": "Why do VHF radio signals used for communication and navigation have a limited range?",
      "choices": [
        "Direct waves interfere with ionosphere waves.",
        "Sky waves are refracted from the D-layer.",
        "Ground waves are absorbed by the Earth's surface.",
        "Because of the curvature of the Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "Because of the curvature of the Earth."
    },
    {
      "question": "The wave length of a radio signal transmitted at a frequency of 118.7 MHz is:",
      "choices": [
        "25.3 m.",
        "2.53 m.",
        "25.3 cm.",
        "2.53 cm."
      ],
      "answer": "2.53 m."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the ICAO frequency range of VORs?",
      "choices": [
        "962 \u2013 1213 MHz",
        "190 \u2013 1750 KHz",
        "108.00 \u2013 117.975 MHz",
        "30 \u2013 300 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "108.00 \u2013 117.975 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the principle of range measurement by a DME interrogator?",
      "choices": [
        "Triangulation",
        "Trilaterion",
        "Propagation delay \u2013 time taken by signal to transmit between interrogator and transponder and back to the interrogator.",
        "Propagation delay \u2013 time taken by signal to transmit between transponder and interrogator and back to the transponder."
      ],
      "answer": "Propagation delay \u2013 time taken by signal to transmit between interrogator and transponder and back to the interrogator."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ waves - signal refracted from E and F layers of ionosphere.",
      "choices": [
        "Ground",
        "Space",
        "Multi-path",
        "Sky"
      ],
      "answer": "Sky"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum permissible tracking error when tracking to or from a VOR?",
      "choices": [
        "+/-2\u00b0",
        "+/-1\u00b0",
        "+/-5\u00b0",
        "+/-10\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/-5\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "A student pilot has just learnt that meteorological information for aircraft en route on long-haul flights is sent by radio. What kind of radio receiver is needed to receive this information?",
      "choices": [
        "Double sideband receiver.",
        "Single sideband receiver.",
        "LF/MF receiver.",
        "VHF receiver."
      ],
      "answer": "Single sideband receiver."
    },
    {
      "question": "The wavelength of a radio signal with a frequency of 121. 9 5 MHz is:",
      "choices": [
        "24.60 cm",
        "2.46 m",
        "2.46 cm",
        "24.60 m"
      ],
      "answer": "2.46 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a DME line of position?",
      "choices": [
        "A circle with the DME transponder at the centre and the radius formed by the ground range.",
        "A circle with the DME transponder at the centre and the radius formed by the DME range.",
        "A circle with the DME transponder at the centre and the circumference formed by the DME range.",
        "A circle with the aircraft at the centre and the radius formed by the DME range."
      ],
      "answer": "A circle with the DME transponder at the centre and the radius formed by the DME range."
    },
    {
      "question": "What system is used by air traffic controllers for the in-flight identification of aircraft not fitted with transponders?",
      "choices": [
        "Airborne weather radar.",
        "In-flight movement detector.",
        "Primary surveillance radar.",
        "Aerodrome movement surface radar."
      ],
      "answer": "Primary surveillance radar."
    },
    {
      "question": "What information can be obtained from a simple primary surveillance radar system?",
      "choices": [
        "Squawk code.",
        "Distance only.",
        "Bearing and distance.",
        "Bearing only."
      ],
      "answer": "Bearing and distance."
    },
    {
      "question": "What information relating to the position of the aircraft can be gained from a single VDF station?",
      "choices": [
        "Range only.",
        "Line of position plus range.",
        "Position fix.",
        "Single line of position only."
      ],
      "answer": "Single line of position only."
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio wave: an electromagnetic wave, comprising: E and H fields __________ to each other.",
      "choices": [
        "parallel",
        "proportional",
        "perpendicular",
        "adjacent"
      ],
      "answer": "perpendicular"
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio waves comprise: a carrier wave and information, modulated on upper and lower __________ bands.",
      "choices": [
        "air",
        "side",
        "level",
        "frequency"
      ],
      "answer": "side"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the accuracy definition for a Class C QDM?",
      "choices": [
        "+/-2\u00b0",
        "+/-10\u00b0",
        "+/-15\u00b0",
        "+/-5\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/-10\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which frequency band transmits on a frequency of 1145 MHz?",
      "choices": [
        "Millimetric",
        "Decimetric",
        "Decametric",
        "Centimetric"
      ],
      "answer": "Decimetric"
    },
    {
      "question": "NDB signals refract from the ionosphere at night, returning to Earth as skywaves, which mix with ground waves, causing signal __________.",
      "choices": [
        "fading",
        "attenuation",
        "parallax",
        "interference"
      ],
      "answer": "fading"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft\u2019s omni-bearing indicator has a selected radial of 315\u00b0. The deviation bar is deflected 2 dots to the left and it is displaying a TO flag. On which radial is the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "139\u00b0",
        "133\u00b0",
        "131\u00b0",
        "319\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "131\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "An RMI is used to indicate a __________ from a VOR:",
      "choices": [
        "distance",
        "bearing",
        "radial",
        "heading"
      ],
      "answer": "radial"
    },
    {
      "question": "What airborne equipment is required to obtain VDF information from a ground station?",
      "choices": [
        "VHF COMM transceiver.",
        "VDF transmitter.",
        "VHF COMM receiver.",
        "VHF NAV receiver."
      ],
      "answer": "VHF COMM transceiver."
    },
    {
      "question": "Pulse length is expressed as:",
      "choices": [
        "Time.",
        "Distance.",
        "An amplitude.",
        "A frequency."
      ],
      "answer": "Time."
    },
    {
      "question": "An electromagnetic wave consists of an oscillating electric field (E) and an oscillating magnetic field (H). Which statement is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "When AC current passes through the antenna, fields E and H are parallel.",
        "The E and H fields are perpendicular to each other.",
        "The H field is parallel to the wire and the field E is perpendicular to the wire.",
        "A dipole antenna can only transmit field (H)."
      ],
      "answer": "The E and H fields are perpendicular to each other."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which form of modulation adjusts the frequency of the signal, whilst maintaining a constant amplitude?",
      "choices": [
        "Phase",
        "Frequency",
        "Amplitude",
        "Pulse"
      ],
      "answer": "Frequency"
    },
    {
      "question": "Modulation is:",
      "choices": [
        "the process of impressing and transporting information by radio waves.",
        "the process to provide a radio carrier wave for transmission.",
        "a continuous wave which is capable of carrying audible signals without modification.",
        "to allow the signal to be amplified to the required power level."
      ],
      "answer": "the process of impressing and transporting information by radio waves."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ : is the number of complete cycles in one second, expressed in Hertz (Hz).",
      "choices": [
        "Cycle",
        "Amplitude",
        "Wavelength",
        "Frequency"
      ],
      "answer": "Frequency"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the acronym ADF stand for?",
      "choices": [
        "Ancillary Directive Finder",
        "Airborne Direction Finder",
        "Automatic Directional Filament",
        "Automatic Direction Finder"
      ],
      "answer": "Automatic Direction Finder"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the term given to the time taken for the pulse to travel from the radar to the target and back to the radar?",
      "choices": [
        "Pulse repetition frequency.",
        "Pulse duration.",
        "Pulse length.",
        "Propagation delay."
      ],
      "answer": "Propagation delay."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the weakening or cancelling out of a signal?",
      "choices": [
        "Absorption",
        "Attenuation",
        "Fading",
        "Interference"
      ],
      "answer": "Attenuation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The electromagnetic waves refracted from the E and F layers of the ionosphere are called:",
      "choices": [
        "Refracted waves.",
        "Ground waves.",
        "Space waves.",
        "Sky waves."
      ],
      "answer": "Sky waves."
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio waves in the VHF and higher frequency bands propagate mainly as:",
      "choices": [
        "Space waves.",
        "Sky waves.",
        "Surface waves.",
        "Earth reflected waves."
      ],
      "answer": "Space waves."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the simplest type of antenna called?",
      "choices": [
        "A dipole.",
        "A loop.",
        "A monopole.",
        "A quadrapole."
      ],
      "answer": "A dipole."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the accuracy definition for a Class B QDM?",
      "choices": [
        "+/-2\u00b0",
        "+/-15\u00b0",
        "+/-5\u00b0",
        "+/-10\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/-5\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Modern radar systems use which type of beam for the detection of weather systems?",
      "choices": [
        "Pencil/conical beam",
        "Fan beam",
        "Spoil beam",
        "Lateral beam"
      ],
      "answer": "Pencil/conical beam"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which frequency band transmits signals between 30 \u2013 300 MHz?",
      "choices": [
        "UHF",
        "HF",
        "SHF",
        "VHF"
      ],
      "answer": "VHF"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a ground range calculated from a DME range?",
      "choices": [
        "Ground Range = \u00bd x DME Range x Altitude",
        "Ground Range = 1.2 x DME Range x Altitude",
        "Ground Range = 1.23 x (\u221aDME Range + \u221a Altitude)",
        "Ground Range\u00b2 = DME Range\u00b2 \u2013 Altitude\u00b2"
      ],
      "answer": "Ground Range\u00b2 = DME Range\u00b2 \u2013 Altitude\u00b2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the needle indicator on the RMI, what bearing is indicated at the point of the needle?",
      "choices": [
        "True bearing to the NDB.",
        "True bearing from the NDB.",
        "Magnetic or compass bearing from the NDB.",
        "Magnetic or compass bearing to the NDB."
      ],
      "answer": "Magnetic or compass bearing to the NDB."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which frequency band transmits signals on wavelengths between 1 m \u2013 10 cm?",
      "choices": [
        "VHF",
        "UHF",
        "SHF",
        "HF"
      ],
      "answer": "UHF"
    },
    {
      "question": "Wavelength is __________ proportional to the frequency.",
      "choices": [
        "sinusoidal",
        "inversely",
        "directly",
        "exponentially"
      ],
      "answer": "inversely"
    },
    {
      "question": "Modern radar systems use inputs from various __________ to generate a display.",
      "choices": [
        "individuals",
        "sensors",
        "reports",
        "documents"
      ],
      "answer": "sensors"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the minimum number of VDF stations required to triangulate a position fix for an aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "2",
        "4",
        "1"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft\u2019s omni-bearing indicator shows the deviation bar deflected 3 dots to the right. How far from the selected radial is the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "3\u00b0",
        "6\u00b0",
        "12\u00b0",
        "1.5\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "6\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What Q code refers to the magnetic bearing from the aircraft to the ground station?",
      "choices": [
        "QTE",
        "QUJ",
        "QDR",
        "QDM"
      ],
      "answer": "QDM"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ distance: the distance from the transmitter to the position of the first returning sky wave.",
      "choices": [
        "Sky",
        "Skip",
        "Multi-path",
        "Ground"
      ],
      "answer": "Skip"
    },
    {
      "question": "For what reason should airborne weather radar systems be used with caution on the ground?",
      "choices": [
        "False indications from other aircraft, that can be mistaken as cumulonimbus clouds.",
        "Disruption of navigation systems.",
        "Transmission of microwaves, potentially harmful to people and animals.",
        "They consume too much power on the ground, owing to the number of reflections."
      ],
      "answer": "Transmission of microwaves, potentially harmful to people and animals."
    },
    {
      "question": "In accordance with the International Telecommunication Union (ITU) a radio signal can be classified by three symbols. What is indicated by the first character of the group A1A?",
      "choices": [
        "Type of information to be transmitted.",
        "Type of modulation of the secondary carrier.",
        "Nature of the signal modulating the main carrier.",
        "Type of modulation of the main carrier."
      ],
      "answer": "Type of modulation of the main carrier."
    },
    {
      "question": "Diffraction is the process by which:",
      "choices": [
        "Radio waves travel over and around obstacles.",
        "A ground wave is attenuated over rough ground.",
        "A direct wave is bent around the form of the earth.",
        "A space wave penetrates the ionosphere."
      ],
      "answer": "Radio waves travel over and around obstacles."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the acronym DME stand for?",
      "choices": [
        "Distance measuring equipment",
        "Directional measuring equipment",
        "Distance mean evaluation",
        "Direct measuring equipment"
      ],
      "answer": "Distance measuring equipment"
    },
    {
      "question": "The frequency which corresponds to a wavelength of 12 cm is:",
      "choices": [
        "2500 KHz",
        "360 MHz",
        "2.5 GHz",
        "3600 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "2.5 GHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of polar radiation diagram is associated with NDB?",
      "choices": [
        "Vertical.",
        "Omni-directional.",
        "Lateral.",
        "Directional."
      ],
      "answer": "Omni-directional."
    },
    {
      "question": "What range is calculated by the DME interrogator?",
      "choices": [
        "Ground range.",
        "RNAV computed range.",
        "User selectable range.",
        "Slant range."
      ],
      "answer": "Slant range."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the accuracy definition for a Class A QDM?",
      "choices": [
        "+/-5\u00b0",
        "+/-15\u00b0",
        "+/-10\u00b0",
        "+/-2\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/-2\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Electromagnetic waves in the VLF - band have a frequency spectrum of:",
      "choices": [
        "30-300 MHz.",
        "3-30 kHz.",
        "300-3000 kHz.",
        "30-300 kHz."
      ],
      "answer": "3-30 kHz."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a VOR radial measured?",
      "choices": [
        "Difference in depth of modulation between the main and side lobes.",
        "Phase difference between the reference and variable phase signals.",
        "Doppler phase shift between the reference and lateral phase signals.",
        "Frequency comparison between the 2 navigational signals."
      ],
      "answer": "Phase difference between the reference and variable phase signals."
    },
    {
      "question": "A vertically-mounted dipole antenna is used for RF transmissions. The receiving antenna has to be:",
      "choices": [
        "aligned horizontally in order to receive the electrical field of the RF transmission in vertical plane.",
        "aligned horizontally in order to receive the electrical field of the RF transmission in horizontal plane.",
        "in the same vertical alignment in order to receive the electrical field of the RF transmission in the horizontal plane.",
        "in the same vertical alignment in order to receive the electrical field of the RF transmission in the vertical plane."
      ],
      "answer": "in the same vertical alignment in order to receive the electrical field of the RF transmission in the vertical plane."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which axes are modern airborne weather radar systems gyroscopically stabilised?",
      "choices": [
        "Roll and yaw.",
        "Pitch and yaw.",
        "Pitch and roll.",
        "Pitch, roll and yaw."
      ],
      "answer": "Pitch and roll."
    },
    {
      "question": "Synchronous transmissions cause __________ errors, which can cause erroneous bearings.",
      "choices": [
        "multi-path",
        "synchronous",
        "curvature",
        "interference"
      ],
      "answer": "multi-path"
    },
    {
      "question": "Between 108.00 - 111.975 MHz, the instrument landing system (ILS) uses frequencies with an __________ number after the decimal point.",
      "choices": [
        "ODD",
        "EVEN",
        "Prime",
        "Whole"
      ],
      "answer": "ODD"
    },
    {
      "question": "RMI Radial __________ (QDR) - at the tail of the needle.",
      "choices": [
        "FROM",
        "TO",
        "Bearing",
        "Heading"
      ],
      "answer": "FROM"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a potential threat to the safety of a flight by setting the tilt of the airborne weather radar beam too high during a climb?",
      "choices": [
        "Interference from satellite signals of similar frequencies may interfere with the beam, causing false readings.",
        "The aircraft may climb through its own beam, causing false reflections.",
        "The beam may not detect the dry, frozen ice particles in the upper sections of thunderstorms.",
        "The higher the beam is tilted the less power that is available to reflect from thunderstorms."
      ],
      "answer": "The beam may not detect the dry, frozen ice particles in the upper sections of thunderstorms."
    },
    {
      "question": "Ground weather radar system is a form of which type of radar system?",
      "choices": [
        "Secondary surveillance radar.",
        "Pulse radar system.",
        "Remote sensing radar.",
        "X-ray radar system."
      ],
      "answer": "Remote sensing radar."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ waves - line-of-sight signal, directly from transmitter to receiver.",
      "choices": [
        "Ground",
        "Sky",
        "Space",
        "Multi-path"
      ],
      "answer": "Space"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which device is described as an electrical device which converts electrical power into radio waves, and vice versa?",
      "choices": [
        "Antenna",
        "ADC",
        "Kalman Filter",
        "Transmitter"
      ],
      "answer": "Antenna"
    },
    {
      "question": "Single Side Band (SSB) is used:",
      "choices": [
        "In VHF transmissions to reduce transmission power.",
        "In HF two-way communication.",
        "With transmissions of the Meteorological Aerodrome Report (METAR).",
        "With NDB transmissions to reduce bandwidth."
      ],
      "answer": "In HF two-way communication."
    }
  ],
  "ASP": [
    {
      "question": "A small twin-engine aircraft usually has __________ generator(s) per engine.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "3",
        "2",
        "4"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The power output of a normally aspirated piston engine increases with increasing altitude at constant Manifold Absolute Pressure (MAP) and RPM because of the:",
      "choices": [
        "Lower back pressure.",
        "Lower friction losses.",
        "Lower losses during the gas change.",
        "Leaner mixture at higher altitudes."
      ],
      "answer": "Lower back pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "Is a combination of OR and NOT. The output is that of an inverted OR gate. This is a description of which function:",
      "choices": [
        "NOT",
        "NAND",
        "OR",
        "NOR"
      ],
      "answer": "NOR"
    },
    {
      "question": "A component consuming 80 watts at 8 amps would require a supply of:",
      "choices": [
        "5 Volts",
        "0.01 kV",
        "100 Volts",
        "0.008 kV"
      ],
      "answer": "0.01 kV"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following are typical AC loads in a commercial jet transport aircraft?\n1- The FMGC.\n2- The VHF radios.\n3- The air conditioning pack control.\n4- The flight deck display units (DUs).\n5- The primary flight controls\u2019 trimmer motors.",
      "choices": [
        "2 4",
        "3 4",
        "1 4",
        "1 5"
      ],
      "answer": "3 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "A small twin-engine aircraft uses one or more __________ to provide __________ power to those systems which require it.",
      "choices": [
        "transformers; DC",
        "transformers; AC",
        "inverters; AC",
        "inverters; DC"
      ],
      "answer": "inverters; AC"
    },
    {
      "question": "When a generator fails it\u2019s __________ possible to power the failed side with the APU generator.",
      "choices": [
        "rarely",
        "usually",
        "never",
        "always"
      ],
      "answer": "usually"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a split bus system, when it is set to __________, the bus tie automatically closes upon failure of 1 main generator.",
      "choices": [
        "OFF",
        "ON",
        "AUTO",
        "ALT"
      ],
      "answer": "AUTO"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following parameters is/are monitored by the CSD: 1- Engine RPM, 2- Frequency, 3- Phase, 4- Voltage.",
      "choices": [
        "2 3",
        "1 2",
        "1 3",
        "1 4"
      ],
      "answer": "2 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "It is NOT recommended to reset a tripped circuit breaker during flight because:",
     "choices": [
        "The member of the flight crew must leave the flight deck.",
        "There is a risk of electrocution.",
        "This should only be done when the aircraft is on the ground with the main battery turned off.",
        "The overload condition may still be present and the electrical damage could become worse."
      ],
      "answer": "The overload condition may still be present and the electrical damage could become worse."
    },
    {
      "question": "In order to produce an alternating voltage of 400 Hz, the number of pairs of poles required in an AC generator running at 6000 rpm is:",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "8",
        "24",
        "12"
      ],
      "answer": "4"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of a voltage regulator is to control the output voltage of the:",
      "choices": [
        "Generator at varying loads and speeds.",
        "TRU.",
        "Batteries at varying loads.",
        "Generators at varying speeds and the batteries at varying loads."
      ],
      "answer": "Generator at varying loads and speeds."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about electromagnetism is/are correct?\n1\u2014 An electrical current flowing through a wire produces a magnetic field around the wire.\n2\u2014 A copper wire moving across a magnetic field will experience current flowing through it.\n3\u2014 The strength of the magnetic field created by current flowing through a wire is inversely proportional to the current flow.\n4\u2014 A ferrous metal core inserted inside a coil of wire will increase the strength of the magnetic field when current flows through the coil.",
      "choices": [
        "3 4",
        "2 3",
        "1 2",
        "1 2 4"
      ],
      "answer": "1 2 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about guarded switches is/are correct?\n1\u2014 One purpose of guarding a switch is to avoid accidental operation of the switch.\n2\u2014 Push button switches are frequently gated.\n3\u2014 'Gating' is one method of guarding against accidental switch selections.\n4\u2014 A gated toggle switch must be depressed (pressed in) before it can be moved out of its gate.\n5\u2014 One purpose of guarding a switch is to ensure that very positive and deliberate actions must be taken to operate the switch.",
      "choices": [
        "1 2 3 4",
        "1 2 3",
        "2 4",
        "1 3 5"
      ],
      "answer": "1 3 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "For lithium and NiCd batteries, thermal runaway can be triggered by:\n1\u2014 Excessive charge rate\n2\u2014 Mechanical damage\n3\u2014 Mechanical shock.\n4\u2014 Chemical shock.\n5\u2014 Excessively low atmospheric pressure.\n6\u2014 Excessively ambient temperature.\n7\u2014 Short circuit.",
      "choices": [
        "1 3 4 7",
        "1 2 3 7",
        "2 3 5 7",
        "1 2 3 5"
      ],
      "answer": "1 2 3 7"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct answer(s).\nThe advantage(s) of an axial flow compressor over a centrifugal type is/are:\n1 - Lower cost of manufacture.\n2 - Lighter and more compact.\n3 - Smaller diameter.\n4 - Greater efficiency.\n5 - Less vulnerable to FOD.",
      "choices": [
        "2 4",
        "3 4",
        "1 3",
        "3 4 5"
      ],
      "answer": "3 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Some components of a turbine engine are required to operate at their maximum temperature. What are the components which are exposed to the greatest thermal loads?",
      "choices": [
        "HP turbine and Jet pipe.",
        "First stage turbine nozzle guide vanes and the first stage of the HP turbine.",
        "Duplex burner and flame tube.",
        "Turbine nozzle guide vanes and the first stage of the LP turbine."
      ],
      "answer": "First stage turbine nozzle guide vanes and the first stage of the HP turbine."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct answer(s). Despite its design, a pitot-type inlet cannot guarantee stable inlet conditions:\n1 - In very high crosswinds.\n2 - In cloud.\n3 - In very heavy rain.\n4 - At very high angle of attack.\n5 - At low speed.\n6 - In severe turbulence.\n7 - When contaminated with ice.",
      "choices": [
        "1 2 3 4",
        "1 4 6 7",
        "2 4 7",
        "1 3 6 7"
      ],
      "answer": "1 4 6 7"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following methods describe valid gas turbine ground starting systems:\n1 - Starting using an electric starter-motor.\n2 - Starting using the natural windmilling of the fan.\n3 - Starting using a pneumatic starter motor driven by compressed air from another running engine.\n4 - Starting using a pneumatic starter motor driven by compressed air supplied by the APU.\n5 - Starting using a pneumatic starter motor driven by compressed air from an external pressure source.\n6 - Starting using an hydraulic motor known as the Power Transfer Unit (PTU).",
      "choices": [
        "1 2 4 5",
        "2 4 6",
        "1 3 4 5",
        "1 3 4 6"
      ],
      "answer": "1 3 4 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "The exhaust system of a commercial turbofan or turbojet engine comprises the following essential and optional components:\n1 - Jet pipe\n2 - Propelling nozzle\n3 - Diffuser\n4 - Exhaust cone\n5 - Bleed system",
      "choices": [
        "1 2 4",
        "1 3 4",
        "2 3 4",
        "1 4 5"
      ],
      "answer": "1 2 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the equation T=MV the velocity that counts towards jet thrust is the \u00a0__________ velocity.",
      "choices": [
        "radial",
        "axial and radial",
        "axial",
        "high speed"
      ],
      "answer": "axial"
    },
    {
      "question": "The oil used to lubricate and cool the bearings is mostly confined within the \u00a0__________.",
      "choices": [
        "bearing chambers",
        "bearing duct",
        "bearing shell",
        "bearing core"
      ],
      "answer": "bearing chambers"
    },
    {
      "question": "A high cylinder head temperature (CHT) typically indicates:",
      "choices": [
        "Incorrectly set propeller pitch.",
        "Excessively high oil pressure.",
        "Excessively lean mixture.",
        "Excessively rich mixture."
      ],
      "answer": "Excessively lean mixture."
    },
    {
      "question": "A compressor which increases the overall power of the engine is a type of __________ boosting.",
      "choices": [
        "altitude",
        "ground",
        "power",
        "attitude"
      ],
      "answer": "ground"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements about the relationship between power, torque and RPM is/are correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Torque varies as RPM/Power.",
        "The less RPM, the more power is available.",
        "The less RPM you require, the more torque there is available.",
        "For a given maximum power, the more torque you demand, the less RPM the engine can give you."
      ],
      "answer": "For a given maximum power, the more torque you demand, the less RPM the engine can give you."
    },
    {
      "question": "A piston engine compression ratio is the ratio of the:",
      "choices": [
        "total volume to the clearance volume.",
        "swept volume to the clearance volume.",
        "total volume to the swept volume.",
        "clearance volume to the swept volume."
      ],
      "answer": "total volume to the clearance volume."
    },
    {
      "question": "An ignition switch in the closed position:",
      "choices": [
        "Grounds the spark magneto and thus renders the ignition circuit live.",
        "Closes the circuit between the magneto and spark plugs.",
        "Grounds the magneto and thus renders the ignition circuit safe.",
        "Provides a starting current to the magneto."
      ],
      "answer": "Grounds the magneto and thus renders the ignition circuit safe."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following components are part of the engine bleed supply:\n1- Isolation valve.\n2- Pressure reducing valve.\n3- Pre-cooler valve.\n4- Engine bleed valve.",
      "choices": [
        "1 2",
        "1",
        "3 4",
        "2 3"
      ],
      "answer": "3 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "An ice detection probe can use differential pressure to provide an indication of ice accretion. Such a probe detects ice accretion due to:",
      "choices": [
        "a decrease in dynamic air pressure in the detector.",
        "a decrease in static air pressure in the detector.",
        "an increase in static air pressure in the detector.",
        "an increase in dynamic air pressure in the detector."
      ],
     "answer": "a decrease in dynamic air pressure in the detector."
    },
    {
      "question": "When a turbo prop pneumatic anti-icing system is switched on whilst at cruise:",
      "choices": [
        "Propeller RPM remains unchanged, turbine temperature rises and torque reduces.",
        "Propeller RPM reduces, turbine temperature reduces and torque increases.",
        "Propeller RPM remains unchanged, turbine temperature reduces and torque reduces.",
        "Propeller RPM remains unchanged, turbine temperature remains unchanged and torque remains unchanged."
      ],
      "answer": "Propeller RPM remains unchanged, turbine temperature rises and torque reduces."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following describes valid fire detection system(s):\n1- Heat increases the internal gas pressure which is sensed by an aneroid capsule.\n2- An oil-filled capsule is linked to an aneroid device. When heated the oil expands, thus expanding the capsule.\n3- A bimetallic strip contains two metals which expand at different rates when heated, this causes the sensing element to curl and close an electrical contactor.\n4- A wire changes its resistance or capacitance when heated. A sensor detects the change in this electrical value.\n5- A labyrinth system only permits light to travel down its path if smoke is present.",
      "choices": [
        "1 3 5",
        "2 3 4",
        "1 2",
        "1 3 4"
      ],
      "answer": "1 3 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flutter can occur in the:\n1 - Torsion box.\n2 - Wings\n3 - Horizontal stabiliser\n4 - Flaps\n5 - Longerons\n6 - Tailplane",
      "choices": [
        "2 3 6",
       "1 2 3 6",
        "1 3 5",
        "2 4 6"
      ],
      "answer": "2 3 6"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft in flight is affected by loads.\nThese may be classified as:",
      "choices": [
        "Thrust, drag, lift and weight.",
        "Compressive, tensile, shear and torsional.",
        "Tensile, shear, twisting and stretching.",
        "Compressive, bending, shear and torsional."
      ],
      "answer": "Compressive, tensile, shear and torsional."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following are valid primary flight control actuation methods:\n1 - Manual: using cables, pulleys and bell-cranks.\n2 - Partially powered: using cables and levers assisted by hydraulic actuators.\n3 - Fully powered: with no mechanical connection between the pilot\u2019s controls and the control surfaces.\n4 - Electrically activated: using hydraulic actuators controlled by electrical signals.",
      "choices": [
        "1 2 3",
        "2 3 4",
        "1 2 3 4",
        "1 2"
      ],
      "answer": "1 2 3 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "During hydroplaning, the friction coefficient between tyre and runway surface is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "1.0.",
        "0.5.",
        "0.25.",
        "0"
      ],
      "answer": "0"
    },
    {
      "question": "In flight, a cantilever wing of an aeroplane containing fuel is subjected to vertical loads that produce a bending moment, which is:",
      "choices": [
        "Lowest at the wing root.",
        "Equal to the zero-fuel weight multiplied by the span.",
        "Highest at the wing root.",
        "Equal to half the weight of the aircraft multiplied by the semi-span."
      ],
      "answer": "Highest at the wing root."
    },
    {
      "question": "Flutter countermeasures include:\n1 - Rearward-mounted engines on the wing\n2 - Forward-mounted engines on the wing\n3 - Low torsional stiffness\n4 - Forward CG bias to the integral wing tanks\n5 - Rearward CG bias to the integral wing tanks\n6 - Good torsional stiffness",
      "choices": [
        "1 2 3 4 5",
        "1 4 6",
        "2 3 6",
        "2 4 6"
      ],
      "answer": "2 4 6"
    },
    {
      "question": "A paralleled system must use generators which output at the same frequency, phase and phase __________.",
      "choices": [
        "angle",
        "frequency",
        "voltage",
        "current"
      ],
      "answer": "angle"
    },
    {
      "question": "High oil temperature and/or excessively low oil pressure in a CSD could lead to:",
      "choices": [
        "AC of the incorrect frequency being supplied to a common busbar.",
        "Loss of oil pressure to the engine's main bearings.",
        "Mechanical failure of the CSD, which interferes with the free running of the gas turbine engine.",
        "Mechanical failure of the engine caused by a seized CSD."
      ],
      "answer": "Mechanical failure of the CSD, which interferes with the free running of the gas turbine engine."
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of the generator breaker is to close when the voltage of the:",
      "choices": [
        "Battery is greater than the generator voltage and to open when the opposite is true.",
        "Alternator is greater than the battery voltage and to open when the opposite is true.",
        "Battery is greater than the alternator voltage and to open when the opposite is true.",
        "Generator is greater than battery voltage and to open when the opposite is true."
      ],
      "answer": "Generator is greater than battery voltage and to open when the opposite is true."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following accurately describes the function or operation of the CSD disconnect system?",
      "choices": [
        "The disconnect unit monitors the output frequency and disconnects the generator from the busbar if it is outside the acceptable limits.",
        "The disconnect unit disconnects the auxiliary gearbox from the engine.",
        "Once operated, the CSD cannot be reconnected in flight",
        "Once operated, the associated generator continues to be driven but there is no electrical output to the busbar(s)."
      ],
      "answer": "Once operated, the CSD cannot be reconnected in flight"
    },
    {
      "question": "A capacitor can be used as a:",
      "choices": [
        "battery",
        "temporary storage device",
        "circuit breaker",
        "resistor"
      ],
      "answer": "temporary storage device"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of static wick dischargers is to:",
      "choices": [
        "dissipate the static charge from the aircraft's skin after landing.",
        "dissipate electrical friction allowing the aircraft to fly higher.",
        "provide a path to ground for static charges when refuelling.",
        "dissipate the static charge of the aircraft ln flight."
      ],
      "answer": "dissipate the static charge of the aircraft ln flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Large turbine engines __________ be started from the aircraft's batteries.",
      "choices": [
        "cannot",
        "can",
        "should",
        "should not"
      ],
      "answer": "cannot"
    },
    {
      "question": "When the AC voltage across a capacitor is kept constant and the frequency is increased, the current through the capacitor will:",
      "choices": [
        "remain the same",
        "increase",
        "decrease",
        "be zero"
      ],
      "answer": "increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a single-engine aircraft electrical system, the majority of loads are connected to the main busbar in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "parallel",
        "series",
        "both parallel and series",
        "neither parallel nor series"
      ],
      "answer": "parallel"
    },
    {
      "question": "ln a DC (Direct Current) circuit, what will happen if the current gets too high and is not detected?",
      "choices": [
        "The wire will overheat and could cause a fire.",
        "The voltage will subsequently increase, and could blow a fuse.",
        "The increased magnetic field will interfere with other circuits nearby.",
        "The circuit breaker will trip, disconnecting the generator from its drive unit."
      ],
      "answer": "The wire will overheat and could cause a fire."
    },
    {
      "question": "When connecting two 12 volt 40 ampere-hour batteries in parallel, what will be their total voltage and capacity?",
      "choices": [
        "24 volt, 40 ampere-hours",
        "12 volt, 40 ampere-hours",
        "12 volt, 80 ampere-hours",
        "24 volt, 80 ampere-hours"
      ],
      "answer": "12 volt, 80 ampere-hours"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reduced power available (e.g. after a generator failure) it is usually advisable or required to switch-off some of the more demanding loads such as the galley ovens and passenger entertainment system. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Frequency sharing.",
        "Overloading.",
        "Load sharing.",
        "Load shedding."
      ],
      "answer": "Load shedding."
    },
    {
      "question": "The voltage of a fully charged lead-acid battery cell is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "1.4 V.",
        "1.8 V.",
        "1.2 V.",
        "2.2 V."
      ],
      "answer": "2.2 V."
    },
    {
      "question": "The CSD is a hydromechanical system serviced by its own supply of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "electricity",
        "oil",
        "hydraulic fluid",
        "fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "oil"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a large commercial jet transport aircraft, DC is supplied via __________ from various AC busbars.",
      "choices": [
        "converter",
        "TRUs",
        "inverter",
        "rectifier"
      ],
      "answer": "TRUs"
    },
    {
      "question": "The capacity of a battery is the:",
      "choices": [
        "amount of Ampere-hour (Ah) that a fully charged battery can supply.",
        "no-load voltage of the battery multiplied by its rated output current.",
        "intensity withstood by the battery during charging.",
        "number of cycles (charging and discharging) that a battery can withstand without deterioration of its cells."
      ],
      "answer": "amount of Ampere-hour (Ah) that a fully charged battery can supply."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a single-engine aircraft after engine start when the generator/alternator output __________ the voltage of the battery, a generator cut-out closes, to connect the generator/alternator to the main busbar.",
      "choices": [
        "exceeds",
        "equals",
        "is less than",
        "is close to"
      ],
      "answer": "exceeds"
    },
    {
      "question": "A transformer rectifier unit (TRU) usually __________ __________ and converts it to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "steps down AC; DC",
        "steps down DC; AC",
        "steps up DC; AC",
        "steps up AC; DC"
      ],
      "answer": "steps down AC; DC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Circuit breakers protecting circuits may be:",
      "choices": [
        "reset at any time",
        "used only in AC circuits",
        "used only in DC circuits",
        "used in AC and DC circuits"
      ],
      "answer": "used in AC and DC circuits"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ servicing busbar allows engineers to power some electrical loads (e.g. cabin lights and cargo hatch operation) without powering up the entire electrical system.",
      "choices": [
        "APU",
        "ground",
        "battery",
        "external"
      ],
      "answer": "ground"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ busbars maintain a source of AC to essential AC loads when other sources of AC have failed.",
      "choices": [
        "essential AC",
        "DC inverter",
        "AC inverter",
        "battery"
      ],
      "answer": "essential AC"
    },
    {
      "question": "When a generator fails it\u2019s __________ possible to power the failed side with the APU generator.",
      "choices": [
        "usually",
        "never",
        "rarely",
        "occasionally"
      ],
      "answer": "usually"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Q = charge (Coulombs). U = potential difference between the plates (Volt). The capacitance C (Farads) is defined by the following formula:",
      "choices": [
        "C = Q / U",
        "C = U A \u2014 Q",
        "C = U2 / Q",
        "C = U / Q"
      ],
      "answer": "C = Q / U"
    },
    {
      "question": "A thermal circuit breaker:",
      "choices": [
        "protects the system in the event of any excessive current",
        "protects the system in the event of a prolonged, excessive current",
        "protects the system in the event of any overheating",
        "protects the system in the event of a prolonged overheating"
      ],
      "answer": "protects the system in the event of a prolonged, excessive current"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is a combination of OR and NOT. The output is that of an inverted OR gate. This is a description of which function:",
      "choices": [
        "NOT",
        "OR",
        "NOR",
        "NAND"
      ],
      "answer": "NOR"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rotor __________ may result in physical damage to the motor.",
      "choices": [
        "runaway",
        "seizure",
        "stall",
        "failure"
      ],
      "answer": "runaway"
    },
    {
      "question": "Because they are similar in design, a generator and electrical motor may be combined into a single __________.",
      "choices": [
        "integrated drive generator (IDG)",
        "starter motor unit",
        "starter-generator unit",
        "alternator"
      ],
      "answer": "starter-generator unit"
    },
    {
      "question": "If a current is passed through a conductor which is positioned perpendicular to a magnetic field:",
      "choices": [
        "A force will be exerted on the conductor.",
        "There will be no effect unless the conductor is moved.",
        "The current will increase.",
        "The intensity of the magnetic field will decrease."
      ],
      "answer": "A force will be exerted on the conductor."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a large helicopter, DC is supplied via __________ from various AC busbars.",
      "choices": [
        "inverter",
        "TRUs",
        "converter",
        "generator"
      ],
      "answer": "TRUs"
    },
    {
      "question": "All inputs to be high (logic1) to get a high output (logic1). This is a description of which function:",
      "choices": [
        "NAND",
        "NOR",
        "AND",
        "NOT"
      ],
      "answer": "AND"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the frequency of the supply in a series capacitive circuit is decreased, the current flowing in the circuit will:",
      "choices": [
        "Increase or decrease, depending on the capacity of the circuit.",
        "Increase",
        "Remain the same",
        "Decrease"
      ],
      "answer": "Decrease"
    },
    {
      "question": "Electric motors on aircraft can be:",
      "choices": [
        "DC 115Hz.",
        "DC 60 Hz.",
        "AC 0 Hz.",
        "AC 400 Hz."
      ],
      "answer": "AC 400 Hz."
    },
    {
      "question": "A parallel busbar system has a bus tie which is normally __________ to link all the generators.",
      "choices": [
        "open",
        "closed",
        "partially open",
        "removed"
      ],
      "answer": "closed"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a single-engine aircraft, if the engine fails, or the generator fails in flight, the only source of electrical power will be the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "inverter",
        "battery",
        "generator",
        "alternator"
      ],
      "answer": "battery"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ busbar system has separate AC busbars for each AC generator.",
      "choices": [
        "joined",
        "separated",
        "split",
        "parallel"
      ],
      "answer": "split"
    },
    {
      "question": "The size of the engine determines the required size of the starter motor because a very large unit requires more __________ to turn it at sufficient RPM during engine start.",
      "choices": [
        "torque",
        "thrust",
        "power",
        "electrical energy"
      ],
      "answer": "torque"
    },
    {
      "question": "A single-engine aircraft\u2019s distribution system is usually __________.",
      "choices": [
        "DC",
        "AC",
        "AC or DC",
        "a combination of AC and DC"
      ],
      "answer": "DC"
    },
    {
      "question": "One indication of inadequate bonding of aircraft components may be:",
      "choices": [
        "Static noise on the radio.",
        "Heavy corrosion on the fuselage skin mountings.",
        "A circuit breaker popping out.",
        "Interference on the VOR receiver."
      ],
      "answer": "Static noise on the radio."
    },
    {
      "question": "A split busbar system can use frequency wild generators but, in practice, the output frequency is normally kept very close to __________ Hz.",
      "choices": [
        "500",
        "200",
        "100",
        "400"
      ],
      "answer": "400"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ busbar provides limited capacity DC to power the most essential DC loads (such as fire extinguishers).",
      "choices": [
        "Essential",
        "Main",
        "BAT",
        "DC"
      ],
      "answer": "BAT"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which type of gate does this schematic symbol represent:",
      "choices": [
        "AND",
        "NOT",
        "NAND",
        "OR"
      ],
      "answer": "OR"
    },
    {
      "question": "The device which monitors and controls generator output and protects the system from abnormal generator outputs by isolating it from its busbar is the:",
      "choices": [
        "CSD disconnect system.",
        "Differential fault protection system.",
        "Generator isolation switch.",
        "Generator control unit."
      ],
      "answer": "Generator control unit."
    },
    {
      "question": "A \u2018frequency wild\u2019 generator produces __________ current whose frequency varies depending on the __________ of the engine.",
      "choices": [
        "DC; number of stators",
        "AC; number of stators",
        "DC; RPM",
        "AC; RPM"
      ],
      "answer": "AC; RPM"
    },
    {
      "question": "AC generators operated in parallel must have the same:",
      "choices": [
        "amperage and kVAR.",
        "frequency and amperage",
        "voltage and amperage",
        "voltage and phase."
      ],
      "answer": "voltage and phase."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a twin-engined commercial jet transport aircraft, each main generator __________ usually sufficiently powerful to power the entire electrical system.",
      "choices": [
        "is",
        "is not",
        "may be",
        "should be"
      ],
      "answer": "is"
    },
    {
      "question": "A CSD is a:",
      "choices": [
        "Constant speed device.",
        "Constant source device.",
        "Constant speed drive.",
        "Control speed drive."
      ],
      "answer": "Constant speed drive."
    },
    {
      "question": "External AC __________ the output provided by a main engine AC generator.",
      "choices": [
        "can be paralleled with",
        "is automatically isolated from",
        "can supplement",
        "is superior to"
      ],
      "answer": "is automatically isolated from"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a small twin-engine aircraft, a short-circuit on the main busbar __________ be overcome by supplying it with electrical power from a different source.",
      "choices": [
        "can",
        "cannot",
        "might",
        "should"
      ],
      "answer": "cannot"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is a combination of OR and NOT.  The output is that of an inverted OR gate. This is a description of which function:",
      "choices": [
        "NOT",
        "OR",
        "NOR",
        "NAND"
      ],
      "answer": "NOR"
    },
    {
      "question": "When all other sources of AC generation have failed, emergency AC can be provided from the DC system via an __________.",
      "choices": [
        "TRUs",
        "inverter",
        "converter",
        "battery"
      ],
      "answer": "inverter"
    },
    {
      "question": "In reference to an inverter unit, which of these relationships between AC and DC is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "x Volts DC -+ x Volts of AC",
        "AC--+ DC",
        "x Volts of DC --+ y Volts of AC",
        "y Volts of DC -+ y Volts of AC"
      ],
      "answer": "x Volts of DC --+ y Volts of AC"
    },
    {
      "question": "A TRU:",
      "choices": [
        "Simultaneously steps-down and converts AC to DC.",
        "Steps-down AC and then converts it to DC.",
        "Can convert AC to DC or vice-versa.",
        "Converts AC to DC and then steps it down."
      ],
      "answer": "Steps-down AC and then converts it to DC."
    },
    {
      "question": "For engine starting, large turbine engines require either external power or internal power from the __________ or another main engine.",
      "choices": [
        "APU",
        "battery",
        "inverter",
        "transformer"
      ],
      "answer": "APU"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a split busbar system, used by a twin-engine commercial jet transport aircraft, the failure of a single main generator can usually be entirely compensated for by __________ the bus tie or by bringing the gas turbine powered APU generator on line.",
      "choices": [
        "closing",
        "opening",
        "isolating",
        "connecting"
      ],
      "answer": "closing"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rotor _____ will result in excessive current and risk of damage or electrical fire.",
      "choices": [
        "seizure",
        "runaway",
        "failure",
        "jam"
      ],
      "answer": "seizure"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most serious threat from multiple or unauthorised resets of a circuit breaker is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "damage to the generator",
        "fire",
        "damage to the electrical components",
        "damage to the fuse"
      ],
      "answer": "fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "In aeronautics, the most commonly used batteries are NiCd because:",
      "choices": [
        "They weigh less than lead-acid batteries.",
        "They are cheaper than lead-acid batteries.",
        "Their output voltage is less constant than lead-acid batteries.",
        "Their electrolyte is neither corrosive nor dangerous."
      ],
      "answer": "They weigh less than lead-acid batteries."
    },
    {
      "question": "The energy flowing through an electrical circuit per second is measured in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "amps",
        "volts",
        "watts",
        "ohms"
      ],
      "answer": "watts"
    },
    {
      "question": "Current will flow through a __________ circuit when an emf is present.",
      "choices": [
        "closed",
        "open",
        "short",
        "long"
      ],
      "answer": "closed"
    },
    {
      "question": "A battery comprises several __________ wired in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "busbars; series",
        "contactors; parallel",
        "cells; parallel",
        "cells; series"
      ],
      "answer": "cells; series"
    },
    {
      "question": "A circuit contains 3 loads (consumers) wired in parallel. The resistances of the loads are: 4 Ohms, 10 Ohms and 400 Ohms. The total resistance of the 3 loads is:",
      "choices": [
        "2.84 Ohms",
        "414 Ohms",
        "4 Ohms",
        "400 Ohms"
      ],
      "answer": "2.84 Ohms"
    },
    {
      "question": "What unit of measurement is used to express electrical work?",
      "choices": [
        "Ampere.",
        "Joule",
        "Ohm.",
        "Watt."
      ],
      "answer": "Joule"
    },
    {
      "question": "ln flight, if the temperature of the constant speed drive (CSD) ls in the red arc the:",
      "choices": [
        "pilot must disconnect it, and the generator is not available for the rest of flight.",
        "pilot must disconnect it and manually control the alternator.",
        "pilot can disconnect it to allow it to cool and use it again.",
        "pilot has to throttle back."
      ],
      "answer": "pilot must disconnect it, and the generator is not available for the rest of flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "When 'on-load' the voltage of a battery should be slightly __________ than the voltage measured across the terminals when the battery is 'off-load'.",
      "choices": [
        "lower",
        "higher",
        "the same",
        "equal"
      ],
      "answer": "lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "An inverter is a:",
      "choices": [
        "filter against radio interference",
        "device for reversing the polarity of the static charge",
        "static discharger",
        "device used to convert DC into AC"
      ],
      "answer": "device used to convert DC into AC"
    },
    {
      "question": "A test to assess the state of charge of a Lead-acid battery would involve:",
      "choices": [
        "Checking the discharge current of the battery \"on-load\".",
        "Comparing the on-load and off-load battery voltages.",
        "Checking the level of the electrolyte.",
        "Checking the discharge current of the battery on-load."
      ],
      "answer": "Comparing the on-load and off-load battery voltages."
    },
    {
      "question": "A current limiter fuse in a DC system is used to:",
      "choices": [
        "Allow a short term overload before rupturing.",
        "Limit the current in the field circuit.",
        "Limit the current in the armature.",
        "Allow no overload before rupturing."
      ],
      "answer": "Allow a short term overload before rupturing."
    },
    {
      "question": "The components which ease the flow of accumulated electrical charge from airframe to atmosphere are called __________ __________ discharge wicks.",
      "choices": [
        "static",
        "electrical",
        "bonding",
        "earthing"
      ],
      "answer": "static"
    },
    {
      "question": "The possibility of a large electrical potential difference between the aircraft and the earth means that the aircraft absolutely must be __________ before the refuelling nozzle is withdrawn from its holder.",
      "choices": [
        "grounded",
        "bonded",
        "isolated",
        "connected"
      ],
      "answer": "grounded"
    },
    {
      "question": "The very rapid magnetic field changes (flux changes) in the primary coil of a magneto are accomplished by the:",
      "choices": [
        "Distributor arm aligning with one of the high tension segments.",
        "Rotor turning past the position of maximum flux in the armature.",
        "Contact breaker points opening.",
        "Contact breaker points closing."
      ],
      "answer": "Contact breaker points opening."
    },
    {
      "question": "The advantage of an electromechanical circuit breaker over a thermally activated circuit breaker is that it can: __________.",
      "choices": [
        "be made sensitive to current direction",
        "be reset multiple times",
        "trip quicker",
        "operate at a higher voltage"
      ],
      "answer": "be made sensitive to current direction"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ overcurrent condition in a circuit may be addressed by resetting the circuit breaker in accordance with the FCOM.",
      "choices": [
        "permanent",
        "transient",
        "high",
        "low"
      ],
      "answer": "transient"
    },
    {
      "question": "Electrical potential is measured in:",
      "choices": [
        "Amperes.",
        "Volts.",
        "Ohms.",
        "Watts."
      ],
      "answer": "Volts."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft wiring loom comprises bundles of wires. If the wires are not shielded, a current flowing through one wire will __________.",
      "choices": [
        "cause current to flow in adjacent wires",
        "cause a short-circuit",
        "cause a build-up of static electricity",
        "reduce current to flow in adjacent wires"
      ],
      "answer": "cause current to flow in adjacent wires"
    },
    {
      "question": "The unit used to measure the capacitance of a capacitor is the:",
      "choices": [
        "Farad.",
        "Joule.",
        "Watt.",
        "Hz."
      ],
      "answer": "Farad."
    },
    {
      "question": "Small, dry ice crystals suspended in the air are __________ to result in accumulated charge on an airframe.",
      "choices": [
        "more likely",
        "less likely",
        "never",
        "always"
      ],
      "answer": "more likely"
    },
    {
      "question": "DC alternators and generators produce a __________ emf the faster they rotate.",
      "choices": [
        "greater",
        "smaller",
        "fluctuating",
        "constant"
      ],
      "answer": "greater"
    },
    {
      "question": "A circuit contains 3 loads (consumers) wired in series. The resistances of the loads are: 4 Ohms, 10 Ohms and 400 Ohms. The total resistance of the 3 loads is:",
      "choices": [
        "4 Ohms",
        "400 Ohms",
        "414 Ohms",
        "0.325 Ohms"
      ],
      "answer": "414 Ohms"
    },
    {
      "question": "The voltage of DC alternators and generators varies with __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "engine RPM",
        "engine torque",
        "aircraft vertical speed",
        "ambient temperature"
      ],
      "answer": "engine RPM"
    },
    {
      "question": "A large drop in battery voltage when placed on-load indicates that the battery is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "in poor condition",
        "open-circuited",
        "a NiCd or lithium type",
        "in good condition"
      ],
      "answer": "in poor condition"
    },
    {
      "question": "The unit of current describes the amount of __________ flowing per unit of time.",
      "choices": [
        "voltage",
        "charge",
        "resistance",
        "power"
      ],
      "answer": "charge"
    },
    {
      "question": "The essential difference between aircraft AC alternators and DC generators (dynamos) is that the:",
      "choices": [
        "The alternators generate much less power than DC generators.",
        "Induced windings of the alternators are rotating (rotor), and the dynamos have a rotary inductor coil",
        "Induced (output) windings of the alternators are fixed (stator), and the dynamos have a fixed inductor (field) coil.",
        "Alternators supply all of the output current through the commutators and brush assemblies."
      ],
      "answer": "Induced (output) windings of the alternators are fixed (stator), and the dynamos have a fixed inductor (field) coil."
    },
    {
      "question": "The phenomenon whereby a voltage and current is generated in a conductor when it is moved across a magnetic field is called electromagnetic __________.",
      "choices": [
        "induction",
        "conduction",
        "resistance",
        "current"
      ],
      "answer": "induction"
    },
    {
      "question": "An accumulation of electric charge on an object is known as: __________ electricity.",
      "choices": [
        "dynamic",
        "electrical",
        "static",
        "alternating"
      ],
      "answer": "static"
    },
    {
      "question": "The unit of measurement for battery capacity is the __________ hour.",
      "choices": [
        "wattage",
        "ampere",
        "voltage",
        "charge"
      ],
      "answer": "ampere"
    },
    {
      "question": "A bimetallic strip is a component used in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "an electromechanical circuit breaker",
        "a fuse",
        "a thermally activated circuit breaker",
        "a relay"
      ],
      "answer": "a thermally activated circuit breaker"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ batteries have a better power to weight ratio than __________ batteries.",
      "choices": [
        "lead-acid; lithium",
        "lithium; lead-acid",
        "Nickel-cadmium; lead-acid",
        "lead-acid; Nickel-cadmium"
      ],
      "answer": "lithium; lead-acid"
    },
    {
      "question": "The unit that converts DC into AC is:",
      "choices": [
        "A transformer rectifier unit.",
        "An inverter.",
        "A thermistor.",
        "An AC generator."
      ],
      "answer": "An inverter."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft battery provides a short-term, limited source of electrical energy. A __________ battery supplies less charge and a __________ maximum rate of discharge.",
      "choices": [
        "warm; zero",
        "cold; zero",
        "warm; smaller",
        "cold; smaller"
      ],
      "answer": "cold; smaller"
    },
    {
      "question": "A voltage is induced across a material with a positive thermal coefficient of resistance. The current flowing through the material will __________ as the material gets hotter.",
      "choices": [
        "increase",
        "decrease",
        "remain constant",
        "fluctuate"
      ],
      "answer": "decrease"
    },
    {
      "question": "The position of a waveform is defined by its __________.",
      "choices": [
        "frequency",
        "displacement angle",
        "phase or phase angle",
        "amplitude"
      ],
      "answer": "phase or phase angle"
    },
    {
      "question": "The unit of power for AC is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Joule",
        "Watt",
        "volt amp",
        "ohm"
      ],
      "answer": "Watt"
    },
    {
      "question": "To charge an aircraft battery, the battery busbar voltage must be __________ than the nominal battery voltage.",
      "choices": [
        "lower",
        "higher",
        "the same as",
        "double"
      ],
      "answer": "higher"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is fitted between the alternator/generator and the busbar to ensure that the battery cannot drive the alternator/generator.",
      "choices": [
        "A reverse current protection device.",
        "A voltage control unit.",
        "A surge protector.",
        "A voltage protection device."
      ],
      "answer": "A reverse current protection device."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct? 1. By increasing the load on an electric motor (i.e. increasing the resistance against rotation), the power output will increase as a result of an increased current flow. 2. The torque of an electrical motor can be calculated by dividing the power by the motor RPM.",
      "choices": [
        "1 and 2 are both incorrect.",
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct.",
        "1 is correct, 2 is incorrect.",
        "1 and 2 are both correct."
      ],
      "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is used to adjust the current flow to the generator's electromagnet?",
      "choices": [
        "An APU.",
        "A voltage control unit.",
        "An electric motor control unit.",
        "A starter unit."
      ],
      "answer": "A voltage control unit."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the unit of measurement for electrical work?",
      "choices": [
        "Watt.",
        "Ohm.",
        "Volt.",
        "Joule."
      ],
      "answer": "Joule."
    },
    {
      "question": "Current which flows in 1 direction only is known as __________ current.",
      "choices": [
        "alternating",
        "static",
        "direct",
        "induced"
      ],
      "answer": "direct"
    },
    {
      "question": "The unit of current is the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "volt",
        "amp",
        "Joule",
        "watt"
      ],
      "answer": "amp"
    },
    {
      "question": "A short-circuit condition __________ rectified by replacing the fuse or resetting the circuit breaker.",
      "choices": [
        "can be",
        "cannot be",
        "may be",
        "should be"
      ],
      "answer": "cannot be"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary threat from multiple or unauthorised resets of a circuit breaker is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "damage to the generator",
        "damage to the battery",
        "electrical fire",
        "damage to the avionics"
      ],
      "answer": "electrical fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "Frequency wild' in relation to an AC generation system means the generator:",
      "choices": [
        "Output frequency is too low.",
        "Output frequency is too high.",
        "Voltage regulator is out of adjustment.",
        "Output frequency varies with engine speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Output frequency varies with engine speed."
    },
    {
      "question": "When the AC generators are connected in parallel, the reactive loads are balanced by means of the:",
      "choices": [
        "excitation current.",
        "frequency controller.",
        "load controller.",
        "engine RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "excitation current."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the event of an AC generator fault, on a twin engine aircraft, the protection device will open:",
      "choices": [
        "The exciter control relay, the generator breaker and the bus tie breaker.",
        "The exciter control relay and the generator breaker.",
        "The generator breaker and the bus tie breaker.",
        "The bus tie breaker."
      ],
      "answer": "The exciter control relay and the generator breaker."
    },
    {
      "question": "Good insulators have many __________ electrons.",
      "choices": [
        "tightly bound",
        "free",
        "conduction",
        "valence"
      ],
      "answer": "tightly bound"
    },
    {
      "question": "kVA is the unit typically used to describe the power output of an aircraft's __________ generator.",
      "choices": [
        "DC",
        "AC",
        "starter",
        "alternating"
      ],
      "answer": "AC"
    },
    {
      "question": "ln reference to an inverter unit, which of these relationships between AC and DC is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "AC--+ DC",
        "y Volts of DC -+ y Volts of AC",
        "x Volts DC -+ x Volts of AC",
        "x Volts of DC --+ y Volts of AC"
      ],
      "answer": "x Volts of DC --+ y Volts of AC"
    },
    {
      "question": "A coil wrapped around a fixed ferrous core creates an electromagnetic force when the coil is energised. This closes a switch to allow high current to pass through a second circuit'. This is a description of a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "battery",
        "solenoid",
        "relay",
        "switch"
      ],
      "answer": "relay"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most serious threat posed by overcurrent in a circuit is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "damage to the generator",
        "fire",
        "damage to the electrical components",
        "damage to the fuse"
      ],
      "answer": "fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "A ferrous metal core moves when a current is caused to flow in a coil of wire wrapped around it'. This is a description of a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "solenoid",
        "relay",
        "battery",
        "generator"
      ],
      "answer": "solenoid"
    },
    {
      "question": "This unit operates as a starter motor during engine start and a DC generator after engine start. It is called a:",
      "choices": [
        "A DC alternator.",
        "A DC starter-generator.",
        "A DC generator.",
        "A DC motor."
      ],
      "answer": "A DC starter-generator."
    },
    {
      "question": "The moving part in an AC generator is usually referred to as the:",
      "choices": [
        "Slip ring.",
        "Oscillator.",
        "Stator.",
        "Rotor."
      ],
      "answer": "Rotor."
    },
    {
      "question": "\"Overcurrent results in excessive heating which causes the circuit protection device to open the circuit'. This is a description of: __________.",
      "choices": [
        "a fuse only",
        "a thermally activated CB or a fuse",
        "an electromechanical CB",
        "any circuit breaker."
      ],
      "answer": "a thermally activated CB or a fuse"
    },
    {
      "question": "Your 40 Ah aircraft battery is fully charged and in peak condition when, during flight, your electrical generator fails. The centre-zero ammeter reads - 20 A. If you don't load-shed immediately, you can expect the battery to last for an absolute maximum of:",
      "choices": [
        "4 hrs",
        "10 hrs",
        "2 hrs",
        "20 hrs"
      ],
      "answer": "2 hrs"
    },
    {
      "question": "The type of gate that requires all 'TRUE' inputs for a 'TRUE' output is:",
      "choices": [
        "NAND.",
        "NOR.",
        "OR.",
        "AND."
      ],
      "answer": "AND."
    },
    {
      "question": "A DC __________ creates electrical current by rotating an electromagnetic field, inside which are coils of wire.",
      "choices": [
        "generator",
        "commutator",
        "alternator",
        "motor"
      ],
      "answer": "alternator"
    },
    {
      "question": "A lithium battery fire can only be extinguished by:",
      "choices": [
        "Carbon Dioxide",
        "Halon",
        "Water or other non-flammable liquids.",
        "BCF"
      ],
      "answer": "Water or other non-flammable liquids."
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ can be reset.",
      "choices": [
        "blown fuse",
        "popped circuit breaker",
        "tripped switch",
        "a short circuit"
      ],
      "answer": "popped circuit breaker"
    },
    {
      "question": "A copper wire, with very good conducting properties, is used to connect the 2 terminals of a battery directly. The result is a __________ circuit which could produce a dangerous amount of heat. A similar condition occurring in an aircraft could result in an electrical fire.",
      "choices": [
        "short",
        "electrical",
        "open",
        "series"
      ],
      "answer": "short"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most common modern type of DC generation device is an __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "generator",
        "commutator",
        "alternator",
        "dynamo"
      ],
      "answer": "alternator"
    },
    {
      "question": "Static electricity is most likely to accumulate on an airframe when the aircraft is flying through very __________ air.",
      "choices": [
        "dry",
        "humid",
        "moist",
        "damp"
      ],
      "answer": "dry"
    },
    {
      "question": "A DC __________ creates electrical current by rotating coils of wire inside an electromagnetic field.",
      "choices": [
        "alternator",
        "commutator",
        "generator",
        "motor"
      ],
      "answer": "generator"
    },
    {
      "question": "An electrical generator driven by an engine creates electrical energy by the process of electromagnetic __________.",
      "choices": [
        "induction",
        "generation",
        "conduction",
        "conversion"
      ],
      "answer": "induction"
    },
    {
      "question": "The unit of frequency is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "volt",
        "hertz",
        "degree",
        "amp"
      ],
      "answer": "hertz"
    },
    {
      "question": "An electrical potential difference generates an __________ force.",
      "choices": [
        "electromotive",
        "electromagnetic",
        "magneto-motive",
        "electrostatic"
      ],
      "answer": "electromotive"
    },
    {
      "question": "Solid-state __________ are used in a DC alternator to cut off the flow of current whenever it reverses direction.",
      "choices": [
        "diodes",
        "commutators",
        "transistors",
        "rectifiers"
      ],
      "answer": "diodes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Poor electrical __________ may cause electrical components to fail or static interference on the radios.",
      "choices": [
        "grounding",
        "bonding",
        "insulation",
        "isolation"
      ],
      "answer": "bonding"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fuses and circuit beakers are 'rated' according to the maximum __________ they can sustain before blowing or popping respectively.",
      "choices": [
        "voltage",
        "current",
        "wattage",
        "resistance"
      ],
      "answer": "current"
    },
    {
      "question": "A well-bonded airframe can be used as a common __________ __________ for electrical circuits.",
      "choices": [
        "earth return",
        "electrical circuit",
        "negative return",
        "positive return"
      ],
      "answer": "earth return"
    },
    {
      "question": "The wire in a fuse is made from material with __________.",
      "choices": [
        "a negative thermal coefficient",
        "a positive thermal coefficient",
        "zero thermal coefficient",
        "high conductivity"
      ],
      "answer": "a positive thermal coefficient"
    },
    {
      "question": "A voltage control unit of a DC generating device must output a constant __________ at all engine RPM.",
      "choices": [
        "current",
        "frequency",
        "voltage",
        "power"
      ],
      "answer": "voltage"
    },
    {
      "question": "A constant speed drive (CSD) that has been disconnected in flight:",
      "choices": [
        "Automatically resets on engine shut-down.",
        "Automatically resets in flight providing engine rpm is below a given value.",
        "Can be reset in flight using the reset mechanism.",
        "Can be reset only on the ground after engine shut-down."
      ],
      "answer": "Can be reset only on the ground after engine shut-down."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ is the unit of electrical potential difference.",
      "choices": [
        "amp",
        "watt",
        "volt",
        "ohm"
      ],
      "answer": "volt"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the voltage of the alternator reduces below the voltage of the battery, then current flow will flow from the __________ to the battery busbar.",
      "choices": [
        "battery",
        "alternator",
        "generator",
        "ammeter"
      ],
      "answer": "battery"
    },
    {
      "question": "To ensure that there is no electrical potential difference between one part of the airframe and another, all parts must be __________ together.",
      "choices": [
        "bonded",
        "charged",
        "grounded",
        "connected"
      ],
      "answer": "bonded"
    },
    {
      "question": "Protecting a circuit from damage caused by excessive current is a function of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "fuses and circuit breakers",
        "circuit breakers only",
        "fuses only",
        "transistors only"
      ],
      "answer": "fuses and circuit breakers"
    },
    {
      "question": "A lithium polymer battery is most likely to be a hazard to the aircraft when:",
      "choices": [
        "The battery has an extreme internal pressure.",
        "The battery is rapidly discharged.",
        "The battery is rapidly charged.",
        "Electrolyte is dripping out of the battery."
      ],
      "answer": "The battery has an extreme internal pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "When using a fuse with a higher rating than prescribed:",
      "choices": [
        "Overcurrent might go undetected and cause a fire.",
        "The current in the circuit will be too high, resulting in a blown fuse.",
        "The whole circuit will overheat, which is a potential fire hazard.",
        "It will take too much time to detect an open circuit."
      ],
      "answer": "Overcurrent might go undetected and cause a fire."
    },
    {
      "question": "The rating of electrical fuses is expressed in:",
      "choices": [
        "Amperes.",
        "Ohms.",
        "Volts.",
        "Watts."
      ],
      "answer": "Amperes."
    },
    {
      "question": "A substantial conductor powered by an electrical source such as a battery or generator which has multiple attachment points for loads (consumers)' is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "A common earth return.",
        "A contactor.",
        "A busbar",
        "A battery."
      ],
      "answer": "A busbar"
    },
    {
      "question": "The number of waves per second, measured from peak to peak, is the __________ of the waveform.",
      "choices": [
        "amplitude",
        "frequency",
        "wavelength",
        "period"
      ],
      "answer": "frequency"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ batteries, when discharging, sustain the correct voltage for a relatively long period before becoming exhausted.",
      "choices": [
        "lead-acid",
        "lithium and NiCd",
        "Zinc-carbon",
        "alkaline"
      ],
      "answer": "lithium and NiCd"
    },
    {
      "question": "Good insulators provide __________ resistance to current flow.",
      "choices": [
        "strong",
        "weak",
        "zero",
        "varying"
      ],
      "answer": "strong"
    },
    {
      "question": "An AC generator driven by a constant speed drive (CSD):",
      "choices": [
        "Requires a voltage controller to maintain constant frequency.",
        "Requires a voltage controller to maintain constant voltage under load.",
        "Does not need a voltage controller since the CSD will ensure constant voltage.",
        "Does not need a voltage controller since an AC generator voltage cannot alter under load."
      ],
      "answer": "Requires a voltage controller to maintain constant voltage under load."
    },
    {
      "question": "If a battery's ammeter shows +24 , what is happening?",
      "choices": [
        "24A is being drained from the batteries.",
        "There is 24V going through the ammeter.",
        "24Ah remain in the battery.",
        "24A is being pushed to the batteries."
      ],
      "answer": "24A is being pushed to the batteries."
    },
    {
      "question": "The AC waveform is a __________ shape.",
      "choices": [
        "flat",
        "eliptical",
        "sinusoidal",
        "triangular"
      ],
      "answer": "sinusoidal"
    },
    {
      "question": "When the voltage of the alternator/generator reduces below the voltage at the busbar, then the current flow will reverse. If nothing is done to stop this, the alternator/generator becomes:",
      "choices": [
        "An electric motor driven by the engine's RPM.",
        "An alternator.",
        "An electric motor driven by the battery.",
        "A commutator."
      ],
      "answer": "An electric motor driven by the battery."
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ is used in a DC __________ to cut off the flow of current whenever it becomes negative.",
      "choices": [
        "commutator; generator",
        "rotor; alternator",
        "armature; commutator",
        "alternator; generator"
      ],
      "answer": "commutator; generator"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the the principle of a ram-air turbine?",
      "choices": [
        "Bleed air drive expansion turbine drives compressor.",
        "Ram air pushes down on a piston...",
        "Wind-driven propeller drives hydraulic pump.",
        "Turbine exhaust gases...reservoir."
      ],
      "answer": "Wind-driven propeller drives hydraulic pump."
    },
    {
      "question": "The pure turbojet has no __________ but the __________ exhaust jet velocity allows it to propel aircraft at very high air speed.",
      "choices": [
        "bypass duct; high",
        "compressor; low",
        "bypass duct; low",
        "compressor; high"
      ],
      "answer": "bypass duct; high"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the combustor section, fuel is combusted at constant __________.",
      "choices": [
        "pressure",
        "velocity",
        "temperature",
        "volume"
      ],
      "answer": "pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "The thermal efficiency of a gas turbine engine will increase with a:",
      "choices": [
        "decrease in ambient air pressure.",
        "decrease in ambient air temperature.",
        "increase in ambient air temp.",
        "increase in humidity."
      ],
      "answer": "decrease in ambient air temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "Bypass engines have an inherently __________ SFC than pure turbojets.",
      "choices": [
        "lower",
        "higher",
        "equal",
        "variable"
      ],
      "answer": "lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "When applying carburettor heating:",
      "choices": [
        "No change occurs in the mixture.",
        "RPM increases immediately.",
        "The mixture becomes richer.",
        "The mixture becomes leaner."
      ],
      "answer": "The mixture becomes richer."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of a diffuser is to convert __________ energy into pressure energy.",
      "choices": [
        "chemical",
        "thermal",
        "kinetic",
        "electrical"
      ],
      "answer": "kinetic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Excessive pressure in the cylinders of an engine equipped with a constant speed propeller, can be caused by the combination of:",
      "choices": [
        "Low manifold pressure and high RPM.",
        "High manifold pressure and low RPM.",
        "Low manifold...low RPM.",
        "High manifold...high RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "High manifold pressure and low RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Engine auxiliary gearboxes:",
      "choices": [
        "Are driven by the output from the free power turbine.",
        "Provide the drives for...airframe.",
        "Always provide drives for...",
        "Never provide a torque..."
      ],
      "answer": "Provide the drives for a wide variety of services and may even provide for the support of the engine in the airframe."
    },
    {
      "question": "An annular combustor which wraps continuously around the main shaft (rather than comprising separate 'combustion tubes') is a type of __________ chamber.",
      "choices": [
        "plenum",
        "can-annular",
        "annular",
        "combustion"
      ],
      "answer": "plenum"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements is correct:",
      "choices": [
        "A gas turbine engine may be re-started in flight with or without the assistance of the APU.",
        "A gas turbine on an all-electric aircraft cannot be started in flight using the windmilling technique.",
        "When using an APU...possible.",
        "A gas turbine engine cannot be re-lit in flight unless it is equipped with an electric starter motor."
      ],
      "answer": "A gas turbine engine may be re-started in flight with or without the assistance of the APU."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a normal engine start, the engine eventually accelerates to, and stabilises at, __________.",
      "choices": [
        "ground idle",
        "flight idle",
        "maximum continuous",
        "take-off"
      ],
      "answer": "ground idle"
    },
    {
      "question": "The rear part of a pitot-style inlet forms a __________ duct.",
      "choices": [
        "divergent",
        "convergent",
        "straight",
        "variable"
      ],
      "answer": "divergent"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a typical gas turbine engine fire detection system tested?",
      "choices": [
        "It cannot be checked apart from a physical wiring check.",
        "Using a heat source.",
        "Using a pressure source.",
        "There is a test circuit that carries out a continuity check."
      ],
      "answer": "There is a test circuit that carries out a continuity check."
    },
    {
      "question": "Handling bleed is used to:",
      "choices": [
        "Supply hot air to de-ice the intake lip.",
        "Supply hot air to de-ice the bypass duct.",
        "Keep the compressor on the working line during engine accelerations.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "answer": "Keep the compressor on the working line during engine accelerations."
    },
    {
      "question": "The average stage compression ratio of a centrifugal compressor is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "40:1",
        "15:1",
        "4:1",
        "1.3:1"
      ],
      "answer": "4:1"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a subsonic airflow, in a divergent duct the:",
      "choices": [
        "static pressure increases, speed decreases and static temperature decreases.",
        "static pressure decreases, speed increases and static temperature decreases.",
        "static pressure decreases, speed increases and static temperature increases.",
        "static pressure increases, speed decreases and static temperature increases."
      ],
      "answer": "static pressure increases, speed decreases and static temperature increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "When the velocity of the gas stream at the nozzle reaches M 1.0, the exhaust system is said to be __________.",
      "choices": [
        "choked",
        "optimised",
        "stalled",
        "flowing"
      ],
      "answer": "choked"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fuel is mixed with __________ air.",
      "choices": [
        "secondary",
        "primary",
        "tertiary",
        "bypass"
      ],
      "answer": "primary"
    },
    {
      "question": "The FCU is controlled by __________ to the thrust lever.",
      "choices": [
        "a mechanical linkage",
        "an electrical link",
        "a hydraulic link",
        "a pneumatic link"
      ],
      "answer": "a mechanical linkage"
    },
    {
      "question": "The effect of ram air on the operation of a gas turbine engine is:",
      "choices": [
        "an increase in the efficiency of the engine.",
        "an increase in the engine rpm for take-off.",
        "an increase in the indicated airspeed (IAS) at which the aeroplane should be flown for optimum range.",
        "a lower efficiency of the engine with an increase in aeroplane speed."
      ],
      "answer": "an increase in the efficiency of the engine."
    },
    {
      "question": "On an aeroplane equipped with a constant speed propeller, the RPM indicator and its associated control lever enable:",
      "choices": [
        "On a twin-engine aeroplane, automatic engine synchronisation.",
        "Display of propeller RPM and control of the propeller regulator.",
        "Selection of engine RPM.",
        "Control of power."
      ],
      "answer": "Display of propeller RPM and control of the propeller regulator."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ requires you to use a different set of performance tables for your take-off calculations.",
      "choices": [
        "De-rate",
        "Flex thrust",
        "Maximum continuous thrust",
        "Climb thrust"
      ],
      "answer": "De-rate"
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of the propeller drive gearbox is to cause the propeller to rotate at an RPM:",
      "choices": [
        "The same as engine RPM.",
        "Greater than engine RPM.",
        "Which varies in its ratio with engine RPM.",
        "Less than engine RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "Less than engine RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Newton's 3rd law, if an object (such as a jet engine) accelerates a mass of air rearwards, it creates an equal and opposite __________ which propels it forward.",
      "choices": [
        "action",
        "reaction",
        "thrust",
        "force"
      ],
      "answer": "reaction"
    },
    {
      "question": "The PRSOV is either operated manually by __________ or automatically by the FADEC system.",
      "choices": [
        "the engine start switch",
        "a mechanical lever",
        "the throttle",
        "the fuel control switch"
      ],
      "answer": "a mechanical lever"
    },
    {
      "question": "During high altitude re-lights, the igniters operate in __________ mode. When continuous ignition is selected, the igniters operate in __________ mode.",
      "choices": [
        "high energy; high energy",
        "high energy; low energy",
        "low energy; low energy",
        "low energy; high energy"
      ],
      "answer": "high energy; low energy"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a turbo-jet, the purpose of the turbine is to ...",
      "choices": [
        "clear the burnt gases, the expansion of which provide the thrust",
        "drive the compressor by using part of the energy from the exhaust gases",
        "drive devices like pumps, regulator, generator.",
        "compress the air in order to provide a better charge of the combustion chamber"
      ],
      "answer": "drive the compressor by using part of the energy from the exhaust gases"
    },
    {
      "question": "Most modern commercial jet aircraft use __________ engines.",
      "choices": [
        "turbofan",
        "turboshaft",
        "turbojet",
        "propfan"
      ],
      "answer": "turbofan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bleed air is taken from the __________ to power the aircraft's pneumatic systems.",
      "choices": [
        "compressor",
        "turbine",
        "combustor",
        "exhaust"
      ],
      "answer": "compressor"
    },
    {
      "question": "The shear neck is a device fitted to prevent:",
      "choices": [
        "Oil leaks, in case of mechanical failure of the gearbox.",
        "Engine failure, in case of excessive speed of the gearbox.",
        "Engine failure, in case of mechanical failure of the gearbox.",
        "Engine fire, in case of mechanical failure of the gearbox."
      ],
      "answer": "Engine failure, in case of mechanical failure of the gearbox."
    },
    {
      "question": "For optimum efficiency, the fan needs to run at relatively __________ RPM and the core needs to run at relatively __________ RPM.",
      "choices": [
        "high; high",
        "high; low",
        "low; high",
        "low; low"
      ],
      "answer": "low; high"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ bearings can absorb only the side loads on a shaft (including its weight force).",
      "choices": [
        "Ball",
        "Roller",
        "Needle",
        "Plain"
      ],
      "answer": "Roller"
    },
    {
      "question": "The temperature of the air passing through the bypass duct is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "much colder than ambient",
        "essentially unchanged from ambient",
        "much hotter than ambient",
        "slightly hotter than ambient"
      ],
      "answer": "essentially unchanged from ambient"
    },
    {
      "question": "A reverse-flow combustor:",
      "choices": [
        "Is commonly used on large turban engines.",
        "Reverses the secondary air.",
        "Is U-shaped to reduce the overall length of the engine.",
        "Reverses the flow of mixture in the snout."
      ],
      "answer": "Is U-shaped to reduce the overall length of the engine."
    },
    {
      "question": "Why is the jet engine exhaust convergent?",
      "choices": [
        "To create more noise.",
        "To reduce friction.",
        "To accelerate the exhaust air.",
        "To reduce noise."
      ],
      "answer": "To accelerate the exhaust air."
    },
    {
      "question": "Variations in mixture ratios for carburettors are achieved by the adjustment of:",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel flow.",
        "Fuel flow, air flow and...",
        "Air flow.",
        "Fuel flow and air flow."
      ],
      "answer": "Fuel flow."
    },
    {
      "question": "As altitude increases, if the mixture is not leaned:",
      "choices": [
        "The volume of air...decreases and the amount of fuel decreases.",
        "The volume of air...fuel...",
        "The density of air...increases.",
        "The density of air...constant."
      ],
      "answer": "The density of air entering the carburettor decreases and the amount of fuel remains constant."
    },
    {
      "question": "Once it has begun, combustion __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "is self-sustaining",
        "always needs...ignition",
        "needs a constant fuel supply",
        "is explosive"
      ],
      "answer": "is self-sustaining"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the exhaust system, the temperature of the gas flow __________, the pressure of the gas flow __________ and the velocity of the gas flow usually __________.",
      "choices": [
        "falls; rises; rises",
        "falls; falls; rises",
        "falls; rises; falls",
        "rises; falls; rises"
      ],
      "answer": "falls; falls; rises"
    },
    {
      "question": "The fuel spray nozzles are connected to, and fed by, the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "fuel pumps",
        "fuel manifold",
        "fuel distributor",
        "fuel lines"
      ],
      "answer": "fuel manifold"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ram effect is a phenomenon associated with __________ air speed.",
      "choices": [
        "low",
        "high",
        "medium",
        "fluctuating"
      ],
      "answer": "high"
    },
    {
      "question": "Specific fuel consumption for a turbo-prop engine can be expressed in kg per:",
      "choices": [
        "unit of shaft power.",
        "hour per unit of shaft power.",
        "hour per km.",
        "hour per nm."
      ],
      "answer": "hour per unit of shaft power."
    },
    {
      "question": "Flow reversal though an axial flow compressor is called a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "compressor stall",
        "compressor surge",
        "compressor failure",
        "engine failure"
      ],
      "answer": "compressor surge"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a non FADEC system, the gas turbine engine is manually shut-down by closing the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "the manifold valve",
        "the spar valve",
        "the LP cock",
        "HP cock (PRSOV)"
      ],
      "answer": "HP cock (PRSOV)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Maximum climb power __________ time limited.",
      "choices": [
        "is not",
        "is",
        "might be",
        "can be"
      ],
      "answer": "is"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the advantages of an annular combustion chamber in a gas turbine engine is:",
      "choices": [
        "a simpler assembly.",
        "that fewer igniters are required.",
        "a reduced thermal stress on the turbine.",
        "a higher structural strength."
      ],
      "answer": "a reduced thermal stress on the turbine."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a turbofan engine, high levels of vibration are __________.",
      "choices": [
        "abnormal",
        "normal",
        "common",
        "acceptable"
      ],
      "answer": "abnormal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Regarding a jet engine, which of the following statements is/are correct? I. Maximum thrust decreases as the pressure altitude increases. II. Specific fuel consumption is inversely proportional to pressure altitude, at constant TAS.",
      "choices": [
        "I is correct; II is correct.",
        "I is correct; II is incorrect.",
        "I is incorrect; II is incorrect.",
        "I is incorrect; II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "I is correct; II is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "A centrifugal compressor __________ suffer from an aerodynamic stall.",
      "choices": [
        "cannot",
        "can",
        "will always",
        "will never"
      ],
      "answer": "cannot"
    },
    {
      "question": "A turbofan engine with an inlet air mass flow of 1000 kg/s and a bypass mass flow of 889 kg/s has a bypass ratio of:",
      "choices": [
        "17.02",
        "1.12",
        "2.12",
        "8.01"
      ],
      "answer": "8.01"
    },
    {
      "question": "The electronic engine control of a FADEC gas turbine engine checks:",
      "choices": [
        "ACTIVE CHANNEL input and output data only.",
        "all input and output data.",
        "output data only.",
        "input data only."
      ],
      "answer": "all input and output data."
    },
    {
      "question": "In addition to fire detection/protection, most auxiliary power units (APUs) have automatic controls for starting, stopping and maintaining operation within safe limits. These controls provide correct sequencing of the starting cycle as well as protection against:",
      "choices": [
        "Overspeed and high oil temperature only.",
        "High turbine gas temperature (TGT), overspeed, loss of oil pressure and high oil temperature.",
        "High TGT and loss of oil pressure only.",
        "High TGT only."
      ],
      "answer": "High turbine gas temperature (TGT), overspeed, loss of oil pressure and high oil temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "The blade angle of a propeller is the angle between the:",
      "choices": [
        "Plane of rotation and the relative airflow.",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation.",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller axis of rotation.",
        "Reference chord line and the relative airflow."
      ],
      "answer": "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation."
    },
    {
      "question": "A thrust reverse system on a high-bypass engine reverses some of the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "hot core air",
        "cold bypass air",
        "entire exhaust stream",
        "turbine exhaust"
      ],
      "answer": "cold bypass air"
    },
    {
      "question": "The APU supplies __________.",
      "choices": [
        "electrical and pneumatic power",
        "pneumatic power only",
        "electrical power only",
        "Electrical and hydraulic power only"
      ],
      "answer": "electrical and pneumatic power"
    },
    {
      "question": "To prevent the extremely dangerous situation of reverse thrust engaging in flight, an __________ is used to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "interlock; prevent the reverser doors from opening",
        "locking pin; prevent the flight deck lever from being operated",
        "warning caption; prevent the flight deck lever from being operated",
        "interlock; prevent the flight deck lever from being operated"
      ],
      "answer": "interlock; prevent the flight deck lever from being operated"
    },
    {
      "question": "A centrifugal compressor __________ suffer a breakdown of stable airflow, resulting in a loss of compression.",
      "choices": [
        "cannot",
        "can",
        "never",
        "always"
      ],
      "answer": "can"
    },
    {
      "question": "The turbine component which directs the flow of gas at the correct angle onto a turbine blade is called a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "stator",
        "inlet guide vane",
        "nozzle guide vane",
        "rotor"
      ],
      "answer": "nozzle guide vane"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of a chip detector in the oil system of an engine/gearbox is to indicate that:",
      "choices": [
        "The seals are worn.",
        "There are metal particles in the oil.",
        "The oil temperature is too high.",
        "The piston rings are worn."
      ],
      "answer": "There are metal particles in the oil."
    },
    {
      "question": "ln a twin spool free turbine engine, the energy delivered by the free turbine stages:",
      "choices": [
        "is used to drive the compressor and the gear box.",
        "is used to drive the generator.",
        "is used to drive the compressor only.",
        "is dependent on the rotational speed of the HP spool."
      ],
      "answer": "is dependent on the rotational speed of the HP spool."
    },
    {
      "question": "Some components of a turbine engine are required to operate at their maximum temperature. What are the components which are exposed to the greatest thermal loads?",
      "choices": [
        "HP turbine and Jet pipe.",
        "Turbine nozzle guide vanes and the first stage of the LP turbine.",
        "First stage turbine nozzle guide vanes and the first stage of the HP turbine.",
        "Duplex burner and flame tube."
      ],
      "answer": "First stage turbine nozzle guide vanes and the first stage of the HP turbine."
    },
    {
      "question": "The graph which shows the axial flow compressor's working line between the two operating margins is called a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "stability map",
        "surge map",
        "compressor map",
        "operating map"
      ],
      "answer": "compressor map"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a multi-spool engine, the LP turbine is located __________ the exhaust section.",
      "choices": [
        "furthest from",
        "closest to",
        "next to",
        "in"
      ],
      "answer": "closest to"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the purpose of Cowl flaps?",
      "choices": [
        "When opened, allows air to flow across the engine improving cooling efficiency.",
        "When opened act as a drag system to slow the aircraft down.",
        "When opened, allows air to flow in the engine intake improving propulsive efficiency.",
        "When opened sends warm air down the carburettor to remove any carb icing."
      ],
      "answer": "When opened, allows air to flow across the engine improving cooling efficiency."
    },
    {
      "question": "Propulsive power is the product of thrust multiplied by the velocity of the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "aircraft",
        "exhaust gas",
        "the engine",
        "the propeller"
      ],
      "answer": "aircraft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of magnetic chip detectors is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Increase lubricating oil adhesion to main surfaces.",
        "Perform the function of a...filter.",
        "Warn of impending failure.",
        "Remove large items of debris..."
      ],
      "answer": "Warn of impending failure."
    },
    {
      "question": "The component of flow through an engine which flows directly from front to rear is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "axial",
        "tangential",
        "radial",
        "turbulent"
      ],
      "answer": "axial"
    },
    {
      "question": "Active clearance control:",
      "choices": [
        "Is a method of ensuring a free gas path through the turbine.",
        "Is a method for managing tip clearance in the turbine, using bleed air.",
        "Uses very hot...turbine case.",
        "Is a method for reducing...creep."
      ],
      "answer": "Is a method for managing tip clearance in the turbine, using bleed air."
    },
    {
      "question": "Most modern turbines use __________ blades.",
      "choices": [
        "impulse-reaction",
        "reaction",
        "impulse",
        "mixed"
      ],
      "answer": "impulse-reaction"
    },
    {
      "question": "Both gas turbine and piston engines use a cycle made up of induction, compression, combustion and exhaust phases. Which of these statements about a gas turbine are correct? 1. The process in a gas turbine engine is continuous 2. Theoretically the combustion occurs at constant volume.",
      "choices": [
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is incorrect.",
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct.",
        "1 is correct, 2 is incorrect.",
        "1 is correct, 2 is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "1 is correct, 2 is incorrect."
    },
    {
      "question": "PRSOV stands for: __________.",
      "choices": [
        "pressure regulating shut-off valve",
        "primary regulating shut-off valve",
        "pressure relief shut-off valve",
        "pressure reducing shut-off valve"
      ],
      "answer": "pressure regulating shut-off valve"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of compressing air is to maximise the mass flow __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "through the core and bypass",
        "through the core",
        "through the bypass",
        "through the engine"
      ],
      "answer": "through the core"
    },
    {
      "question": "Blades are shrouded to reduce __________.",
      "choices": [
        "blade creep",
        "blade stall",
        "tip losses",
        "vibration"
      ],
      "answer": "tip losses"
    },
    {
      "question": "The danger of excessively cold fuel is that:",
      "choices": [
        "It clogs up the combustor.",
        "It contains a lot of water.",
        "It is unable to burn.",
        "It is prone to waxing."
      ],
      "answer": "It is prone to waxing."
    },
    {
      "question": "A pitot-style inlet makes full use of the __________ effect at high forward air speeds.",
      "choices": [
        "ram rise",
        "ram",
        "pitot",
        "venturi"
      ],
      "answer": "ram"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cascade vanes help to reverse the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "hot stream",
        "cold stream",
        "entire stream",
        "core stream"
      ],
      "answer": "cold stream"
    },
    {
      "question": "Take-off thrust __________.",
      "choices": [
        "can be used indefinitely.",
        "is not available...de-rate...",
        "is time limited.",
        "is not available when flex..."
      ],
      "answer": "is time limited."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the alpha and beta ranges respectively the governed elements of turboprop propeller controls are as follows:",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel flow and pitch.",
        "Propeller RPM and engine RPM.",
        "Reverse thrust and blade angle.",
        "Engine RPM and fuel flow."
      ],
      "answer": "Propeller RPM and engine RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "If both FADEC channels are lost:",
      "choices": [
        "The engine will continue to run normally because of the hydro-mechanical back-up system.",
        "The engine will continue to run but will be unresponsive to thrust lever movements and no engine indications will be visible on the display.",
        "The engine will shut down.",
        "The engine will continue to run and will respond to thrust lever movements, but no engine indications will be visible on the display."
      ],
      "answer": "The engine will shut down."
    },
    {
      "question": "In very cold weather, a slightly higher than normal engine oil pressure during start-up:",
      "choices": [
        "Is acceptable, if it decreases after startup.",
        "Requires an oil change.",
        "Is unacceptable and requires the engine to be shut down.",
        "Is unacceptable but does not require the engine to be shut down."
      ],
      "answer": "Is acceptable, if it decreases after startup."
    },
    {
      "question": "The axial compressor of a gas turbine engine usually has more stages than its driving turbine because:",
      "choices": [
        "the compressor consumes much more power than the turbine.",
        "turbine speed is much higher than compressor speed.",
        "bleed air is taken from the compressor.",
        "the power output of a turbine stage is higher than the power consumption of a compressor stage."
      ],
      "answer": "the power output of a turbine stage is higher than the power consumption of a compressor stage."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ pumps suck used oil from the bearing chamber sumps into the oil return lines.",
      "choices": [
        "Scavenge",
        "Manifold drain",
        "Pressure",
        "Return"
      ],
      "answer": "Scavenge"
    },
    {
      "question": "Aircraft engines equipped with FADEC have redundancy built in with regards to data input and control output. This is to ensure:",
      "choices": [
        "that engine parameters displays are not lost should one channel fail.",
        "the engine parameter recording for post-flight maintenance purposes.",
        "uninterrupted engine operation if one channel fails.",
        "that analogue signals can be converted to digital data even if a single FADEC channel fails."
      ],
      "answer": "uninterrupted engine operation if one channel fails."
    },
    {
      "question": "If the manifold pressure is increased, the blade angle of a constant speed propeller:",
      "choices": [
        "Will increase.",
        "Will reduce so that the engine RPM can increase.",
        "Will increase and after a short time will reduce.",
        "Will remain the same."
      ],
      "answer": "Will increase."
    },
    {
      "question": "The turbine __________ the gas flow to power the compressor.",
      "choices": [
        "extracts energy from",
        "gives energy to",
        "cools",
        "heats"
      ],
      "answer": "extracts energy from"
    },
    {
      "question": "The compressor __________ the gas flow.",
      "choices": [
        "takes energy from",
        "gives energy to",
        "pressurises",
        "cools"
      ],
      "answer": "gives energy to"
    },
    {
      "question": "Most high-bypass (unmixed) turbofan engines are equipped with a cold exhaust reverser (fan reverser) only in order to:",
      "choices": [
        "save costs and mass at the expense of a reduction ln available reverse thrust.",
        "reduce the risk of exhaust gas re-ingestion .",
        "prevent disturbance of cold exhaust reversed airflow by the hot exhaust reversed gas flow.",
        "prevent extra fuel consumption due to operation of the hot exhaust reverser (turbine reverser)."
      ],
      "answer": "save costs and mass at the expense of a reduction ln available reverse thrust."
    },
    {
      "question": "Clamshells or buckets are used to reverse the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "cold stream",
        "hot stream",
        "bypass stream",
        "entire stream"
      ],
      "answer": "hot stream"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements about an impulse turbine are correct or incorrect?    I. The pressure rises across the nozzle guide vanes. Il. The pressure rises across the rotor blades.",
      "choices": [
        "I is incorrect; II is incorrect.",
        "I is incorrect; II is correct.",
        "I is correct; II is incorrect.",
        "I is correct; II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "I is incorrect; II is incorrect."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the airflow through a single-spool axial flow turbo-jet engine, the axial velocity of the air is greatest:",
      "choices": [
        "as it leaves the compressor.",
        "on exit from the propelling nozzle.",
        "as it leaves the turbine.",
        "within the combustion chamber."
      ],
      "answer": "on exit from the propelling nozzle."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of a mixer unit is to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "reduce noise",
        "add fuel to the gas flow",
        "reverse the gas flow",
        "increase thrust"
      ],
      "answer": "reduce noise"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the igniter plugs is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Initiate and sustain combustion under normal conditions.",
        "Time the spark to coincide with compression.",
        "Provide power to the spark plugs.",
        "Initiate combustion and to sustain it under adverse conditions."
      ],
      "answer": "Initiate combustion and to sustain it under adverse conditions."
    },
    {
      "question": "Pressurised __________ prevent oil from escaping out of the bearing chambers.",
      "choices": [
        "diaphragms",
        "labyrinth seals",
        "carbon seals",
        "lip seals"
      ],
      "answer": "labyrinth seals"
    },
    {
      "question": "An LP spool comprises:",
      "choices": [
        "A fan, shaft and LP turbine.",
        "A fan and shaft.",
        "An LP compressor or fan, shaft and HP compressor.",
        "An LP compressor or fan, shaft and LP turbine."
      ],
      "answer": "An LP compressor or fan, shaft and LP turbine."
    },
    {
      "question": "Where is EGT typically measured?",
      "choices": [
        "Combustion chamber.",
        "HP turbine outlet.",
        "In the jet pipe.",
        "HP compressor outlet."
      ],
      "answer": "HP turbine outlet."
    },
    {
      "question": "The APU supplies __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "3-phase electrical power and pneumatic power",
        "Single-phase electrical power and pneumatic power",
        "pneumatic power only",
        "electrical power only"
      ],
      "answer": "3-phase electrical power and pneumatic power"
    },
    {
      "question": "An engine which uses a gas turbine core to drive a helicopter rotor is a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "turboshaft",
        "turbojet",
        "turbofan",
        "propfan"
      ],
      "answer": "turboshaft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ground idle is a __________ RPM than flight idle.",
      "choices": [
        "higher",
        "lower",
        "greater",
        "faster"
      ],
      "answer": "lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "The space between a pair of stator blades forms a __________ duct.",
      "choices": [
        "divergent",
        "convergent",
        "straight",
        "constant area"
      ],
      "answer": "divergent"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a centrifugal compressor the air is mechanically forced to flow from the __________ to the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "diffuser; eye",
        "diffuser; diffuser",
        "eye; diffuser",
        "eye; eye"
      ],
      "answer": "eye; diffuser"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements about a reaction turbine is correct or incorrect? 1. The pressure remains constant across the nozzle guide vanes. 2 The pressure rises across the rotor blades.",
      "choices": [
        "1 is correct, 2 is correct.",
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is incorrect.",
        "1 is correct, 2 is incorrect.",
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "1 is correct, 2 is incorrect."
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider the variable-pitch propeller of a turbo-prop aircraft. During deceleration:",
      "choices": [
        "With propeller windmilling, the thrust is zero and the propeller supplies engine power.",
        "When feathered, the propeller produces thrust and absorbs no engine power.",
        "When braking, the propeller supplies negative thrust and absorbs engine power.",
        "At zero power, the propeller thrust is zero and the engine power absorbed is nil."
      ],
      "answer": "When braking, the propeller supplies negative thrust and absorbs engine power."
    },
    {
      "question": "A 'hung start' is the failure of an engine to accelerate to its normal idle speed. It may be caused by:",
      "choices": [
        "Failure of the fuel to ignite in the starting sequence after the engine has been accelerated to the required RPM by the starter.",
        "An attempt to ignite the fuel before the engine has been accelerated sufficiently by the starter.",
        "Compressor surging.",
        "The starter cutting out early in the starting sequence before the engine has accelerated to the required RPM for ignition."
      ],
      "answer": "An attempt to ignite the fuel before the engine has been accelerated sufficiently by the starter."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is a temporary limitation on maximum thrust, set by entering an assumed temperature which is higher than ambient.",
      "choices": [
        "Flex thrust",
        "De-rate",
        "Climb thrust",
        "Maximum continuous thrust"
      ],
      "answer": "Flex thrust"
    },
    {
      "question": "The inner walls of the flame tube are protected by __________ air.",
      "choices": [
        "secondary",
        "primary",
        "tertiary",
        "cooling"
      ],
      "answer": "secondary"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the manifold drain is:",
      "choices": [
        "To drain excess oil from the combustor.",
        "To prevent fouling...during engine running.",
        "To prevent fouling...after shut-down.",
        "To expel fuel from the engine during an engine fire."
      ],
      "answer": "To prevent fouling of the spray nozzles and sooting of the combustor after shut-down."
    },
    {
      "question": "The LP pump is part of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "the aircraft's fuel system",
        "the engine's fuel system",
        "the hydraulic system",
        "the pneumatic system"
      ],
      "answer": "the aircraft's fuel system"
    },
    {
      "question": "The entire axial flow compressor is situated in a __________ duct.",
      "choices": [
        "divergent",
        "convergent",
        "straight",
        "diverging"
      ],
      "answer": "convergent"
    },
    {
      "question": "Air oil separators are required because:",
      "choices": [
        "Oil naturally combines with air.",
        "Bearings tend to aerate the oil.",
        "Labyrinth seals aerate the oil in the bearing chambers.",
        "There are unavoidable air leaks in the lubrication system."
      ],
      "answer": "Labyrinth seals aerate the oil in the bearing chambers."
    },
    {
      "question": "Across an entire axial flow compressor, the overall pressure rise is typically about Answer Question  __________   to 1.",
      "choices": [
        "15",
        "25",
        "35",
        "45"
      ],
      "answer": "35"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pressure relief valve in an oil system that does not seat correctly could result in:",
      "choices": [
        "Low oil pressure.",
        "Low oil temperature.",
        "High oil pressure.",
        "Excessive oil consumption."
      ],
      "answer": "Low oil pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "A mixture setting richer than best power has to be used during climb segments This results in a:",
      "choices": [
        "Lower cylinder head temperature.",
        "Increase of power.",
        "Higher torque.",
        "Higher efficiency."
      ],
      "answer": "Lower cylinder head temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "The by-pass air in a turbo fan engine has the effect of a lower specific fuel consumption by causing an overall:",
      "choices": [
        "Decrease in average exhaust gas flow velocity and a higher mass flow.",
        "Decrease in combustion chamber temperature and higher thermal efficiency.",
        "Increase in average exhaust gas flow velocity thus increasing engine pressure ratio.",
        "Increase in the mean jet temperature and increase in thermal efficiency."
      ],
      "answer": "Decrease in average exhaust gas flow velocity and a higher mass flow."
    },
    {
      "question": "What may happen during a continuous climb with a mixture setting fully rich?",
      "choices": [
        "The engine will operate smoother even though fuel consumption is increased.",
        "Increase of the power available.",
        "The engine will overheat.",
        "Fouling of spark plugs."
      ],
      "answer": "Fouling of spark plugs."
    },
    {
      "question": "The oil used to lubricate and cool the bearings is mostly confined within the __________",
      "choices": [
        "bearing duct",
        "bearing shell",
        "bearing chambers",
        "lubrication system"
      ],
      "answer": "bearing chambers"
    },
    {
      "question": "Scarfing is a technique for:",
      "choices": [
        "Increasing exhaust gas pressure.",
        "Reducing exhaust back flow.",
        "Reducing exhaust noise.",
        "Increasing exhaust flow."
      ],
      "answer": "Reducing exhaust noise."
    },
    {
      "question": "The measured output power components of a constant frequency AC system are:",
      "choices": [
        "Amperes and kilowatts.",
        "Volts and amperes.",
        "kVA and kVAR.",
        "Volts and kilowatts."
      ],
      "answer": "kVA and kVAR."
    },
    {
      "question": "The technique of looking at engine parameters such as vibration level, oil pressure and oil temperature and noting their change over time is known as __________ monitoring or (analysis).",
      "choices": [
        "performance",
        "trend",
        "vibration",
        "health"
      ],
      "answer": "trend"
    },
    {
      "question": "The bypass air in a turbo fan engine has the effect of a lower specific fuel consumption by causing an overall:",
      "choices": [
        "increase in average exhaust gas flow velocity thus increasing engine pressure ratio.",
        "decrease in average exhaust gas flow velocity and a higher mass flow.",
        "decrease in combustion chamber temperature and higher thermal efficiency.",
        "increase in the mean jet temperature and increase in thermal efficiency."
      ],
      "answer": "decrease in average exhaust gas flow velocity and a higher mass flow."
    },
    {
      "question": "EPR is the ratio of __________ to __________",
      "choices": [
        "inlet pressure; outlet pressure",
        "outlet pressure; inlet pressure",
        "turbine pressure; intake pressure",
        "exhaust pressure; ram pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "outlet pressure; inlet pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "A turbofan engine with a bypass air mass flow of 200 kg/s and a HP compressor mass flow of 20 kg/s has a bypass ratio of:",
      "choices": [
        "10",
        "11",
        "1.1",
        "9"
      ],
      "answer": "10"
    },
    {
      "question": "The breakdown of stable airflow across one or more stages is called a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "compressor surge",
        "compressor stall",
        "compressor vibration",
        "compressor failure"
      ],
      "answer": "compressor stall"
    },
    {
      "question": "High-bypass engines usually generate __________ exhaust noise.",
      "choices": [
        "more",
        "less",
        "the same",
        "greater"
      ],
      "answer": "less"
    },
    {
      "question": "The volume of the scavenge pump(s) in an engine lubrication system is greater than that of the pressure pump(s) in order to:",
      "choices": [
        "Ensure that the engine sump remains dry.",
        "Ensure heat is dissipated more effectively.",
        "Prevent cavitation of the oil system feed-lines.",
        "Compensate for thermal expansion of the lubricating fluid."
      ],
      "answer": "Ensure that the engine sump remains dry."
    },
    {
      "question": "A minimum ground speed for thrust reverse operation is usually specified:",
      "choices": [
        "To reduce damage to the runway surface.",
        "To avoid reingestion of hot gases.",
        "To reduce excessive noise in the airport environs.",
        "To maximise wheel braking efficiency."
      ],
      "answer": "To avoid reingestion of hot gases."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements about a reaction turbine are correct or incorrect?   I. The pressure drops across the nozzle guide vanes. Il. The pressure drops across the rotor blades.",
      "choices": [
        "I is incorrect; II is correct.",
        "I is correct; II is correct.",
        "I is correct; II is incorrect.",
        "I is incorrect; II is incorrect."
      ],
      "answer": "I is incorrect; II is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "The entire turbine is contained within a __________ air annulus.",
      "choices": [
        "divergent",
        "convergent",
        "straight",
        "cylindrical"
      ],
      "answer": "divergent"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bypass engines are efficient because the air passing through bypass does not have to be __________.",
      "choices": [
        "heated",
        "accelerated",
        "compressed",
        "cooled"
      ],
      "answer": "heated"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thrust = mass x velocity. The 'velocity' in this equation is the difference in the speed of the exhaust gas flow and the speed of the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "jet inflow",
        "aircraft",
        "engine",
        "atmosphere"
      ],
      "answer": "aircraft"
    },
    {
      "question": "How do the gas parameters change within the stator of a compressor stage? The temperature increases, the:",
      "choices": [
        "Pressure increases and the speed increases.",
        "Pressure decreases and the speed increases.",
        "Pressure decreases and the speed decreases.",
        "Pressure increases and the speed decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "Pressure increases and the speed decreases."
    },
    {
      "question": "The bypass ratio is the ratio of bypass air mass flow to core __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "mass flow",
        "velocity",
        "temperature",
        "pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "mass flow"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the principle advantage of using propeller reduction gears?",
      "choices": [
        "To enable the engine RPM to be increased with an accompanying increase in propeller RPM.",
        "To enable the engine RPM to be increased with an accompanying increase in power and allow the propeller to remain at a lower, more efficient RPM.",
        "The diameter and blade area of the propeller can be increased.",
        "To enable the propeller RPM to be increased without accompanying increase in engine RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "To enable the engine RPM to be increased with an accompanying increase in power and allow the propeller to remain at a lower, more efficient RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ air is used for cooling.",
      "choices": [
        "Secondary",
        "Primary",
        "Tertiary",
        "Bypass"
      ],
      "answer": "Secondary"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the venturi in a carburettor is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Create a rise in pressure at the throat before the mixture enters the induction system.",
        "Ensure complete atomisation of the fuel before entering the injection system.",
        "Create the suction necessary to cause fuel to flow through the carburettor main jets.",
        "Prevent enrichment of the mixture due to high air velocity through the carburettor."
      ],
      "answer": "Create the suction necessary to cause fuel to flow through the carburettor main jets."
    },
    {
      "question": "A turbofan engine with an inlet air mass flow of 300 kg/s and a bypass mass flow of 250 kg/s has a bypass ratio of:",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "1.2",
        "5",
        "6.1"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the combustor, the pressure of the gas __________ and the velocity of the gas __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "remains constant; increases",
        "remains constant; decreases",
        "increases; remains constant",
        "decreases; increases"
      ],
      "answer": "remains constant; increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "Across a turbine stage, the pressure __________, the temperature __________ and the velocity __________.",
      "choices": [
        "falls; rises; falls",
        "rises; falls; falls",
        "falls; rises; rises",
        "falls; falls; falls"
      ],
      "answer": "falls; falls; falls"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of these statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "On some twin-spool engines, a PMU is used because a MEC is only able to directly control N1.",
        "On some twin-spool engines, a PMU is used to refine the thrust lever demands sent to the MEC to adjust N2 to achieve the desired N1.",
        "On some twin-spool engines, a PMU is provided in case of failure of the MEC.",
        "On some twin-spool engines, a PMU is used to refine the thrust lever demands sent to the MEC to adjust N1 to achieve the desired N2."
      ],
      "answer": "On some twin-spool engines, a PMU is used to refine the thrust lever demands sent to the MEC to adjust N2 to achieve the desired N1."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of gas turbine engine trending is:",
      "choices": [
        "to obtain a timely indication when an engine requires to be shut down due to problems.",
        "to enhance maintenance planning and detect anomalies.",
        "to assess engine condition using non-destructive inspection.",
        "to collect metal particles from the oil system."
      ],
      "answer": "to enhance maintenance planning and detect anomalies."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Auxiliary Power Unit (APU) has its own AC generator which:",
      "choices": [
        "must have the same characteristics as the main AC generator so that it can be easily coupled with the latter.",
        "is driven at constant speed through a Constant Speed Drive (CSD) in the same way as the main AC generator.",
        "supplies the aircraft with three-phase 115 V, 400 Hz AC.",
        "is excited by its Generator Control Unit (GCU) as soon as the APU starts up."
      ],
      "answer": "supplies the aircraft with three-phase 115 V, 400 Hz AC."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary factor limiting the maximum thrust of a gas turbine is the turbine __________ temperature.",
      "choices": [
        "outlet",
        "inlet",
        "exhaust",
        "combustion"
      ],
      "answer": "inlet"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thrust loads created by each spool are transmitted to the airframe via __________ bearings.",
      "choices": [
        "ball",
        "roller",
        "needle",
        "plain"
      ],
      "answer": "ball"
    },
    {
      "question": "The fuel is filtered __________ the HP pump.",
      "choices": [
        "before",
        "after",
        "before and after",
        "only when hot"
      ],
      "answer": "before and after"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pre-ignition is:",
      "choices": [
        "The rapid chemical...before the spark plug has fired.",
        "Caused by hot spots...",
        "The ignition of the...fired.",
        "The detonation of the...TDC)."
      ],
      "answer": "The ignition of the mixture before the spark plug has fired."
    },
    {
      "question": "A governor is always fitted to a __________ __________ system.",
      "choices": [
        "constant speed, variable pitch",
        "constant pitch, variable speed",
        "variable pitch , variable speed",
        "constant speed, constant pitch"
      ],
      "answer": "constant speed, variable pitch"
    },
    {
      "question": "The power output of a piston engine is directly proportional to:",
      "choices": [
        "exhaust back pressure and RPM.",
        "work and velocity",
        "torque and RPM.",
        "force and distance."
      ],
      "answer": "torque and RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Each stroke requires __________ revolution(s) of the crankshaft.",
      "choices": [
        "one",
        "a half",
        "two",
        "one and a half"
      ],
      "answer": "a half"
    },
    {
      "question": "Before flight the correct operation of the CSU must be checked. This is done by operating the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "throttle lever",
        "RPM lever",
        "mixture lever",
        "CSU lever"
      ],
      "answer": "RPM lever"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a piston engine installation, the item which creates thrust is the _____.",
      "choices": [
        "propeller.",
        "engine.",
        "turbocharger",
        "gearbox"
      ],
      "answer": "propeller."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a test of the magnetos before flight you should expect __________.",
      "choices": [
        "no change in RPM",
        "a temporary rise in RPM",
        "a temporary drop in RPM",
        "a permanent drop in RPM"
      ],
      "answer": "a temporary drop in RPM"
    },
    {
      "question": "When detonation is recognised in a piston engine, the correct procedure is to:",
      "choices": [
        "reduce manifold pressure and fully enrich the mixture.",
        "reduce manifold pressure and lean the mixture.",
        "increase manifold pressure and fully enrich the mixture.",
        "increase manifold pressure and lean the mixture."
      ],
      "answer": "reduce manifold pressure and fully enrich the mixture."
    },
    {
      "question": "Diesel engines have a __________ compression ratio than petrol engines.",
      "choices": [
        "lower",
        "higher",
        "same",
        "variable"
      ],
      "answer": "higher"
    },
    {
      "question": "Power = ___/ Time.",
      "choices": [
        "Force",
        "Speed",
        "Torque",
        "Energy"
      ],
      "answer": "Energy"
    },
    {
      "question": "The mass of fuel required to produce a given amount of power for a given amount of time is a direct measure of the engine's __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "specific fuel consumption",
        "volumetric efficiency",
        "thermal efficiency",
        "power-to-weight ratio"
      ],
      "answer": "specific fuel consumption"
    },
    {
      "question": "The greatest amount of rotational drag is experienced by the propeller when the blades are set to __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "coarse",
        "fine",
        "feathered",
        "zero pitch"
      ],
      "answer": "coarse"
    },
    {
      "question": "The stoichiometric ratio is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "15 parts air to 1 part fuel",
        "15 parts fuel to 1 part air",
        "1 part air to 15 parts fuel",
        "1 part fuel to 1 part air"
      ],
      "answer": "15 parts air to 1 part fuel"
    },
    {
      "question": "Diesel engines, compared to petrol engines have:",
      "choices": [
        "a lower compression ratio.",
        "a variable compression ratio.",
        "the same compression ratio.",
        "a higher compression ratio."
      ],
      "answer": "a higher compression ratio."
    },
    {
      "question": "Aero engines are normally air cooled __________.",
      "choices": [
        "to save excessive weight",
        "to ensure even cooling over each cylinder",
        "to ensure optimum cooling",
        "to increase efficiency"
      ],
      "answer": "to save excessive weight"
    },
    {
      "question": "The pitch control unit is driven by __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "only by spring pressure",
        "only by hydraulic pressure",
        "hydraulic pressure and (sometimes) spring pressure",
        "hydraulic pressure and electrical power"
      ],
      "answer": "hydraulic pressure and (sometimes) spring pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the engine control element the pilot may expect on the flight deck of an aircraft with a piston engine controlled by FADEC?",
      "choices": [
        "Mixture lever",
        "Throttle valve control lever",
        "FADEC restart switch",
        "Crank switch"
      ],
      "answer": "Crank switch"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a steady climb at relatively low speed and high power, you are monitoring the CHT. In addition, you are regularly checking the oil indications. You should expect:",
      "choices": [
        "A steady decrease in the oil temperature as the ambient temperature reduces.",
        "The oil temperature to remain constant.",
        "A steady increase in the oil temperature.",
        "The oil temperature to rise - but only if the cowl flaps are closed."
      ],
      "answer": "A steady increase in the oil temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider a piston-engine aircraft with a constant speed propeller. Upon reaching cruising altitude when less power is required, engine power is",
      "choices": [
        "maintained but the blade angle is decreased, to decrease RPM.",
        "reduced by lowering the manifold pressure while RPM and blade angle are maintained.",
        "reduced by lowering the manifold pressure and increasing the blade angle, to decrease RPM.",
        "reduced by lowering the manifold pressure and decreasing the blade angle, to decrease RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "reduced by lowering the manifold pressure and increasing the blade angle, to decrease RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "The extremely rapid chemical decomposition of the mixture, after burning has been initiated by the spark plug, is called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "pre-ignition",
        "detonation",
        "combustion",
        "explosion"
      ],
      "answer": "detonation"
    },
    {
      "question": "An intercooler fitted between a supercharger and the inlet manifold will:",
      "choices": [
        "increase the combustion temperature.",
        "reduce the mass flow through the engine.",
        "minimise the risk of detonation.",
        "reduce pre-ignition."
      ],
      "answer": "minimise the risk of detonation."
    },
    {
      "question": "An autofeathering system is necessary on a commercial __________ __________ aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "multi-engine",
        "single-engine",
        "turbo-charged",
        "super-charged"
      ],
      "answer": "multi-engine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ignition occurs in each cylinder of a four stroke engine (TDC = Top Dead Centre):",
      "choices": [
        "before TDC at each second crankshaft revolution.",
        "before TDC at each crankshaft revolution.",
        "behind TDC at each crankshaft revolution.",
        "behind TDC at each second crankshaft revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "before TDC at each second crankshaft revolution."
    },
    {
      "question": "The multiple components which seal the piston skirt are known as __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "piston bearings",
        "skirt rings",
        "piston rings",
        "cylinder rings"
      ],
      "answer": "piston rings"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a torque force which is always acting at 90 degrees to the axis of rotation, Power (P) =",
      "choices": [
        "T x \u03c9/time",
        "T x sin F",
        "T x \u03c9",
        "T x F"
      ],
      "answer": "T x \u03c9"
    },
    {
      "question": "Altitude boosting sustains engine performance up to the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "critical altitude",
        "rated altitude",
        "maximum altitude",
        "service ceiling"
      ],
      "answer": "critical altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a piston engine, specific fuel consumption is defined as the :",
      "choices": [
        "quantity of fuel required to run the engine for one minute at maximum operating conditions.",
        "maximum fuel consumption of the aircraft.",
        "mass of fuel required to produce unit power for unit time.",
        "designed fuel consumption for a given RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "mass of fuel required to produce unit power for unit time."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is the primary reason why diesel engines do not need spark plugs.",
      "choices": [
        "Higher cylinder pressure",
        "Highly volatile diesel fuel",
        "Higher compression ratio",
        "Higher fuel pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "Higher cylinder pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "On some piston engine designs __________ is used to control the amount of cooling air flowing over the engine.",
      "choices": [
        "a cowl flap",
        "alternate air",
        "a waste gate",
        "an intercooler"
      ],
      "answer": "a cowl flap"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ratio of compressed mixture to mixture at ambient pressure is a measure of the engine's __________.",
      "choices": [
        "volumetric efficiency",
        "thermal efficiency",
        "compression ratio",
        "fuel efficiency"
      ],
      "answer": "volumetric efficiency"
    },
    {
      "question": "The crankshaft controls the opening and closing of the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "none of these",
        "inlet and exhaust valves",
        "exhaust valves",
        "inlet valves"
      ],
      "answer": "none of these"
    },
    {
      "question": "The combination of factors most likely to lead to engine overheating are __________.",
      "choices": [
        "high power and high airspeed",
        "high power and slow airspeed",
        "low power and low airspeed",
        "low power and high airspeed"
      ],
      "answer": "high power and slow airspeed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements is/are true?",
      "choices": [
        "A diesel engine is lighter than a petrol engine.",
        "All diesel engines are fuel injected.",
        "A diesel engine can use AVGAS...",
        "The carburettor...icing."
      ],
      "answer": "All diesel engines are fuel injected."
    },
    {
      "question": "The period of relatively little movement of the piston around TDC and BDC is known as the __________ crank angle.",
      "choices": [
        "ineffective",
        "effective",
        "dead",
        "live"
      ],
      "answer": "ineffective"
    },
    {
      "question": "A higher compression ratio __________ the thermal efficiency of an engine.",
      "choices": [
        "increases",
        "decreases",
        "has no effect on",
        "fluctuates"
      ],
      "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "Torque = r x",
      "choices": [
        "A",
        "T",
        "F",
        "E"
      ],
      "answer": "F"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary functions of the lubrication system of an air-cooled piston engine is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Operate constant speed propellers.",
        "Provide cooling and...control unit.",
        "Reduce internal friction...",
        "Reduce internal friction...warm."
      ],
      "answer": "Reduce internal friction and provide cooling."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ may sometimes be detected by a knocking sound coming from the engine.",
      "choices": [
        "Detonation",
        "Pre-ignition",
        "Knocking",
        "Pinking"
      ],
      "answer": "Detonation"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an internal combustion engine, the purpose of combusting fuel with air is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Add energy to the gas.",
        "Reduce noxious emissions.",
        "Cool the gas.",
        "Add energy to the fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "Add energy to the gas."
    },
    {
      "question": "The correct formula to calculate the total displacement of a multi-cylinder piston engine is the:",
      "choices": [
        "piston area x piston stroke",
        "piston area x piston stroke x number of cylinders",
        "cylinder length x cylinder diameter",
        "cylinder volume x number of cylinders"
      ],
      "answer": "piston area x piston stroke x number of cylinders"
    },
    {
      "question": "The part of a piston engine that transforms reciprocating movement into rotary motion is called the:",
      "choices": [
        "piston",
        "crankshaft",
        "camshaft",
        "reduction gear"
      ],
      "answer": "crankshaft"
    },
    {
      "question": "During engine start, the spark plugs are electrically powered by the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "magnetos",
        "generators",
        "battery",
        "alternator"
      ],
      "answer": "magnetos"
    },
    {
      "question": "The reading on the engine oil pressure gauge is the:",
      "choices": [
        "pressure in the oil tank.",
        "difference between...pump pressure.",
        "pressure of the oil...pump.",
        "pressure of the oil...pump."
      ],
      "answer": "pressure of the oil downstream of the pressure pump."
    },
    {
      "question": "When used, intercoolers are placed between the turbocharger and __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "the exhaust manifold",
        "the inlet manifold",
        "the waste gate",
        "the carburettor"
      ],
      "answer": "the inlet manifold"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________. system has: a reservoir; an oil pump and PRV; a scavenge pump and a pressure filter.",
      "choices": [
        "wet sump",
        "dry sump",
        "pressure",
        "closed"
      ],
      "answer": "dry sump"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ultimate purpose of propeller synchronising and synchrophasing systems is:",
      "choices": [
        "To reduce engine wear.",
        "To reduce metal fatigue...",
        "To reduce cabin pressure.",
        "To increase comfort..."
      ],
      "answer": "To increase comfort for passengers and crew."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a climb in a standard atmosphere with constant MAP and RPM indications and at a constant mixture setting, the power output of a piston engine:",
      "choices": [
        "Increases.",
        "Only stays constant...forward.",
        "Stays constant.",
        "Decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "Increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "100LL AVGAS is dyed __________.",
      "choices": [
        "red",
        "straw",
        "blue",
        "green"
      ],
      "answer": "blue"
    },
    {
      "question": "When you wish to increase air speed you should lead with the __________ lever and follow up with the __________ lever.",
      "choices": [
        "RPM; throttle",
        "RPM; RPM",
        "throttle; RPM",
        "throttle; throttle"
      ],
      "answer": "RPM; throttle"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ __________ prevents the blades from going to fully coarse on shut-down.",
      "choices": [
        "fine pitch stop",
        "centrifugal latch",
        "feathering lock",
        "coarse pitch stop"
      ],
      "answer": "centrifugal latch"
    },
    {
      "question": "Black exhaust smoke is a symptom of an excessively __________ mixture.",
      "choices": [
        "lean",
        "hot",
        "rich",
        "cold"
      ],
      "answer": "rich"
    },
    {
      "question": "A moment of force is more commonly known as ____.",
      "choices": [
        "torque.",
        "momentum.",
        "force.",
        "acceleration."
      ],
      "answer": "torque."
    },
    {
      "question": "A high SFC indicates __________ efficiency.",
      "choices": [
        "poor",
        "good",
        "excellent",
        "high"
      ],
      "answer": "poor"
    },
    {
      "question": "A loss of power caused by fuel starvation, resulting from vapourised fuel in the fuel lines is known as __________ lock.",
      "choices": [
        "vapour",
        "line",
        "fuel",
        "pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "vapour"
    },
    {
      "question": "The component of a piston engine which determines the valve timing is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "crankshaft",
        "camshaft",
        "connecting rod",
        "piston"
      ],
      "answer": "camshaft"
    },
    {
      "question": "inside a reciprocating engine, the connecting rods and the crankshaft convert the (1 ) .... motion of the (2) ..... into a (3) \u2026.. motion.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) linear; (2) piston; (3) rotary",
        "(1) rotary; (2) camshaft; (3) linear",
        "(1) linear; (2) camshaft; (3) rotary",
        "(1) rotary; (2) piston; (3) linear"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) linear; (2) piston; (3) rotary"
    },
    {
      "question": "When in flight, a piston engine is stopped and the propeller blade pitch angle is near 90\u00b0 , the propeller is said to be:",
      "choices": [
        "Transparent.",
        "At zero drag.",
        "Windmilling.",
        "Feathered."
      ],
      "answer": "Feathered."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a constant speed propeller unit, power is indicated by MAP and:",
      "choices": [
        "The EGT gauge",
        "The CHT gauge.",
        "The RPM gauge",
        "The boost light."
      ],
      "answer": "The RPM gauge"
    },
    {
      "question": "At 15\u00baC, AVGAS has a specific gravity (SG) of about __________.",
      "choices": [
        "0.62",
        "0.72",
        "0.85",
        "0.92"
      ],
      "answer": "0.72"
    },
    {
      "question": "As well as always avoiding overboosting, the primary means of preserving engine life is __________ throttle handling.",
      "choices": [
        "gentle",
        "firm",
        "positive",
        "assertive"
      ],
      "answer": "gentle"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a piston engine, the purpose of an altitude mixture control is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Weaken the mixture because of reduced exhaust back pressure at altitude.",
        "Prevent a weak mixture when the throttle is opened rapidly at altitude.",
        "Correct for variations in the fuel/air ratio due to decreased air density at altitude.",
        "Enrich the mixture due to decreased air density at altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Correct for variations in the fuel/air ratio due to decreased air density at altitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "High oil temperature often results in low oil pressure because of the change in the __________ of the oil.",
      "choices": [
        "chemical composition",
        "viscosity",
        "density",
        "volume"
      ],
      "answer": "viscosity"
    },
    {
      "question": "The power of a piston engine, which is measured by a friction brake, is:",
      "choices": [
        "Indicated horse power.",
        "Brake horse power.",
        "Heat loss power.",
        "Friction horse power."
      ],
      "answer": "Brake horse power."
    },
    {
      "question": "Because of the change in exhaust back-pressure, volumetric efficiency __________ in the climb.",
      "choices": [
        "decreases",
        "increases",
        "remains constant",
        "fluctuates"
      ],
      "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "The altitude at which a turbocharger can no longer sustain the required amount of boost, is known as the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "full throttle height",
        "critical altitude",
        "maximum altitude",
        "service ceiling"
      ],
      "answer": "critical altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "Diesel engines __________ require a mixture control lever in the cockpit.",
      "choices": [
        "do not",
        "do",
        "should",
        "must"
      ],
      "answer": "do not"
    },
    {
      "question": "On four-stroke piston engines, the theoretical valve and ignition settings are readjusted in order to increase the:",
      "choices": [
        "compression ratio",
        "piston displacement",
        "engine RPM",
        "overall efficiency"
      ],
      "answer": "overall efficiency"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an internal combustion engine, the piston converts _____ energy into mechanical energy.",
      "choices": [
        "pressure.",
        "kinetic",
        "heat.",
        "chemical"
      ],
      "answer": "pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "Two spark plugs per cylinder are used to improve combustion efficiency and because of the need to provide __________.",
      "choices": [
        "extra power at high altitude",
        "redundancy in case of magneto failure",
        "extra power at low altitude",
        "more reliable ignition"
      ],
      "answer": "redundancy in case of magneto failure"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the actions to un-feather a variable pitch prop:",
      "choices": [
        "Push the propeller lever forward...producing thrust.",
        "Pull the propeller backward...",
        "Push the propeller lever...no thrust.",
        "Pull the propeller lever...no thrust."
      ],
      "answer": "Push the propeller lever forward into the normal operating range which results in a blade angle producing thrust."
    },
    {
      "question": "The hydraulic pressure fed to the PCU is regulated by the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "engine",
        "CSU",
        "current blade pitch",
        "pilot"
      ],
      "answer": "CSU"
    },
    {
      "question": "On an aeroplane equipped with a manual feathering system the pilot can feather the propeller by:",
      "choices": [
        "pulling the power levers rearwards.",
        "pushing the propeller...",
        "pushing the power lever forwards.",
        "pulling the propeller control..."
      ],
      "answer": "pulling the propeller control lever rearwards."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a constant speed propeller system, a useful phrase for remembering the correct sequence for the throttle and RPM lever is:",
      "choices": [
        "Throttle up - rev back'",
        "Rev up - throttle back'",
        "Throttle back - rev up'",
        "Rev back - throttle up'"
      ],
      "answer": "Rev up - throttle back'"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a steady climb at relatively low speed and high power, you are monitoring the CHT.  In addition, you are regularly checking the oil indications. You should expect:",
      "choices": [
        "A steady decrease in the oil temperature ...ambient temperature reduces.",
        "The oil temperature to rise - but only if the cowl flaps are closed.",
        "A steady increase in the oil temperature.",
        "The oil temperature to remain constant."
      ],
      "answer": "A steady increase in the oil temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "More engine power can be absorbed when the blade pitch is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "fined",
        "coarsened",
        "reduced",
        "increased"
      ],
      "answer": "coarsened"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a petrol engine the mixture adjustment can be finessed by referring to:",
      "choices": [
        "The RPM gauge.",
        "The CHT gauge.",
        "The EGT gauge",
        "The torque gauge."
      ],
      "answer": "The EGT gauge"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 2 primary purposes of an engine oil system are lubrication and __________.",
      "choices": [
        "cleaning",
        "cooling",
        "filtering",
        "sealing"
      ],
      "answer": "cooling"
    },
    {
      "question": "When altitude increases without adjustment of the mixture ratio, the piston engine performance is affected because of:",
      "choices": [
        "An increase of air density...becomes too high.",
        "A decrease of air density...becomes too low.",
        "A decrease of air density...too high.",
        "An increase of air density...too low."
      ],
      "answer": "A decrease of air density with a fuel flow which becomes too high."
    },
    {
      "question": "Thrust = (_____ - _____)",
      "choices": [
        "Vjet; Vflight",
        "Vflight; Vjet",
        "Vjet; Vjet",
        "Vflight; Vflight"
      ],
      "answer": "Vjet; Vflight"
    },
    {
      "question": "The engine mechanically drives the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Magnetos and distributor",
        "Distributor only",
        "Magnetos only",
        "Neither magnetos nor distributor"
      ],
      "answer": "Magnetos and distributor"
    },
    {
      "question": "One advantage of operating at high altitude is the reduced __________ __________ in the exhaust.",
      "choices": [
        "back pressure",
        "emissions",
        "noise",
        "temperature"
      ],
      "answer": "back pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "To prevent vapour locking, which can lead to fuel starvation, a common type of limitation imposed by the MEL in large transport aeroplanes for complete boost pump failure is:",
      "choices": [
        "Extra reserve fuel has to be carried.",
        "No fuel may be carried...",
        "Maximum operating altitude...",
        "Minimum fuel temperature limitation."
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum operating altitude limitation."
    },
    {
      "question": "All __________ piston engines lose power during the intitial part of a climb to high altitude.",
      "choices": [
        "normally aspirated",
        "turbocharged",
        "supercharged",
        "normally-aspirated and turbocharged"
      ],
      "answer": "normally aspirated"
    },
    {
      "question": "The \"slipstream effect\" of a propeller is most prominent at:",
      "choices": [
        "low airspeeds with high power setting.",
        "low airspeeds with low...",
        "high airspeeds with high...",
        "high airspeeds with low power setting."
      ],
      "answer": "low airspeeds with high power setting."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of valve timing is to maximise the amount of _____ entering the cylinder and to _____ the amount of waste gas leaving the cylinder.",
      "choices": [
        "air; reduce",
        "charge; maximise",
        "fuel; maximise",
        "charge; reduce"
      ],
      "answer": "charge; maximise"
    },
    {
      "question": "Power is the rate of doing work. In a piston engine, power is a function of RPM x __________.",
      "choices": [
        "the mass of charge",
        "the mixture ratio",
        "the compression ratio",
        "the throttle setting"
      ],
      "answer": "the mass of charge"
    },
    {
      "question": "Force = Mass x ______?",
      "choices": [
        "Acceleration",
        "Speed",
        "Velocity",
        "Power"
      ],
      "answer": "Acceleration"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the statement correctly from the options below. The turbocharger waste gate is located in a (1) ___ and the turbine achieves the maximum RPM when the valve ls (2) ____.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) turbine engine; (2) open",
        "(1) turbine engine; (2) closed",
        "(1) piston engine; (2) closed",
        "(1) piston engine; (2) open"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) piston engine; (2) closed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Regarding the piston engine, what is the relationship between the compression ratio and the required fuel octane?",
      "choices": [
        "The higher the compression ratio, the higher the octane rating required. To prevent detonation.",
        "The lower the compression ratio, the lower the octane rating required. To prevent detonation.",
        "The higher compression ratio engines require low octane fuel to increase detonation.",
        "The octane of the fuel and compression ratio have no correlation."
      ],
      "answer": "The higher the compression ratio, the higher the octane rating required. To prevent detonation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Petrol engines produce less __________ than diesel engines.",
      "choices": [
        "carbon monoxide",
        "soot",
        "nitrogen oxides",
        "unburned hydrocarbons"
      ],
      "answer": "soot"
    },
    {
      "question": "The component of a piston engine which converts linear motion into rotary motion is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "camshaft",
        "crankshaft",
        "connecting rod",
        "piston"
      ],
      "answer": "crankshaft"
    },
    {
      "question": "FADEC __________ the number of controls in the cockpit.  It also reduces the engine-handling task.",
      "choices": [
        "increases",
        "reduces",
        "maintains",
        "has no effect on"
      ],
      "answer": "reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a constant-speed propeller unit, as airspeed increases, blade pitch __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "fines",
        "coarsens",
        "remains the same",
        "decreases"
      ],
      "answer": "coarsens"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a dry sump system the air-cooled oil cooler is located:",
      "choices": [
        "Between the scavenge pump and the reservoir.",
        "In the reservoir.",
        "In the return lines feeding the main bearings.",
        "Between the pressure pump and the engine."
      ],
      "answer": "Between the scavenge pump and the reservoir."
    },
    {
      "question": "The main reason for opening the cowl flaps is to control the:",
      "choices": [
        "oil temperature",
        "EGT (exhaust gas temperature)",
        "cabin temperature",
        "CHT (cylinder head temperature)"
      ],
      "answer": "CHT (cylinder head temperature)"
    },
    {
      "question": "The particular parts of the camshaft which lift the push rods are known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "tappets",
        "con rods",
        "cams",
        "bearings"
      ],
      "answer": "cams"
    },
    {
      "question": "Alternate air is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "filtered",
        "unfiltered",
        "heated",
        "cooled"
      ],
      "answer": "unfiltered"
    },
    {
      "question": "Carburettor icing is more likely at __________ power settings.",
      "choices": [
        "high",
        "low",
        "cruise",
        "maximum"
      ],
      "answer": "low"
    },
    {
      "question": "The mechanism in the propeller hub which drives the blade pitch to different angles is the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "CSU",
        "PCU",
        "governor",
        "pitch control"
      ],
      "answer": "PCU"
    },
    {
      "question": "An excessively lean mixture results in a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "lower EGT",
        "higher EGT",
        "lower CHT",
        "higher CHT"
      ],
      "answer": "lower EGT"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tappet clearance is provided to:",
      "choices": [
        "Allow for increased RPM.",
        "Maintain the gap between the push rod and valve rocker despite thermal expansion of the valve stem.",
        "Allow the ignition to be advanced.",
        "Allow for thermal expansion between the camshaft and push rod."
      ],
      "answer": "Maintain the gap between the push rod and valve rocker despite thermal expansion of the valve stem."
    },
    {
      "question": "The component which warms the interior of cylinder before engine start is the __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "spark plug",
        "glow plug",
        "injector",
        "carburettor"
      ],
      "answer": "glow plug"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a constant speed propeller installation, if the throttle is advanced but the RPM lever is not moved, the torque will __________ provided that adequate power is available. If adequate power is not available, the RPM may __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "decrease; decrease",
        "increase; increase",
        "increase; decrease",
        "decrease; increase"
      ],
      "answer": "increase; decrease"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a petrol engine, the lean mixture required in the cruise is set using:",
      "choices": [
        "The RPM lever.",
        "The throttle lever.",
        "The EGT gauge.",
        "The mixture control lever."
      ],
      "answer": "The mixture control lever."
    },
    {
      "question": "The power of a normally aspirated piston engine decreases during a climb with a constant power lever setting because of the:",
      "choices": [
        "Decreasing outside air temperature.",
        "Decreasing air density.",
        "Increasing engine temperature.",
        "Increasing air density."
      ],
      "answer": "Decreasing air density."
    },
    {
      "question": "Excessive engine cooling in the descent can cause damage to the engine due to __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "high friction caused by high viscosity oil",
        "thermal shock",
        "low oil pressure",
        "increased engine speed"
      ],
      "answer": "thermal shock"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an internal combustion engine, fuel is added because it is a source of:",
      "choices": [
        "Chemical energy.",
        "Mechanical energy",
        "Potential energy.",
        "Kinetic energy."
      ],
      "answer": "Chemical energy."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a fixed pitch propeller system, power is approximately indicated by the:",
      "choices": [
        "The torque gauge.",
        "The boost warning light.",
        "The CHT gauge.",
        "The RPM gauge."
      ],
      "answer": "The RPM gauge."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is added to AVGAS to control detonation.",
      "choices": [
        "Coolant",
        "Dye",
        "Lead",
        "Water"
      ],
      "answer": "Lead"
    },
    {
      "question": "Depending on the piston engine design, __________ are used to alleviate the symptoms of carburettor icing.",
      "choices": [
        "alternate air or carburettor heating",
        "intake flaps",
        "ice diverters",
        "fuel heating"
      ],
      "answer": "alternate air or carburettor heating"
    },
    {
      "question": "Carburetted engines __________ be fitted with FADEC.",
      "choices": [
        "can",
        "can not",
        "may",
        "should"
      ],
      "answer": "can not"
    },
    {
      "question": "The propeller is attached to, and driven by, the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "camshaft",
        "crankshaft",
        "connecting rod",
        "piston"
      ],
      "answer": "crankshaft"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a constant-speed propeller unit, a dangerously excessive power demand may be indicated by the:",
      "choices": [
        "The RPM gauge.",
        "The boost warning light.",
        "The EGT gauge.",
        "The oil temperature gauge."
      ],
      "answer": "The boost warning light."
    },
    {
      "question": "At low power settings the butterfly valve is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "almost closed",
        "fully open",
        "partially open",
        "fully closed"
      ],
      "answer": "almost closed"
    },
    {
      "question": "A turbocharger is:",
      "choices": [
        "Powered by an electric motor on some types.",
        "Powered by the exhaust gases.",
        "Powered by the crankshaft.",
        "A method of compressing the fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "Powered by the exhaust gases."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary disadvantage of water cooling is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "the relative inefficiency of liquid cooling",
        "the weight of the coolant",
        "the cost",
        "the complexity of the system"
      ],
      "answer": "the weight of the coolant"
    },
    {
      "question": "For piston engines fuel/air ratio or mixture is the ratio between the:",
      "choices": [
        "Mass of fuel and volume of air entering the carburettor.",
        "Volume of fuel and volume of air...",
        "Mass of fuel and mass...",
        "Volume of fuel and volume of air...carburettor."
      ],
      "answer": "Mass of fuel and mass of air entering the cylinder."
    },
    {
      "question": "In order to get the optimum efficiency of a piston engine, the positions of the intake and exhaust valve just after the power stroke are:",
      "choices": [
        "both valves closed.",
        "both valves open.",
        "exhaust...intake valve open.",
        "intake valve closed and exhaust valve open."
      ],
      "answer": "intake valve closed and exhaust valve open."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary purpose of an adjustable blade pitch system is:",
      "choices": [
        "To allow the engine to absorb more power.",
        "To accommodate FADEC.",
        "To allow the propeller to absorb more power.",
        "To reduce noise levels in the cabin."
      ],
      "answer": "To allow the propeller to absorb more power."
    },
    {
      "question": "The crank assembly of a piston engine comprises the:",
      "choices": [
        "propeller, crankshaft, pistons and connecting rods.",
        "crankshaft, camshaft,...push rods.",
        "crankshaft, connecting...",
        "crankcase, crankshaft, connecting rods and pistons."
      ],
      "answer": "crankshaft, connecting rods and pistons."
    },
    {
      "question": "The process by which the opening of inlet and exhaust valves is carefully sequenced is known as __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "valve lead",
        "valve timing",
        "ignition timing",
        "valve overlap"
      ],
      "answer": "valve timing"
    },
    {
      "question": "The component which converts the continuous supply of AC current into a series of pulses is called the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "distributor",
        "camshaft",
        "magneto",
        "rectifier"
      ],
      "answer": "distributor"
    },
    {
      "question": "The higher compression ratio of a diesel engine means that the engine block has __________ weight than a similar powered petrol engine and usually needs to be water cooled.",
      "choices": [
        "more",
        "less",
        "the same",
        "similar"
      ],
      "answer": "more"
    },
    {
      "question": "When the pilot moves the mixture lever of a piston engine towards a lean position the:",
      "choices": [
        "Volume of air entering the carburettor is increased.",
        "Volume of air entering the carburettor is reduced.",
        "Amount of fuel entering the cylinders is increased.",
        "Amount of fuel entering the cylinders is reduced."
      ],
      "answer": "Amount of fuel entering the cylinders is reduced."
    },
    {
      "question": "To avoid the extremely dangerous situation of reverse thrust being selected in the air:",
      "choices": [
        "A coarse pitch stop is activated by a weight-on-wheels switch.",
        "A coarse pitch stop is fitted to the RPM lever.",
        "A coarse pitch stop is fitted to the power lever.",
        "A fine pitch stop is activated by a weight-on-wheels switch."
      ],
      "answer": "A fine pitch stop is activated by a weight-on-wheels switch."
    },
    {
      "question": "Diesel engines always produce a certain amount of soot, because:",
      "choices": [
        "the fuel droplets are too small.",
        "the mixture is always too rich.",
        "the fuel droplets coming from the atomiser do not burn completely.",
        "the intake air is too cold."
      ],
      "answer": "the fuel droplets coming from the atomiser do not burn completely."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary cause of decreasing piston engine performance with altitude is the reduction in air __________.",
      "choices": [
        "density",
        "temperature",
        "pressure",
        "humidity"
      ],
      "answer": "density"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assuming the same swept volume and no turbo charger, diesel engines compared to petrol engines:",
      "choices": [
        "produce less maximum power output.",
        "produce a higher maximum power output.",
        "operate at higher exhaust gas temperatures.",
        "show a higher fuel flow at the same power output."
      ],
      "answer": "produce less maximum power output."
    },
    {
      "question": "A disadvantage of the wet sump system is excessive oiling at __________ RPM.",
      "choices": [
        "low",
        "high",
        "idle",
        "cruise"
      ],
      "answer": "high"
    },
    {
      "question": "The working cycle of a four-stroke engine is:",
      "choices": [
        "compression induction, power, exhaust.",
        "induction, compression, power, exhaust.",
        "induction, power, compression, exhaust.",
        "induction, compression, expansion, power."
      ],
      "answer": "induction, compression, power, exhaust."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a piston engine if the ratio of air to fuel is approximately 9:1 the mixture is:",
      "choices": [
        "Rich.",
        "Weak.",
        "Chemically correct.",
        "Too weak to support combustion."
      ],
      "answer": "Rich."
    },
    {
      "question": "Hydraulic tappets:",
      "choices": [
        "Are used to provide hydraulic power to the engine.",
        "Are used to provide hydraulic power to the valve rockers.",
        "Are used to power the camshaft hydraulically.",
        "Are used to automatically adjust the tappet clearance."
      ],
      "answer": "Are used to automatically adjust the tappet clearance."
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of an accelerator pump in the carburettor of a piston engine is to:",
      "choices": [
        "enable engine starting.",
        "enable proper functioning of a piston engine during throttle advance.",
        "enable engine idling.",
        "maintain a constant mixture in a piston engine at low and high power settings."
      ],
      "answer": "enable proper functioning of a piston engine during throttle advance."
    },
    {
      "question": "The pressure of the combusted mixture drives the __________ motion of the piston.",
      "choices": [
        "rotary",
        "linear",
        "torque",
        "reciprocating"
      ],
      "answer": "linear"
    },
    {
      "question": "Increasing the RPM is likely to increase the symptoms of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "pre-ignition",
        "detonation",
        "carburettor icing",
        "fuel starvation"
      ],
      "answer": "pre-ignition"
    },
    {
      "question": "A potential sign of impending engine problems may be indicated by a falling indication on the oil:",
      "choices": [
        "Temperature gauge.",
        "Pressure gauge.",
        "Quantity gauge.",
        "Flow gauge."
      ],
      "answer": "Pressure gauge."
    },
    {
      "question": "The working principle of the waste gate is to control the amount of boost by regulating the flow of __________ over the turbocharger's turbine.",
      "choices": [
        "charge",
        "mixture",
        "exhaust gas",
        "fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "exhaust gas"
    },
    {
      "question": "If you increase power substantially, the overboost warning light may illuminate if you don't first adjust the:",
      "choices": [
        "The mixture control lever.",
        "The throttle lever.",
        "The RPM lever.",
        "The fuel pump lever."
      ],
      "answer": "The RPM lever."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a diesel engine, combustion of the mixture is initiated by __________.",
      "choices": [
        "a glow plug",
        "the heat of compression",
        "a spark plug",
        "fuel pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "the heat of compression"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a fixed-pitch propeller system at any given altitude, increasing the RPM, __________ the engine's power output.",
      "choices": [
        "decreases",
        "increases",
        "does not affect",
        "stabilizes"
      ],
      "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a propeller-driven aircraft, the force which propels the aircraft through the air is called _____.",
      "choices": [
        "Thrust.",
        "Torque.",
        "Drag.",
        "Lift."
      ],
      "answer": "Thrust."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the cruise, with all the parameters correctly set, if the altitude is reduced, to maintain the same mixture the fuel flow should:",
      "choices": [
        "Increase or decrease, depending on the engine type.",
        "Remain the same.",
        "Decrease.",
        "Increase."
      ],
      "answer": "Increase."
    },
    {
      "question": "Some FADEC installations may offer single-lever control of the engine. All FADEC installations dispense with the __________ lever.",
      "choices": [
        "RPM",
        "mixture",
        "throttle",
        "power"
      ],
      "answer": "mixture"
    },
    {
      "question": "The pilot sets the regulating speed for the CSU using the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "RPM lever",
        "throttle lever",
        "mixture lever",
        "propeller lever"
      ],
      "answer": "RPM lever"
    },
    {
      "question": "Excessive use of the __________ before engine start increases the risk of carburettor fire.",
      "choices": [
        "priming pump",
        "starter motor",
        "mixture control",
        "throttle lever"
      ],
      "answer": "priming pump"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the propeller is overspeeding the CSU will direct pressure to the __________ side of the PCU actuator.",
      "choices": [
        "coarse",
        "fine",
        "high",
        "low"
      ],
      "answer": "coarse"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ engine initiates combustion by the heat of compression.",
      "choices": [
        "diesel",
        "petrol",
        "gas",
        "turbine"
      ],
      "answer": "diesel"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a bootstrap cooling system, the bleed air is compressed to:",
      "choices": [
        "Ensure an adequate air flow across the secondary heat exchanger.",
        "Maintain a constant cabin mass air flow.",
        "Ensure an adequate temperature drop in the secondary heat exchanger.",
        "Increase the cabin air supply pressure when the inlet pressure is too low."
      ],
      "answer": "Ensure an adequate temperature drop in the secondary heat exchanger."
    },
    {
      "question": "In an air cycle machine (bootstrap system), bleed air downstream of the first heat exchanger is:",
      "choices": [
        "Compressed, passed through the second heat exchanger and then passed across an expansion turbine.",
        "Compressed, then passed across an expansion turbine and finally passed across the second heat exchanger.",
        "Passed across an expansion turbine, then directly passed to the second heat exchanger.",
        "Passed across an expansion turbine, compressed and then passed through the second heat exchanger."
      ],
      "answer": "Compressed, passed through the second heat exchanger and then passed across an expansion turbine."
    },
    {
      "question": "50% of the cabin air is recycled by re-circulation fans.  The remaining air exits via the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "outflow valve",
        "pressure relief valve",
        "pack bypass valve",
        "recirculation valve"
      ],
      "answer": "outflow valve"
    },
    {
      "question": "JET-B has a __________ freezing point than JET-A1 or JET-A.",
      "choices": [
        "lower",
        "higher",
        "similar",
        "same"
      ],
      "answer": "lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following describes which flight deck oxygen selection: Oxygen is mixed with air and supplied to the pilot when he breathes in.  Progressively more oxygen is supplied as the cabin altitude increases.",
      "choices": [
        "100%.",
        "Low.",
        "Override.",
        "Normal (airmix)."
      ],
      "answer": "Normal (airmix)."
    },
    {
      "question": "In normal operation the maximum cabin altitude for transport aeroplanes is:",
      "choices": [
        "25 000 ft.",
        "10 000 ft.",
        "15 000 ft.",
        "8000 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "8000 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Spark-ignition engines will run using __________ but this type of fuel should never be used.",
      "choices": [
        "JET-A1",
        "AVGAS",
        "MOGAS",
        "JET-B"
      ],
      "answer": "MOGAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "A gaseous fire loop system is tested by:",
      "choices": [
        "Checking the continuity of the system.",
        "Checking the wiring harness for faults but not the sensor.",
        "Heating up the loop.",
        "Checking the sensor with external pressurised gas."
      ],
      "answer": "Heating up the loop."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is the differential pressure ice detector (Smiths Ice detector) activated?",
      "choices": [
        "By an increase in static pressure .",
        "By a decrease in static pressure.",
        "By an increase in dynamic pressure.",
        "By a decrease ln dynamic pressure."
      ],
      "answer": "By a decrease ln dynamic pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "The fuel cross-feed system:",
      "choices": [
        "Is only used on the ground for fuel transfer from one tank to another.",
        "Is only used to feed an engine from a tank in the opposite wing.",
        "Is only used in flight for fuel transfer from one tank to another.",
        "Allows feeding of any engine from any fuel tank."
      ],
      "answer": "Allows feeding of any engine from any fuel tank."
    },
    {
      "question": "The following sentence describes which flight deck oxygen selection: Each pilot can override the normal (airmix) option with this switch. This prevents smoke inhalation via the airmix valve.",
      "choices": [
        "Normal (airmix).",
        "100%.",
        "Low.",
        "Override."
      ],
      "answer": "100%."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the density of JET-A 1?",
      "choices": [
        "0.6 kg/l .",
        "0. 9 kg/l.",
        "0. 72 kg/l.",
        "0.8 kg/l."
      ],
      "answer": "0.8 kg/l."
    },
    {
      "question": "A gaseous fire loop system is tested by checking the:",
      "choices": [
        "Integrity of the sensing and warning circuits.",
        "Resistance of the wiring harness.",
        "Sensor with external pressurised gas.",
        "Continuity of the sensing loop."
      ],
      "answer": "Integrity of the sensing and warning circuits."
    },
    {
      "question": "AVGAS 100LL is a __________ lead fuel which is dyed __________.",
      "choices": [
        "high; green",
        "high; blue",
        "low; blue",
        "low; green"
      ],
      "answer": "low; blue"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cabin differential pressure means the pressure difference between:",
      "choices": [
        "Actual cabin pressure and selected pressure.",
        "Flight deck and passenger cabin.",
        "Cabin pressure and ambient air pressure.",
        "Cabin pressure and ambient air pressure at MSL."
      ],
      "answer": "Cabin pressure and ambient air pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a RAT?",
      "choices": [
        "A propeller which provides a pressure for the hydraulics of the aircraft.",
        "A type of airframe.",
        "A ram air test system.",
        "A type of storage used on board the aircraft for volatile memory."
      ],
      "answer": "A propeller which provides a pressure for the hydraulics of the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "An __________ ice detector compares information from a detector loop with information from a reference loop to infer airframe icing.",
      "choices": [
        "mechanical",
        "electrical",
        "electromechanical",
        "optical"
      ],
      "answer": "electrical"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the air, spoilers __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "are locked in the fully retracted position",
        "may be extended to increase drag",
        "are used as speed brakes",
        "cannot be used"
      ],
      "answer": "may be extended to increase drag"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cabin pressure is indicated on the flight deck as __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "cabin altitude",
        "cabin vertical speed",
        "pressure in millibars",
        "cabin pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "cabin altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a disadvantage of MOGAS in relation to AVGAS:",
      "choices": [
        "Higher risk of becoming wax like and clogging up fuel lines.",
        "Can ignite without a spark and cause an explosion.",
        "Higher risk of ice in carburettor.",
        "More expensive."
      ],
      "answer": "Higher risk of ice in carburettor."
    },
    {
      "question": "Fracture of a duct can cause __________.",
      "choices": [
        "an over-pressured hydraulic reservoir",
        "an explosion",
        "a hot gas leak",
        "loss of pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "a hot gas leak"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following correctly lists valid types of aircraft fuel tank:",
      "choices": [
        "Ring, drum, wing.",
        "Structural, external, flexible.",
        "Integral, expandable, bladder.",
        "Integral, drum, bladder."
      ],
      "answer": "Integral, drum, bladder."
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider a piston-engined aircraft, in which of the following cases is a separate engine-driven fuel pump always required?",
      "choices": [
        "To facilitate fuel flow when the fuel tank is located above the engine.",
        "To supply positive fuel pressure to a fuel injection system.",
        "For operating in sub-zero temperatures, to prevent fuel waxing.",
        "When there is a fuel filter located between the fuel tank and the engine."
      ],
      "answer": "To supply positive fuel pressure to a fuel injection system."
    },
    {
      "question": "The fuel __________ system allows the aircraft's fore/aft CG position to be changed by moving fuel from one or more main tanks to a trim tank.",
      "choices": [
        "cross-feed",
        "trim",
        "transfer",
        "jettison"
      ],
      "answer": "trim"
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the main functions of the fuel system.",
      "choices": [
        "Even distribution of fuel among the tanks.",
        "Provision of fuel to the engines, appropriate pressure to enable engine operation.",
        "Fuel storage and filtering.",
        "Ensuring that the central tank is emptied first."
      ],
      "answer": "Provision of fuel to the engines, appropriate pressure to enable engine operation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement about the tail ice-protection system is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "It uses heat from hydraulic fluid running through the leading-edge pipelines.",
        "The tail is protected from ice accretion by ram air.",
        "It is mandatory for aeroplanes to have a tail ice-protection system. The tail is protected from ice accretion by ram air.",
        "Some aeroplane tails have ice-protection systems."
      ],
      "answer": "Some aeroplane tails have ice-protection systems."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the pack cooling fans in the air conditioning system is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Supply the Passenger Service Unit (PSU) with fresh air.",
        "Cool the APU compartment.",
        "Supply the heat exchangers...cruise.",
        "Supply the heat exchangers...ground."
      ],
      "answer": "Supply the heat exchangers with cooling air during slow flights and ground operation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Assuming cabin differential pressure has reached the required value in normal flight conditions, if flight altitude and air-conditioning system settings are maintained the:",
      "choices": [
        "Outflow valves will move to the fully closed position.",
        "Pressurisation system ceases to function until leakage reduces the pressure.",
        "Outflow valves will move to the fully open position.",
        "Mass air flow through the cabin is constant."
      ],
      "answer": "Mass air flow through the cabin is constant."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a fire detection system __________ are provided for redundancy.",
      "choices": [
        "3-loops",
        "2-loops",
        "4-loops",
        "1 loop"
      ],
      "answer": "2-loops"
    },
    {
      "question": "The temperature of the bleed air in the duct from the engine is approximately __________ \u00baC.",
      "choices": [
        "50",
        "1000",
        "400",
        "90"
      ],
      "answer": "400"
    },
    {
      "question": "Regarding fire detection, ion detectors are used to detect:",
      "choices": [
        "Over temperature.",
        "Smoke",
        "Over temperature and fire.",
        "Fire."
      ],
      "answer": "Smoke"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fuel pressure is measured:",
      "choices": [
        "In the line between the high-pressure filter and the high-pressure pump.",
        "In the line between the booster pump and the engine.",
        "Always at the outlet of the high-pressure pump only.",
        "At the outlet from the fuel control unit."
      ],
      "answer": "In the line between the booster pump and the engine."
    },
    {
      "question": "Valid types of wing leading edge anti-icing systems include:",
      "choices": [
        "Intake air, inflatable boots, engine oil, electrically heated mats.",
        "Bleed air, fluid, electrically heated mats, inflatable boots.",
        "Inflatable boots, bleed air, intake air, electrically heated mats.",
        "Inflatable boots, bleed air, fluid, infra-red heated mats."
      ],
      "answer": "Bleed air, fluid, electrically heated mats, inflatable boots."
    },
    {
      "question": "Some aircraft are equipped with fuel tanks for trimming purpose, where are these tanks usually positioned:",
      "choices": [
        "ln the rear part of the aircraft, near the tail.",
        "Near the CG position.",
        "ln the front part of the aircraft, near the nose.",
        "At the wing tip."
      ],
      "answer": "ln the rear part of the aircraft, near the tail."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which type of electric power supplies the low pressure pumps of the fuel system on most transport jet aeroplanes?",
      "choices": [
        "115 V AC",
        "28 V AC",
        "28 V DC",
        "115 V DC"
      ],
      "answer": "115 V AC"
    },
    {
      "question": "The engine air intakes of large transport aircraft are usually protected against ice by:",
      "choices": [
        "hot engine oil.",
        "inflatable boots.",
        "pressurised fluid.",
        "hot bleed air."
      ],
      "answer": "hot bleed air."
    },
    {
      "question": "To improve visibility during heavy rain, rain repellent fluid is used in conjunction with:",
      "choices": [
        "windscreen wipers .",
        "a windscreen washer.",
        "electrical ant-icing.",
        "de-icing fluid."
      ],
      "answer": "windscreen wipers ."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ helps to even-out pressure fluctuations during take-off.",
      "choices": [
        "Ground pressurisation",
        "Bleed isolation",
        "Cabin pressure",
        "Differential pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "Ground pressurisation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of an air conditioning pack inlet flow valve (pack valve) is to:",
      "choices": [
        "regulate cabin pressure to the selected altitude.",
        "discharge cabin air to atmosphere if cabin pressure rises above the selected altitude.",
        "regulate cabin pressure at the maximum cabin pressure differential.",
        "maintain a constant and sufficient air mass flow to ventilate the cabin."
      ],
      "answer": "maintain a constant and sufficient air mass flow to ventilate the cabin."
    },
    {
      "question": "The use of a hot air wing anti-icing system:",
      "choices": [
        "Does not affect aerodynamic performance of the wing and causes a reduction in maximum thrust.",
        "Does not affect aerodynamic performance of the wing and causes no reduction in maximum thrust.",
        "Reduces aerodynamic performance of the wing and causes a reduction in maximum thrust.",
        "Reduces aerodynamic performance of the wing and causes no reduction in maximum thrust."
      ],
      "answer": "Does not affect aerodynamic performance of the wing and causes a reduction in maximum thrust."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a normal pressurised climb after take-off:",
      "choices": [
        "the cabin differential pressure is maintained constant.",
        "cabin pressure decreases more slowly than atmospheric pressure.",
        "absolute cabin pressure increases to compensate for the fall in pressure outside the aeroplane.",
        "the pressurisation system is inoperative until an altitude of 10 000 feet is reached."
      ],
      "answer": "cabin pressure decreases more slowly than atmospheric pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "Cabin air for a large aeroplane during flight:",
      "choices": [
        "Is temperature controlled.",
        "Has a constant oxygen ratio regulated to a preset value.",
        "Has an increased oxygen ratio.",
        "Has a reduced oxygen ratio."
      ],
      "answer": "Is temperature controlled."
    },
    {
      "question": "The correct order of decreasing freezing points of the three mentioned fuels is:",
      "choices": [
        "Jet B, Jet A, Jet A-1.",
        "Jet B, Jet A-1, Jet A.",
        "Jet A, Jet A-1, Jet B.",
        "Jet A-1 Jet A, Jet B."
      ],
      "answer": "Jet A, Jet A-1, Jet B."
    },
    {
      "question": "Vapour lock is:",
      "choices": [
        "A blockage in a fuel feed line caused by a fuel vapour bubble.",
        "Exhaust gas obstruction caused by an engine overheating.",
        "The effect of water vapour bubbles in the induction manifold caused by condensation.",
        "Abnormal mixture enrichment caused by excessive gasoline vaporisation in the carburettor."
      ],
      "answer": "A blockage in a fuel feed line caused by a fuel vapour bubble."
    },
    {
      "question": "When a bimetallic strip is used as a switch in a fire detection loop, a delay is incorporated after a fire alarm is triggered in order to:",
      "choices": [
        "Delay the triggering of the fire extinguishers and increase their efficiency.",
        "Wait for the triggering of the second fire detection loop in order to confirm the fire.",
        "Avoid false alarms in case of vibrations.",
        "Allow temperatures to equalise."
      ],
      "answer": "Avoid false alarms in case of vibrations."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct statement concerning chemical oxygen generators:",
      "choices": [
        "They combust 2 elements in a sealed container producing a supply of warm oxygen for a maximum of 5 minutes.",
        "They combust 2 elements in a sealed container producing a supply of warm oxygen...mask.",
        "They combust 2 elements in a sealed container producing a supply of cold oxygen...mask.",
        "They combust 2 elements in a sealed container producing a supply of warm oxygen...mask."
      ],
      "answer": "They combust 2 elements in a sealed container producing a supply of warm oxygen delivered continuously to each unsealed passenger mask."
    },
    {
      "question": "Audio and visual warnings sound if the cabin altitude exceeds __________ ft.",
      "choices": [
        "20 000",
        "10 000",
        "15000",
        "5000"
      ],
      "answer": "10 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ commercial jet transport aircraft have onboard anti-icing and/or de-icing for the fin.",
      "choices": [
        "All",
        "Not all",
        "Most",
        "Few"
      ],
      "answer": "Not all"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a fuel system, the oil to fuel heat exchanger allows:",
      "choices": [
        "Jet engine oil cooling through thermal exchange with fuel flowing from tanks.",
        "Fuel cooling so as to prevent vapour creation likely to un-prime the nozzles.",
        "Temporary (on as needed basis) fuel heating by the engine oil to prevent icing...",
        "Fuel heating as required whenever fuel filter clogging is detected."
      ],
      "answer": "Jet engine oil cooling through thermal exchange with fuel flowing from tanks."
    },
    {
      "question": "Light aircraft use intake air passing over a heat exchanger to provide __________ air to the cabin.",
      "choices": [
        "ambient",
        "warm",
        "cold",
        "pressurized"
      ],
      "answer": "warm"
    },
    {
      "question": "50% of the cabin air is recycled by re-circulation fans. The remaining air exits via the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "outflow valve",
        "pressure relief valve",
        "pack bypass valve",
        "recirculation valve"
      ],
      "answer": "outflow valve"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a jet aeroplane, fuel heaters are:",
      "choices": [
        "Installed in each tank.",
        "Installed only in the centre tank.",
        "Located on the engines.",
        "Not necessary at all."
      ],
      "answer": "Located on the engines."
    },
    {
      "question": "Smoke detector systems are installed in the",
      "choices": [
        "upper cargo compartments (class E).",
        "wheel wells.",
        "engine nacelles.",
        "fuel tanks."
      ],
      "answer": "upper cargo compartments (class E)."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a commercial jet transport aircraft, there are/is at least __________ packs.",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "4",
        "2",
        "1"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Airmix setting on a flight crew oxygen mask mixes oxygen with __________.",
      "choices": [
        "air taken directly from the air conditioning packs",
        "air from the flight deck",
        "cabin air",
        "ambient air"
      ],
      "answer": "air from the flight deck"
    },
    {
      "question": "Passenger masks can be commanded down by the crew or will drop automatically if the cabin altitude exceeds __________ ft.",
      "choices": [
        "25 000",
        "10 000",
        "15 000",
        "20 000"
      ],
      "answer": "15 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the pressure in the cabin tends to become lower than the outside ambient air pressure the:",
      "choices": [
        "negative pressure relief valve will open.",
        "negative pressure relief valve will close.",
        "outflow valve opens completely.",
        "air cycle machine will stop."
      ],
      "answer": "negative pressure relief valve will open."
    },
    {
      "question": "These characteristics describe which type of detection system. Current can only flow if smoke is available to provide the path for the current.",
      "choices": [
        "Optical fire detector.",
        "Ionising smoke detector.",
        "Ionising fire detector.",
        "Optical smoke detector."
      ],
      "answer": "Ionising smoke detector."
    },
    {
      "question": "The main task of the fuel system is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Feed engines with fuel, run ground supply units, move fuel for mass and balance purposes.",
        "Feed engines with fuel, heat up the aircraft, isolate tanks, allow fuel dumping.",
        "Feed engines with fuel, isolate tanks, allow fuel dumping, power in house electrical equipment.",
        "Feed engines with fuel,...optimization of centre of gravity."
      ],
      "answer": "Feed engines with fuel, allowing refuelling and defuelling, isolate tanks, allow fuel dumping, optimization of centre of gravity."
    },
    {
      "question": "JET-A has a freezing point of about __________\u00baC.",
      "choices": [
        "-60",
        "-40",
        "-27",
        "-47"
      ],
      "answer": "-40"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pack can be driven by an electrical compressor or by engine bleed air. The cargo compartment __________ pressurised.",
      "choices": [
        "is",
        "is never",
        "is not",
        "should be"
      ],
      "answer": "is"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight deck oxygen is usually stored as a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "gas",
        "powder",
        "liquid",
        "solid"
      ],
      "answer": "gas"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a commercial jet transport, the __________ pressure fuel pumps are located in or near the fuel tanks.",
      "choices": [
        "high",
        "low",
        "intermediate",
        "boost"
      ],
      "answer": "low"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sensors are heated to __________ ice formation on them.",
      "choices": [
        "prevent",
        "remove",
        "detect",
        "sense"
      ],
      "answer": "prevent"
    },
    {
      "question": "Diesel and turbine engines use __________.",
      "choices": [
        "AVGAS",
        "JET-A1",
        "MOGAS",
        "AVTUR"
      ],
      "answer": "JET-A1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using drip sticks, the quantity of fuel is determined by measurement of:",
      "choices": [
        "Drip sticks & data tables in the aircraft documentation.",
        "Directly from the drip sticks only.",
        "From the dripsticks and the fuel\u2019s specific gravity.",
        "Dripsticks and current OAT."
      ],
      "answer": "Drip sticks & data tables in the aircraft documentation."
    },
    {
      "question": "The term 'bootstrap', when used to identify a cabin air conditioning and pressurisation system, refers to the:",
      "choices": [
        "Cooling air across the inter-cooler heat exchanger.",
        "Source of the air supply.",
        "Cold air unit (air cycle machine) arrangement.",
        "Means by which pressurisation is controlled."
      ],
      "answer": "Cold air unit (air cycle machine) arrangement."
    },
    {
      "question": "The pneumatic system of a large commercial jet transport aircraft may be powered by __________ from the engine. It __________ electrically powered.",
      "choices": [
        "bleed air; may be",
        "bypass air; may be",
        "bleed air; is never",
        "bypass air; is never"
      ],
      "answer": "bleed air; may be"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assuming cabin pressure decreases, the cabin rate of climb indicator should indicate:",
      "choices": [
        "A rate of descent dependent upon the cabin differential pressure.",
        "Zero.",
        "A rate of climb.",
        "A rate of descent of approximately 300 feet per minutes."
      ],
      "answer": "A rate of climb."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is indicated in the cockpit of a modern airliner?",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel Specific Gravity.",
        "Fuel colour.",
        "Fuel temperature.",
        "Fuel Type"
      ],
      "answer": "Fuel temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "Cabin crew are provided with __________ for smoke protection.",
      "choices": [
        "smoke hoods",
        "oxygen masks",
        "gas masks",
        "breathing apparatus"
      ],
      "answer": "smoke hoods"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary purpose of pressure breathing is to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "provide a supply of oxygen under normal conditions",
        "provide protection against smoke inhalation",
        "ensure sufficient oxygen saturation in the blood",
        "deliver oxygen under pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "ensure sufficient oxygen saturation in the blood"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ __________ type sensor detects changes in its resonance to infer airframe icing.",
      "choices": [
        "vibrating rod",
        "aneroid capsule",
        "thermocouple",
        "pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "vibrating rod"
    },
    {
      "question": "Electrically powered ice protection devices on aircraft are used as:",
      "choices": [
        "De-icing devices for pitot-tubes, static ports and windshields.",
        "Anti-icing devices for pitot-tubes, static ports and windshields.",
        "De-icing devices for wings, wheel bays and aerials.",
        "Anti-icing devices for wings, wheel bays and aerials."
      ],
      "answer": "Anti-icing devices for pitot-tubes, static ports and windshields."
    },
    {
      "question": "The main function of an air cycle machine is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Pump the conditioned air into the cabin.",
        "Decrease the pressure of the bleed air.",
        "Remove the water from the bleed air.",
        "Cool the bleed air."
      ],
      "answer": "Cool the bleed air."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum cabin differential pressure of an aeroplane with a maximum certified altitude of 41 000 ft is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "15.5 PSI.",
        "3.5 PSI.",
        "13.5 PSI.",
        "9 PSI."
      ],
      "answer": "9 PSI."
    },
    {
      "question": "In an aircraft oxygen system __________ and ________ must not be used anywhere in or on the system.",
      "choices": [
        "water; grease",
        "water; oil",
        "oil; water",
        "oil; grease"
      ],
      "answer": "oil; grease"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bleeds must be selected __________ before starting a gas turbine engine.",
      "choices": [
        "off",
        "on",
        "auto",
        "open"
      ],
      "answer": "off"
    },
    {
      "question": "Commercial jet aircraft have a pressure refuelling system whose main purpose is to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "eliminate the risk of a fuel vapour explosion",
        "reduce the time taken to refuel",
        "increase the pressure in the fuel tanks",
        "reduce risk of fuel spillage"
      ],
      "answer": "reduce the time taken to refuel"
    },
    {
      "question": "Generally, for large aeroplanes, electrical heating for ice protection is used on:",
      "choices": [
        "Pitot tubes.",
        "Fin leading edges.",
        "Elevator leading edges.",
        "Slat leading edges."
      ],
      "answer": "Pitot tubes."
    },
    {
      "question": "Spark-ignition engines use __________.",
      "choices": [
        "MOGAS",
        "JET-A1",
        "AVGAS",
        "Diesel"
      ],
      "answer": "AVGAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rate of change of cabin pressure is indicated as cabin __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "differential change",
        "vertical speed",
        "pressure change",
        "rate change"
      ],
      "answer": "vertical speed"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the cabin altitude rises (aircraft in level flight), the differential pressure:",
      "choices": [
        "Decreases.",
        "Increases.",
        "Remains constant.",
        "May exceed the maximum...taken."
      ],
      "answer": "Decreases."
    },
    {
      "question": "Cabin crew have portable __________ sets available to them as well as their in-seat oxygen supply.",
      "choices": [
        "oxygen",
        "air",
        "breathing",
        "emergency"
      ],
      "answer": "oxygen"
    },
    {
      "question": "Maximum aircraft altitude is dictated, amongst other things, by a maximum differential pressure between the cabin and atmosphere of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "8-9 psi",
        "1-2 psi",
        "15-20 psi",
        "9-10 psi"
      ],
      "answer": "8-9 psi"
    },
    {
      "question": "The SG of AVGAS 100LL is about__________.",
      "choices": [
        "0.72",
        "0.8",
        "0.65",
        "0.92"
      ],
      "answer": "0.72"
    },
    {
      "question": "To fine tune the temperature in different parts of the cabin __________ is used.",
      "choices": [
        "cold ambient air",
        "trim air",
        "hot air",
        "bleed air"
      ],
      "answer": "trim air"
    },
    {
      "question": "Why are additives added to Jet A fuel?",
      "choices": [
        "To make the fuel more economical.",
        "To kill any bacteria.",
        "To prevent any ice forming in the fuel.",
        "To make the fuel more stable."
      ],
      "answer": "To prevent any ice forming in the fuel."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ commercial jet transport aircraft have onboard anti-icing and/or de-icing for the wing, stabiliser leading edges and engine nacelles.",
      "choices": [
        "Few",
        "Most",
        "All",
        "Some"
      ],
      "answer": "Most"
    },
    {
      "question": "The wing ice protection system currently used for most large turboprop transport aeroplanes is a:",
      "choices": [
        "Liquid de-icing system.",
        "Hot air system.",
        "Pneumatic system with inflatable boots.",
        "Electrical de-icing system."
      ],
      "answer": "Pneumatic system with inflatable boots."
    },
    {
      "question": "Light aircraft may have an electrically driven __________ type of pump to power __________ instruments.",
      "choices": [
        "vacuum; gyroscopic",
        "vacuum; pitot static",
        "compressor; gyroscopic",
        "compressor or vacuum; gyroscopic"
      ],
      "answer": "compressor or vacuum; gyroscopic"
    },
    {
      "question": "The fuel-oil heat exchanger:",
      "choices": [
        "Cools both the oil and the fuel.",
        "Cools the oil and heats the fuel.",
        "Heats the fuel only.",
        "Cools the oil only."
      ],
      "answer": "Cools the oil and heats the fuel."
    },
    {
      "question": "Oxygen masks __________ provide smoke protection.",
      "choices": [
        "do",
        "do not",
        "might",
        "can"
      ],
      "answer": "do not"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following describes which flight deck oxygen selection: Oxygen is mixed with air and supplied to the pilot when he breathes in. Progressively more oxygen is supplied as the cabin altitude increases.",
      "choices": [
        "Low.",
        "100%.",
        "Normal (airmix).",
        "Override."
      ],
      "answer": "Normal (airmix)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Power for windscreen heating ls usually:",
      "choices": [
        "28 volts DC.",
        "3 phase AC.",
        "15 volts OC .",
        "single phase AC."
      ],
      "answer": "3 phase AC."
    },
    {
      "question": "A cabin rate of descent:",
      "choices": [
        "is always the same as the aeroplanes rate of descent.",
        "results in a cabin pressure decrease.",
        "results in a cabin pressure increase.",
        "is not possible at constant aeroplane altitudes ."
      ],
      "answer": "results in a cabin pressure increase."
    },
    {
      "question": "The pressurisation outflow valve:",
      "choices": [
        "Is located in the front of the fuselage; it opens to increase cabin pressure and closes to decrease cabin pressure.",
        "Is located in the rear of the fuselage; it closes to increase cabin pressure and opens to decrease cabin pressure.",
        "Is located in the front of the fuselage; it closes to increase cabin pressure and opens to decrease cabin pressure.",
        "Is located in the rear of the fuselage; it opens to increase cabin pressure and closes to decrease cabin pressure."
      ],
      "answer": "Is located in the rear of the fuselage; it closes to increase cabin pressure and opens to decrease cabin pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "Fire detection loops are provided by fire wires around the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "fuel tanks",
        "engine",
        "cargo compartment",
        "APU"
      ],
      "answer": "engine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a large transport aeroplane the main temperature reduction of the conditioned air is achieved in:",
      "choices": [
        "The heat exchangers.",
        "An expansion turbine.",
        "A condenser.",
        "An evaporator."
      ],
      "answer": "The heat exchangers."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ can use a gravity feed system to provide fuel at pressure to the EDP.",
      "choices": [
        "All light aircraft",
        "High-wing light aircraft",
        "Low-wing light aircraft.",
        "Turboprop light aircraft"
      ],
      "answer": "High-wing light aircraft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bleed air off-take may be automatically restricted at __________ power.",
      "choices": [
        "cruise",
        "full",
        "high",
        "low"
      ],
      "answer": "high"
    },
    {
      "question": "JET-B __________ used for normal commercial air transport operations because of its __________ flashpoint.",
      "choices": [
        "can be; higher",
        "can be; lower",
        "must not; higher",
        "must not; lower"
      ],
      "answer": "must not; lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "Before entering the cabin, conditioned air passes through a __________ filter.",
      "choices": [
        "HEPA",
        "bypass",
        "LEAP",
        "carbon"
      ],
      "answer": "HEPA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cabin pressurisation is regulated by the:",
      "choices": [
        "Engines' RPM.",
        "Cabin inlet valve(s).",
        "Engines' bleed valves.",
        "Cabin outflow valve(s)."
      ],
      "answer": "Cabin outflow valve(s)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight deck windows are protected against icing with:",
      "choices": [
        "De-icing fluid applied before flight.",
        "Anti-icing fluid applied in flight.",
        "Electrical heating supplied by the DC system.",
        "Electrical heating supplied by the AC system."
      ],
      "answer": "Electrical heating supplied by the AC system."
    },
    {
      "question": "In-seat oxygen supply __________ the only supply of oxygen available to cabin crew.",
      "choices": [
        "is",
        "is not",
        "might be",
        "should be"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ are used to physically check the fuel contents in each tank.",
      "choices": [
        "Drip Sticks",
        "Fuel quantity gauges",
        "Fuel sticks",
        "Sight glasses"
      ],
      "answer": "Drip Sticks"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following sentence describes which flight deck oxygen selection:Each pilot can override the normal (airmix) option with this switch. This prevents smoke inhalation via the airmix valve.",
      "choices": [
        "Low.",
        "Override.",
        "Normal (airmix).",
        "100%."
      ],
      "answer": "100%."
    },
    {
      "question": "The correct statement about rain protection for cockpit windshields is that:",
      "choices": [
        "Rain repellent should never be sprayed onto the windshield unless the rainfall is very heavy.",
        "The electric de-icing system for cockpit windows is also suitable for rain protection.",
        "Wipers are sufficient under heavy rain conditions to provide adequate view through the cockpit windows.",
        "Rain repellent should never be sprayed onto the windshield unless the rainfall is very light."
      ],
      "answer": "Rain repellent should never be sprayed onto the windshield unless the rainfall is very heavy."
    },
    {
      "question": "A passenger mask __________ sealed against noxious fumes.",
      "choices": [
        "isn't",
        "is",
        "could be",
        "must be"
      ],
      "answer": "isn't"
    },
    {
      "question": "If a fuel sample is cloudy and clears slowly from the top it is an indication of:",
      "choices": [
        "Air in the fuel.",
        "Water in the fuel.",
        "Cold soaked fuel.",
        "Wax in the fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "Water in the fuel."
    },
    {
      "question": "AVGAS 100 is a __________ lead fuel which is dyed __________.",
      "choices": [
        "low; blue",
        "low; green",
        "high; green",
        "high; blue"
      ],
      "answer": "high; green"
    },
    {
      "question": "These characteristics describe which type of detection system: It uses a light source, detector and labyrinth. Light can only travel along the zig-zag path if smoke is present.",
      "choices": [
        "Electromechanical smoke detector.",
        "Optical fire detector.",
        "Ionising smoke or fire detector.",
        "Optical smoke detector."
      ],
      "answer": "Optical smoke detector."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the case of flight deck oxygen, __________ pressure oxygen is sent to a demand regulator which __________ the pressure of oxygen sent to the mask.",
      "choices": [
        "high; increases",
        "high; reduces",
        "low; increases",
        "low; reduces"
      ],
      "answer": "high; reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a piston engine aircraft, a filter is installed in the fuel system to:",
      "choices": [
        "Remove particles and impurities from the fuel that could damage the engine.",
        "Store a small amount of fuel under a certain pressure.",
        "Allow a person to take a sample of the fuel and to empty the fuel tank for maintenance.",
        "Extract the water from the fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "Remove particles and impurities from the fuel that could damage the engine."
    },
    {
      "question": "JET-A1 has a freezing point of about __________\u00baC.",
      "choices": [
        "-27",
        "-40",
        "-47",
        "-60"
      ],
      "answer": "-47"
    },
    {
      "question": "Unusable fuel' is found in the __________ part of the fuel tank, which is unreachable by the LP pump inlets.",
      "choices": [
        "lowest",
        "highest",
        "side",
        "central"
      ],
      "answer": "lowest"
    },
    {
      "question": "Methods which remove ice contamination from an aircraft are called:",
      "choices": [
        "Ice-stabilisation.",
        "De-icing.",
        "Ice-protection.",
        "Anti-icing."
      ],
      "answer": "De-icing."
    },
    {
      "question": "In large commercial transport aircraft, ventilation, temperature control and air for cabin pressurisation are provided by __________.",
      "choices": [
        "the APU",
        "the air conditioning packs",
        "the pneumatic system bleed ducts",
        "ram air"
      ],
      "answer": "the air conditioning packs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Main cabin temperature is:",
      "choices": [
        "Only controllable at maximum cabin differential pressure.",
        "Controlled automatically, or by flight crew selection.",
        "Controlled by individual passenger.",
        "Not controllable at the maximum cabin differential pressure."
      ],
      "answer": "Controlled automatically, or by flight crew selection."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is/are correct? I. The freezing point for Jet A is at a lower temperature than that for Jet B. II. The flash point for Jet A is at about the same temperature as that for Jet B.",
      "choices": [
        "I is correct; II is correct.",
        "I is incorrect; II is correct.",
        "I is correct; II is incorrect.",
        "I is incorrect; II is incorrect."
      ],
      "answer": "I is incorrect; II is incorrect."
    },
    {
      "question": "How does the rain repellent work on windscreens?",
      "choices": [
        "Causes the water to form beads and roll off the windscreen.",
        "Causes the water to form tiny particles.",
        "Cause the water to evaporate on impact.",
        "Causes the water to absorb in to the liquid."
      ],
      "answer": "Causes the water to form beads and roll off the windscreen."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aneroid capsule type ice detector sensor senses __________ to infer airframe icing.",
      "choices": [
        "changes in ambient pressure",
        "changes in dynamic pressure",
        "changes of pressure in the sensor",
        "changes of air temperature"
      ],
      "answer": "changes of pressure in the sensor"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight deck windows are constructed with __________ for __________.",
      "choices": [
        "a single layer; cost reduction",
        "multiple layers; visibility",
        "a single layer; aesthetics",
        "multiple layers; strength"
      ],
      "answer": "multiple layers; strength"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name of the control surface that rotates an aeroplane about its longitudinal axis?",
      "choices": [
        "The elevator.",
        "The trim tabs.",
        "The ailerons.",
        "The rudder."
      ],
      "answer": "The ailerons."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following design features contribute towards the safety of normal access doors fitted to commercial air transport aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "Tapered edges, single locking mechanism, positive cabin pressure.",
        "Tapered edges, single locking...negative",
        "Tapered edges, pins and stops,...",
        "Serrated edges, pins and stops,..."
      ],
      "answer": "Tapered edges, pins and stops, positive cabin pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "Touch down protection is a system which __________ before landing.",
      "choices": [
        "pre-charges brake pressure",
        "releases brake pressure",
        "increases brake pressure",
        "decreases brake pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "releases brake pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "The reduction in braking effectiveness towards the end of a landing run is known as __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "brake limiting",
        "brake wear",
        "brake fade",
        "brake slip"
      ],
      "answer": "brake fade"
    },
    {
      "question": "Autobrake is automatically __________ if the pilot applies brakes manually.",
      "choices": [
        "activated",
        "de-activated",
        "engaged",
        "armed"
      ],
      "answer": "de-activated"
    },
    {
      "question": "Primary controls have a trimming facility whose purpose is to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "null the loads felt by the pilot",
        "re-centre the controls",
        "balance the aircraft",
        "trim the aircraft"
      ],
      "answer": "null the loads felt by the pilot"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ maintains pressure in one part of a system, when pressure is falling elsewhere.",
      "choices": [
        "restrictor",
        "priority valve",
        "hydraulic fuse",
        "PRV"
      ],
      "answer": "priority valve"
    },
    {
      "question": "When hydraulic systems have failed when using a fully powered flight control system, movement of the normal pilot's control input will result in:",
      "choices": [
        "A lack of response.",
        "Activation of the standby hydraulic system.",
        "Jamming of the actuator.",
        "A corresponding movement of a control surface."
      ],
      "answer": "A lack of response."
    },
    {
      "question": "Pascal\u2019s Law states that:",
      "choices": [
        "Pressure exerted externally...directions throughout the fluid.",
        "Pressure exerted anywhere...vertically...",
        "Pressure increases with...fluid.",
        "Pressure exerted anywhere...directions..."
      ],
      "answer": "Pressure exerted anywhere in a confined, incompressible fluid is transmitted equally in all directions throughout the fluid."
    },
    {
      "question": "In hydraulic systems, the standard imperial unit of pressure is:",
      "choices": [
        "Ft lbs",
        "Kg per square in",
        "Lb per square in",
        "Lb per square cm"
      ],
      "answer": "Lb per square in"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum permissible mass for the aircraft plus payload but with no useable fuel is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Maximum Ramp Mass",
        "Maximum Zero Fuel Mass",
        "The Basic Empty Mass",
        "Maximum Structural Mass"
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum Zero Fuel Mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a conventional aluminium structure, the skin of a wing is mounted on __________ and longerons.",
      "choices": [
        "doublers",
        "ribs",
        "cross-beams",
        "main spars"
      ],
      "answer": "ribs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct statement below:",
      "choices": [
        "Hydraulic systems are much heavier than mechanical systems.",
        "Hydraulic systems are better than...",
        "Mechanical systems are preferable to...",
        "A large amount of energy is lost..."
      ],
      "answer": "Hydraulic systems are better than mechanical ones because they can deliver very large amounts of force with little effort."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is hard time maintenance?",
      "choices": [
        "When components are replaced after a set amount of hours or cycles of operations.",
        "When components are made to be extra durable.",
        "When components are given a hard time.",
        "When components are replaced as they are damaged."
      ],
      "answer": "When components are replaced after a set amount of hours or cycles of operations."
    },
    {
      "question": "Brake fade is caused by excessive __________.",
      "choices": [
        "tyre heating",
        "type pressure",
        "brake temperature",
        "brake pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "brake temperature"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ flight controls can be actuated by electric or hydraulic motors.",
      "choices": [
        "Secondary",
        "Primary",
        "Tertiary",
        "Backup"
      ],
      "answer": "Secondary"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about 'nose wheel first landing' is correct:",
      "choices": [
        "Although a nose wheel first landing shouldn't happen, the nose wheel strut and mounts are built to withstand the associated shocks and loads.",
        "A nose wheel landing on an aircraft with a long fuselage will not cause damage to the fuselage structure.",
        "The nose wheel strut and mounts are not built to withstand the shock of a nose wheel first landing and may either collapse or be severely damaged.",
        "Nose wheel first landing is the correct landing procedure in a severe crosswind."
      ],
      "answer": "The nose wheel strut and mounts are not built to withstand the shock of a nose wheel first landing and may either collapse or be severely damaged."
    },
    {
      "question": "In commercial aircraft, passenger loading doors are always:",
      "choices": [
        "Only at the front and rear of the fuselage.",
        "Only on the port side.",
        "On either side of the fuselage.",
        "Only on the starboard side."
      ],
      "answer": "Only on the port side."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to EASA CS the worst effect of a CATASTROPHIC FAILURE on the flight crew could be:",
      "choices": [
        "A slight increase in workload.",
        "Physical discomfort or a significant increase in workload.",
        "Fatalities or incapacitation.",
        "Physical distress or excessive workload, impairs ability to perform tasks."
      ],
      "answer": "Fatalities or incapacitation."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum permissible mass at the start of the take-off run is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Maximum Ramp Mass",
        "Maximum Structural Take-off Mass",
        "Maximum Landing Mass",
        "Maximum Taxi Mass"
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum Structural Take-off Mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ activates an interlock in the landing gear lever to prevent inadvertent raising on the ground.",
      "choices": [
        "weight-on-wheels switch",
        "undercarriage locking pin",
        "squat switch",
        "gear safety switch"
      ],
      "answer": "weight-on-wheels switch"
    },
    {
      "question": "A structural shell is called a __________ structure.",
      "choices": [
        "torsion box",
        "semi-monocoque",
        "monocoque",
        "stressed skin"
      ],
      "answer": "monocoque"
    },
    {
      "question": "A swash-plate pump, operated by a control piston is a description of which of the following:",
      "choices": [
        "A type of actuator.",
        "A type of RAT.",
        "A type of constant pressure pump.",
        "A type of spur gear pump."
      ],
      "answer": "A type of constant pressure pump."
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ vents excess pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "shut-off valve",
        "PRV or relief valve",
        "hydraulic fuse",
        "check valve"
      ],
      "answer": "PRV or relief valve"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an aircraft fuselage structure, the floor panels are supported by one or more __________.",
      "choices": [
        "stringers",
        "cross-beams",
        "longerons",
        "frames"
      ],
      "answer": "cross-beams"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bogies contain multiple wheels, each pair of wheels are mounted on an __________ attached to the bogie beam.",
      "choices": [
        "axle",
        "bogie",
        "wheel support",
        "strut"
      ],
      "answer": "axle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements about rudder pedal nose wheel steering is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Rudder pedal nose wheel steering provides the same deflection of the nose wheel as hand wheel steering (tiller) control.",
        "Rudder pedal nose wheel steering functions on the ground only.",
        "Rudder pedal nose wheel steering does not function during take-off.",
        "Rudder pedal nose wheel steering provides a larger deflection of the nose wheel than hand wheel steering (tiller)."
      ],
      "answer": "Rudder pedal nose wheel steering functions on the ground only."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ hydraulic systems use a pump to generate hydraulic pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "active",
        "passive",
        "powered",
        "pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "active"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ controls create no movement of the pilot\u2019s controls when the control surface is 'wiggled' on the pre-flight walkround.",
      "choices": [
        "Irreversible",
        "Manual",
        "Integrated",
        "Reversible"
      ],
      "answer": "Irreversible"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________-acting actuator directs hydraulic pressure to either side of the piston, to move it in two directions.",
      "choices": [
        "double",
        "reverse",
        "single",
        "hydraulic"
      ],
      "answer": "double"
    },
    {
      "question": "The parts of the structure most prone to stress are the wing __________.",
      "choices": [
        "roots",
        "tips",
        "leading edges",
        "trailing edges"
      ],
      "answer": "roots"
    },
    {
      "question": "The brake __________ is usually operated by 2 or 3 hydraulic pistons.",
      "choices": [
        "calliper",
        "shoe",
        "pad",
        "lining"
      ],
      "answer": "calliper"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ bulkheads are located at each end of the fuselage of a pressurised aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Non-structural",
        "Structural",
        "Pressure",
        "Load-bearing"
      ],
      "answer": "Pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pascal\u2019s law states:",
      "choices": [
        "Every object in a state of uniform motion will remain...unless an external force acts on it.",
        "Pressure will be sensed equally throughout the fluid.",
        "The force produced by a fluid...quantity of fluid present.",
        "The volume of an ideal gas...proportional to the absolute temperature."
      ],
      "answer": "Pressure will be sensed equally throughout the fluid."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum permissible mass before the aircraft starts to taxi is the: __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Maximum Structural Ramp Mass",
        "Maximum Zero Fuel Mass",
        "Maximum Structural Take-Off Mass",
        "Maximum Landing Mass"
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum Structural Ramp Mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a hydraulic braking system, an accumulator is pre-charged to 1200 psi. If an electrically driven hydraulic pump is started and provides a system pressure of 3000 psi, the pressure gauge, which is connected to the gas section of the accumulator, will read:",
      "choices": [
        "1800 psi.",
        "4200 psi.",
        "1200 psi.",
        "3000 psi."
      ],
      "answer": "3000 psi."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a typical commercial transport aircraft the landing gear operating system is usually:",
      "choices": [
        "Mechanically driven.",
        "Hydraulically driven.",
        "Electrically driven.",
        "Pneumatically driven."
      ],
      "answer": "Hydraulically driven."
    },
    {
      "question": "You are making external checks of your aircraft before take-off. Which of the following is acceptable:",
      "choices": [
        "Small cuts and scrapes showing on the main tread.",
        "Cuts in the tyre sidewalls but no cuts in the tyre tread.",
        "Tread wear indicator no longer visible, but the tyre is otherwise in very good condition.",
        "An over (but not under) inflated tyre."
      ],
      "answer": "Small cuts and scrapes showing on the main tread."
    },
    {
      "question": "All computer mediation absent, a simple relationship between pilot input and control surface movement and high pilot workload' best describes __________ fly-by-wire mode.",
      "choices": [
        "degraded operation",
        "direct law",
        "assisted operation",
        "alternate law"
      ],
      "answer": "direct law"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft in flight is affected by loads. These may be classified as:",
      "choices": [
        "Tensile, shear, twisting and stretching.",
        "Compressive, tensile, shear and torsional.",
        "Thrust, drag, lift and weight.",
        "Compressive, bending, shear and torsional."
      ],
      "answer": "Compressive, tensile, shear and torsional."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the function of an auto-slat system?",
      "choices": [
        "It provides improved handling qualities by retracting the slats at high angles of attack.",
        "It provides improved stall...landing.",
        "It is activated together with...slat setting.",
        "It provides for increased...icing conditions."
      ],
      "answer": "It provides improved stall characteristics at high angles of attack during take-off, approach, and landing."
    },
    {
      "question": "Reservoirs __________ pressurised.",
      "choices": [
        "cannot be",
        "are sometimes",
        "are not",
        "should be"
      ],
      "answer": "are sometimes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hydraulic fluid in the reservoir is pressurised to:",
      "choices": [
        "Prevent overheating of the pump.",
        "Prevent cavitation in the pump.",
        "Prevent vapour locking.",
        "Ensure sufficient pump output."
      ],
      "answer": "Prevent cavitation in the pump."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ hydraulic systems use human effort to generate hydraulic pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "passive",
        "active",
        "powered",
        "pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "passive"
    },
    {
      "question": "When 'RTO' is selected on the auto-brake control panel, maximum auto-braking begins __________ above a certain speed during the rejected take-off.",
      "choices": [
        "automatically",
        "after a single application of brakes",
        "after multiple brake applications",
        "manually"
      ],
      "answer": "automatically"
    },
    {
      "question": "The structural shape of the fuselage is defined by the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "frames",
        "ribs",
        "stringers",
        "skin"
      ],
      "answer": "frames"
    },
    {
      "question": "A partially powered flying control comprises:",
      "choices": [
        "An electrical linkage between the pilot's control and the servo valve controlling an actuator which moves the control surface.",
        "An hydraulic actuator attached in parallel to mechanical linkages. Movement of the pilot\u2019s controls simultaneously moves the control surface and a servo, which moves the actuator.",
        "A mechanical linkage from the pilot's controls which operates a servo valve controlling an actuator which moves the control surface.",
        "A mechanical linkage attached in series to an hydraulic actuator. Movement of the pilot\u2019s controls simultaneously moves the control surface and a servo, which moves the actuator."
      ],
      "answer": "An hydraulic actuator attached in parallel to mechanical linkages. Movement of the pilot\u2019s controls simultaneously moves the control surface and a servo, which moves the actuator."
    },
    {
      "question": "On landing, disc brakes must absorb much of the __________ energy of the aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "potential",
        "kinetic",
        "thermal",
        "braking"
      ],
      "answer": "kinetic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Wings must have sufficient bending flexibility to absorb __________ loads.",
      "choices": [
        "lateral",
        "horizontal",
        "shear",
        "vertical"
      ],
      "answer": "vertical"
    },
    {
      "question": "The pressures used in aircraft systems are between __________ and __________ psi.",
      "choices": [
        "1000; 8000",
        "2000; 5000",
        "500; 5000",
        "2000; 8000"
      ],
      "answer": "2000; 5000"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the load in the upper and lower girder of the spar of a cantilever wing during straight and level flight?",
      "choices": [
        "Tension in lower and upper girder.",
        "Torsion in the lower and upper girder.",
        "Compression in the upper girder and tension in the lower girder.",
        "Tension in the upper girder and compression in the lower girder."
      ],
      "answer": "Compression in the upper girder and tension in the lower girder."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purposes of an accumulator in a hydraulic system are to:",
      "choices": [
        "Cool the hydraulic fluid and serve as a limited alternate source of pressure.",
        "Cool the hydraulic fluid and serve as a main pressure source for normal operation.",
        "Damp pressure fluctuations and serve as a main pressure source for normal operation.",
        "Damp pressure fluctuations and serve as a limited alternate source of pressure."
      ],
      "answer": "Damp pressure fluctuations and serve as a limited alternate source of pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a large commercial jet transport aircraft spoilers on the __________ surface of the wings extend to disrupt lift immediately after touch-down.",
      "choices": [
        "upper",
        "upper and lower",
        "lower",
        "front"
      ],
      "answer": "upper"
    },
    {
      "question": "The hydraulic control panel of a large commercial jet transport allows pumps to be switched on and usually gives warnings or indications of abnormal __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "pressure and fluid quantity",
        "pressure, temperature and fluid quantity",
        "fluid quantity, pressure, ...and fuses",
        "fluid quantity"
      ],
      "answer": "pressure, temperature and fluid quantity"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a conventional aluminium fuselage structure, frames determine the shape. The skin is reinforced by: __________.",
      "choices": [
        "stiffeners, stringers and longerons",
        "composite shells",
        "aluminium plates",
        "steel"
      ],
      "answer": "stiffeners, stringers and longerons"
    },
    {
      "question": "Feel is required to discourage the pilot from excessive control inputs, primarily at __________ speed. A Q-feel system is sensitive to __________ pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "high; static",
        "low; static",
        "high; dynamic",
        "low; dynamic"
      ],
      "answer": "high; dynamic"
    },
    {
      "question": "The principle of damage tolerance in structural design of an aircraft is based on the:",
      "choices": [
        "capability to withstand a certain amount of weakening of the structure without catastrophic failure.",
        "replacement of parts after a given number of cycles or hours of use.",
        "fact that there is no need to inspect the structure.",
        "monitoring of critical parameters and the replacement of parts if a limit value is exceeded."
      ],
      "answer": "capability to withstand a certain amount of weakening of the structure without catastrophic failure."
    },
    {
      "question": "The brake wear indicator pins must be checked __________.",
      "choices": [
        "at the start of every day",
        "before every flight",
        "when braking feels reduced",
        "on a weekly basis"
      ],
      "answer": "before every flight"
    },
    {
      "question": "After using the emergency gear extension system it __________ possible to retract the gear.",
      "choices": [
        "is not",
        "is",
        "may be",
        "will be"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum permissible mass on landing, in normal circumstances is defined by the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Maximum Structural Landing Mass",
        "Maximum Zero Fuel Mass",
        "Maximum All-Up Mass",
        "Maximum Take off mass"
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum Structural Landing Mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "The capability of a braking system is primarily limited by its capacity to absorb __________.",
      "choices": [
        "heat",
        "tyre creep",
        "mechanical shear",
        "braking pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "heat"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight deck windows are __________ to increase their ability to withstand a birdstrike.",
      "choices": [
        "cooled",
        "heated",
        "polarised",
        "reinforced"
      ],
      "answer": "heated"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements about landing gear is/are correct?",
      "choices": [
        "*Nose wheel steering is the only method of steering a tricycle landing gear system.",
        "*Nose wheel steering is only possible on a tricycle gear system.",
        "*An excessively compressed oleo might indicate low oil quantity, or low nitrogen pressure, or both.",
        "The two main types of landing gear are: a tricycle with a nose wheel; tail wheel."
      ],
      "answer": "The two main types of landing gear are: a tricycle with a nose wheel; tail wheel."
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider a pre-flight inspection of the aircraft tyres. Which option describes a condition where a tyre can still be acceptable (airworthy)?",
      "choices": [
        "An improperly inflated tyre.",
        "Embedded foreign objects within the tyre tread.",
        "Circumferential cracks within the tyre's side wall.",
        "A couple of cuts within the tyre tread."
      ],
      "answer": "A couple of cuts within the tyre tread."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following best describes shimmy:",
      "choices": [
        "Shimmy primarily occurs to bogies, taking the form of violent oscillations left and right, causing shuddering and vibration.",
        "Shimmy primarily occurs to nose wheels, causing loss of braking effectiveness.",
        "Shimmy primarily occurs to nose wheels, taking the form of violent oscillations left and right, causing shuddering and vibration felt through the aircraft.",
        "none of these"
      ],
      "answer": "Shimmy primarily occurs to nose wheels, taking the form of violent oscillations left and right, causing shuddering and vibration felt through the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Why are hydraulic fluids hazardous to humans?",
      "choices": [
        "Fluid vapour can cause breathing difficulties.",
        "They react with other fluids causing extreme heat and therefore a risk of burning.",
        "They are irritating to the skin and eyes.",
        "They conduct electricity and there is a risk of shock."
      ],
      "answer": "They are irritating to the skin and eyes."
    },
    {
      "question": "Baffle plates in a reservoir __________ the returning fluid.",
      "choices": [
        "heat",
        "filter",
        "pressurise",
        "de-aerate"
      ],
      "answer": "de-aerate"
    },
    {
      "question": "The landing gear is locked up by __________.",
      "choices": [
        "interlock",
        "hydraulic up-locks",
        "over-centre locks",
        "gear pins"
      ],
      "answer": "hydraulic up-locks"
    },
    {
      "question": "Excessive movement of a tyre around its rim is known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "aquaplaning",
        "tyre creep",
        "brake creep",
        "tyre slip"
      ],
      "answer": "tyre creep"
    },
    {
      "question": "The tensile strength of composite structural compound is highest when aligning the fibres with the direction of the load",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "False",
        "Sometimes",
        "Rarely"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the creep marks indicate excessive movement, the tyre must be __________.",
      "choices": [
        "re-balanced",
        "replaced",
        "re-fitted",
        "re-inflated"
      ],
      "answer": "re-fitted"
    },
    {
      "question": "The electrically driven pump used to operate the landing gear is an example of an/a __________ system.",
      "choices": [
        "limiter",
        "bypass",
        "constant pressure",
        "on demand"
      ],
      "answer": "on demand"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a basic hydraulic system: A hydraulic pump generates pressure and a selector valve to direct pressurised fluid to either side of the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "actuator",
        "reservoir",
        "accumulator",
        "pump"
      ],
      "answer": "actuator"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which part of the fuselage carries loads imposed by pressurisation?",
      "choices": [
        "Stringers.",
        "Skin.",
        "Spars.",
        "Ribs."
      ],
      "answer": "Skin."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct:",
      "choices": [
        "Commercial aircraft require...third.",
        "Commercial aircraft require...separate.",
        "Commercial aircraft may use a PTU...",
        "Commercial aircraft require...system."
      ],
      "answer": "Commercial aircraft require, as a minimum, duplicated hydraulic systems which are completely separate."
    },
    {
      "question": "If the grooves or tread of a tyre are worn down then:",
      "choices": [
        "They can be retreaded several times.",
        "They must be replaced.",
        "They can be retreaded just once.",
        "They can continue to be used."
      ],
      "answer": "They can be retreaded several times."
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________-acting actuator directs hydraulic pressure to one side of a piston.",
      "choices": [
        "double",
        "reverse",
        "single",
        "hydraulic"
      ],
      "answer": "single"
    },
    {
      "question": "After lowering the gear using the emergency system __________ must be used as soon as possible after the aircraft has come to a halt on the ground.",
      "choices": [
        "ground safety switches",
        "ground locking pins",
        "over locking pins",
        "locking device"
      ],
      "answer": "ground locking pins"
    },
    {
      "question": "The technique of duplicating critical parts of an aircraft's structure so that if one part fails, the other can safely carry all the loads, is a design safety method known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "duplex",
        "critical path analysis",
        "redundancy",
        "safe-life"
      ],
      "answer": "redundancy"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is exceptionally powerful, so the device must be carefully managed and set precisely as calculated for take-off.",
      "choices": [
        "A trimmable horizontal stabiliser",
        "The trim tab",
        "The tailplane",
        "Stabilizer"
      ],
      "answer": "A trimmable horizontal stabiliser"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a CS 25 requirement for an unpressurised aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "A direct vision window capable of being opened in flight.",
        "Loading doors on the starboard side.",
        "Doors hinging on the horizontal side.",
        "A direct vision window...ground only."
      ],
      "answer": "A direct vision window capable of being opened in flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Stresses and strains within an airframe are present __________.",
      "choices": [
        "in flight and on the ground",
        "only in flight",
        "only on ground",
        "never"
      ],
      "answer": "in flight and on the ground"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a hydraulic system, __________ is multiplied when small pistons operate much larger ones.",
      "choices": [
        "pressure",
        "moments",
        "force",
        "energy"
      ],
      "answer": "force"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ adds grip to a tyre by expelling water, and usually has a ribbed pattern.",
      "choices": [
        "Rating",
        "Plying",
        "Fusing",
        "Tread"
      ],
      "answer": "Tread"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where there are joints in an aircraft structure, a second overlapping layer of material may be used. These are known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "doublers",
        "overbondings",
        "lappers",
        "structural support"
      ],
      "answer": "doublers"
    },
    {
      "question": "When landing on a slippery runway, the autobrake system (ABS):",
      "choices": [
        "Reduces the brake pressure to prevent a wheel skid.",
        "Deactivates as it can NOT maintain the selected deceleration.",
        "Applies full brake pressure to prevent a runway overrun.",
        "Increases the brake pressure to obtain the selected deceleration."
      ],
      "answer": "Increases the brake pressure to obtain the selected deceleration."
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of an accumulator in a hydraulic brake system is:",
      "choices": [
        "To supply a limited amount of brake energy in the event of loss of all hydraulic systems supplying the brakes.",
        "To function as a buffer to assist the hydraulic system during heavy braking.",
        "To store the hydraulic energy recovered by the anti-skid system to prevent wheel locking.",
        "To damp pressure fluctuations of the autobrake system."
      ],
      "answer": "To supply a limited amount of brake energy in the event of loss of all hydraulic systems supplying the brakes."
    },
    {
      "question": "The characteristics of hydraulic fluids are:",
      "choices": [
        "Thermal stability, high compressibility and high volatility.",
        "Thermal stability, anti-corrosive and high flash point.",
        "Thermal stability, anti-corrosive and high volatility.",
        "Anti-corrosive, high flash point and high compressibility."
      ],
      "answer": "Thermal stability, anti-corrosive and high flash point."
    },
    {
      "question": "A fully powered control:",
      "choices": [
        "Is a reversible control.",
        "Has an actuator which assists in moving the control column.",
        "Is an irreversible control.",
        "When electrically driven...surfaces."
      ],
      "answer": "Is an irreversible control."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a spur gear pump, the output pressure depends on __________.",
      "choices": [
        "gear winding",
        "RPM",
        "actuator resistance",
        "ambient temperature"
      ],
      "answer": "RPM"
    },
    {
      "question": "A tyre's __________ rating indicates the tyre\u2019s strength.",
      "choices": [
        "fuse",
        "ply",
        "tread",
        "plug"
      ],
      "answer": "ply"
    },
    {
      "question": "Secondary flight controls are often operated by a screw jack actuator which has a locking function to __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "prevent the control from being extended at high airspeeds",
        "trim the primary control surface",
        "hold the control in the desired position",
        "lock the actuator"
      ],
      "answer": "hold the control in the desired position"
    },
    {
      "question": "The landing gear is locked down by __________ down-locks and __________ locks.",
      "choices": [
        "hydraulic; interlock",
        "hydraulic; over-centre",
        "hydraulic; retractable",
        "manual; over-centre"
      ],
      "answer": "hydraulic; over-centre"
    },
    {
      "question": "If a piston in a cylinder is connected by a tube to another cylinder which also has a piston:",
      "choices": [
        "The mass of one piston is slowly translated into the movement...",
        "A venturi effect is created.",
        "Pressure on one piston is not felt...",
        "Pressure on one piston is immediately..."
      ],
      "answer": "Pressure on one piston is immediately translated into a force on the other."
    },
    {
      "question": "In large aircraft wings, the main spar usually comprises a type of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "pressure bulkhead",
        "torsion box",
        "rib or frame",
        "structural support"
      ],
      "answer": "torsion box"
    },
    {
      "question": "On landing, a sudden emergency requires you to apply maximum possible braking.  The subsequent risk is __________ caused by the transfer of energy from the braking system to the tyre. A __________ may activate to release excessive tyre pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "tyre overheat; fusible plug",
        "tyre wear; fusible plug",
        "tyre overheat; hydraulic fuse",
        "tyre wear; hydraulic fuse"
      ],
      "answer": "tyre overheat; fusible plug"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hydroplane protection systems may be applied to the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "front wheels on a bogie",
        "main and nose wheels",
        "rear wheels on a bogie",
        "all wheels"
      ],
      "answer": "rear wheels on a bogie"
    },
    {
      "question": "There are 2 types of hydraulic fluid: __________ and mineral. It is __________ to mix the 2 types.",
      "choices": [
        "synthetic; permissible",
        "organic; forbidden",
        "synthetic; forbidden",
        "organic; permissible"
      ],
      "answer": "synthetic; forbidden"
    },
    {
      "question": "A sheet of __________ can be created so that it has different strength and stiffness in different directions.",
      "choices": [
        "Composite Material",
        "Aluminium",
        "Steel",
        "Metal Alloy"
      ],
      "answer": "Composite Material"
    },
    {
      "question": "The main spar is attached to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "two or more fuselage frames",
        "a series of longerons",
        "a central wing box",
        "the leading edge"
      ],
      "answer": "a central wing box"
    },
    {
      "question": "Anti-skid can operate __________ time(s) per second and substantially reduces the landing roll in poor surface friction conditions.",
      "choices": [
        "a few",
        "many",
        "one single",
        "twice"
      ],
      "answer": "many"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hydrostatic pressure acts __________.",
      "choices": [
        "horizontally only",
        "vertically only",
        "perpendicularly only",
        "in all directions simultaneously"
      ],
      "answer": "in all directions simultaneously"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ forces are imposed by asymmetric flight.",
      "choices": [
        "Horizontal",
        "No additional",
        "Lateral",
        "Vertical"
      ],
      "answer": "Lateral"
    },
    {
      "question": "An artificial feel system:",
      "choices": [
        "is necessary in a reversible flight control actuator unit.",
        "is mounted in parallel with a spring tab.",
        "functions in series with an irreversible hydraulic actuator.",
        "functions in parallel with an irreversible hydraulic actuator."
      ],
      "answer": "functions in parallel with an irreversible hydraulic actuator."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following correctly describes the anti-skid system:",
      "choices": [
        "If a rapid acceleration or deceleration of any wheel is sensed, the anti-skid system automatically applies brake pressure to the affected wheel.",
        "The anti-skid computer uses sensors which measure main wheel rotation to detect any rapid deceleration of a wheel.",
        "The anti-skid computer uses sensors which measure main wheel rotation to detect any rapid acceleration of a wheel.",
        "The anti-skid computer uses sensors which measure main and nose wheel rotation to detect any rapid deceleration of any wheel."
      ],
      "answer": "The anti-skid computer uses sensors which measure main wheel rotation to detect any rapid deceleration of a wheel."
    },
    {
      "question": "Measures to prevent or reduce shimmy include:",
      "choices": [
        "Taxiing on one engine.",
        "Steerable main bogies.",
        "Shimmy dampers",
        "Marstrand tyres."
      ],
      "answer": "Shimmy dampers"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is required to ensure that each pilot sits at the design eye point?",
      "choices": [
        "A throttle reference position.",
        "An eye reference position.",
        "An indirect vision indicator.",
        "A direct vision window."
      ],
      "answer": "An eye reference position."
    },
    {
      "question": "Light single-engine aircraft typically use __________ disc(s) per wheel.",
      "choices": [
        "a single",
        "multiple",
        "one",
        "two"
      ],
      "answer": "a single"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ automatically supplies a service from the highest power source.",
      "choices": [
        "relief valve",
        "priority valve",
        "shuttle valve",
        "pressure valve"
      ],
      "answer": "shuttle valve"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following are specific countermeasure(s) to ensure that the floors don't buckle in the event of an in-flight failure of a cargo compartment door:",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "4",
        "2",
        "1"
      ],
      "answer": "3"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ratio of the change in size of the deformed structure to the size of the non-deformed structure is called",
      "choices": [
        "traction.",
        "stress.",
        "torsion .",
        "strain."
      ],
      "answer": "strain."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the components which give the fuselage its cross-sectional shape?",
      "choices": [
        "Bulkheads and floor beams.",
        "Frames and bulkheads.",
        "Bulkheads and longerons.",
        "Frames and stringers."
      ],
      "answer": "Frames and bulkheads."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements concerning sidesticks is most accurate",
      "choices": [
        "When simultaneous inputs...accepted by the computers",
        "When simultaneous inputs...PF's inputs..",
        "Sidestick controllers sometimes degrade...",
        "Sidestick controllers allow ... is doing"
      ],
      "answer": "Sidestick controllers sometimes degrade..."
    },
    {
      "question": "The illumination of the green landing gear light indicates that the landing gear is:",
      "choices": [
        "Not in the required position.",
        "In the required position.",
        "Locked-down.",
        "Locked-down and its door is locked."
      ],
      "answer": "Locked-down."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a hard-time maintenance programme, a component must be replaced:",
      "choices": [
        "If there is evidence of stress...",
        "If it fails a visual inspection.",
        "At a specified number of flight...",
        "After a complaint from the flight crew."
      ],
      "answer": "At a specified number of flight..."
    },
    {
      "question": "A sandwich type structure is often used in aircraft because of its:",
      "choices": [
        "high temperature resistance.",
        "low mass and low stiffness.",
        "low mass and high stiffness.",
        "ease of deformation under load."
      ],
      "answer": "low mass and high stiffness."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a large commercial aircraft, when you select landing gear UP, __________ to avoid spinning tyres rubbing against the wheel bay walls.",
      "choices": [
        "you must manually centre...",
        "a nose wheel centering system operates",
        "a tyre deflation system activates",
        "tyre speed system"
      ],
      "answer": "a nose wheel centering system operates"
    },
    {
      "question": "A fuselage shell constructed over frames and ribs is a __________ design.",
      "choices": [
        "monocoque",
        "semi-monocoque",
        "torsion box",
        "stressed skin"
      ],
      "answer": "semi-monocoque"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ automatically shuts-off a leaking part of a system.",
      "choices": [
        "PRV valve",
        "shut-off valve",
        "fuse",
        "pressure reducing valve"
      ],
      "answer": "fuse"
    },
    {
      "question": "The autobrake system is disconnected during landing:",
      "choices": [
        "After a preset elapsed time.",
        "When selecting the reverse thrust.",
        "Below a specific speed.",
        "By pilot action."
      ],
      "answer": "By pilot action."
    },
    {
      "question": "On 'more electric' aircraft, such as the Boeing 787, the brake callipers are operated __________.",
      "choices": [
        "hydraulically",
        "electrically",
        "pneumatically",
        "mechanically"
      ],
      "answer": "electrically"
    },
    {
      "question": "High pressure systems typically operate at:",
      "choices": [
        "Up to 5000 psi.",
        "Up to 10000 psi.",
        "Up to 2000 psi.",
        "Up to 1000 psi."
      ],
      "answer": "Up to 5000 psi."
    },
    {
      "question": "A secondary flight control __________ directly change the yaw, pitch or roll of the aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "does",
        "does not",
        "always",
        "never"
      ],
      "answer": "does not"
    },
    {
      "question": "In asymmetric flight there is a significant risk of overstressing the airframe with large __________ inputs.",
      "choices": [
        "rudder",
        "elevator",
        "aileron",
        "flap"
      ],
      "answer": "rudder"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hydrostatic pressure is primarily the result of:",
      "choices": [
        "The weight force...on the Earth.",
        "The temperature of the fluid.",
        "The weight force...on itself.",
        "The motion of the fluid."
      ],
      "answer": "The weight force...on itself."
    },
    {
      "question": "After losing the normal hydraulic system that powers the brakes on most large transport aeroplanes, the alternate supply is provided by:",
      "choices": [
        "Another hydraulic system.",
        "Accumulators only.",
        "Pneumatic pressure.",
        "Manual actuation of the brakes."
      ],
      "answer": "Another hydraulic system."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about composites is true?",
      "choices": [
        "Composites can suffer...metals.",
        "Different types of composite...",
        "All composites conduct...",
        "Composites can't be used to create..."
      ],
      "answer": "Different types of composite..."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a basic hydraulic system: At pressures of between 2000 and 5000 psi, hydraulic fluid is considered to be __________.",
      "choices": [
        "flammable",
        "incompressible",
        "compressible",
        "unstable"
      ],
      "answer": "incompressible"
    },
    {
      "question": "The pressure hull experiences the following 2 main types of stress:",
      "choices": [
        "Shear stress and torsion stress",
        "Axial stress and bending stress",
        "Hoop stress and shear stress",
        "Axial stress and hoop stress"
      ],
      "answer": "Axial stress and hoop stress"
    },
    {
      "question": "Unpressurised aircraft __________ plug type doors.",
      "choices": [
        "usually have",
        "don't have",
        "always have",
        "rarely have"
      ],
      "answer": "don't have"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ reduces the flow speed of an hydraulic system.",
      "choices": [
        "hydraulic fuse",
        "relief valve",
        "restrictor valve",
        "pressure relief valve"
      ],
      "answer": "restrictor valve"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a light single-engine aircraft, the secondary flight controls are __________ operated manually.",
      "choices": [
        "always",
        "never",
        "often",
        "seldom"
      ],
      "answer": "often"
    },
    {
      "question": "The device which helps to prevent excessive loads being applied to the fin at high airspeeds is called a:",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "1",
        "2",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "4"
    },
    {
      "question": "The main structural component of the wing is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "wing rib",
        "wing root",
        "main spar or torsion box",
        "wing tip"
      ],
      "answer": "main spar or torsion box"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statement(s) concerning auto-brake is/are correct:",
      "choices": [
        "The auto-brake system works even if the anti-skid system is not working.",
        "The auto-brake system is armed on touch down.",
        "The auto-brake system must be armed by the crew before landing.",
        "The auto-brake system applies a small amount of brake pressure before landing."
      ],
      "answer": "The auto-brake system must be armed by the crew before landing."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about hydraulic braking systems is/ are correct:",
      "choices": [
        "Emergency brake pressure is provided by a brake enhancer.",
        "Emergency brake pressure is provided by a brake accumulator.",
        "Emergency braking usually allows 20 applications.",
        "Emergency braking usually only allows a single application of the brakes."
      ],
      "answer": "Emergency brake pressure is provided by a brake accumulator."
    },
    {
      "question": "In between the bulkheads there may be other __________ bulkheads.",
      "choices": [
        "structural",
        "non-structural",
        "structural and non-structural",
        "load-bearing"
      ],
      "answer": "structural and non-structural"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bonding a new tread pattern onto a worn tyre is called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "treading",
        "re-treading",
        "re-rating",
        "re-fusing"
      ],
      "answer": "re-treading"
    },
    {
      "question": "The viscosity of a hydraulic fluid should be:",
      "choices": [
        "low to minimise power...",
        "high to provide good...",
        "low to provide good...",
        "high to minimise power..."
      ],
      "answer": "low to minimise power..."
    },
    {
      "question": "The doors of pressurised aircraft are usually:",
      "choices": [
        "Hydraulically or electrically...",
        "Over-centre locking.",
        "Made from composite materials.",
        "A plug type design."
      ],
      "answer": "A plug type design."
    },
    {
      "question": "A leak in the hydraulic system might be indicated by which of the following:",
      "choices": [
        "2006-01-02 00:00:00",
        "2005-01-03 00:00:00",
        "2005-02-04 00:00:00",
        "2025-02-03 00:00:00"
      ],
      "answer": "2025-02-03 00:00:00"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the manifold pressure is increased, the blade angle of a constant speed propeller:",
      "choices": [
        "Will increase.",
        "Will reduce so that the engine RPM can increase.",
        "Will increase and after a short time will reduce.",
        "Will remain the same."
      ],
      "answer": "Will increase."
    },
    {
      "question": "Black exhaust smoke is a symptom of an excessively __________ mixture.",
      "choices": [
        "lean",
        "hot",
        "rich",
        "cold"
      ],
      "answer": "rich"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of a chip detector in the oil system of an engine/gearbox is to indicate that:",
      "choices": [
        "The seals are worn.",
        "There are metal particles in the oil.",
        "The oil temperature is too high.",
        "The piston rings are worn."
      ],
      "answer": "There are metal particles in the oil."
    },
    {
      "question": "Bypass engines have an inherently __________ SFC than pure turbojets.",
      "choices": [
        "lower",
        "higher",
        "equal",
        "variable"
      ],
      "answer": "lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "The bypass air in a turbo fan engine has the effect of a lower specific fuel consumption by causing an overall:",
      "choices": [
        "increase in average exhaust gas flow velocity thus increasing engine pressure ratio.",
        "decrease in average exhaust gas flow velocity and a higher mass flow.",
        "decrease in combustion chamber temperature and higher thermal efficiency.",
        "increase in the mean jet temperature and increase in thermal efficiency."
      ],
      "answer": "decrease in average exhaust gas flow velocity and a higher mass flow."
    },
    {
      "question": "Specific fuel consumption for a turbo-prop engine can be expressed in kg per:",
      "choices": [
        "unit of shaft power.",
        "hour per unit of shaft power.",
        "hour per km.",
        "hour per nm."
      ],
      "answer": "hour per unit of shaft power."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the purpose of Cowl flaps?",
      "choices": [
        "When opened, allows air to flow across the engine improving cooling efficiency.",
        "When opened act as a drag system to slow the aircraft down.",
        "When opened, allows air to flow in the engine intake improving propulsive efficiency.",
        "When opened sends warm air down the carburettor to remove any carb icing."
      ],
      "answer": "When opened, allows air to flow across the engine improving cooling efficiency."
    },
    {
      "question": "EPR is the ratio of __________ to __________",
      "choices": [
        "inlet pressure; outlet pressure",
        "outlet pressure; inlet pressure",
        "turbine pressure; intake pressure",
        "exhaust pressure; ram pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "outlet pressure; inlet pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the alpha and beta ranges respectively the governed elements of turboprop propeller controls are as follows:",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel flow and pitch.",
        "Propeller RPM and engine RPM.",
        "Reverse thrust and blade angle.",
        "Engine RPM and fuel flow."
      ],
      "answer": "Propeller RPM and engine RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "A 'hung start' is the failure of an engine to accelerate to its normal idle speed. It may be caused by:",
      "choices": [
        "Failure of the fuel to ignite in the starting sequence after the engine has been accelerated to the required RPM by the starter.",
        "An attempt to ignite the fuel before the engine has been accelerated sufficiently by the starter.",
        "Compressor surging.",
        "The starter cutting out early in the starting sequence before the engine has accelerated to the required RPM for ignition."
      ],
      "answer": "An attempt to ignite the fuel before the engine has been accelerated sufficiently by the starter."
    },
    {
      "question": "When starting a turbine engine, the igniters were incorrectly left off and a wet start occurred. The pilot aborted the start sequence, waited a while, and then initiated the start sequence again with the igniters correctly selected on. After ignition in the second start sequence, what will happen?",
      "choices": [
        "A wet start will happen again, because excessive fuel from the previous start attempt has not been removed.",
        "The fuel deposits from the previous start attempt in the combustion chamber will burn up instantaneously, resulting in an explosing and a rapid rise of TGT.",
        "The engine will operate with significantly lower TGT value, until all the excessive fuel from the previous start attempt has been burnt.",
        "The turbine engine will continue to operatre withing normal range, since the excessive fuel is drained by drain valves in the combustion section."
      ],
      "answer": "The turbine engine will continue to operatre withing normal range, since the excessive fuel is drained by drain valves in the combustion section."
    },
    {
      "question": "When connecting two 12 volt 40 ampere-hour batteries in parallel, what will be their total voltage and capacity?",
      "choices": [
        "24 volt, 40 ampere-hours",
        "12 volt, 40 ampere-hours",
        "12 volt, 80 ampere-hours",
        "24 volt, 80 ampere-hours"
      ],
      "answer": "12 volt, 80 ampere-hours"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the possible causes of a hot start, and what are the indications of one? A hot start can be caused by...",
      "choices": [
        "an early starter cut-out, fuel mis-scheduling, or strong tailwinds. The engine may spend a considerable time at very low RPM (sub-idle) but should continue to accelerate, the turbine temperatures may appear high or exceed the limitations.",
        "a late starter cut-out, insufficient fuel supply, or strong headwinds. The engine will accelerate to flight idle RPM and the turbine temperatures may appear low.",
        "an early starter cut-out, fuel mis-scheduling, or strong tailwinds. The engine may spend a considerable time at very low RPM (sub-idle) and stops accelerating, the turbine temperatures may appear high or exceed the limitations.",
        "high outside air temperature, fuel mis-scheduling, or high starter motor RPM. The engine may spend a considerable time at very high RPM but stops accelerating, the turbine temperatures may appear high or exceed the limitations."
      ],
      "answer": "an early starter cut-out, fuel mis-scheduling, or strong tailwinds. The engine may spend a considerable time at very low RPM (sub-idle) but should continue to accelerate, the turbine temperatures may appear high or exceed the limitations."
    },
    {
      "question": "AC generators operated in parallel must have the same:",
      "choices": [
        "amperage and kVAR.",
        "frequency and amperage",
        "voltage and amperage",
        "voltage and phase."
      ],
      "answer": "voltage and phase."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a commercial jet transport aircraft, there are/is at least __________ packs.",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "4",
        "2",
        "1"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Smoke detector systems are installed in the",
      "choices": [
        "upper cargo compartments (class E).",
        "wheel wells.",
        "engine nacelles.",
        "fuel tanks."
      ],
      "answer": "upper cargo compartments (class E)."
    },
    {
      "question": "During engine start, the spark plugs are electrically powered by the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "magnetos",
        "generators",
        "battery",
        "alternator"
      ],
      "answer": "magnetos"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is correct about a gust lock system?          1. irreversible flight controls should hve a gust lock.        2. There is no need for a gust luck on reversible flight controls",
      "choices": [
        "1 correct, 2 correct",
        "1 correct, 2 incorrect",
        "1 incorrect, 2 correct",
        "1 incorrect, 2 incorrect"
      ],
      "answer": "1 incorrect, 2 incorrect"
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of the rudder limiter system is:",
      "choices": [
        "to restrict rudder delflection during flight at high IAS",
        "to reduce pilot's workload during engine failure",
        "to restrict the rudder deflection during flight at high Mach numbers",
        "to limit pedal movement in heavy turbulence"
      ],
      "answer": "to restrict rudder delflection during flight at high IAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "In asymmetric flight there is a significant risk of overstressing the airframe with large __________ inputs.",
      "choices": [
        "rudder",
        "elevator",
        "aileron",
        "flap"
      ],
      "answer": "rudder"
    },
    {
      "question": "In large commercial transport aircraft, ventilation, temperature control and air for cabin pressurisation are provided by __________.",
      "choices": [
        "the APU",
        "the air conditioning packs",
        "the pneumatic system bleed ducts",
        "ram air"
      ],
      "answer": "the air conditioning packs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where is EGT typically measured?",
      "choices": [
        "Combustion chamber.",
        "HP turbine outlet.",
        "In the jet pipe.",
        "HP compressor outlet."
      ],
      "answer": "HP turbine outlet."
    },
    {
      "question": "What information is provided by cockpit indications as regards starting and operating the APU?",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel flow.",
        "Bleed air temperature.",
        "Air inlet pressure.",
        "Fault status."
      ],
      "answer": "Fault status."
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________. system has: a reservoir; an oil pump and PRV; a scavenge pump and a pressure filter.",
      "choices": [
        "wet sump",
        "dry sump",
        "pressure",
        "closed"
      ],
      "answer": "dry sump"
    },
    {
      "question": "A disadvantage of the wet sump system is excessive oiling at __________ RPM.",
      "choices": [
        "low",
        "high",
        "idle",
        "cruise"
      ],
      "answer": "high"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a dry sump system the air-cooled oil cooler is located:",
      "choices": [
        "Between the scavenge pump and the reservoir.",
        "In the reservoir.",
        "In the return lines feeding the main bearings.",
        "Between the pressure pump and the engine."
      ],
      "answer": "Between the scavenge pump and the reservoir."
    },
    {
      "question": "The blade angle of a propeller is the angle between the:",
      "choices": [
        "Plane of rotation and the relative airflow.",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation.",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller axis of rotation.",
        "Reference chord line and the relative airflow."
      ],
      "answer": "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary reason for venting an engine oil tank is to:",
      "choices": [
        "cool the oil.",
        "prevent overflow.",
        "allow for expansion of hot oil.",
        "prevent excessive pressure in the tank."
      ],
      "answer": "prevent excessive pressure in the tank."
    },
    {
      "question": "If the ground wire between the magnetos and the ignition switch of a piston engine becomes disconnected the most noticeable result will be that...",
      "choices": [
        "the power developed by the engine will be greatly reduced.",
        "the engine cannot be started with the ignition switch in the \u201cON\u201d position.",
        "the engine cannot be shut down by turning the ignition switch to the \u201cOFF\u201d position.",
        "a still operating engine will run down."
      ],
      "answer": "the engine cannot be shut down by turning the ignition switch to the \u201cOFF\u201d position."
    },
    {
      "question": "The thermal efficiency of a piston engine is about:",
      "choices": [
        "0.3",
        "0.7",
        "0.8",
        "0.5"
      ],
      "answer": "0.3"
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of the propeller drive gearbox is to cause the propeller to rotate at an RPM:",
      "choices": [
        "The same as engine RPM.",
        "Greater than engine RPM.",
        "Which varies in its ratio with engine RPM.",
        "Less than engine RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "Less than engine RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "When measuring the two terminals of a charging 12 V lead acid battery with a voltmeter, what reading will be observed?",
      "choices": [
        "12V",
        "14V",
        "18V",
        "28V"
      ],
      "answer": "14V"
    },
    {
      "question": "The term 'bootstrap', when used to identify a cabin air conditioning and pressurisation system, refers to the:",
      "choices": [
        "Cooling air across the inter-cooler heat exchanger.",
        "Source of the air supply.",
        "Cold air unit (air cycle machine) arrangement.",
        "Means by which pressurisation is controlled."
      ],
      "answer": "Cold air unit (air cycle machine) arrangement."
    },
    {
      "question": "regarding an airconpack, what is it called when its not using any cooling fluid.",
      "choices": [
        "Airco",
        "Bootstrap system",
        "Heat exchanger",
        "Packs"
      ],
      "answer": "Bootstrap system"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a fuel system, the oil to fuel heat exchanger allows:",
      "choices": [
        "Jet engine oil cooling through thermal exchange with fuel flowing from tanks.",
        "Fuel cooling so as to prevent vapour creation likely to un-prime the nozzles.",
        "Temporary (on as needed basis) fuel heating by the engine oil to prevent icing...",
        "Fuel heating as required whenever fuel filter clogging is detected."
      ],
      "answer": "Jet engine oil cooling through thermal exchange with fuel flowing from tanks."
    },
    {
      "question": "A split busbar system can use frequency wild generators but, in practice, the output frequency is normally kept very close to __________ Hz.",
      "choices": [
        "500",
        "200",
        "100",
        "400"
      ],
      "answer": "400"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a piston engine, turbocharger boost pressure can be monitored by...",
      "choices": [
        "a cylinder head temperature gauge, a manifold pressure gauge and engine RPM readings.",
        "engine RPM readings and a manifold pressure gauge.",
        "a manifold pressure gauge only.",
        "a cylinder head temperature gauge and manifold pressure gauge."
      ],
      "answer": "a manifold pressure gauge only."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is/are correct? I. The freezing point for Jet A is at a lower temperature than that for Jet B. II. The flash point for Jet A is at about the same temperature as that for Jet B.",
      "choices": [
        "I is correct; II is correct.",
        "I is incorrect; II is correct.",
        "I is correct; II is incorrect.",
        "I is incorrect; II is incorrect."
      ],
      "answer": "I is incorrect; II is incorrect."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary functions of the lubrication system of an air-cooled piston engine is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Operate constant speed propellers.",
        "Provide cooling and...control unit.",
        "Reduce internal friction and provide cooling.",
        "Reduce internal friction...warm."
      ],
      "answer": "Reduce internal friction and provide cooling."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the venturi in a carburettor is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Create a rise in pressure at the throat before the mixture enters the induction system.",
        "Ensure complete atomisation of the fuel before entering the injection system.",
        "Create the suction necessary to cause fuel to flow through the carburettor main jets.",
        "Prevent enrichment of the mixture due to high air velocity through the carburettor."
      ],
      "answer": "Create the suction necessary to cause fuel to flow through the carburettor main jets."
    },
    {
      "question": "The correct order of decreasing freezing points of the three mentioned fuels is:",
      "choices": [
        "Jet B, Jet A, Jet A-1.",
        "Jet B, Jet A-1, Jet A.",
        "Jet A, Jet A-1, Jet B.",
        "Jet A-1 Jet A, Jet B."
      ],
      "answer": "Jet A, Jet A-1, Jet B."
    },
    {
      "question": "A pressure relief valve in an oil system that does not seat correctly could result in:",
      "choices": [
        "Low oil pressure.",
        "Low oil temperature.",
        "High oil pressure.",
        "Excessive oil consumption."
      ],
      "answer": "Low oil pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "Why is the jet engine exhaust convergent?",
      "choices": [
        "To create more noise.",
        "To reduce friction.",
        "To accelerate the exhaust air.",
        "To reduce noise."
      ],
      "answer": "To accelerate the exhaust air."
    },
    {
      "question": "The richness of a fuel/air mixture ratio is the:",
      "choices": [
        "Volume of fuel relative to the mass of the volume of air.",
        "Volume of fuel relative to the volume of air.",
        "Real mixture ratio relative to the theoretical ratio.",
        "Mass of fuel relative to the volume of air."
      ],
      "answer": "Volume of fuel relative to the volume of air."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of gas turbine engine trending is:",
      "choices": [
        "to obtain a timely indication when an engine requires to be shut down due to problems.",
        "to enhance maintenance planning and detect anomalies.",
        "to assess engine condition using non-destructive inspection.",
        "to collect metal particles from the oil system."
      ],
      "answer": "to enhance maintenance planning and detect anomalies."
    },
    {
      "question": "On an aeroplane equipped with a constant speed propeller, the RPM indicator and its associated control lever enable:",
      "choices": [
        "On a twin-engine aeroplane, automatic engine synchronisation.",
        "Display of propeller RPM and control of the propeller regulator.",
        "Selection of engine RPM.",
        "Control of power."
      ],
      "answer": "Display of propeller RPM and control of the propeller regulator."
    },
    {
      "question": "The average stage compression ratio of an axial compressor is approximately...",
      "choices": [
        "1.1 - 1.4 : 1",
        "40:1",
        "3-5:1",
        "1:14"
      ],
      "answer": "1.1 - 1.4 : 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a climb in a standard atmosphere with constant MAP and RPM indications and at a constant mixture setting, the power output of a piston engine:",
      "choices": [
        "Increases.",
        "Only stays constant...forward.",
        "Stays constant.",
        "Decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "Increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "The extremely rapid chemical decomposition of the mixture, after burning has been initiated by the spark plug, is called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "pre-ignition",
        "detonation",
        "combustion",
        "explosion"
      ],
      "answer": "detonation"
    },
    {
      "question": "When detonation is recognised in a piston engine, the correct procedure is to:",
      "choices": [
        "reduce manifold pressure and fully enrich the mixture.",
        "reduce manifold pressure and lean the mixture.",
        "increase manifold pressure and fully enrich the mixture.",
        "increase manifold pressure and lean the mixture."
      ],
      "answer": "reduce manifold pressure and fully enrich the mixture."
    },
    {
      "question": "What may happen during a continuous climb with a mixture setting fully rich?",
      "choices": [
        "The engine will operate smoother even though fuel consumption is increased.",
        "Increase of the power available.",
        "The engine will overheat.",
        "Fouling of spark plugs."
      ],
      "answer": "Fouling of spark plugs."
    },
    {
      "question": "A mixture setting richer than best power has to be used during climb segments This results in a:",
      "choices": [
        "Lower cylinder head temperature.",
        "Increase of power.",
        "Higher torque.",
        "Higher efficiency."
      ],
      "answer": "Lower cylinder head temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "As altitude increases, if the mixture is not leaned:",
      "choices": [
        "The volume of air...decreases and the amount of fuel decreases.",
        "The volume of air...fuel...",
        "The density of air...increases.",
        "The density of air entering the carburettor decreases and the amount of fuel remains constant."
      ],
      "answer": "The density of air entering the carburettor decreases and the amount of fuel remains constant."
    },
    {
      "question": "Variations in mixture ratios for carburettors are achieved by the adjustment of:",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel flow.",
        "Fuel flow, air flow and...",
        "Air flow.",
        "Fuel flow and air flow."
      ],
      "answer": "Fuel flow."
    },
    {
      "question": "An excessively lean mixture results in a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "lower EGT",
        "higher EGT",
        "lower CHT",
        "higher CHT"
      ],
      "answer": "lower EGT"
    },
    {
      "question": "When applying carburettor heating:",
      "choices": [
        "No change occurs in the mixture.",
        "RPM increases immediately.",
        "The mixture becomes richer.",
        "The mixture becomes leaner."
      ],
      "answer": "The mixture becomes richer."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the mixture ratio for a power cruise?",
      "choices": [
        "15:1",
        "12:1",
        "17:1",
        "9:1"
      ],
      "answer": "15:1"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the mixture ratio for a econ cruise?",
      "choices": [
        "15:1",
        "12:1",
        "17:1",
        "9:1"
      ],
      "answer": "17:1"
    },
    {
      "question": "What it threat of low octane fuel? (Low fuel grade)",
      "choices": [
        "Higher manifold pressure",
        "detonation",
        "a cooling effect on cylinders",
        "vapour locking"
      ],
      "answer": "detonation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Regarding the piston engine, what is the relationship between the compression ratio and the required fuel octane?",
      "choices": [
        "The higher the compression ratio, the higher the octane rating required. To prevent detonation.",
        "The lower the compression ratio, the lower the octane rating required. To prevent detonation.",
        "The higher compression ratio engines require low octane fuel to increase detonation.",
        "The octane of the fuel and compression ratio have no correlation."
      ],
      "answer": "The higher the compression ratio, the higher the octane rating required. To prevent detonation."
    },
    {
      "question": "On an aeroplane equipped with a constant speed propeller, the RPM indicator and its associated control lever enable:",
      "choices": [
        "On a twin-engine aeroplane, automatic engine synchronisation.",
        "Display of propeller RPM and control of the propeller regulator.",
        "Selection of engine RPM.",
        "Control of power."
      ],
      "answer": "Display of propeller RPM and control of the propeller regulator."
    },
    {
      "question": "A coil wrapped around a fixed ferrous core creates an electromagnetic force when the coil is energised. This closes a switch to allow high current to pass through a second circuit'. This is a description of a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "battery",
        "solenoid",
        "relay",
        "switch"
      ],
      "answer": "relay"
    },
    {
      "question": "A ferrous metal core moves when a current is caused to flow in a coil of wire wrapped around it'. This is a description of a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "solenoid",
        "relay",
        "battery",
        "generator"
      ],
      "answer": "solenoid"
    },
    {
      "question": "A sandwich type structure is often used in aircraft because of its:",
      "choices": [
        "high temperature resistance.",
        "low mass and low stiffness.",
        "low mass and high stiffness.",
        "ease of deformation under load."
      ],
      "answer": "low mass and high stiffness."
    },
    {
      "question": "Over center mechanisms in landing gear systems are generally used to;",
      "choices": [
        "Lock the landing gear in place.",
        "Keep the landing gear doors closed.",
        "Deflates the tyres automatically if the temperature rises too high.",
        "Stops landing gear swaying."
      ],
      "answer": "Lock the landing gear in place."
    },
    {
      "question": "Primary controls have a trimming facility whose purpose is to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "null the loads felt by the pilot",
        "re-centre the controls",
        "balance the aircraft",
        "trim the aircraft"
      ],
      "answer": "null the loads felt by the pilot"
    },
    {
      "question": "An AC generator driven by a constant speed drive (CSD):",
      "choices": [
        "Requires a voltage controller to maintain constant frequency.",
        "Requires a voltage controller to maintain constant voltage under load.",
        "Does not need a voltage controller since the CSD will ensure constant voltage.",
        "Does not need a voltage controller since an AC generator voltage cannot alter under load."
      ],
      "answer": "Requires a voltage controller to maintain constant voltage under load."
    },
    {
      "question": "Secondary flight controls are often operated by a screw jack actuator which has a locking function to __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "prevent the control from being extended at high airspeeds",
        "trim the primary control surface",
        "hold the control in the desired position",
        "lock the actuator"
      ],
      "answer": "hold the control in the desired position"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ flight controls can be actuated by electric or hydraulic motors.",
      "choices": [
        "Secondary",
        "Primary",
        "Tertiary",
        "Backup"
      ],
      "answer": "Secondary"
    },
    {
      "question": "Viscosity is...",
      "choices": [
        "the temperature dependence of an oil.",
        "the pressure resistance of an oil.",
        "the flow velocity inside the oil lines.",
        "the tendency of a liquid or gas to resist flow."
      ],
      "answer": "the tendency of a liquid or gas to resist flow."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purposes of an accumulator in a hydraulic system are to:",
      "choices": [
        "Cool the hydraulic fluid and serve as a limited alternate source of pressure.",
        "Cool the hydraulic fluid and serve as a main pressure source for normal operation.",
        "Damp pressure fluctuations and serve as a main pressure source for normal operation.",
        "Damp pressure fluctuations and serve as a limited alternate source of pressure."
      ],
      "answer": "Damp pressure fluctuations and serve as a limited alternate source of pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of an accumulator in a hydraulic brake system is:",
      "choices": [
        "To supply a limited amount of brake energy in the event of loss of all hydraulic systems supplying the brakes.",
        "To function as a buffer to assist the hydraulic system during heavy braking.",
        "To store the hydraulic energy recovered by the anti-skid system to prevent wheel locking.",
        "To damp pressure fluctuations of the autobrake system."
      ],
      "answer": "To supply a limited amount of brake energy in the event of loss of all hydraulic systems supplying the brakes."
    },
    {
      "question": "The engine air intakes of large transport aircraft are usually protected against ice by:",
      "choices": [
        "hot engine oil.",
        "inflatable boots.",
        "pressurised fluid.",
        "hot bleed air."
      ],
      "answer": "hot bleed air."
    },
    {
      "question": "A lithium polymer battery is most likely to be a hazard to the aircraft when:",
      "choices": [
        "The battery has an extreme internal pressure.",
        "The battery is rapidly discharged.",
        "The battery is rapidly charged.",
        "Electrolyte is dripping out of the battery."
      ],
      "answer": "The battery has an extreme internal pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "The voltage of a fully charged lead-acid battery cell is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "1.4 V.",
        "1.8 V.",
        "1.2 V.",
        "2.2 V."
      ],
      "answer": "2.2 V."
    },
    {
      "question": "The blade angle of a propeller is the angle between the:",
      "choices": [
        "Plane of rotation and the relative airflow.",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation.",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller axis of rotation.",
        "Reference chord line and the relative airflow."
      ],
      "answer": "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the venturi in a carburettor is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Create a rise in pressure at the throat before the mixture enters the induction system.",
        "Ensure complete atomisation of the fuel before entering the injection system.",
        "Create the suction necessary to cause fuel to flow through the carburettor main jets.",
        "Prevent enrichment of the mixture due to high air velocity through the carburettor."
      ],
      "answer": "Create the suction necessary to cause fuel to flow through the carburettor main jets."
    },
    {
      "question": "Cabin pressurisation is regulated by the:",
      "choices": [
        "Engines' RPM.",
        "Cabin inlet valve(s).",
        "Engines' bleed valves.",
        "Cabin outflow valve(s)."
      ],
      "answer": "Cabin outflow valve(s)."
    },
    {
      "question": "JET-B __________ used for normal commercial air transport operations because of its __________ flashpoint.",
      "choices": [
        "can be; higher",
        "can be; lower",
        "must not; higher",
        "must not; lower"
      ],
      "answer": "must not; lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where is the biggest energy loss in a turbine engine?",
      "choices": [
        "Ram air",
        "Thermal efficiency",
        "Low flashpoint fuel",
        "High flashpoint"
      ],
      "answer": "Thermal efficiency"
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of the propeller drive gearbox is to cause the propeller to rotate at an RPM:",
      "choices": [
        "The same as engine RPM.",
        "Greater than engine RPM.",
        "Which varies in its ratio with engine RPM.",
        "Less than engine RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "Less than engine RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a characteristic of oil with high viscosity?",
      "choices": [
        "Sticky",
        "Watery",
        "Thin",
        "Fast-flowing"
      ],
      "answer": "Sticky"
    },
    {
      "question": "When all other sources of AC generation have failed, emergency AC can be provided from the DC system via an __________.",
      "choices": [
        "TRUs",
        "inverter",
        "converter",
        "battery"
      ],
      "answer": "inverter"
    },
    {
      "question": "An inverter is a:",
      "choices": [
        "filter against radio interference",
        "device for reversing the polarity of the static charge",
        "static discharger",
        "device used to convert DC into AC"
      ],
      "answer": "device used to convert DC into AC"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a large commercial jet transport aircraft, DC is supplied via __________ from various AC busbars.",
      "choices": [
        "converter",
        "TRUs",
        "inverter",
        "rectifier"
      ],
      "answer": "TRUs"
    },
    {
      "question": "An excessively rich mixture in a piston engine can be detected by:",
      "choices": [
        "White smoke from the exhaust",
        "Black smoke from the exhaust",
        "High cylinder head temperature",
        "Long purple flame from the intake"
      ],
      "answer": "Black smoke from the exhaust"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of a chip detector in the oil system of an engine/gearbox is to indicate that...",
      "choices": [
        "There are metal particles in the oil",
        "The piston rings are worn",
        "The seals are worn",
        "The oil temperature is too high"
      ],
      "answer": "There are metal particles in the oil"
    },
    {
      "question": "The bypass air in a turbo fan engine has the effect of a lower specific fuel consumption by causing an overall...",
      "choices": [
        "Decrease in average exhaust gas flow velocity and a higher IR",
        "Increase in exhaust gas velocity increasing engine pressure ratio",
        "Decrease in combustion chamber temperature and higher thermal efficiency",
        "Increase in the mean jet temperature and increase in thermal efficiency"
      ],
      "answer": "Decrease in average exhaust gas flow velocity and a higher IR"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a piston engine, specific fuel consumption is defined as the...",
      "choices": [
        "Mass of fuel required to produce unit power for unit time",
        "Designed fuel consumption for a given RPM",
        "Quantity of fuel required to run the engine for one minute at maximum operating conditions",
        "Maximum fuel consumption of the aircraft"
      ],
      "answer": "Mass of fuel required to produce unit power for unit time"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the purpose of cowl flaps on an aeroplane?",
      "choices": [
        "Air flow across the engine is reduced when they are open, which decreases cooling efficiency",
        "Air flow into the engine air intake is decreased when they are open, which decreases engine performance",
        "Air flow across the engine is increased when they are open, which increases cooling efficiency",
        "Air flow into the engine air intake is increased when they are open, which increases engine performance"
      ],
      "answer": "Air flow across the engine is increased when they are open, which increases cooling efficiency"
    },
    {
      "question": "The turboprop alpha-range power lever is the range of power lever positions between...",
      "choices": [
        "Flight idle and maximum power",
        "Ground idle and flight idle",
        "Maximum reverse and ground idle",
        "Flight idle and maximum reverse"
      ],
      "answer": "Flight idle and maximum power"
    },
    {
      "question": "With regard to a piston engine, the relationship between the compression ratio and the required fuel octane rating is: the...",
      "choices": [
        "Required octane rating is independent of the compression ratio",
        "Higher compression ratio, lower octane rating required",
        "Higher compression ratio, higher octane rating required",
        "Lower compression ratio, higher octane rating required"
      ],
      "answer": "Higher compression ratio, higher octane rating required"
    },
    {
      "question": "An abortive (hung) start is the term used to describe an attempt to start in which the engine...",
      "choices": [
        "Lights up, but fails to accelerate sufficiently",
        "Fails to light up",
        "Commences initial rotation, but fails to receive any fuel",
        "Will not rotate"
      ],
      "answer": "Lights up, but fails to accelerate sufficiently"
    },
    {
      "question": "What information is provided by cockpit indications as regards starting and operating the APU?",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel flow",
        "Fault status",
        "Bleed air temperature",
        "Air inlet pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "Fault status"
    },
    {
      "question": "The blade angle of a propeller is the angle between the:",
      "choices": [
        "Reference chord line and the relative airflow",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller axis of rotation",
        "Plane of rotation and the relative airflow"
      ],
      "answer": "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary reason for venting an engine oil tank is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Cool the oil",
        "Prevent overflow",
        "Allow for expansion of hot oil",
        "Prevent excessive pressure in the tank"
      ],
      "answer": "Prevent excessive pressure in the tank"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\n1. The freezing point for Jet A is at a lower temperature than that for Jet B\n2. The flash point for Jet A is at a higher temperature than that for Jet B",
      "choices": [
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct",
        "Both 1 and 2 are correct",
        "1 is correct, 2 is incorrect",
        "Both 1 and 2 are incorrect"
      ],
      "answer": "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct"
    },
    {
      "question": "What may happen to a piston engine during a continuous climb with a mixture setting fully rich?",
      "choices": [
        "Increase of the power available",
        "Engine will operate more smoothly but fuel consumption increases",
        "The engine will overheat",
        "Fouling of spark-plugs"
      ],
      "answer": "Fouling of spark-plugs"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the venturi in a carburettor is to...",
      "choices": [
        "Ensure complete atomisation of the fuel before entering the injection system",
        "Prevent enrichment of the mixture due to high air velocity through the carburettor",
        "Create a rise in pressure at the throat before the mixture enters the induction system",
        "Create the suction necessary to cause fuel to flow through the carburettor main jets"
      ],
      "answer": "Create the suction necessary to cause fuel to flow through the carburettor main jets"
    },
    {
      "question": "For piston engines, mixture ratio is the ratio between the...",
      "choices": [
        "Mass of fuel and mass of air entering the cylinder",
        "Mass of fuel and volume of air entering the carburettor",
        "Volume of fuel and volume of air entering the carburettor",
        "Volume of fuel and volume of air entering the cylinder"
      ],
      "answer": "Mass of fuel and mass of air entering the cylinder"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a piston engine, the chemically correct fuel/air ratio is:",
      "choices": [
        "1:15",
        "1:09",
        "1:10",
        "Not given"
      ],
      "answer": "1:15"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of \u201cengine trending\u201d for a gas turbine engine is...",
      "choices": [
        "To test performance at various temperatures",
        "To test spool-up time and compare with AFM",
        "To flight test in high density altitude",
        "To measure and analyse current engine performance to predict future life"
      ],
      "answer": "To measure and analyse current engine performance to predict future life"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where is EGT typically measured?",
      "choices": [
        "In the jet pipe",
        "HP compressor outlet",
        "Combustion chamber",
        "HP turbine outlet"
      ],
      "answer": "HP turbine outlet"
    },
    {
      "question": "The blade angle of a propeller is the angle between the:",
      "choices": [
        "Reference chord line and the relative airflow",
        "Plane of rotation and the relative airflow",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller axis of rotation",
        "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation"
      ],
      "answer": "Reference chord line and the propeller plane of rotation"
    },
    {
      "question": "A \u2018hung start\u2019 is the failure of an engine to accelerate to its normal idle speed. It may be caused by:",
      "choices": [
        "Igniting fuel before engine is accelerated sufficiently",
        "Failure of fuel to ignite after sufficient RPM",
        "Starter cuts out early before required RPM",
        "Compressor surging"
      ],
      "answer": "Igniting fuel before engine is accelerated sufficiently"
    },
    {
      "question": "The fuel-oil heat exchanger of a gas turbine engine:",
      "choices": [
        "Cools both the oil and the fuel",
        "Cools the oil only",
        "Cools the oil and heats the fuel",
        "Heats the fuel only"
      ],
      "answer": "Cools the oil and heats the fuel"
    },
    {
      "question": "A tachometer measures...",
      "choices": [
        "Engine vibration",
        "Angular momentum",
        "Angular speed",
        "Engine operating hours"
      ],
      "answer": "Angular speed"
    },
    {
      "question": "On an aeroplane equipped with a constant speed propeller, the RPM indicator and its associated control lever enable:",
      "choices": [
        "Control of power",
        "Automatic engine synchronisation",
        "Display of propeller RPM and control of the propeller regulator",
        "Selection of engine RPM"
      ],
      "answer": "Display of propeller RPM and control of the propeller regulator"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements about rudder limiting are correct or incorrect?\nI. A rudder ratio changer system limits both rudder and rudder pedal deflection as the IAS increases\nII. A variable stop system reduces the rudder deflection for a given rudder pedal deflection as the IAS increases",
      "choices": [
        "I is correct, II is correct",
        "I is incorrect, II is incorrect",
        "I is correct, II is incorrect",
        "I is incorrect, II is correct"
      ],
      "answer": "I is incorrect, II is incorrect"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements about a gust lock system are correct or incorrect?\nI. A gust lock can be used in flight to reduce the effects of turbulence\nII. Reversible flight controls should have a gust lock",
      "choices": [
        "I is incorrect, II is correct",
        "I is correct, II is correct",
        "I is correct, II is incorrect",
        "I is incorrect, II is incorrect"
      ],
      "answer": "I is incorrect, II is correct"
    },
    {
      "question": "The reason for providing a gearbox in a piston engine is to...",
      "choices": [
        "Allow engine and propeller to rotate at same speed",
        "Allow high RPM for propeller",
        "Allow engine to run at efficient RPM while propeller runs at optimal RPM",
        "Reduce drag on engine"
      ],
      "answer": "Allow engine to run at efficient RPM while propeller runs at optimal RPM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which value is closest to the thermal efficiency of a piston engine?",
      "choices": [
        "0.1",
        "0.2",
        "0.3",
        "0.5"
      ],
      "answer": "0.3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Why is a convergent nozzle used in a gas turbine engine?",
      "choices": [
        "To increase exhaust gas temperature",
        "To reduce pressure",
        "To accelerate exhaust gases",
        "To cool down airflow"
      ],
      "answer": "To accelerate exhaust gases"
    },
    {
      "question": "Purpose of pressure relief valve in lubrication system?",
      "choices": [
        "Prevent low pressure",
        "Prevent high pressure",
        "Control fuel flow",
        "Vent air"
      ],
      "answer": "Prevent high pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which fuel has the lowest freezing point?",
      "choices": [
        "Jet A",
        "Jet B",
        "AVGAS",
        "Diesel"
      ],
      "answer": "Jet B"
    },
    {
      "question": "Purpose of CSD (Constant Speed Drive)?",
      "choices": [
        "Maintain constant engine speed",
        "Maintain constant generator frequency",
        "Reduce fuel use",
        "Stabilise oil pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "Maintain constant generator frequency"
    },
    {
      "question": "Octane rating is a measure of...",
      "choices": [
        "Viscosity",
        "Ignition temperature",
        "Resistance to detonation",
        "Fuel density"
      ],
      "answer": "Resistance to detonation"
    },
    {
      "question": "AC frequency in aircraft is typically...",
      "choices": [
        "50 Hz",
        "60 Hz",
        "400 Hz",
        "1000 Hz"
      ],
      "answer": "400 Hz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Air cycle machine is part of which system?",
      "choices": [
        "Electrical",
        "Air conditioning",
        "Fuel",
        "Hydraulics"
      ],
      "answer": "Air conditioning"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the ammeter show when at 0 on the + side?",
      "choices": [
        "Battery discharging",
        "Battery charging",
        "No current flow",
        "System fault"
      ],
      "answer": "Battery charging"
    },
    {
      "question": "Too lean mixture in piston engine causes...",
      "choices": [
        "Overheating",
        "Fouled plugs",
        "More power",
        "Higher efficiency"
      ],
      "answer": "Overheating"
    },
    {
      "question": "In cruise, a richer mixture leads to...",
      "choices": [
        "Higher power",
        "Lower fuel flow",
        "Engine damage",
        "Overheating"
      ],
      "answer": "Higher power"
    },
    {
      "question": "Magnetos are still running when switch is off \u2014 why?",
      "choices": [
        "They are battery powered",
        "They are not grounded",
        "The switch is broken",
        "They are automatic"
      ],
      "answer": "They are not grounded"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thermal efficiency of piston engine is about...",
      "choices": [
        "0.1",
        "0.3",
        "0.5",
        "0.7"
      ],
      "answer": "0.3"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is EMF and how is it created?",
      "choices": [
        "Electromagnetic force; by heat",
        "Electromotive force; by magnetic flux and movement",
        "Electrical motor frequency; by voltage",
        "Energy magnetic field; by capacitor"
      ],
      "answer": "Electromotive force; by magnetic flux and movement"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rich mixture leads to...",
      "choices": [
        "Hotter engine",
        "More evaporation and cooling",
        "Detonation",
        "More power"
      ],
      "answer": "More evaporation and cooling"
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens when carburetor heat is applied?",
      "choices": [
        "Mixture becomes leaner",
        "Mixture becomes richer",
        "No change",
        "Engine stops"
      ],
      "answer": "Mixture becomes richer"
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens if two batteries are connected in parallel?",
      "choices": [
        "Voltage adds up",
        "Voltage remains the same, capacity increases",
        "Voltage drops",
        "No current flows"
      ],
      "answer": "Voltage remains the same, capacity increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is an oxygen pressure demand system?",
      "choices": [
        "Oxygen flows continuously",
        "Oxygen is mixed with nitrogen",
        "Oxygen flows only when inhaling",
        "Oxygen is only available at low altitudes"
      ],
      "answer": "Oxygen flows only when inhaling"
    },
    {
      "question": "Why does the elevator trim switch on a yoke have two switches?",
      "choices": [
        "To allow faster trimming",
        "To prevent trim runaway",
        "To control both pitch and roll",
        "To reduce pilot workload"
      ],
      "answer": "To prevent trim runaway"
    },
    {
      "question": "The phenomenon whereby a voltage and current is generated in a conductor when it is moved across a magnetic field is called electromagnetic __________.",
      "choices": [
        "induction",
        "conduction",
        "resistance",
        "current"
      ],
      "answer": "induction"
    },
    {
      "question": "kVA is the unit typically used to describe the power output of an aircraft's __________ generator.",
      "choices": [
        "DC",
        "AC",
        "starter",
        "alternating"
      ],
      "answer": "AC"
    },
    {
      "question": "A TRU:",
      "choices": [
        "Simultaneously steps-down and converts AC to DC.",
        "Steps-down AC and then converts it to DC.",
        "Can convert AC to DC or vice-versa.",
        "Converts AC to DC and then steps it down."
      ],
      "answer": "Steps-down AC and then converts it to DC."
    },
    {
      "question": "A DC __________ creates electrical current by rotating coils of wire inside an electromagnetic field.",
      "choices": [
        "alternator",
        "commutator",
        "generator",
        "motor"
      ],
      "answer": "generator"
    },
    {
      "question": "The essential difference between aircraft AC alternators and DC generators (dynamos) is that the:",
      "choices": [
        "The alternators generate much less power than DC generators.",
        "Induced windings of the alternators are rotating (rotor), and the dynamos have a rotary inductor coil",
        "Induced (output) windings of the alternators are fixed (stator), and the dynamos have a fixed inductor (field) coil.",
        "Alternators supply all of the output current through the commutators and brush assemblies."
      ],
      "answer": "Induced (output) windings of the alternators are fixed (stator), and the dynamos have a fixed inductor (field) coil."
    },
    {
      "question": "After using the emergency gear extension system it __________ possible to retract the gear.",
      "choices": [
        "is not",
        "is",
        "may be",
        "will be"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    }
  ],
  "INS": [
    {
      "question": "Complete the following conversion to the nearest whole degree: -40\u00b0F converts to __________\u00b0C and __________K",
      "choices": [
        "-30; 233",
        "-40; 233",
        "-40; 173",
        "-50; 203"
      ],
      "answer": "-40; 233"
    },
    {
      "question": "The measured temperature using an aircraft-mounted sensor that is not in direct sunlight?",
      "choices": [
        "SAT",
        "OAT",
        "TAT",
        "RAT"
      ],
      "answer": "OAT"
    },
    {
      "question": "Adjusting QFE to sea level using ISA conditions gives __________.",
      "choices": [
        "QFE",
        "QFF",
        "Ambient",
        "QNH"
      ],
      "answer": "QNH"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct effect on Machmeter indications for the problem given below: Pitot blockage when the aircraft is climbing.",
      "choices": [
        "Small over-read.",
        "Under-read - may be large.",
        "Freezes.",
        "Over-read - may be large."
      ],
      "answer": "Over-read - may be large."
    },
    {
      "question": "An air data computer (ADC): The combination of the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "2, 5.",
        "1, 2.",
        "2, 3, 4.",
        "3, 4, 5."
      ],
      "answer": "3, 4, 5."
    },
    {
      "question": "Is the minimum standard of altimeter which might meet RVSM accuracy requirements.",
      "choices": [
        "Servo-assisted Altimeter",
        "Simple Altimeter",
        "Sensitive Altimeter",
        "Radio Altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Servo-assisted Altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the option which correctly completes the following statement: The pressure altitude is the altitude corresponding :",
      "choices": [
        "In ambient atmosphere, to the reference pressure PS.",
        "In standard atmosphere, to the reference pressure PS.",
        "In ambient atmosphere, to the pressure PS prevailing at this point",
        "In standard atmosphere, to the pressure PS prevailing at this point."
      ],
      "answer": "In standard atmosphere, to the pressure PS prevailing at this point."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct effect on Machmeter indications for the problem given below: Pitot leak in a pressurised aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Under-read - may be large.",
        "Small over-read.",
        "Freezes.",
        "Over-read - may be large."
      ],
      "answer": "Under-read - may be large."
    },
    {
      "question": "An Air Data Computer (ADC):",
      "choices": [
        "Converts air data measurements given by ATC from the ground in order to provide correct altitude and speed information.",
        "Is an auxiliary system that provides altitude information in the event that the static source is blocked.",
        "Transforms air data measurements into electric impulses driving servo motors in instruments.",
        "Measures position error in the static system and transmits this information to ATC to provide correct altitude reporting."
      ],
      "answer": "Transforms air data measurements into electric impulses driving servo motors in instruments."
    },
    {
      "question": "Direct-reading temperature probes used on light aircraft are normally mounted __________.",
      "choices": [
        "under the wing.",
        "near the windshield.",
        "on the side of the fuselage.",
        "on the tail fin."
      ],
      "answer": "near the windshield."
    },
    {
      "question": "Near-zero friction means almost no lag and greater accuracy.",
      "choices": [
        "Simple Altimeter",
        "Sensitive Altimeter",
        "Servo-assisted Altimeter",
        "GPS Altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Servo-assisted Altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "An airspeed indicator displays:",
      "choices": [
        "TAS",
        "IAS",
        "EAS",
        "CAS"
      ],
      "answer": "IAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Has a stack of aneroid capsules connected by levers and gears to multiple pointer hands.",
      "choices": [
        "Simple Altimeter",
        "Servo-assisted Altimeter",
        "Sensitive Altimeter",
        "Encoding Altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Sensitive Altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Europe altimeters are calibrated in:",
      "choices": [
        "Metres.",
        "PSI.",
        "Yards.",
        "Feet."
      ],
      "answer": "Feet."
    },
    {
      "question": "The relationship between pressure units is: 1 millibar=__________ hPa.",
      "choices": [
        "100",
        "1000",
        "1",
        "10"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The AoA sensor consists of a __________ that receives the signal from __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Capacitance sensor, the differential probe",
        "Potentiometer wiper, the slotted probe",
        "Potentiometer wiper, the wind wane",
        "Piezoelectric sensor, the slotted probe"
      ],
      "answer": "Potentiometer wiper, the wind wane"
    },
    {
      "question": "Total pressure is:",
      "choices": [
        "Displayed as a Mach number.",
        "Static pressure + dynamic pressure.",
        "\u00bd\u03c1V\u00b2.",
        "Displayed as an indicated air speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Static pressure + dynamic pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "During the cruise at FL400, the pilot tubes of your aircraft become blocked by volcanic ash. After starting a descent, what should you be aware of? The airspeed display will:",
      "choices": [
        "over-read.",
        "be frozen.",
        "under-read.",
        "be unaffected."
      ],
      "answer": "under-read."
    },
    {
      "question": "The only reference pressure which can be accurately set is QFE, while on the ground before take-off.",
      "choices": [
        "Sensitive Altimeter",
        "Servo-assisted Altimeter",
        "Simple Altimeter",
        "Radio Altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Simple Altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "To prevent __________ IVSIs have a mass acting as a piston inside a cylinder.",
      "choices": [
        "excess pressure",
        "lag",
        "over-pressure",
        "hysteresis"
      ],
      "answer": "lag"
    },
    {
      "question": "What can be said regarding a small aircraft's Angle of Attack (AoA) sensor?",
      "choices": [
        "It is a small radar dish on top of the cockpit.",
        "It is a small vane on the leading edge of the wing.",
        "It is located on the tall of the aircraft.",
        "It is located on the side of the fuselage."
      ],
      "answer": "It is a small vane on the leading edge of the wing."
    },
    {
      "question": "If the TAS is 300 kt and the SAT is -50\u00b0C, the TAT is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "-59\u00baC",
        "-41\u00baC",
        "-53\u00baC",
        "-34\u00baC"
      ],
      "answer": "-41\u00baC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Remote-reading temperature probes usually measure __________. This is useful because it determines the relationship between IAS and TAS. This temperature is displayed on the flight deck and used by the ADC.",
      "choices": [
        "SAT",
        "OAT",
        "TAT",
        "EGT"
      ],
      "answer": "TAT"
    },
    {
      "question": "Detail the colour of the ASI speed scale markings for the arc showing caution speed range?",
      "choices": [
        "White",
        "Green",
        "Yellow",
        "Blue"
      ],
      "answer": "Yellow"
    },
    {
      "question": "The commonly used unit of temperature in aviation is degrees __________. In the USA, degrees __________ is commonly used. Absolute temperature is measured using the __________ scale.",
      "choices": [
        "kelvin; Celsius; Fahrenheit",
        "Fahrenheit; Celsius ; kelvin",
        "Celsius; Fahrenheit; kelvin",
        "Fahrenheit: kelvin; Celsius"
      ],
      "answer": "Celsius; Fahrenheit; kelvin"
    },
    {
      "question": "The altimeter is supplied with:",
      "choices": [
        "Dynamic pressure.",
        "Differential pressure.",
        "Total pressure.",
        "Static pressure."
      ],
      "answer": "Static pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "One capsule is connected to a pointer hand.",
      "choices": [
        "Sensitive Altimeter",
        "Simple Altimeter",
        "Servo-assisted Altimeter",
        "Radio Altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Simple Altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "At a constant calibrated airspeed (CAS), the Mach number:",
      "choices": [
        "Decreases when the altitude increases.",
        "Increases when the outside temperature increases.",
        "Increases when the altitude increases.",
        "Increases when the outside temperature decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "Increases when the altitude increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "Always has an altitude reporting function.",
      "choices": [
        "Simple Altimeter",
        "Servo-assisted Altimeter",
        "Sensitive Altimeter",
        "Mechanical Altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Servo-assisted Altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this diagram:",
      "choices": [
        "A is CAS, B is TAS and C is Mach.",
        "A is TAS, B is CAS and C is Mach.",
        "A is Mach, B is CAS and C is TAS.",
        "A is TAS, B is Mach and C is CAS."
      ],
      "answer": "A is CAS, B is TAS and C is Mach."
    },
    {
      "question": "Detail the colour of the indicator moving to show maximum operating speed or mach (VMO/MMO) description of an ASI speed scale markings?",
      "choices": [
        "Red & White stripes",
        "White",
        "Red",
        "Blue"
      ],
      "answer": "Red & White stripes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Maintaining CAS and flight level constant, a fall in ambient temperature results in:",
      "choices": [
        "Lower TAS because air density increases.",
        "Higher TAS because air density decreases.",
        "Higher TAS because air density increases.",
        "Lower TAS because air density decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "Lower TAS because air density increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "VNO is the maximum speed:",
      "choices": [
        "not to be exceeded except in still air and with caution.",
        "with flaps extended in landing position.",
        "which must never be exceeded.",
        "at which the flight controls can be fully deflected."
      ],
      "answer": "not to be exceeded except in still air and with caution."
    },
    {
      "question": "If the ambient air temperature is -33\u00b0C what is the local speed of sound?",
      "choices": [
        "604 kt.",
        "661 kt.",
        "682 kt.",
        "584 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "604 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "Pitot/static systems on large aircraft:",
      "choices": [
        "Have redundancy thanks to multiple, interconnected and substitutable sources.",
        "Sometimes use MEMS sensors located in an ADC.",
        "Are always discrete systems to protect against data contamination.",
        "Are only ever pneumatic to prevent data-corruption error."
      ],
      "answer": "Have redundancy thanks to multiple, interconnected and substitutable sources."
    },
    {
      "question": "VMO and MMO:",
      "choices": [
        "Are the regulation limited maximum operating airspeed and Mach number respectively.",
        "Are the commercial aviation terms for VNE and MNE.",
        "Are different names for the same thing.",
        "Have the same safety margin as VNE."
      ],
      "answer": "Are the regulation limited maximum operating airspeed and Mach number respectively."
    },
    {
      "question": "The temperature that determines relationship between TAS and IAS?",
      "choices": [
        "OAT",
        "TAT",
        "SAT",
        "EGT"
      ],
      "answer": "TAT"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the following conversion to the nearest whole degree: 100K converts to __________\u00b0C",
      "choices": [
        "173",
        "-183",
        "-173",
        "-153"
      ],
      "answer": "-173"
    },
    {
      "question": "Causes erroneous indications on a pressurised aircraft because cabin pressure changes at a different rate from static pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "Blockage.",
        "Leak.",
        "Icing.",
        "Failure."
      ],
      "answer": "Leak."
    },
    {
      "question": "If TAS is 480 kt and OAT is -43\u00b0C, what is the Mach number?",
      "choices": [
        "0.72.",
        "0.81.",
        "1.23.",
        "0.69."
      ],
      "answer": "0.81."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane is descending from FL390 to ground level at maximum speed. For this descent what are the speed limits?",
      "choices": [
        "Initially MMO, then VMO below a given flight level.",
        "Initially VMO, then MMO below a given flight level.",
        "VMO only during all the descent.",
        "MMO only during all the descent."
      ],
      "answer": "Initially MMO, then VMO below a given flight level."
    },
    {
      "question": "Normal or near-normal indications on an unpressurised aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Blockage.",
        "Leak.",
        "Rupture.",
        "Freezing."
      ],
      "answer": "Leak."
    },
    {
      "question": "Displays either inertial data or a blend of air data and inertial data on PFD.",
      "choices": [
        "Inertial VSI",
        "VSI.",
        "Instantaneous VSI.",
        "Mechanical VSI"
      ],
      "answer": "Inertial VSI"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mach number is:",
      "choices": [
        "Indicated by a pointer hand on a mechanical Machmeter, or a numerical drum in a MASI displaying ADC-calculated data, or a number prefixed by 'M' displayed near the EFIS speed tape.",
        "Always indicated by a single pointer hand.",
        "Indicated by a pointer hand when generated by ADC data, or a drum or a digital Mach indication when driven by a mechanical Machmeter.",
        "Always indicated by a single pointer hand."
      ],
      "answer": "Indicated by a pointer hand on a mechanical Machmeter, or a numerical drum in a MASI displaying ADC-calculated data, or a number prefixed by 'M' displayed near the EFIS speed tape."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is cruising at FL410, Mach 0.86. The ISA deviation is -12\u00b0C. What is the TAS of the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "647 kt",
        "466 kt",
        "566 kt",
        "479 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "479 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a barometric type instantaneous Vertical Speed indicator (IVSI), what ls used to quickly respond to altitude changes and provide Instant climb/descent Indications?",
      "choices": [
        "Information from an air data inertial reference system.",
        "An accelerometer to temporally change the pressure in the capsule.",
        "A piston to temporarily change the diameter of the metering unit.",
        "An accelerometer mechanically linked to the capsule, to expand it faster."
      ],
      "answer": "An accelerometer to temporally change the pressure in the capsule."
    },
    {
      "question": "Pitot/static system heating:",
      "choices": [
        "Prevents ice from blocking the pressure sensors.",
        "Avoids thermodynamic error.",
        "Removes temperature error from pressure measurements.",
        "Ensures pressure sensing is always based on ISA air density at 15\u00b0C."
      ],
      "answer": "Prevents ice from blocking the pressure sensors."
    },
    {
      "question": "The 'E' bar of the E-I bar transducer is driven by a motor which also drives the pointer hands and numerical display.",
      "choices": [
        "Simple Altimeter",
        "Servo-assisted Altimeter",
        "Sensitive Altimeter",
        "Encoding Altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Servo-assisted Altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hydraulic pressure is usually measured in psi, which stands for __________.",
      "choices": [
        "People per square inch.",
        "Pressure per square inch.",
        "Pounds per square inch.",
        "Pascal per square inch."
      ],
      "answer": "Pounds per square inch."
    },
    {
      "question": "In aviation the normal pressure unit used is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Pascal",
        "Hectopascal",
        "Bar",
        "PSI"
      ],
      "answer": "Hectopascal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Detail the colour of the line showing best rate of climb speed with one engine inoperative of an ASI speed scale markings?",
      "choices": [
        "Green",
        "Blue",
        "Red & White stripes",
        "Yellow"
      ],
      "answer": "Blue"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is not sufficiently accurate for training or commercial aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Servo-assisted Altimeter",
        "Simple Altimeter",
        "Sensitive Altimeter",
        "Digital Altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Simple Altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "Instrument error' describes a category of errors caused by:",
      "choices": [
        "Icing of the static ports.",
        "Imperfections in the manufacture or calibration of the instrument and wear and tear during service.",
        "Changes in pressure when the aircraft pitches and turns.",
        "Connecting the wrong pressure source to the instrument during installation."
      ],
      "answer": "Imperfections in the manufacture or calibration of the instrument and wear and tear during service."
    },
    {
      "question": "Vane detectors are __________.",
      "choices": [
        "sensitive to damage",
        "robust",
        "heated",
        "inaccurate"
      ],
      "answer": "sensitive to damage"
    },
    {
      "question": "What angle of bank should you adopt on the attitude indicator for a standard rate (rate 1) turn while flying at an TAS of 130 kts?",
      "choices": [
        "15\u00b0",
        "20\u00b0",
        "23\u00b0",
        "18\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "20\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the following phrase: The signal on an angle of attack sensor is created by a (1 ) __ and is subject to (2) __ error.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) magnetic sensor; (2) variation .",
        "(1) capacitor; (2) scale.",
        "(1) potentiometer; (2) position.",
        "(1) piezoelectric; (2) deviation."
      ],
      "answer": "(1) potentiometer; (2) position."
    },
    {
      "question": "VNO, the upper limit of the normal operating speed range is indicated by:",
      "choices": [
        "H",
        "E",
        "G",
        "C"
      ],
      "answer": "C"
    },
    {
      "question": "Vane detectors are pivoted well __________ of their centre of pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "aft",
        "forward",
        "above",
        "below"
      ],
      "answer": "forward"
    },
    {
      "question": "ISA sea level pressure is: __________ in Hg",
      "choices": [
        "1013.25",
        "29.92",
        "14.7",
        "1023.25"
      ],
      "answer": "29.92"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct effect on Machmeter indications for the problem given below: Pitot blockage when the aircraft is descending.",
      "choices": [
        "Over-read - may be large.",
        "Under-read - may be large.",
        "Small over-read.",
        "Freezes."
      ],
      "answer": "Under-read - may be large."
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the following conversion to the nearest whole degree: 82\u00b0F converts to __________\u00b0C",
      "choices": [
        "18",
        "30",
        "28",
        "17"
      ],
      "answer": "28"
    },
    {
      "question": "The units displayed on a VSI are:",
      "choices": [
        "Feet per minute (fpm) or metres per second (m/s). 1 m/s = 200 fpm.",
        "Feet per minute (ft/min) or metres per minute (m/min). 1 m/min = 3.8 ft/min.",
        "Feet per second (fps) or metres per second (mps). 1 fps = 3.8 m/s.",
        "Metres per minute (mpm) or centimetres per second (cps). 1 mpm = 1.7 cps."
      ],
      "answer": "Feet per minute (fpm) or metres per second (m/s). 1 m/s = 200 fpm."
    },
    {
      "question": "1 __________ is approximately equal to atmospheric pressure at sea level. It is equal to 1000 __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Pascal; hPa",
        "Bar; PSI",
        "Bar; in Hg",
        "Bar; hPa"
      ],
      "answer": "Bar; hPa"
    },
    {
      "question": "Indication lags behind actual vertical speed.",
      "choices": [
        "Inertial VSI",
        "VSI.",
        "Instantaneous VSI.",
        "ADC-driven VSI"
      ],
      "answer": "VSI."
    },
    {
      "question": "A system using one or more ADCs, comprises __________ which collect analogue data, air data modules to convert analogue data to digital data, __________ to manipulate the data and one or more display units to display information to the pilot.",
      "choices": [
        "sensors; a digitiser",
        "ADMs; a computer",
        "ADMs; a digitiser",
        "sensors; a computer"
      ],
      "answer": "sensors; a computer"
    },
    {
      "question": "A warm column of air is __________ than a relatively cold column.",
      "choices": [
        "Exactly the same density",
        "less dense",
        "denser",
        "more viscous"
      ],
      "answer": "less dense"
    },
    {
      "question": "The colour of the arc showing flap operating speed range of an ASI speed scale markings is:",
      "choices": [
        "White",
        "Green",
        "Yellow",
        "Red"
      ],
      "answer": "White"
    },
    {
      "question": "Has a basic accelerometer to overcome lag.",
      "choices": [
        "Inertial VSI",
        "Instantaneous VSI.",
        "VSI.",
        "Mechanical VSI"
      ],
      "answer": "Instantaneous VSI."
    },
    {
      "question": "The limits of the green scale of an airspeed indicator are:",
      "choices": [
        "VS1 for the lower limit and VNE for the upper limit",
        "VS1 for the lower limit and VLO for the upper limit.",
        "VS0 for the lower limit and VNO for the upper limit.",
        "VS1 for the lower limit and VNO for the upper limit."
      ],
      "answer": "VS1 for the lower limit and VNO for the upper limit."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Machmeter doesn't suffer from compressibility error because:",
      "choices": [
        "It measures dynamic pressure divided by static pressure, which is the same ratio that determines compressibility error.",
        "Speed isn't shown on instrument face, so it can't be in error.",
        "The mnemonic ECTM proves that to get from TAS to Mach you don't have to consider EAS, so this error is irrelevant.",
        "It is corrected by carefully calibrating the instrument scale to account for EAS being higher than CAS at high speeds."
      ],
      "answer": "It measures dynamic pressure divided by static pressure, which is the same ratio that determines compressibility error."
    },
    {
      "question": "The exact value for the SPS is __________ hPa.",
      "choices": [
        "1023.25",
        "1003.25",
        "1013.25",
        "1012.35"
      ],
      "answer": "1013.25"
    },
    {
      "question": "The colour of the arc showing normal operating speed range of an ASI speed scale markings is:",
      "choices": [
        "Red",
        "Yellow",
        "White",
        "Green"
      ],
      "answer": "Green"
    },
    {
      "question": "If you are flying through turbulence, you can expect the IVSI to (1) __ . You should (2) __ small fluctuations.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) under-react; (2) Ignore",
        "(1) under-react; (2) respond slowly to",
        "(1) over-react; (2) respond slowly to",
        "(1) over-react; (2) Ignore"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) over-react; (2) Ignore"
    },
    {
      "question": "When displayed on the flight deck of a CAT aircraft, AoA indications are usually shown as an analogue or analogue/digital display __________.",
      "choices": [
        "on a discreet AoA gauge.",
        "on the PFD.",
        "on the ND.",
        "on the EICAS."
      ],
      "answer": "on the PFD."
    },
    {
      "question": "If 520 kt TAS is M0.86, what is the OAT?",
      "choices": [
        "-33\u00baC.",
        "24\u00baC.",
        "-24\u00baC",
        "33\u00baC."
      ],
      "answer": "-33\u00baC."
    },
    {
      "question": "Detail the colour of the line showing maximum speed VNE of an ASI speed scale markings?",
      "choices": [
        "White",
        "Red",
        "Green",
        "Blue"
      ],
      "answer": "Red"
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens to your ASI when your static port has icing blockage (in a climb)?",
      "choices": [
        "Reads zero",
        "Over read",
        "Under read",
        "Nothing"
      ],
      "answer": "Under read"
    },
    {
      "question": "The temperature outside the aircraft that is not affected by the movement of the aircraft through the air?",
      "choices": [
        "OAT",
        "SAT",
        "TAT",
        "RAT"
      ],
      "answer": "SAT"
    },
    {
      "question": "When the sea level OAT is +25\u00b0C, the deviation from standard temperature for aerodynamic computations is:",
      "choices": [
        "+15\u00b0C",
        "-15\u00b0C",
        "+10\u00b0C",
        "0\u00b0C"
      ],
      "answer": "+10\u00b0C"
    },
    {
      "question": "The relationship between pressure units is: 1 hPa =__________ Pa.",
      "choices": [
        "10",
        "1000",
        "100",
        "10 000"
      ],
      "answer": "100"
    },
    {
      "question": "The higher the rate of change of pressure, the __________ the expansion or contraction of the capsule and the movement of the pointer hand connected to it.",
      "choices": [
        "greater",
        "lesser",
        "slower",
        "unchanged"
      ],
      "answer": "greater"
    },
    {
      "question": "The unit of pressure used in the US is __________ of mercury.",
      "choices": [
        "Bar",
        "Inches",
        "Centimetre",
        "PSI"
      ],
      "answer": "Inches"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "ADCs contain air data modules for the pitot and static systems. They calculate Mach number using TAT, static and pitot pressure.",
        "Pitot and static sensors are connected to nearby air data modules. Digital data is sent to the ADC which (on CAT aircraft) uses stored calibration data which removes most types of sensor error. This produces accurate outputs to ASI, altimeter, VSI and Mach number displays in CAT aircraft.",
        "ADCs are a single point of connection for the pitot and static systems. They comprise an altimeter, ASI, and Machmeter.",
        "On a modern CAT aircraft, alternate pitot and static sources send digital data directly to the EFIS display units (DUs)."
      ],
      "answer": "Pitot and static sensors are connected to nearby air data modules. Digital data is sent to the ADC which (on CAT aircraft) uses stored calibration data which removes most types of sensor error. This produces accurate outputs to ASI, altimeter, VSI and Mach number displays in CAT aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "ISA sea level pressure is: approximately __________ psi.",
      "choices": [
        "1013.25",
        "14.7",
        "1023.25",
        "29.92"
      ],
      "answer": "14.7"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the ADC fails, which of the following instruments related to the pitot-static instruments are affected?",
      "choices": [
        "1 and 3.",
        "1, 2, 3 and 4 .",
        "1, 2 and 3.",
        "1 and 2."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2 and 3."
    },
    {
      "question": "Remote-reading temperature probes are mounted on a protruding leg to ensure that the sensed air is __________ the boundary layer.",
      "choices": [
        "inside",
        "outside",
        "within",
        "below"
      ],
      "answer": "outside"
    },
    {
      "question": "The input data of an ADC (Air Data Computer) is: 1. OAT. 2. TAT. 3. Static pressure. 4. Total pressure. The combination of the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 4.",
        "2, 3, 4.",
        "1, 3, 4.",
        "1, 2, 3, 4."
      ],
      "answer": "2, 3, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct effect on Machmeter indications for the problem given below: Static leak in a pressurised aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Over-read - may be large.",
        "Small over-read.",
        "Freezes.",
        "Under-read - may be large."
      ],
      "answer": "Under-read - may be large."
    },
    {
      "question": "An air data computer (ADC): 1. Supplies the ground speed... The combination of the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "2, 3, 4.",
        "1, 2.",
        "3, 4, 5.",
        "2, 5."
      ],
      "answer": "3, 4, 5."
    },
    {
      "question": "You leave airfield A with QNH 1010 hPa set. You arrive overhead airfield B, which has a QNH of 1020 hPa, without adjusting your altimeter. With an indicated altitude of 3000 ft, what is your true altitude, if there is no temperature error?",
      "choices": [
        "3300 ft",
        "2700 ft",
        "3030 ft",
        "2970 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "3300 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The data outputs from the ADC (Air Data Computer) are: 1. Altitude. 2. Mach number. 3. IAS. 4. TAS. 5. SAT. The combination of all of the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3, 4, 5.",
        "1, 4.",
        "2, 3, 4.",
        "1, 3, 5."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5."
    },
    {
      "question": "The pressure measured at ground level at an airfield is called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "QFF",
        "QFE",
        "QNH",
        "ambient"
      ],
      "answer": "QFE"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane is in a steady climb. The autothrottle maintains a constant Mach number. If the total temperature remains constant, the calibrated airspeed:",
      "choices": [
        "Remains constant.",
        "Decreases if the static temperature is lower than the standard temperature, increases if higher.",
        "Decreases.",
        "Increases."
      ],
      "answer": "Decreases."
    },
    {
      "question": "The measured temperature outside the aircraft, that is affected by adiabatic heating, because the relative airflow at the sensor is reduced to zero?",
      "choices": [
        "TAT",
        "SAT",
        "OAT",
        "RAT"
      ],
      "answer": "TAT"
    },
    {
      "question": "The open-ended tube parallel to the longitudinal axis of the aircraft senses the:",
      "choices": [
        "Static pressure.",
        "Total pressure.",
        "Total pressure plus static pressure.",
        "Dynamic pressure."
      ],
      "answer": "Total pressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "In some CIS and Asian countries altimeters are calibrated in:",
      "choices": [
        "Metres.",
        "Yards.",
        "PSI.",
        "Feet."
      ],
      "answer": "Metres."
    },
    {
      "question": "If you are flying through turbulence, you can expect the IVSI to (1) __ . You should (2) __ gradual changes.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) under-read; (2) Ignore",
        "(1) over-read; (2) respond slowly to",
        "(1) under-read; (2) respond slowly to",
        "(1) over-read; (2) Ignore"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) over-read; (2) Ignore"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are at a sea level airfield with an outside air temperature of -15\u00baC (ISA-30). You set the correct QNH of 1030 hPa. You have to pass over a mountain shortly after departure, and need a true altitude of at least 4000 ft for safe clearance. The indicated altitude you must be at before passing over the mountain is:",
      "choices": [
        "3520 ft",
        "4120 ft",
        "4480 ft",
        "3880 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "4480 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Direct-reading temperature probes used on light aircraft __________ suffer from position error and significant instrument error.",
      "choices": [
        "never",
        "do",
        "don't",
        "sometimes"
      ],
      "answer": "do"
    },
    {
      "question": "May indicate erratically in turbulence.",
      "choices": [
        "Instantaneous VSI.",
        "VSI.",
        "Inertial VSI",
        "Mechanical VSI"
      ],
      "answer": "Instantaneous VSI."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct effect on Machmeter indications for the problem given below: Static blockage when the aircraft is descending.",
      "choices": [
        "Over-read - may be large.",
        "Freezes.",
        "Small over-read.",
        "Under-read - may be large."
      ],
      "answer": "Over-read - may be large."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct effect on Machmeter indications for the problem given below: Static leak in an unpressurised aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Under-read - may be large.",
        "Small over-read.",
        "Freezes.",
        "Small under-read."
      ],
      "answer": "Small over-read."
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the following conversion to the nearest whole degree: 16\u00b0C converts to __________\u00b0F",
      "choices": [
        "61",
        "51",
        "57",
        "27"
      ],
      "answer": "61"
    },
    {
      "question": "The temperature that determines the local speed of sound?",
      "choices": [
        "SAT",
        "OAT",
        "TAT",
        "RAT"
      ],
      "answer": "SAT"
    },
    {
      "question": "100 kt is equivalent to:",
      "choices": [
        "87 km/h, and 54 mph",
        "185 km/h, and 115 mph",
        "54 km/h, and 87 mph",
        "115 km/h, and 185 mph"
      ],
      "answer": "185 km/h, and 115 mph"
    },
    {
      "question": "The position error of an ASI results from:",
      "choices": [
        "The difference in air density from sea level ISA density.",
        "Mechanical differences in individual instruments.",
        "The fact that air becomes more compressible at high speeds.",
        "The effects of the airflow around the static vent and pitot head."
      ],
      "answer": "The effects of the airflow around the static vent and pitot head."
    },
    {
      "question": "The SI unit of pressure is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Bar",
        "Pascal",
        "Hectopascal",
        "PSI"
      ],
      "answer": "Pascal"
    },
    {
      "question": "In light aircraft made in USA, ________ is commonly used.",
      "choices": [
        "metres per second",
        "km per hour",
        "mph",
        "kt"
      ],
      "answer": "mph"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 'barber pole' VMO/MMO takes inputs from: 1. Aneroid capsule. 2. Differential pressure. 3. Temperature. The combination of correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1,2,3.",
        "2,3.",
        "1,2.",
        "1,3."
      ],
      "answer": "1,2."
    },
    {
      "question": "ISA sea level pressure is: __________ mb",
      "choices": [
        "14.7",
        "29.92",
        "1013.25",
        "1023.25"
      ],
      "answer": "1013.25"
    },
    {
      "question": "Indication decreases to zero and stays there, regardless of vertical speed.",
      "choices": [
        "Blockage.",
        "Leak",
        "Rupture.",
        "Icing."
      ],
      "answer": "Blockage."
    },
    {
      "question": "May have a numerical value displayed, as well as a logarithmic pointer scale.",
      "choices": [
        "VSI.",
        "Inertial VSI",
        "Instantaneous VSI.",
        "Simple VSI"
      ],
      "answer": "Inertial VSI"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a simple light aircraft using a single ADC:",
      "choices": [
        "ADC failure requires you to use the standby pressure instruments.",
        "Results in loss of your primary attitude information.",
        "ADC failure results in loss of all pressure-sensing displays.",
        "Causes the OAT gauge to misread."
      ],
      "answer": "ADC failure requires you to use the standby pressure instruments."
    },
    {
      "question": "Has limited accuracy and range.",
      "choices": [
        "Sensitive Altimeter",
        "Servo-assisted Altimeter",
        "Simple Altimeter",
        "Radio Altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Simple Altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "At constant weight, regardless of altitude, an aircraft always lifts off at a constant:",
      "choices": [
        "CAS",
        "TAS",
        "Ground speed",
        "EAS"
      ],
      "answer": "EAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Remote-reading temperature probes are used on CAT aircraft. To reduce position error, they are usually mounted on the fuselage where the airflow is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "stationary",
        "smooth",
        "turbulent",
        "reversed"
      ],
      "answer": "smooth"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about null-seeking probes is correct? Null seeking probes:",
      "choices": [
        "Use a servo motor to rotate the probe until there is no differential pressure between the slots.",
        "Use a servo motor to rotate the probe until there is a differential pressure is sensed between the slots.",
        "Are sensitive to the difference in pressure sensed in slots either side of the fixed probe.",
        "Are usually mounted on the leading edge of the wing."
      ],
      "answer": "Use a servo motor to rotate the probe until there is no differential pressure between the slots."
    },
    {
      "question": "The sealed case of a VSI is connected to static pressure via a metering unit to create __________ in the case.",
      "choices": [
        "excess pressure",
        "a pressure lag",
        "a vacuum",
        "over-pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "a pressure lag"
    },
    {
      "question": "The limits of the yellow arc (caution speed range) of an airspeed indicator are:",
      "choices": [
        "VLO for the lower limit and VNE for the upper limit.",
        "VLE for the lower limit and VNE for the upper limit.",
        "VFE for the lower limit and VNE for the upper limit.",
        "VNO for the lower limit and VNE for the upper limit."
      ],
      "answer": "VNO for the lower limit and VNE for the upper limit."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct effect on Machmeter indications for the problem given below: Static blockage when the aircraft is climbing.",
      "choices": [
        "Freezes.",
        "Small over-read.",
        "Under-read - may be large.",
        "Over-read - may be large."
      ],
      "answer": "Under-read - may be large."
    },
    {
      "question": "On the ground, during a left turn, the rate of turn indicator indicates:",
      "choices": [
        "Needle to the left, ball to the right.",
        "Needle to the left, ball to the left.",
        "Needle in the middle, ball to the right.",
        "Needle in the middle, ball to the left."
      ],
      "answer": "Needle to the left, ball to the right."
    },
    {
      "question": "Inertia causes the piston to move when the __________ changes.",
      "choices": [
        "aircraft's height",
        "aircraft's pitch rate",
        "aircraft's speed",
        "aircraft's roll rate"
      ],
      "answer": "aircraft's pitch rate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Static pressure is:",
      "choices": [
        "The pressure of the unaccelerated air, measured at the nose of the aircraft just behind the propeller.",
        "The sum of the mass of the gas and its velocity squared, divided by air density.",
        "The pressure force caused by the mass of the air above.",
        "The sum of stagnation and pitot pressures."
      ],
      "answer": "The pressure force caused by the mass of the air above."
    },
    {
      "question": "The relationship between pressure units is: 1 Bar =__________ hPa.",
      "choices": [
        "10",
        "100",
        "1000",
        "10 000"
      ],
      "answer": "1000"
    },
    {
      "question": "The temperature obtained by subtracting the ram rise from the TAT?",
      "choices": [
        "TAT",
        "OAT",
        "SAT",
        "RAT"
      ],
      "answer": "SAT"
    },
    {
      "question": "Static system leaks cause the altimeter to:",
      "choices": [
        "Under-read in all aircraft types.",
        "Over-read in all aircraft types.",
        "Under-read if the aircraft is pressurised and over-read if it is unpressurised.",
        "Over-read if the aircraft is pressurised and under-read if it is unpressurised."
      ],
      "answer": "Under-read if the aircraft is pressurised and over-read if it is unpressurised."
    },
    {
      "question": "The local speed of sound:",
      "choices": [
        "Depends on the density of the air and the pressure altitude.",
        "Depends on the absolute temperature of the air.",
        "Is 661 kt.",
        "Depends on the temperature of the air and the aircraft's TAS."
      ],
      "answer": "Depends on the absolute temperature of the air."
    },
    {
      "question": "Vane detectors__________ the angle of attack at the wing.",
      "choices": [
        "infer",
        "measure",
        "calculate",
        "ignore"
      ],
      "answer": "infer"
    },
    {
      "question": "The output data calculated by the ADC (Air Data Computer) is 1. Attitude. 2. Pressure altitude. 3. TAT. 4. TAS. 5. CAS. The combination of the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 3, 4, 5.",
        "2, 3, 4, 5.",
        "1, 2, 4.",
        "2, 3, 5."
      ],
      "answer": "2, 3, 4, 5."
    },
    {
      "question": "The error in altimeter readings caused by the variation of the static pressure near the source is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Instrument error.",
        "Position pressure error.",
        "Hysteresis effect.",
        "Barometric error."
      ],
      "answer": "Position pressure error."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is climbing at 800 ft/min, It is the equivalent of:",
      "choices": [
        "28.6 m/sec",
        "4.1 m/sec",
        "12 m/sec",
        "43.2 m/sec"
      ],
      "answer": "4.1 m/sec"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a null-seeking AoA device protected from icing?",
      "choices": [
        "Pneumatic heat.",
        "Electric heating.",
        "Chemically.",
        "No protection at all."
      ],
      "answer": "Electric heating."
    },
    {
      "question": "After compass errors have been minimised, a card is displayed on or near the compass which records any residual __________.",
      "choices": [
        "acceleration",
        "swinging",
        "deficit",
        "deviation"
      ],
      "answer": "deviation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Has the lowest weight and volume.",
      "choices": [
        "Direct-reading",
        "Remote indicating",
        "Both.",
        "Neither"
      ],
      "answer": "Direct-reading"
    },
    {
      "question": "With an increase in magnetic latitude there will be a decrease in the:",
      "choices": [
        "total magnetic force of the Earth's magnetic field.",
        "vertical component of the Earth's magnetic field.",
        "angle of dip .",
        "directive force."
      ],
      "answer": "directive force."
    },
    {
      "question": "Concerning magnetic compasses, deviation is:",
      "choices": [
        "Compass North.",
        "The angular difference between Magnetic North and True North.",
        "The angular difference between Magnetic North and Compass North.",
        "A card in the cockpit showing compass heading errors."
      ],
      "answer": "The angular difference between Magnetic North and Compass North."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ pole of a magnet is attracted to the Magnetic South pole.",
      "choices": [
        "South",
        "North",
        "East",
        "West"
      ],
      "answer": "North"
    },
    {
      "question": "Known as permanent magnetism.",
      "choices": [
        "Soft",
        "Electro",
        "Aero",
        "Hard"
      ],
      "answer": "Hard"
    },
    {
      "question": "Compass deviations are minimised by __________ the compass. This is done with electrical components and engines all __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "hanging; off",
        "swinging; off",
        "hanging; on",
        "swinging; on"
      ],
      "answer": "swinging; on"
    },
    {
      "question": "It provides a heading reference for the compass card and other aircraft systems.",
      "choices": [
        "Flux Valve.",
        "Gyro Unit.",
        "Precession Amplifier",
        "Stator."
      ],
      "answer": "Gyro Unit."
    },
    {
      "question": "Has substantial error caused by accelerations.",
      "choices": [
        "Both.",
        "Remote indicating",
        "Direct-reading",
        "Neither"
      ],
      "answer": "Direct-reading"
    },
    {
      "question": "Close to the __________ poles dip can be great enough to cause the compass to stop working.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "magnetic and true",
        "magnetic",
        "geographic"
      ],
      "answer": "magnetic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select which of these errors would be expected from a direct-reading compass in situation described below: Northern hemisphere, turning left through North-East.",
      "choices": [
        "Under-read",
        "Accurate",
        "Freeze",
        "Over-read"
      ],
      "answer": "Over-read"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about hard and soft iron in relation to magnetism is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Both hard and soft iron are of a non-permanent nature.",
        "Hard iron magnetism is of a permanent nature and soft iron is of a non-permanent nature.",
        "Hard iron is of a non-permanent nature and soft iron is of a permanent nature.",
        "Both hard and soft iron are of a permanent nature."
      ],
      "answer": "Hard iron magnetism is of a permanent nature and soft iron is of a non-permanent nature."
    },
    {
      "question": "It uses 3 coils to create an alternating field matching the locally sensed magnetic field.",
      "choices": [
        "Precession Amplifier",
        "Stator.",
        "Detector Coil.",
        "Flux Valve."
      ],
      "answer": "Stator."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a magnetic meridian of the Earth's magnetic field?",
      "choices": [
        "The deviation of magnetic force lines.",
        "The vertical component of magnetic force lines.",
        "The variation of magnetic force lines.",
        "The horizontal component of magnetic force lines."
      ],
      "answer": "The horizontal component of magnetic force lines."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select which of these errors would be expected from a direct-reading compass in situation described below: Southern hemisphere, turning right through South-East.",
      "choices": [
        "Under-read",
        "Over-read",
        "Freeze",
        "Accurate"
      ],
      "answer": "Under-read"
    },
    {
      "question": "At the magnetic equator, when accelerating after take-off on heading West, a direct reading compass:",
      "choices": [
        "Under reads the heading.",
        "Indicates the correct heading.",
        "Overreads the heading.",
        "Indicates a turn to the South."
      ],
      "answer": "Indicates the correct heading."
    },
    {
      "question": "Synchronising must be done after extensive __________.",
      "choices": [
        "instrument flying",
        "manoeuvring",
        "cross-country",
        "straight flight"
      ],
      "answer": "manoeuvring"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the Flux Valve is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Nothing.",
        "Electrically sense the vertical component of the Earth's magnetic field.",
        "Electrically sense the horizontal component of the Earth's magnetic field.",
        "Sense the horizontal and vertical components of the Earth's magnetic field."
      ],
      "answer": "Electrically sense the horizontal component of the Earth's magnetic field."
    },
    {
      "question": "Depends on attitude and location.",
      "choices": [
        "Soft",
        "Hard",
        "Aero",
        "Electro"
      ],
      "answer": "Soft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Electrically-driven AI acceleration errors are __________ than the errors experienced by a pneumatically-driven AI.",
      "choices": [
        "the same as",
        "smaller",
        "larger",
        "non-existent"
      ],
      "answer": "smaller"
    },
    {
      "question": "It is located in a wingtip or tailplane, as far as possible from the aircraft's electrical components.",
      "choices": [
        "Stator.",
        "Flux Valve.",
        "Detector Coil.",
        "Gyro Unit."
      ],
      "answer": "Flux Valve."
    },
    {
      "question": "The indication of the directional gyro is valid only for a limited period of time. The causes of this inaccuracy are rotation of the Earth and:",
      "choices": [
        "The aircraft's movement over the surface of the Earth, and the vertical component of the Earth's magnetic field.",
        "The aircraft's movement over the surface of the Earth.",
        "Longitudinal accelerations, and the vertical component of the Earth's magnetic field.",
        "Longitudinal accelerations, and the aircraft's movement over the surface of the Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "The aircraft's movement over the surface of the Earth."
    },
    {
      "question": "Magnetic dip\u2026",
      "choices": [
        "Varies with latitude. It's greatest close to the magnetic poles where the magnetic field moves towards the vertical.",
        "Causes variation to decrease in the northern hemisphere and increase in the southern hemisphere.",
        "Is greatest at the equator and weakest at the true poles.",
        "Is the reduction in the strength of the Earth's magnetic field associated with solar wind events."
      ],
      "answer": "Varies with latitude. It's greatest close to the magnetic poles where the magnetic field moves towards the vertical."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the northern hemisphere, an aircraft takesoff on a runway with an alignment of 045\u00b0 . During the take-off run, the compass indicates:",
      "choices": [
        "A value below 045\u00b0.",
        "A value above 045\u00b0.",
        "225\u00b0.",
        "045\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "A value below 045\u00b0."
    },
    {
      "question": "The aircraft's AI shows the aircraft's attitude in respect to ________ and ______.",
      "choices": [
        "pitch, yaw",
        "yaw, roll",
        "pitch, roll",
        "roll, turn"
      ],
      "answer": "pitch, roll"
    },
    {
      "question": "Suffers from deviation error owing to aircraft magnetism which is corrected using a deviation card.",
      "choices": [
        "Both.",
        "Remote indicating",
        "Neither",
        "Direct-reading"
      ],
      "answer": "Direct-reading"
    },
    {
      "question": "Directional gyros are principally exploited for its property of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "precession",
        "rigidity",
        "procession",
        "gimballing"
      ],
      "answer": "rigidity"
    },
    {
      "question": "For increased TAS and same rate of turn, lift and 'g' must:",
      "choices": [
        "Remain unchanged",
        "decrease",
        "Increase",
        "be zero"
      ],
      "answer": "Increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "When adjusting the magnets for compass errors you introduce an almost equal and opposite magnetic field to that of the __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "Earth",
        "aircraft",
        "gyro",
        "sun"
      ],
      "answer": "aircraft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The angle between the magnetic field lines and the horizontal is known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "dip",
        "declination",
        "drift",
        "variation"
      ],
      "answer": "dip"
    },
    {
      "question": "Can share heading information with other aircraft systems.",
      "choices": [
        "Direct-reading",
        "Both.",
        "Neither",
        "Remote indicating"
      ],
      "answer": "Remote indicating"
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to the rotation of the Earth, the apparent drift of a horizontal free gyroscope at a latitude of 30\u00b0N is:",
      "choices": [
        "2\u00b0 per hour to the right.",
        "15\u00b0 per hour to the left.",
        "7.5\u00b0 per hour to the right.",
        "11\u00b0 per hour to the left."
      ],
      "answer": "7.5\u00b0 per hour to the right."
    },
    {
      "question": "A rapidly spinning gyro tends to maintain its orientation in inertial space. This property of gyroscopes is called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "induction",
        "rigidity",
        "precession",
        "gimballing"
      ],
      "answer": "rigidity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Only present when current is flowing.",
      "choices": [
        "Hard",
        "Aero",
        "Electro",
        "Soft"
      ],
      "answer": "Electro"
    },
    {
      "question": "A standard pneumatic gyro AI is affected by deceleration, showing an erroneous indication of:",
      "choices": [
        "Pitch up and roll right.",
        "Pitch down and roll right.",
        "Pitch down and roll left.",
        "Pitch up and roll left."
      ],
      "answer": "Pitch down and roll left."
    },
    {
      "question": "When at right angles to the stator field it has no output.",
      "choices": [
        "Stator.",
        "Precession Amplifier",
        "Detector Coil.",
        "Flux Valve."
      ],
      "answer": "Detector Coil."
    },
    {
      "question": "A Rate 1 turn is __________ degrees per __________.",
      "choices": [
        "3; minute",
        "3; second",
        "1; second",
        "1; 30 seconds"
      ],
      "answer": "3; second"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select which of these errors would be expected from a direct-reading compass in situation described below: In climb with pitch angle of 25\u00ba.",
      "choices": [
        "Over-read",
        "Under-read",
        "Accurate",
        "Freeze"
      ],
      "answer": "Freeze"
    },
    {
      "question": "If during manoeuvre the limits of the __________ are reached, any further pitch or roll disturbs the gyro.",
      "choices": [
        "axes",
        "casing",
        "gimbals",
        "rotor"
      ],
      "answer": "gimbals"
    },
    {
      "question": "The latitude at which the apparent wander of a directional gyro is equal to 0 is:",
      "choices": [
        "The North Pole.",
        "The Equator.",
        "Mid-Latitude.",
        "South pole."
      ],
      "answer": "The Equator."
    },
    {
      "question": "At a low bank angle, the measurement of rate-of-turn consists of measuring the:",
      "choices": [
        "yaw rate of the aircraft.",
        "bank of the aircraft.",
        "roll rate of the aircraft.",
        "pitch rate of the aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "yaw rate of the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "The direction \"magnetic north\" at a position on the Earth is the:",
      "choices": [
        "direction of the horizontal component of the Earth's magnetic field at that position.",
        "great circle between the position and the magnetic North Pole.",
        "compass North at that position corrected for variation.",
        "isogonal to the magnetic North Pole."
      ],
      "answer": "direction of the horizontal component of the Earth's magnetic field at that position."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about magnetic variation is correct? Magnetic variation\u2026",
      "choices": [
        "Is a measure of the difference in magnetic heading between 2 places resulting from local effects such as magnetotonic rock formations.",
        "Is the change in the magnetic field over time at any given location on the Earth, caused by the movement of molten metal in the Earth's core.",
        "Is the result of the magnetic poles not being at the true poles; it varies depending on your location on the Earth's surface.",
        "Is the difference between the alignment of gridlines on a map and the true lines of longitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Is the result of the magnetic poles not being at the true poles; it varies depending on your location on the Earth's surface."
    },
    {
      "question": "The properties of a gyroscope are: 1 - rigidity in space 2 - rigidly on earth 3 - precession 4 - Schuler oscillations The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 3.",
        "2, 3.",
        "1, 4.",
        "2, 4."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a directional gyro aligned to the correct heading?",
      "choices": [
        "Press the knob on the instrument to start the auto-align process.",
        "Just before take-off press the align button on the standby compass.",
        "Press and hold in the knob on the face of the DI while turning it until the compass and DI show the same heading.",
        "Turn the knob until the heading agrees with the direct-reading compass and then turn on the power supply."
      ],
      "answer": "Press and hold in the knob on the face of the DI while turning it until the compass and DI show the same heading."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which direction of travel is total drift greatest in a directional gyro?",
      "choices": [
        "West.",
        "East.",
        "North.",
        "South."
      ],
      "answer": "East."
    },
    {
      "question": "For increased TAS and same rate of turn, bank angle must:",
      "choices": [
        "Decrease",
        "Reduce",
        "Remain unchanged",
        "Increase"
      ],
      "answer": "Increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft takes off in the northern hemisphere from a runway with an alignment of 045\u00b0. During a rolling take-off, the magnetic compass indicates:",
      "choices": [
        "A value above 045\u00b0 in the southern hemisphere.",
        "A value below 045\u00b0.",
        "A value above 045\u00b0 in the northern hemisphere.",
        "045\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "A value below 045\u00b0."
    },
    {
      "question": "Is completely immune from turning error.",
      "choices": [
        "Direct-reading",
        "Neither",
        "Both.",
        "Remote indicating"
      ],
      "answer": "Neither"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select which of these errors would be expected from a direct-reading compass in situation described below: Northern hemisphere, heading East, decelerating.",
      "choices": [
        "Under-read",
        "Over-read",
        "Freeze",
        "Accurate"
      ],
      "answer": "Over-read"
    },
    {
      "question": "Typical attitude indicator displays have:",
      "choices": [
        "Brown earth and blue sky, yellow FD bars or V-index, and white ILS indications.",
        "A black background with a white line to indicate the horizon and a 'W'-shaped aircraft symbol.",
        "Blue for sky and green for ground, with pitch indications every 10\u00b0 and roll indications every 15\u00b0.",
        "Brown for ground and blue for sky, with index marks typically every 5\u00b0 in pitch, and every 10\u00b0 in roll, up to at least 30\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "Brown for ground and blue for sky, with index marks typically every 5\u00b0 in pitch, and every 10\u00b0 in roll, up to at least 30\u00b0."
    },
    {
      "question": "The inclination of the Earth's magnetic field at the magnetic equator is equal to:",
      "choices": [
        "180\u00b0",
        "90\u00b0",
        "0\u00b0",
        "45\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "0\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Before flight, the __________ switch, often labelled __________ is used to align the compass.",
      "choices": [
        "synchronising; CCW/CW",
        "synchronising; ALIGN/ATT",
        "erecting; CCW/CW",
        "erecting; ALIGN/ATT"
      ],
      "answer": "synchronising; CCW/CW"
    },
    {
      "question": "The location of the Earth's magnetic poles:",
      "choices": [
        "periodically wander (as much as 15 km every year).",
        "is static in time.",
        "is the same as the geographical poles.",
        "is static in time with respect to the geographical poles."
      ],
      "answer": "periodically wander (as much as 15 km every year)."
    },
    {
      "question": "In an AHRS, what does the three-axis magnetometer provide?",
      "choices": [
        "The horizontal component of the earth's magnetic field.",
        "The vertical component of the earth's magnetic field.",
        "The orientation of magnetic North only.",
        "The horizontal and vertical components of the earth's magnetic field."
      ],
      "answer": "The horizontal and vertical components of the earth's magnetic field."
    },
    {
      "question": "For same bank angle and increased TAS, rate of turn will:",
      "choices": [
        "Remain unchanged",
        "Decrease",
        "Increase",
        "become zero"
      ],
      "answer": "Decrease"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select which of these errors would be expected from a direct-reading compass in situation described below: Southern hemisphere, heading West, accelerating.",
      "choices": [
        "Accurate",
        "Over-read",
        "Freeze",
        "Under-read"
      ],
      "answer": "Under-read"
    },
    {
      "question": "Needs an electrical supply to function.",
      "choices": [
        "Direct-reading",
        "Remote indicating",
        "Neither",
        "Both."
      ],
      "answer": "Remote indicating"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the turn indicator display?",
      "choices": [
        "Rate of change of heading.",
        "Rate of change of roll.",
        "Balance of the turn.",
        "Angle of bank."
      ],
      "answer": "Rate of change of heading."
    },
    {
      "question": "Directional gyros provide a __________ reference.",
      "choices": [
        "altitude",
        "heading",
        "attitude",
        "speed"
      ],
      "answer": "heading"
    },
    {
      "question": "Turning errors in a direct-reading compass can be mitigated by using __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Compensating magnets.",
        "An attitude indicator.",
        "A stopwatch.",
        "A GPS."
      ],
      "answer": "A stopwatch."
    },
    {
      "question": "During pre-flight check, serviceability of a direct reading standby compass indication can be compared preferably with:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 4 and 5",
        "1, 2, 3, 4 and 5",
        "1, 2 and 3",
        "1 and 2"
      ],
      "answer": "1 and 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "The basic properties of a gyroscope are: 1. Rigidity in space. 2. Nutation. 3. Gyroscopic precession. 4. Gyroscopic drift. The combination of all the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3.",
        "1, 2, 4.",
        "1, 3, 4.",
        "1, 3."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3."
    },
    {
      "question": "The rotational speed of an air-driven gyro is normally:",
      "choices": [
        "24 000 RPM.",
        "50 RPM.",
        "400-800 RPM.",
        "9000-12 000 RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "9000-12 000 RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Considering an air driven artificial horizon, when an aircraft decelerates on ground during the landing, the result is:",
      "choices": [
        "A false nose-up indication.",
        "A correct and constant pitch indication.",
        "A right or left wing down indication depending on the runway direction.",
        "A false nose-down indication."
      ],
      "answer": "A false nose-down indication."
    },
    {
      "question": "A Rate 1 turn:",
      "choices": [
        "Takes 3 minutes to turn through 180\u00b0.",
        "Takes 2 minutes to turn through 180\u00b0.",
        "Takes 1 minute to turn through 360\u00b0.",
        "Takes 2 minutes to turn through 360\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "Takes 2 minutes to turn through 360\u00b0."
    },
    {
      "question": "The north pole of a magnet repels the __________ pole of another magnet nearby, and attracts the __________ pole.",
      "choices": [
        "South; North",
        "North; South",
        "South; South",
        "North; North"
      ],
      "answer": "North; South"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot wishes to turn left on to a northerly heading with 10\u00b0 bank at a latitude of 50\u00b0 North. Using a direct reading compass, in order to achieve this he must stop the turn on an approximate heading of:",
      "choices": [
        "015\u00b0",
        "030\u00b0",
        "355\u00b0",
        "330\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "030\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a vacuum operated attitude indicator, automatic erection of the gyro is performed by:",
      "choices": [
        "Adjusting the miniature airplane.",
        "The pendulous unit.",
        "A caging device.",
        "A counter-weight on the horizon bar."
      ],
      "answer": "The pendulous unit."
    },
    {
      "question": "Has the most accurate and stable indications.",
      "choices": [
        "Direct-reading",
        "Remote indicating",
        "Both.",
        "Neither"
      ],
      "answer": "Remote indicating"
    },
    {
      "question": "Greatly enhanced by a soft iron core.",
      "choices": [
        "Electro",
        "Soft",
        "Hard",
        "Aero"
      ],
      "answer": "Electro"
    },
    {
      "question": "Gyroscopic rigidity depends on the gyroscope rotor's:",
      "choices": [
        "Mass distribution, material and power source.",
        "Mass distribution, rotational speed and mass.",
        "Sensed point of application of force and the distance its mass is from the spin axis.",
        "Mass, density and diameter."
      ],
      "answer": "Mass distribution, rotational speed and mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "It converts a weak AC into a signal capable of driving a small motor.",
      "choices": [
        "Detector Coil.",
        "Gyro Unit.",
        "Stator.",
        "Precession Amplifier"
      ],
      "answer": "Precession Amplifier"
    },
    {
      "question": "When a force is applied to the rotor of a gyro, the rotor moves as if the force was applied __________ degrees, in the direction of __________, from where it was applied.",
      "choices": [
        "90; rotation",
        "90; force",
        "180; rotation",
        "45; rotation"
      ],
      "answer": "90; rotation"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many gyros are in an AHRS (attitude and heading reference system)?",
      "choices": [
        "5",
        "2",
        "3",
        "4"
      ],
      "answer": "3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Proportional to the number of coils and to the current flow.",
      "choices": [
        "Soft",
        "Aero",
        "Electro",
        "Hard"
      ],
      "answer": "Electro"
    },
    {
      "question": "Suffers from jamming at some attitudes.",
      "choices": [
        "Direct-reading",
        "Neither",
        "Remote indicating",
        "Both."
      ],
      "answer": "Direct-reading"
    },
    {
      "question": "During flight, the ball of a slip indicator is central. What does this indicate? That the:",
      "choices": [
        "Sum of all forces is acting in the vertical gravitational plane.",
        "Aircraft rate of change of heading is equivalent to 3 degrees per second.",
        "Aircraft rate of change of yaw is equivalent to 3 degrees per second.",
        "Sum of all forces is acting through the normal axis of the aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "Sum of all forces is acting through the normal axis of the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "For increased rate of turn with same TAS, bank angle must:",
      "choices": [
        "Decrease",
        "Increase",
        "Reduce",
        "Remain unchanged"
      ],
      "answer": "Increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "Directional gyros are __________ tied.",
      "choices": [
        "vertically",
        "horizontally",
        "magnetic north",
        "spatially"
      ],
      "answer": "horizontally"
    },
    {
      "question": "A gyroscope is a device comprising a __________ mounted so that it can spin rapidly about its axis.",
      "choices": [
        "sphere",
        "motor",
        "solid disc",
        "solid gimbal"
      ],
      "answer": "solid disc"
    },
    {
      "question": "A standard pneumatic gyro AI is affected by acceleration, showing an erroneous indication of:",
      "choices": [
        "Pitch down and roll left.",
        "Pitch up and roll right.",
        "Pitch down and roll right.",
        "Pitch up and roll left."
      ],
      "answer": "Pitch up and roll right."
    },
    {
      "question": "Without any external action, the axis of a free gyroscope is fixed with reference to:",
      "choices": [
        "Space.",
        "The aircraft.",
        "The apparent vertical.",
        "The Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "Space."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying a true track of 360\u00b0 from 5\u00b0 south to 5\u00b0 north. What is the average apparent wander rate?",
      "choices": [
        "0\u00b0 per hour.",
        "Depends upon ground speed.",
        "- 5\u00b0 per hour.",
        "+ 5\u00b0 per hour."
      ],
      "answer": "0\u00b0 per hour."
    },
    {
      "question": "The rigidity of a gyro is improved by:",
      "choices": [
        "Decreasing RPM and concentrating the mass on the periphery of the rotor.",
        "Increasing RPM and concentrating the mass on the periphery of the rotor.",
        "Decreasing RPM and concentrating the mass at the hub of the rotor.",
        "Increasing RPM and concentrating the mass at the hub of the rotor."
      ],
      "answer": "Increasing RPM and concentrating the mass on the periphery of the rotor."
    },
    {
      "question": "Compass errors are accurately measured on various headings, and then minimised by adjusting __________ within the compass.",
      "choices": [
        "buttons",
        "magnets",
        "electromagnets",
        "screws"
      ],
      "answer": "magnets"
    },
    {
      "question": "A gyro with 1 gimbal has __________ axes of freedom and __________ degree of freedom.",
      "choices": [
        "2; 1",
        "1; 2",
        "2; 2",
        "1; 1"
      ],
      "answer": "2; 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select which of these errors would be expected from a direct-reading compass in situation described below: Northern hemisphere, heading North, accelerating.",
      "choices": [
        "Over-read",
        "Accurate",
        "Freeze",
        "Under-read"
      ],
      "answer": "Accurate"
    },
    {
      "question": "A gyro with 2 gimbals has __________ axes of freedom and __________ degrees of freedom.",
      "choices": [
        "3; 3",
        "2; 2",
        "2; 1",
        "3; 2"
      ],
      "answer": "3; 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "An AI gyro has __________ degrees of freedom.",
      "choices": [
        "2",
        "1",
        "0",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Manoeuvre causes directional gyro drift because the gyro starts erecting towards the aircraft's __________ during manoeuvres.",
      "choices": [
        "attitude",
        "altitude",
        "heading",
        "velocity"
      ],
      "answer": "attitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "A simple magnetic compass aligns itself with the __________ and __________ (Z component) of the Earth's magnetic field.",
      "choices": [
        "vertical; horizontal",
        "horizontal; vertical",
        "latitudinal; longitudinal",
        "isogonal; agonic"
      ],
      "answer": "horizontal; vertical"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ page shows departure, destination and alternate airfields.",
      "choices": [
        "Route",
        "Performance",
        "IDENT",
        "Position"
      ],
      "answer": "Route"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ position is normally derived from a mathematical analysis of IRS, GNSS, DME VOR and LOC information.",
      "choices": [
        "IRS",
        "FMC mix",
        "aircraft",
        "GPS"
      ],
      "answer": "FMC mix"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ __________ command bars are superimposed when selected by the pilot.",
      "choices": [
        "Flight director",
        "Flight organiser",
        "Flight supervisor",
        "Flight manager"
      ],
      "answer": "Flight director"
    },
    {
      "question": "A type of ADS-C contract often sent to multiple aircraft simultaneously is the \u2026",
      "choices": [
        "Demand contract.",
        "Event contract.",
        "Emergency contract.",
        "Period contract."
      ],
      "answer": "Demand contract."
    },
    {
      "question": "Plan mode is oriented __________. Heading information is not displayed. The currently selected waypoint (on the CDU) is displayed at the centre of the screen.",
      "choices": [
        "North down",
        "North up",
        "Track up",
        "Track down"
      ],
      "answer": "North up"
    },
    {
      "question": "ICAO CNS/ATM:",
      "choices": [
        "Is a type of FANS 1/B equipment.",
        "Is a protocol for data link based communication navigation and surveillance between ATCUs and aircraft.",
        "Is a protocol for satellite based navigation.",
        "Is a protocol for data link based communication between ATCUs and aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "Is a protocol for data link based communication navigation and surveillance between ATCUs and aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "PFD attitude information comprises an attitude indicator, with __________ symbol.",
      "choices": [
        "an aircraft",
        "a bank angle",
        "a pitch scale",
        "a horizon line"
      ],
      "answer": "an aircraft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The AIRAC cycle is __________days. Data is rigorously controlled and verified.",
      "choices": [
        "7",
        "30",
        "28",
        "14"
      ],
      "answer": "28"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the risks to the associated EFB application: Access to manuals: - __________or FCOM information required in flight may not be available.",
      "choices": [
        "MEL",
        "FCOM",
        "data entry",
        "charts"
      ],
      "answer": "MEL"
    },
    {
      "question": "ADS-C Period contracts....",
      "choices": [
        "Are sent every 8 minutes.",
        "Are sent at a time interval published in the AIP for the airspace concerned.",
        "Are sent every 5 minutes.",
        "Are sent at a time interval set by ATC when they establish the contract."
      ],
      "answer": "Are sent at a time interval set by ATC when they establish the contract."
    },
    {
      "question": "During alignment INS platforms are levelled and aligned with __________.",
      "choices": [
        "True North",
        "Magnetic South",
        "True South",
        "Magnetic North"
      ],
      "answer": "True North"
    },
    {
      "question": "Stand-alone INS typically has a position error of about __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "3 to 5 NM per hour.",
        "1 to 2 NM per hour.",
        "5 to 10 NM per hour.",
        "0.1 to 0.5 NM per hour."
      ],
      "answer": "1 to 2 NM per hour."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about the vertical speed display is/are correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Vertical speed is shown to the right of the speed tape.",
        "Vertical speed is shown on the PFD and ND",
        "The vertical speed display can show certain types of TCAS RA guidance information.",
        "Vertical speed is shown to the left of the altitude tape."
      ],
      "answer": "The vertical speed display can show certain types of TCAS RA guidance information."
    },
    {
      "question": "An accurate aircraft clock is important because:",
      "choices": [
        "It provides a time reference for FMC speed calculations.",
        "It provides a time reference for ACARS, ADS, CPDLC and engine and systems maintenance.",
        "GMT time is added to the radar plot of the aircraft when mode S is in use.",
        "It is used to calculate the time remaining to the active waypoint and groundspeed."
      ],
      "answer": "It provides a time reference for ACARS, ADS, CPDLC and engine and systems maintenance."
    },
    {
      "question": "During alignment, accelerometers and computers determine orientation of the local _____ relative to the aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "vertical",
        "horizontal",
        "longitudinal",
        "lateral"
      ],
      "answer": "vertical"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the initial alignment of an inertial navigation system (INS) the equipment:",
      "choices": [
        "Will accept a 10\u00b0 error in initial latitude and initial longitude.",
        "Will not accept a 10\u00b0 error in initial latitude but will accept a 10\u00b0 error in initial longitude.",
        "Will accept a 10\u00b0 error in initial latitude but will not accept a 10\u00b0 error in initial longitude.",
        "Will not accept a 10\u00b0 error in initial latitude or initial longitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Will not accept a 10\u00b0 error in initial latitude but will accept a 10\u00b0 error in initial longitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "The next database in the AIRAC cycle is loaded into the system by the __________ several days before the effective date.",
      "choices": [
        "ATC",
        "engineers",
        "flight despatcher",
        "crew"
      ],
      "answer": "engineers"
    },
    {
      "question": "The radio altimeter's antenna beam width is __________ to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "very narrow; eliminate all sensing errors",
        "sufficiently wide; eliminate all sensing errors",
        "sufficiently wide; allow for typical pitch and roll attitudes",
        "very narrow; allow for typical pitch and roll attitudes"
      ],
      "answer": "very narrow; allow for typical pitch and roll attitudes"
    },
    {
      "question": "During alignment IRS platforms determine the __________ and establish aircraft __________ heading.",
      "choices": [
        "vertical; true",
        "vertical; magnetic",
        "horizontal; true",
        "horizontal; magnetic"
      ],
      "answer": "vertical; true"
    },
    {
      "question": "Selecting 'NAV' on the IRS / ADIRU controller:",
      "choices": [
        "Set the unit in normal operation.",
        "Sets a reversion mode for when the ADC fails.",
        "Selects radio navigation in preference to inertial position information.",
        "Forces the FMC to use the IRU position in preference to GPS."
      ],
      "answer": "Set the unit in normal operation."
    },
    {
      "question": "With an RLG system __________ can begin within a few seconds.",
      "choices": [
        "navigation",
        "alignment",
        "calculation",
        "data entry"
      ],
      "answer": "alignment"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which feature matches which system? An enhanced database used as reference to show ground features and obstructions on the PFD or HUD.",
      "choices": [
        "AVS",
        "SVS",
        "EVS",
        "CVS"
      ],
      "answer": "SVS"
    },
    {
      "question": "The FMA is:",
      "choices": [
        "Only useful when conducting an autoland.",
        "Typically at the bottom of the PFD, and shows when the autopilot and auto thrust are engaged or armed.",
        "Typically on the ND, and comprises boxes showing RNP, ANP and position error.",
        "Typically at the top of the PFD, and comprises boxes showing auto thrust, lateral and vertical modes engaged or armed."
      ],
      "answer": "Typically at the top of the PFD, and comprises boxes showing auto thrust, lateral and vertical modes engaged or armed."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which feature matches which system? Enables reduced minima on take-off and landing because of the greater visibility afforded to the pilot.",
      "choices": [
        "EVS",
        "CVS",
        "SVS",
        "AVS"
      ],
      "answer": "EVS"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a radio altimeter, filtering prioritises the __________ frequency shift, so __________ surface is measured.",
      "choices": [
        "lowest; smoothest",
        "highest; nearest",
        "highest; furthest",
        "lowest; nearest"
      ],
      "answer": "lowest; nearest"
    },
    {
      "question": "A typical EFIS installation consists of:",
      "choices": [
        "1 PFD DU and 1 ND DU per pilot, with EICAS DUs in the centre. They are not interchangeable but each can show all data.",
        "1 DU for each pilot and 2 central DUs which share information.",
        "3 identical DUs per pilot, with the inner one of each being able to share information or transfer data.",
        "2 identical DUs per pilot, with 2 more in the centre for other information. Data may be transferred from one display to another if a DU fails."
      ],
      "answer": "2 identical DUs per pilot, with 2 more in the centre for other information. Data may be transferred from one display to another if a DU fails."
    },
    {
      "question": "Computer connecting to ground services using the most cost-effective means available.",
      "choices": [
        "Printer",
        "DCDU",
        "Annunciator",
        "ATSU"
      ],
      "answer": "ATSU"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which annunciator will be lit until the system is ready for use?",
      "choices": [
        "ALIGN.",
        "ATT. Attitude.",
        "FAULT.",
        "NAV. Navigation."
      ],
      "answer": "ALIGN."
    },
    {
      "question": "With an older generation mechanical rate gyro, rotation about the sensed axis causes _________ which is measured and used to calculate the rotation rate of the platform.",
      "choices": [
        "wander",
        "frequency shift",
        "precession",
        "topple"
      ],
      "answer": "precession"
    },
    {
      "question": "EFB software 'type' certification can be either:",
      "choices": [
        "Type 1 - small risks from misuse or malfunction, or Type 2 - larger risks from misuse of malfunction.",
        "Type A - No measured risk from misuse or malfunction, and Type B - acceptable measured risk from misuse or malfunction.",
        "Type A - Misuse or malfunction has no adverse effect on flight safety, and Type B - applications where evaluation of the hazards presented by misuse or malfunction are required.",
        "Type 1 - no adverse effects on flight safety if it fails, or Type 2 - minor risk of major incident if it fails."
      ],
      "answer": "Type A - Misuse or malfunction has no adverse effect on flight safety, and Type B - applications where evaluation of the hazards presented by misuse or malfunction are required."
    },
    {
      "question": "A standby instrument system is necessary in case of complete EFIS failure. These instruments are __________.",
      "choices": [
        "either mechanical or electronic",
        "always electronic",
        "always mechanical",
        "never used"
      ],
      "answer": "either mechanical or electronic"
    },
    {
      "question": "To obtain at a given moment the instantaneous speed from the accelerations:",
      "choices": [
        "it is necessary to integrate the acceleration once with respect to time, and to know the initial speed and the initial position.",
        "it is necessary to integrate the acceleration once with respect to time, and to know the initial position only.",
        "it is necessary to integrate the acceleration once with respect to time, and to know the Initial speed only.",
        "integrating the acceleration once with respect to time is sufficient."
      ],
      "answer": "it is necessary to integrate the acceleration once with respect to time, and to know the Initial speed only."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the characteristics of the communication links that are used in aircraft: Medium transmission rate:",
      "choices": [
        "Annunciator",
        "VHF",
        "SATCOM",
        "HF"
      ],
      "answer": "HF"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the characteristics of the communication links that are used in aircraft: Global coverage:",
      "choices": [
        "HF",
        "SATCOM",
        "VHF",
        "VHF & SATCOM"
      ],
      "answer": "SATCOM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is true?",
      "choices": [
        "Either MAP or PLAN mode should be used for navigation during the cruise of flight.",
        "ND display mode selections should be left unchanged during flight.",
        "Appropriate range, mode and data selections made in flight can improve situation awareness.",
        "To avoid confusion, ND range selections should be left unchanged in flight, but display mode selections may be necessary."
      ],
      "answer": "Appropriate range, mode and data selections made in flight can improve situation awareness."
    },
    {
      "question": "The type of ADS-C contract where multiple contracts can be established with the same aircraft simultaneously is the\u2026",
      "choices": [
        "Emergency contract.",
        "Demand contract.",
        "Period contract.",
        "Event contract."
      ],
      "answer": "Event contract."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ page shows SIDs, airways and STARs.",
      "choices": [
        "Position",
        "Performance",
        "IDENT",
        "Route"
      ],
      "answer": "Route"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the risks to the associated EFB application: Performance calculations: - errors of __________ or calculation could result in runway overrun.",
      "choices": [
        "MEL",
        "data entry",
        "charts",
        "FCOM"
      ],
      "answer": "data entry"
    },
    {
      "question": "PLAN mode is used __________.",
      "choices": [
        "for flying your flight plan in flight.",
        "for checking your flight plan before flight.",
        "for aligning the IRS.",
        "during takeoff and landing."
      ],
      "answer": "for checking your flight plan before flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the characteristics of the communication links that are used in aircraft: Short-range (line of sight):",
      "choices": [
        "VHF & SATCOM",
        "SATCOM",
        "HF",
        "VHF"
      ],
      "answer": "VHF"
    },
    {
      "question": "The area of the CDU screen reserved for data entry, before it is inserted into the system, is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "The scratchpad.",
        "A compulsory data field.",
        "An optional data field.",
        "The data line."
      ],
      "answer": "The scratchpad."
    },
    {
      "question": "Selecting 'ATT' on the IRS control panel:",
      "choices": [
        "Is done following a failure indication to recover attitude information only.",
        "Allows a fast-align of the IRUs and will recover NAV functionality if the aircraft is straight and level.",
        "Allows updating of position as a navigation facility is overflown at a known time.",
        "Starts the auto-alignment process."
      ],
      "answer": "Is done following a failure indication to recover attitude information only."
    },
    {
      "question": "There are always 2 navigation databases: the __________ and the standby databases.",
      "choices": [
        "latest",
        "effective",
        "current",
        "active"
      ],
      "answer": "active"
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio height is used for various auto-flight and system functions. Loss of signal may result in:",
      "choices": [
        "Loss of vertical speed information below 1000 ft.",
        "Loss of altitude information below 2500 ft.",
        "Reversion from fail active to fail passive autoland capability.",
        "Degraded function of systems requiring a radio height input."
      ],
      "answer": "Degraded function of systems requiring a radio height input."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a ring laser gyro, the dither motor prevents lock-in:",
      "choices": [
        "At low input rotational rates.",
        "At all rotational rates.",
        "At high input rotational rates.",
        "At zero rotational rates"
      ],
      "answer": "At low input rotational rates."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which feature matches which system? Has limited sensitivity because it uses temperature and temperature differences to produce an image.",
      "choices": [
        "AVS",
        "EVS",
        "CVS",
        "SVS"
      ],
      "answer": "EVS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Waypoints can be entered in an INS memory in different formats. In which of the following formats can waypoints be entered into all INSs?",
      "choices": [
        "By Waypoints name",
        "Geographical co-ordinates",
        "Hexadecimal",
        "Bearing and distance"
      ],
      "answer": "Geographical co-ordinates"
    },
    {
      "question": "INS/IRS are the main source of __________ data, and one of the main sources of navigation data in commercial aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "heading",
        "direction",
        "altitude",
        "attitude"
      ],
      "answer": "attitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "Compared with a conventional gyro, a laser gyro:",
      "choices": [
        "Has a fairly long starting cycle.",
        "Has a longer life cycle.",
        "Consumes a lot of power.",
        "Is influenced by temperature."
      ],
      "answer": "Has a longer life cycle."
    },
    {
      "question": "The sensors of an INS measure:",
      "choices": [
        "Precession.",
        "Acceleration.",
        "Velocity.",
        "The horizontal component of the earth's rotation."
      ],
      "answer": "Acceleration."
    },
    {
      "question": "Stand-alone INS can calculate which of the following, when also provided with reference to a variation database:",
      "choices": [
        "Latitude and longitude.",
        "Wind direction and speed.",
        "True heading and true track.",
        "Magnetic heading and track."
      ],
      "answer": "Magnetic heading and track."
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio Altimeter is calibrated to show __________ height in the landing attitude.",
      "choices": [
        "fuselage tail cone",
        "wheel",
        "flight deck",
        "lowest point"
      ],
      "answer": "wheel"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the risks to the associated EFB application: Mass and balance calculations: - errors could result in __________ or out-of-limits loading",
      "choices": [
        "FCOM",
        "charts",
        "data entry",
        "over-weight"
      ],
      "answer": "over-weight"
    },
    {
      "question": "The data used, and the code giving the instructions to the computer about what to do with the data, are known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Hardware.",
        "Interface.",
        "Software.",
        "Equipment."
      ],
      "answer": "Software."
    },
    {
      "question": "Expanded map modes show similar data to full/rose modes but show a compass arc of about __________ degrees.",
      "choices": [
        "180",
        "90",
        "120",
        "45"
      ],
      "answer": "90"
    },
    {
      "question": "NAV' is selected on the IRS or ADIRU control panel. If alignment is complete the system will go into __________ mode. If alignment hasn't been carried out, the system will __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Initial Position; automatically enter ALIGN mode",
        "Navigation; automatically enter ALIGN mode",
        "Navigation; navigate with reduced accuracy",
        "Alignment; automatically enter ALIGN mode"
      ],
      "answer": "Navigation; automatically enter ALIGN mode"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which feature matches which system? Uses external sensors such as IR cameras to generate a real-time image on the PFD or HUD.",
      "choices": [
        "CVS",
        "EVS",
        "AVS",
        "SVS"
      ],
      "answer": "EVS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Can receive messages from the ground and the flight deck.",
      "choices": [
        "DCDU",
        "Annunciator",
        "CDU/MCDU",
        "Printer"
      ],
      "answer": "Printer"
    },
    {
      "question": "ADS-C Emergency contracts are:",
      "choices": [
        "Established by ATC after receiving a PAN PAN or a MAYDAY call. They require downlinks every minute.",
        "Established by the pilot. They highlight the aircraft to ATC and send frequent downlinks.",
        "Established by either ATC or the crew in response to any emergency.",
        "Established by the aircraft automatically when a Master Warning is triggered."
      ],
      "answer": "Established by the pilot. They highlight the aircraft to ATC and send frequent downlinks."
    },
    {
      "question": "The aircraft must be __________ during alignment, so in-flight realignment is __________, although you may be able to recover attitude information.",
      "choices": [
        "moving; unreliable",
        "unpowered; slower",
        "stationary; not possible",
        "stationary; unreliable"
      ],
      "answer": "stationary; not possible"
    },
    {
      "question": "A message or data downlink means:",
      "choices": [
        "a transmission of signals from an aircraft in flight to a station on the Earth.",
        "uploading ATIS / weather / maintenance data to an airborne unit.",
        "downloading ATIS / weather / maintenance data from a ground control unit via the onboard Internet connection.",
        "downloading and printing the ATC clearance from the Controller Pilot Data Link Communication (CPDLC)."
      ],
      "answer": "a transmission of signals from an aircraft in flight to a station on the Earth."
    },
    {
      "question": "A computer, its associated equipment, and the devices used to input and output data are known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Software.",
        "Interface.",
        "Hardware.",
        "Equipment."
      ],
      "answer": "Hardware."
    },
    {
      "question": "FANS was developed by ICAO:",
      "choices": [
        "To effectively monitor aircraft systems' status information and fuel consumption.",
        "To allow more aircraft to safely and efficiently utilise a given volume of airspace.",
        "To provide a more efficient, safe, and cost-effective system for communication.",
        "In order to automate and distribute departure slots."
      ],
      "answer": "To allow more aircraft to safely and efficiently utilise a given volume of airspace."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the purpose of an onboard ATSU?",
      "choices": [
        "Manages the data link information exchange between the. aircraft and the Air Traffic.",
        "Thrust management.",
        "Fuel management.",
        "Management of the Human Machine Interface."
      ],
      "answer": "Manages the data link information exchange between the. aircraft and the Air Traffic."
    },
    {
      "question": "Strap-down systems are fixed to the aircraft structure and normally consist of __________ and 3 accelerometers.",
      "choices": [
        "2 rate gyros",
        "2 ring laser gyros",
        "3 ring laser gyros",
        "3 earth gyros"
      ],
      "answer": "3 ring laser gyros"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which feature matches which system? Limited because it is not based on sensory information so cannot reduce your approach minima.",
      "choices": [
        "AVS",
        "SVS",
        "CVS",
        "EVS"
      ],
      "answer": "SVS"
    },
    {
      "question": "IRS is a self-contained system because:",
      "choices": [
        "The system has a battery back-up which guarantees the well-functioning of the system in case of power-failure.",
        "The system has the ability to calculate the aircraft\u2019s position with an accuracy comparable to the GPS& position",
        "The system calculates the position of the aircraft without reference to externally generated (man-made) signals.",
        "The system has the ability to calculate the aircraft\u2019s radio position without any reference to either man &made or natural information"
      ],
      "answer": "The system calculates the position of the aircraft without reference to externally generated (man-made) signals."
    },
    {
      "question": "During an instrument approach procedure, which of the following heights are radio altimeter alerts related to?",
      "choices": [
        "terrain",
        "obstacle",
        "runway",
        "decision"
      ],
      "answer": "decision"
    },
    {
      "question": "Because of their location, standby instruments may be challenging to use from the__________ seat.",
      "choices": [
        "right",
        "left",
        "jump",
        "observer's"
      ],
      "answer": "right"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary advantage of an external digital data-bus is:",
      "choices": [
        "Reduced requirement for electromagnetic shielding.",
        "Reduced weight.",
        "Increased speed of transmission.",
        "Multiple redundant data paths within a single cable."
      ],
      "answer": "Reduced weight."
    },
    {
      "question": "A machine which manipulates data according to a list of instructions is called a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "sensor",
        "computer",
        "transducer",
        "interface"
      ],
      "answer": "computer"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an inertial navigation systems, a TAS input is:",
      "choices": [
        "Required for the Automatic Flight Control System (AFCS) to compute a heading according to track.",
        "Required for polar navigation only.",
        "Not required.",
        "Required to provide a wind direction and velocity read out."
      ],
      "answer": "Required to provide a wind direction and velocity read out."
    },
    {
      "question": "Informs pilots of the receipt of messages.",
      "choices": [
        "Printer",
        "CDU/MCDU",
        "ATSU",
        "Annunciator"
      ],
      "answer": "Annunciator"
    },
    {
      "question": "Used where integration cannot provide functionality needed.",
      "choices": [
        "CDU/MCDU",
        "DCDU",
        "Annunciator",
        "Printer"
      ],
      "answer": "DCDU"
    },
    {
      "question": "ACARS allows air/ground datalink communications for:",
      "choices": [
        "Airline Operational Communication only (AOC).",
        "Air Traffic Control Communication only (ATC).",
        "Airline Operational and Air Traffic Communications (AOC & ATC).",
        "Airline Operational and Public Communications (AOC & PC)."
      ],
      "answer": "Airline Operational and Air Traffic Communications (AOC & ATC)."
    },
    {
      "question": "The strapdown IRS:",
      "choices": [
        "Is located away from the aircraft CG and uses laser gyros to calculate accelerations.",
        "Is located close to the aircraft CG, and uses laser gyros to calculate angular movements.",
        "ls most reliable with a low frequency laser beam.",
        "Consists of gyros and accelerometers. The gyros keep the platform level and the accelerometers calculate acceleration."
      ],
      "answer": "Is located close to the aircraft CG, and uses laser gyros to calculate angular movements."
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio altitude is shown numerically on PFD when the aircraft is at or below 2500 ft. On many aircraft it changes to a white analogue display during the approach. It changes to an amber colour on descent through __________.",
      "choices": [
        "DH",
        "the Mapt",
        "500 ft",
        "MDA"
      ],
      "answer": "DH"
    },
    {
      "question": "How long will the ADIRU alignment approximately take at around 60\u00b0 North?",
      "choices": [
        "More than 30 minutes.",
        "5 minutes.",
        "30 seconds.",
        "10 minutes."
      ],
      "answer": "10 minutes."
    },
    {
      "question": "The radio altimeter uses __________ wave, __________ modulated transmission.",
      "choices": [
        "continuous; amplitude",
        "intermittent; amplitude",
        "continuous; frequency",
        "intermittent; frequency"
      ],
      "answer": "continuous; frequency"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which feature matches which system? A system integrating 2 systems to give a wide angle of view, combined with a real-time image.",
      "choices": [
        "SVS",
        "EVS",
        "AVS",
        "CVS"
      ],
      "answer": "CVS"
    },
    {
      "question": "The radio altimeter has __________ antenna,__________ for transmission, __________ for reception.",
      "choices": [
        "2; 1; 1",
        "3; 1; 2",
        "2; 2; 0",
        "3; 2; 1"
      ],
      "answer": "2; 1; 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The principle of a laser gyro is based on:",
      "choices": [
        "Frequency difference between 2 laser beams rotating in opposite direction.",
        "A gyroscope associated with a laser compensating for apparent wander due to the rotation of the earth.",
        "A gyroscope associated with a laser compensating for gimballing errors.",
        "2 rotating cavities provided with mirrors."
      ],
      "answer": "Frequency difference between 2 laser beams rotating in opposite direction."
    },
    {
      "question": "A data field, identified by empty boxes, is a:",
      "choices": [
        "A compulsory data field.",
        "The scratchpad.",
        "An optional data field.",
        "The title line."
      ],
      "answer": "A compulsory data field."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the characteristics of the communication links that are used in aircraft: High quality transmission:",
      "choices": [
        "SATCOM",
        "HF",
        "VHF",
        "VHF & SATCOM"
      ],
      "answer": "VHF & SATCOM"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a peripheral device like a printer or a supplemental hard drive directly connected to a computer?",
      "choices": [
        "Via the internal bus(ses).",
        "Via the read-only memory.",
        "Via the central processing unit.",
        "Via the external bus(ses)."
      ],
      "answer": "Via the external bus(ses)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the risks to the associated EFB application: Access to charts: - Approach __________ necessary for a safe approach may be unavailable.",
      "choices": [
        "over-weight",
        "charts",
        "data entry",
        "FCOM"
      ],
      "answer": "charts"
    },
    {
      "question": "A traditional ring laser gyro (RLG) uses two laser beams travelling in __________ around a triangular path. The differences in the distances travelled due to the device's rotation causes a slight __________ which is measured to calculate the unit's rotation rate.",
      "choices": [
        "the same direction; wave amplitude change",
        "opposite directions; frequency shift",
        "the same direction; frequency shift",
        "opposite directions; wave amplitude change"
      ],
      "answer": "opposite directions; frequency shift"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which feature matches which system? Has safety implications if the aircraft's positioning accuracy is degraded.",
      "choices": [
        "SVS",
        "CVS",
        "EVS",
        "AVS"
      ],
      "answer": "SVS"
    },
    {
      "question": "On modern aircraft you will normally find 2, or more commonly 3:",
      "choices": [
        "IRUs and a combined air data concentrator.",
        "Air Data Inertial Reference Units (ADIRUs) each integrating an ADC and an IRU.",
        "Inertial Navigation Systems with integrated Air Data Compensators.",
        "Air data systems and a combined inertial reference unit"
      ],
      "answer": "Air Data Inertial Reference Units (ADIRUs) each integrating an ADC and an IRU."
    },
    {
      "question": "The IRU's performance is checked post-flight by looking either at each unit\u2019s residual __________ or the difference between each IRU's position and the position calculated by __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "topple rate; the FMC",
        "groundspeed; the FMC",
        "topple rate; the crew",
        "groundspeed; the crew"
      ],
      "answer": "groundspeed; the FMC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum altitude at which a radio altimeter provides indications?",
      "choices": [
        "2500",
        "1000",
        "50",
        "100"
      ],
      "answer": "2500"
    },
    {
      "question": "Aircraft position is __________ during alignment, which takes around __________ minutes at mid latitude, longer at higher latitudes.",
      "choices": [
        "entered; 5",
        "determined; 10 to 20",
        "available; 10 to 20",
        "entered; 10 to 20"
      ],
      "answer": "entered; 10 to 20"
    },
    {
      "question": "A carrier wave with a linear ramp modulation is continuously transmitted by the radio altimeter. The system compares the __________ of the transmitted and received signals to determine the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "frequency; height above datum",
        "wavelength; height above datum",
        "strength; height above the surface",
        "frequency; height above the surface"
      ],
      "answer": "frequency; height above the surface"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the advantages of the RLG compared with a mechanical gyro system is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "reduced time before alignment begins.",
        "the ability to sense angular rotation in more than one plane.",
        "they are more expensive, but relatively better value for money in terms of accuracy versus cost.",
        "they have very high-speed moving parts, providing greater accuracy."
      ],
      "answer": "reduced time before alignment begins."
    },
    {
      "question": "Early gyro-mechanically stabilised systems are conventionally called __________, while strap-down systems are called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "INS; IRS",
        "IRS; INS",
        "FMS; FMC",
        "AHRS; ADIRU"
      ],
      "answer": "INS; IRS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Stand-alone INS can calculate which of the following, with the additional input of TAS:",
      "choices": [
        "Magnetic heading and track.",
        "Latitude and longitude.",
        "True heading and true track.",
        "Wind direction and speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Wind direction and speed."
    },
    {
      "question": "Digital data is moved within and between computers and input/output devices via a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "ethernet cable",
        "data-bus",
        "data concentrator",
        "serial port"
      ],
      "answer": "data-bus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Routes where the FANS-1/A concept is used:",
      "choices": [
        "Are used during high traffic times only.",
        "Are designated for FANS with sequence number.",
        "Are controlled by global ICAO ATC units.",
        "Require specific RNP capabilities."
      ],
      "answer": "Require specific RNP capabilities."
    },
    {
      "question": "The FANS concept makes use of:",
      "choices": [
        "Satellite communication and satellite navigation.",
        "Conventional communication only and satellite navigation.",
        "Voice communication for air navigation system position updating.",
        "VOR-DME position updating for air navigation."
      ],
      "answer": "Satellite communication and satellite navigation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Comparing the media used to transmit datalink communications, the appropriate classification from the slowest to the fastest data transmission rate is:",
      "choices": [
        "SATCOM, HF datalink, VHF datalink.",
        "SATCOM, VHF datalink, HF datalink.",
        "HF datalink, SATCOM, VHF datalink.",
        "HF datalink, VHF datalink, SATCOM."
      ],
      "answer": "HF datalink, VHF datalink, SATCOM."
    },
    {
      "question": "A data entry field containing underscore dashes is a:",
      "choices": [
        "Scratchpad area.",
        "Compulsory data field.",
        "Optional data field.",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "Optional data field."
    },
    {
      "question": "Selected Mach number is indicated by the:",
      "choices": [
        "Speed bug on a corresponding IAS on the tape, with the Mach number shown on the MCP speed window.",
        "Speed bug on a corresponding IAS on the tape, with the Mach number shown as a numerical indication outside the tape.",
        "FMC CDU, because the speed tape only shows IAS.",
        "IAS values on the speed tape changing to Mach at the crossover altitude. The selected Mach number is in an enlarged font."
      ],
      "answer": "Speed bug on a corresponding IAS on the tape, with the Mach number shown as a numerical indication outside the tape."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ have ultimate responsibility for ensuring that the new database is made active on the effective date.",
      "choices": [
        "Crew",
        "Flight despatchers",
        "Engineers",
        "ATC"
      ],
      "answer": "Crew"
    },
    {
      "question": "A stable platform inertial navigation system uses:",
      "choices": [
        "A single platform with 2 accelerometers.",
        "2 separate platforms with 2 gyroscopes.",
        "2 separate platforms with 2 accelerometers.",
        "A single platform with two gyroscopes."
      ],
      "answer": "A single platform with 2 accelerometers."
    },
    {
      "question": "Decision altitude/height is shown:",
      "choices": [
        "On the altitude tape next to the corresponding barometric altitude.",
        "Numerically on the ND, then decision altitude as an index on the radio altimeter dial display.",
        "On the ND at the top right",
        "Numerically on the PFD, and then decision height as an index on the radio altitude dial display."
      ],
      "answer": "Numerically on the PFD, and then decision height as an index on the radio altitude dial display."
    },
    {
      "question": "Any colour except red, amber, yellow or green alert lights, captions and messages.",
      "choices": [
        "Advisory",
        "Warning",
        "Caution",
        "Instant"
      ],
      "answer": "Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane has a yaw damper that is unserviceable, and by the MEL is restricted to fly only at or below FL170. What is the potential problem that the yaw damper is intended to prevent from happening at high altitudes?",
      "choices": [
        "Excessive longitudinal stability.",
        "Dutch roll.",
        "Excessive directional stability.",
        "Spiral instability."
      ],
      "answer": "Dutch roll."
    },
    {
      "question": "Modes enter this state when selected only if certain criteria are met.",
      "choices": [
        "Armed",
        "Engaged",
        "Selected",
        "Active"
      ],
      "answer": "Armed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode 'Localizer ARM' active on Flight Director means:",
      "choices": [
        "Coupling has occurred and system provides control data to capture the centreline.",
        "Localizer is armed and coupling will occur when flag warning disappears.",
        "System is armed for localizer approach and coupling will occur upon capturing centre line.",
        "Localizer approach not authorized."
      ],
      "answer": "System is armed for localizer approach and coupling will occur upon capturing centre line."
    },
    {
      "question": "When using AP or FD: Data being used must be checked via the FMS CDU/MCDU and modes must be checked via the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "ND",
        "HIS",
        "FMA",
        "PFD"
      ],
      "answer": "FMA"
    },
    {
      "question": "The correction of the control surface deflection made by the automatic pilot calculator... The combination of all the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3.",
        "1, 2.",
        "1, 2, 3, 4.",
        "2, 3, 4."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2."
    },
    {
      "question": "If autoland downgrade occurs after alert height:",
      "choices": [
        "It will not be annunciated, but a further downgrade, preventing autoland, causes AP disconnection and requires an immediate go-around.",
        "It will not be annunciated but you must initiate an immediate go-around.",
        "It will be annunciated because an immediate go-around is required.",
        "It will be annunciated. Continue only if visual references permit a manual landing."
      ],
      "answer": "It will not be annunciated, but a further downgrade, preventing autoland, causes AP disconnection and requires an immediate go-around."
    },
    {
      "question": "LAND3' implies __________ APs engaged or __________ multi-channel AP(s) engaged. This gives a __________ autoland capability.",
      "choices": [
        "2; 2; fail-operational",
        "2; 2; fail-passive",
        "3; 2; fail-operational",
        "3; 2; fail-passive"
      ],
      "answer": "3; 2; fail-operational"
    },
    {
      "question": "Requires a HUD, EVS and/or CVS.",
      "choices": [
        "FOALS",
        "FPALS",
        "FOHLS",
        "CAT IIILS"
      ],
      "answer": "FOHLS"
    },
    {
      "question": "The PF makes mode and parameter selections.",
      "choices": [
        "Both",
        "Manual",
        "Automatic",
        "Neither"
      ],
      "answer": "Automatic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Stall warnings may comprise: aerodynamic buffet, warning lights, buzzers or messages, and a __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "stick pusher",
        "stick shaker",
        "clacker",
        "vocal warning"
      ],
      "answer": "stick shaker"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of an autoland system is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Reduce aircraft wear through smoother landings and gentler braking.",
        "Allow landing in higher crosswinds.",
        "Allow landing with no minimum visibility.",
        "Allow landing in visibility too low for a manual landing."
      ],
      "answer": "Allow landing in visibility too low for a manual landing."
    },
    {
      "question": "The overspeed warning on a conventional ASI is the VMO/MMO pointer.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Sometimes",
        "Not applicable"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a final approach, the flight director is engaged in the G/S mode (tracking the ILS Glide Slope). If the horizontal command bar is deviating upward, it means that:",
      "choices": [
        "The aircraft is below the glide slope.",
        "The pitch angle must be reduced.",
        "The aircraft is above the glide slope.",
        "The pitch angle must be increased."
      ],
      "answer": "The pitch angle must be increased."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is NOT true?",
      "choices": [
        "The magnitude of autopilot output signals increase with decreasing airspeed.",
        "Autopilot output pitch signals vary with flap setting to account for the associated changes in longitudinal stability.",
        "The magnitude of autopilot output signals diminishes with increasing speed.",
        "Landing gear and flap positions have no effect on autopilot output signal magnitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Landing gear and flap positions have no effect on autopilot output signal magnitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a modern aircraft, the flight director modes are displayed on the:",
      "choices": [
        "Control panel of the flight director only.",
        "Upper strip of the ND (Navigation Display).",
        "Upper strip of the PFD (Primary Flight Display).",
        "Upper strip of the ECAM (Electronic Centralised A/C Management)."
      ],
      "answer": "Upper strip of the PFD (Primary Flight Display)."
    },
    {
      "question": "The computer of the autopilot system uses, among others, input signals from the... The combination of all the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3, 4.",
        "1, 4.",
        "2, 3.",
        "1, 3, 4."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "The A/T controls air speed:",
      "choices": [
        "By varying engine thrust, except when in TOGA mode.",
        "Only by varying engine thrust.",
        "Either by varying engine thrust or by varying the aircraft's pitch attitude.",
        "Either by varying engine thrust or by varying aircraft's pitch attitude, depending on the aircraft type."
      ],
      "answer": "Either by varying engine thrust or by varying the aircraft's pitch attitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "For large EFIS aircraft, an aural warning associated with overspeed warning is required.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only in cruise",
        "Not required"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sequences modes when a descent is started.",
      "choices": [
        "Thrust",
        "Retard/Idle",
        "Retard/Arm",
        "Speed"
      ],
      "answer": "Retard/Arm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Immediate awareness and later response required.",
      "choices": [
        "Caution",
        "Advisory",
        "Instant",
        "Warning"
      ],
      "answer": "Caution"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thrust is modulated as required to achieve and maintain the parameter set in the FMS or on the MCP.",
      "choices": [
        "Thrust",
        "Retard/Idle",
        "Speed",
        "%MCT%TOGA"
      ],
      "answer": "Speed"
    },
    {
      "question": "The VMO/MMO pointer is a large red and white 'barber's pole' indicating the lower of VMO and MMO against the airspeed scale.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only on some aircraft",
        "This is VNE"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "If an autoland capability downgrade occurs before alert height:",
      "choices": [
        "It will be annunciated. Go-around if RVR is too high for reversion. If RVR permits reversion continue using a higher approach category with a lower DH.",
        "You may continue the autoland approach with only 1 channel because the risk of a further failure, in the short time remaining, is deemed minimal.",
        "It will be annunciated. Go-around if RVR is too low for reversion. If RVR permits, continue the approach using a lower approach category with a higher DH.",
        "It will not be annunciated."
      ],
      "answer": "It will be annunciated. Go-around if RVR is too low for reversion. If RVR permits, continue the approach using a lower approach category with a higher DH."
    },
    {
      "question": "In fly-by-wire (FBW) aircraft, auto-trim functions during automatic and manual flight.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only in manual",
        "Only in automatic"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "N1 or EPR passed from the FMS is the target.",
      "choices": [
        "Retard/Idle",
        "Thrust",
        "Speed",
        "%MCT%TOGA"
      ],
      "answer": "Thrust"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode has a box around it for a period of time.",
      "choices": [
        "Armed",
        "Reversion",
        "Engaged",
        "Selected"
      ],
      "answer": "Engaged"
    },
    {
      "question": "Immediate awareness and response required.",
      "choices": [
        "Caution",
        "Advisory",
        "Instant",
        "Warning"
      ],
      "answer": "Warning"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight envelope protection (FEP) systems:",
      "choices": [
        "Actively prevent the aircraft from exceeding any aerodynamic limit.",
        "Actively resist the aircraft approaching any safety margin.",
        "Passively resist bank or roll exceeding set fixed values.",
        "Actively resist the aircraft leaving the normal flight envelope."
      ],
      "answer": "Actively resist the aircraft leaving the normal flight envelope."
    },
    {
      "question": "Low frequency.",
      "choices": [
        "Rudder control",
        "Yaw Damper",
        "Aileron trim",
        "Elevator trim"
      ],
      "answer": "Rudder control"
    },
    {
      "question": "The aircraft follows a predefined rate of change of trajectory to achieve the new parameter.",
      "choices": [
        "Initial Phase",
        "Holding Phase",
        "Capture Phase",
        "Transition Phase"
      ],
      "answer": "Capture Phase"
    },
    {
      "question": "This phase is sometimes also known as the tracking phase.",
      "choices": [
        "Holding Phase",
        "Capture Phase",
        "Initial Phase",
        "Following Phase"
      ],
      "answer": "Holding Phase"
    },
    {
      "question": "Energy awareness\u2026",
      "choices": [
        "Is never adequate with A/T engaged; manual thrust control is always safer.",
        "Is unaffected by A/T because the noise of the engines provides adequate cues.",
        "Can be lowered if you don't carefully monitor your speed and thrust setting.",
        "Is always improved by using autothrust."
      ],
      "answer": "Can be lowered if you don't carefully monitor your speed and thrust setting."
    },
    {
      "question": "The flight envelope protection system prevents the aircraft from exceeding the limits of the following parameters... The combination that of all correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3, 4, 5.",
        "2, 3, 4, 5.",
        "2, 3, 4.",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "2, 3, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "High frequency.",
      "choices": [
        "Yaw Damper",
        "Rudder control",
        "Aileron control",
        "Elevator control"
      ],
      "answer": "Yaw Damper"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is a valid description of the requirements for warnings, cautions and advisories?",
      "choices": [
        "Warnings must be in direct line-of-sight when seated. Typically attention-getter lights are mounted on the forward overhead panel.",
        "Most modern aircraft now only use captions on EICAS or EWD: red for warnings, amber for cautions, and white for advisories.",
        "Warnings, cautions and advisories must have attention-getter lights on the glareshield: red for warnings, amber for cautions and any other colour for advisory alerts.",
        "Warnings and cautions must be in direct line-of-sight when seated. Typically attention-getter lights on the glareshield are provided."
      ],
      "answer": "Warnings and cautions must be in direct line-of-sight when seated. Typically attention-getter lights on the glareshield are provided."
    },
    {
      "question": "Used on go-around.",
      "choices": [
        "Thrust",
        "TOGA",
        "%MCT%Speed",
        "Retard/Arm"
      ],
      "answer": "TOGA"
    },
    {
      "question": "The pilot of a modern, large turbojet aeroplane sets the vertical speed mode of the autopilot to carry out a climb. What must he/she be particularly careful of?",
      "choices": [
        "The engines may overspeed as the autothrottle attempts to maintain airspeed.",
        "If the climb is prolonged, there is a risk that the airspeed may reduce towards the stall.",
        "The autopilot may select a rate of climb outside the maximum permissible limit of the aeroplane.",
        "The aeroplane may overspeed in an attempt to maintain the rate of climb."
      ],
      "answer": "If the climb is prolonged, there is a risk that the airspeed may reduce towards the stall."
    },
    {
      "question": "When the autopilot ls engaged, the role of the automatic pitch trim is to:",
      "choices": [
        "respond to altitude changes in Altitude Hold mode.",
        "relieve the autopilot servo motor and return the aircraft in-trim when disconnecting the autopilot .",
        "block the elevator and pilot the aircraft only via the trim tab actuator or the horizontal stabiliser.",
        "synchronise the longitudinal loop."
      ],
      "answer": "relieve the autopilot servo motor and return the aircraft in-trim when disconnecting the autopilot ."
    },
    {
      "question": "A fail-operational hybrid landing system is fitted to an aircraft. What does this consist of?",
      "choices": [
        "A fail-operational landing system with a synthetic vision overlay, enabling better monitoring, and so a lower minimum RVR, than is possible with a simple fail-operational automatic landing system.",
        "A fail-operational landing system which, If the runway has NO low visibility approach aid, can overlay the enhanced vision system on the head-up display to allow continued operations below normal RVR minima.",
        "A fail-passive guidance system and a secondary independent landing system enabling automatic landing if the guidance system fails.",
        "A fall-passive automatic landing system and a secondary independent guidance system such as a head-up display (HUD). This enables the pilot to land manually if the automatic landing system fails."
      ],
      "answer": "A fall-passive automatic landing system and a secondary independent guidance system such as a head-up display (HUD). This enables the pilot to land manually if the automatic landing system fails."
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode appears in large font on the top row of the FMA.",
      "choices": [
        "Reversion",
        "Armed",
        "Engaged",
        "Inactive"
      ],
      "answer": "Engaged"
    },
    {
      "question": "In FBW aircraft, auto-trim operates at half speed when there is a risk of overspeed or underspeed.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Sometimes",
        "Not applicable"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "CMD' or 'SINGLE CH' or 'NO AUTOLAND' implies __________ AP engaged giving __________ autoland capability.",
      "choices": [
        "1; fail-operational",
        "1; fail-passive",
        "1; no",
        "2; fail-operational"
      ],
      "answer": "1; no"
    },
    {
      "question": "EFIS aircraft represent overspeed using a red and black, or red and white, 'barber's pole' on the speed tape at and above VMO/MMO.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only on Airbus",
        "Only on Boeing"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify which FEP functions are exclusive to FBW aircraft. Stall Protection.",
      "choices": [
        "Fly-By-Wire Only",
        "All Systems",
        "Conventional Only",
        "None"
      ],
      "answer": "All Systems"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following is an example of a warnings, cautions or advisory: Engine vibration.",
      "choices": [
        "Caution",
        "Warning",
        "Advisory",
        "Information"
      ],
      "answer": "Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "The autopilot is disengaged. What kind of warning will the flight crew get?",
      "choices": [
        "An aural warning only.",
        "A visual warning only.",
        "Both a visual and an aural warning.",
        "A vibration in the flight controls."
      ],
      "answer": "Both a visual and an aural warning."
    },
    {
      "question": "The flight envelope protection system prevents the aircraft from exceeding the limits of the following parameters (among others):",
      "choices": [
        "2, 3, 4, 5.",
        "2",
        "1, 2, 3, 4, 5.",
        "2, 3, 4."
      ],
      "answer": "2, 3, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "Associated with AP/FD modes which control airspeed with pitch.",
      "choices": [
        "Retard/Arm",
        "Speed",
        "Thrust",
        "%MCT%TOGA"
      ],
      "answer": "Thrust"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about the AP and FD is/are correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Modes are identical for the FD and the AP and are selected using the same MCP (FCU) controls.",
        "AP modes are mostly the same as FD modes except during initial descent from cruise altitude.",
        "More modes are available for the FD (e.g. smooth climb) because the sensitivity of the AP is limited.",
        "The increased sensitivity of the FD modes means that the FD bars are usually slightly deflected when the AP is engaged."
      ],
      "answer": "Modes are identical for the FD and the AP and are selected using the same MCP (FCU) controls."
    },
    {
      "question": "A fail-operational hybrid system is:",
      "choices": [
        "A fail-passive automatic landing system with a secondary automatic landing system in case the primary system fails.",
        "A fail-passive automatic landing system with a secondary independent guidance system such as a HUD to allow manual landing if the primary system fails.",
        "A fail-operational automatic landing system supplemented with SVS, CVS and HUD.",
        "A fail-operational secondary with a fail-passive primary automatic landing system supplemented by CVS and SVS."
      ],
      "answer": "A fail-passive automatic landing system with a secondary independent guidance system such as a HUD to allow manual landing if the primary system fails."
    },
    {
      "question": "Air speed fluctuations can cause the A/T to overcompensate, leading to speed oscillations.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Depends on mode",
        "Not applicable"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following is an example of a warnings, cautions or advisory: Cabin depressurisation.",
      "choices": [
        "Caution",
        "Advisory",
        "Warning",
        "Information"
      ],
      "answer": "Warning"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 2 functions of an AFCS are: Aircraft __________, stabilising the aircraft around its centre of gravity. Aircraft __________, along the aircraft's flight path.",
      "choices": [
        "guidance; guidance",
        "control; control",
        "guidance; control",
        "control; guidance"
      ],
      "answer": "control; guidance"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary purpose of a flight director system is to\u2026",
      "choices": [
        "Fly the aircraft automatically using a closed-loop system.",
        "Provide pitch and roll attitudes to the AP.",
        "Provide a backup attitude guidance system only when the AP is switched off.",
        "Provide rate guidance to reduce pilot workload, increase accuracy and smoothness of flying, and reduce aircraft fatigue."
      ],
      "answer": "Provide rate guidance to reduce pilot workload, increase accuracy and smoothness of flying, and reduce aircraft fatigue."
    },
    {
      "question": "The mode controls the aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Armed",
        "Engaged",
        "Active",
        "Standby"
      ],
      "answer": "Engaged"
    },
    {
      "question": "Comprises a Fail-Passive automatic landing system and a secondary independent guidance system enabling the pilot to complete a manual landing after the failure of the primary system.",
      "choices": [
        "FOALS",
        "FPALS",
        "FOHLS",
        "CAT IIIB"
      ],
      "answer": "FOHLS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode is on the second row of the FMA.",
      "choices": [
        "Reversion",
        "Engaged",
        "Armed",
        "Selected"
      ],
      "answer": "Armed"
    },
    {
      "question": "The horizontal stabiliser must be in the 'green band' for landing.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only for CAT III",
        "Depends on weight"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following is an example of a warnings, cautions or advisory: Unreliable airspeed.",
      "choices": [
        "Caution",
        "Advisory",
        "Warning",
        "Memo"
      ],
      "answer": "Warning"
    },
    {
      "question": "Depending on aircraft type, the following parameters cause a take-off configuration warning to activate: Pitch trim not in the normal range, or not in agreement with FMS or sensed CG.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only if flaps set",
        "Only if slats set"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify which FEP functions are exclusive to FBW aircraft. Overspeed Protection.",
      "choices": [
        "Fly-By-Wire Only",
        "All Systems",
        "None",
        "Conventional Only"
      ],
      "answer": "All Systems"
    },
    {
      "question": "A flight control system ls fail-passive if, in the event of a failure:",
      "choices": [
        "the system operates as a fail-operational hybrid landing system.",
        "there is no significant out-of-trim condition or deviation of flight path or attitude and the landing is completed automatically.",
        "there is no significant out-of-trim condition or deviation of flight path or attitude but the landing is not completed automatically.",
        "the system operates as a fall-operational system."
      ],
      "answer": "there is no significant out-of-trim condition or deviation of flight path or attitude but the landing is not completed automatically."
    },
    {
      "question": "The A/T should be left engaged, no matter how big the turbulence-induced fluctuations become.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Always",
        "Only on approach"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "Aircraft manufacturers set the stall warning speed:",
      "choices": [
        "A safe margin below the actual stalling speed of the aircraft.",
        "10 kt above the speed at which the aircraft will stall.",
        "A safe margin above the actual stalling speed of the aircraft.",
        "10 kt below the speed at which the aircraft will stall."
      ],
      "answer": "A safe margin above the actual stalling speed of the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Amber or yellow alert lights, captions and messages.",
      "choices": [
        "Advisory",
        "Instant",
        "Warning",
        "Caution"
      ],
      "answer": "Caution"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the main inputs to the autopilot/autoflight?",
      "choices": [
        "Air Data Computer, Inertial Referencing System, Mode Control Panel.",
        "Air Data Computer, GPWS, TCAS.",
        "Inertial Referencing System, Mode Control Panel, TCAS.",
        "Inertial Referencing System, Mode Control Panel, GPWS."
      ],
      "answer": "Air Data Computer, Inertial Referencing System, Mode Control Panel."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a heading capture mode, the autopilot gives a bank attitude input:",
      "choices": [
        "Of a fixed value equal to 20\u00b0.",
        "Proportional to the aircraft indicated airspeed but not exceeding a value of 25\u00b0.",
        "Proportional to the deviation between the selected heading and the current heading but not exceeding a given value.",
        "Of a fixed value equal to 30\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "Proportional to the deviation between the selected heading and the current heading but not exceeding a given value."
    },
    {
      "question": "When using AP or FD: You can only properly determine which modes are engaged or armed by looking at the indications on the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "FMA",
        "FMS",
        "CDU",
        "PFD"
      ],
      "answer": "FMA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is this a characteristics of a yaw damper or of other rudder control systems: Large magnitude.",
      "choices": [
        "Yaw Damper",
        "Rudder control",
        "Pitch Trim",
        "Aileron Trim"
      ],
      "answer": "Rudder control"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the level of alert matching each description: No aural alert required.",
      "choices": [
        "Caution",
        "Instant",
        "Warning",
        "Advisory"
      ],
      "answer": "Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "LAND2' implies __________APs engaged giving a __________ autoland capability.",
      "choices": [
        "2; fail-operational",
        "1; fail-operational",
        "1; fail-passive",
        "2; fail-passive"
      ],
      "answer": "2; fail-passive"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is this statements about the trim system true or false? There is always a trim system for each axis.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only in FBW",
        "Only in conventional"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statements is true with regard to the operation of a Mach trim system:",
      "choices": [
        "It only operates above a pre-determined Mach number.",
        "It operates over the full aeroplane speed range.",
        "It only operates when the autopilot is engaged.",
        "It operates to counteract the larger than normal forward movements of the wing centre of pressure at high subsonic airspeeds."
      ],
      "answer": "It only operates above a pre-determined Mach number."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following correctly describes the difference between an armed mode and an engaged mode in an autopilot system?",
      "choices": [
        "They are the same thing: different manufacturers use different terminology",
        "Only a three-axis autopilot can operate in an engaged mode.",
        "An armed mode will only become engaged when the flight crew switches to the engaged mode.",
        "An armed mode will only become engaged when certain criteria are met."
      ],
      "answer": "An armed mode will only become engaged when certain criteria are met."
    },
    {
      "question": "During cruise with full automation engaged and the autothrottle in speed mode. How is speed control achieved?",
      "choices": [
        "The autothrottle maintains constant engine thrust, while the autopilot uses the elevator to maintain altitude.",
        "The autothrottle will vary engine thrust, while the autopilot varies the aircraft pitch to maintain altitude.",
        "The autopilot maintains constant pitch, while the autothrottle maintains rated N1 thrust.",
        "The autopilot varies the aircraft pitch, while the autothrottle maintains constant engine thrust."
      ],
      "answer": "The autothrottle will vary engine thrust, while the autopilot varies the aircraft pitch to maintain altitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the level of alert matching each description: Awareness required, subsequent response may be necessary.",
      "choices": [
        "Advisory",
        "Warning",
        "Instant",
        "Caution"
      ],
      "answer": "Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane has a yaw damper that is unserviceable... What is the potential problem that the yaw damper is intended to prevent from happening at high altitudes?",
      "choices": [
        "Dutch roll.",
        "Excessive longitudinal stability.",
        "Excessive directional stability.",
        "Spiral instability."
      ],
      "answer": "Dutch roll."
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight Envelope Protection systems of an aircraft with conventional flight controls (non fly-by-wire) can include:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3, 4.",
        "2, 3, 4.",
        "2, 4.",
        "1, 3."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct AP/FD mode state for this statement: Not all modes can be in this state.",
      "choices": [
        "Engaged",
        "Armed",
        "Selected",
        "Inactive"
      ],
      "answer": "Armed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight Director Information supplied by an FD computer is presented in the form of command bars on the following instrument:",
      "choices": [
        "ADI Attitude Director Indicator.",
        "HSI Horizontal Situation Indicator.",
        "RMI Radio Magnetic Indicator.",
        "BDHI Bearing Distance Heading Indicator."
      ],
      "answer": "ADI Attitude Director Indicator."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct system type relating to each characteristic... There must be no out-of-trim condition following the failure of an autopilot.",
      "choices": [
        "FOALS",
        "FPALS",
        "FOHLS",
        "CAT II"
      ],
      "answer": "FPALS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Three axis autopilot permits control in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "roll, pitch and yaw.",
        "roll, pitch and speed.",
        "roll, pitch and bank.",
        "speed, altitude and heading."
      ],
      "answer": "roll, pitch and yaw."
    },
    {
      "question": "For large aircraft, an aural warning must be associated with the overspeed warning if a barber's pole is used.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Sometimes",
        "Not applicable"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is this a characteristics of a yaw damper or of other rudder control systems: High frequency.",
      "choices": [
        "Rudder control",
        "Yaw Damper",
        "Elevator control",
        "Aileron control"
      ],
      "answer": "Yaw Damper"
    },
    {
      "question": "The yaw damper system controls:",
      "choices": [
        "the ailerons, with Mach Number as the input signal.",
        "the rudder, with the angular rate about the yaw axis as the Input signal.",
        "the ailerons, with the angular rate about the yaw axis as the input signal.",
        "the rudder, with Mach Number as the Input signal."
      ],
      "answer": "the rudder, with the angular rate about the yaw axis as the Input signal."
    },
    {
      "question": "Has a time limit, typically 5 minutes, extended to 10 following an engine failure.",
      "choices": [
        "Retard/Idle",
        "Retard/Arm",
        "TOGA",
        "Thrust"
      ],
      "answer": "TOGA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Its sub mode is indicated above the engine instruments.",
      "choices": [
        "Speed",
        "Retard/Arm",
        "Thrust",
        "%MCT%TOGA"
      ],
      "answer": "Thrust"
    },
    {
      "question": "Failure of systems not directly involved in the autoland process __________ influence the ability to perform an autoland. They __________ affect your minima/DH for the approach.",
      "choices": [
        "may; do not",
        "do not; do not",
        "do not; may",
        "may; may"
      ],
      "answer": "may; may"
    },
    {
      "question": "The system can still carry out an automatic landing following the failure of an autopilot.",
      "choices": [
        "FOALS",
        "FOHLS",
        "FPALS",
        "CAT IIIA"
      ],
      "answer": "FOALS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Air speed and trend vectors are a good aid to setting manual thrust.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only in turbulence",
        "Only in wind shear"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode change accompanied by an aural alert.",
      "choices": [
        "Armed",
        "Reversion",
        "Engaged",
        "Selected"
      ],
      "answer": "Reversion"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following is an example of a warnings, cautions or advisory: Engine failure.",
      "choices": [
        "Warning",
        "Advisory",
        "Caution",
        "Information"
      ],
      "answer": "Caution"
    },
    {
      "question": "Depending on aircraft type, the following parameters cause a take-off configuration warning to activate: Take-off speed is not set in the FMS.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only for V1",
        "Only for VR"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight director (FD) indications: In left turn with 25 degrees of bank passing heading 005. The set heading is 360.",
      "choices": [
        "Down",
        "Right",
        "Up",
        "Central"
      ],
      "answer": "Right"
    },
    {
      "question": "When using AP or FD: If FD guidance is incorrect it should be __________.",
      "choices": [
        "left on but ignored",
        "turned off",
        "followed carefully",
        "re-selected"
      ],
      "answer": "turned off"
    },
    {
      "question": "When can more than one autopilot be engaged at the same time in an aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "Never.",
        "At any time.",
        "When flying above FL50.",
        "During autoland."
      ],
      "answer": "During autoland."
    },
    {
      "question": "Depending on aircraft type, the following parameters cause a take-off configuration warning to activate: The flaps/slats are not in agreement with the setting in the FMS.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only if flaps are down",
        "Only if slats are extended"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "There are 2 main variants of autothrust installation. Modes are selected only on the MCP or TOGA switches. The thrust levers __________ with A/T commands. Mode selections can be made using the thrust levers. The levers __________ with A/T commands.",
      "choices": [
        "remain static; remain static",
        "remain static; move",
        "move; remain static",
        "move; move"
      ],
      "answer": "move; remain static"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about stall warning and protection is/are true?",
      "choices": [
        "Stall warning systems simply provide warnings; stall protection systems actively resist the aircraft entering a stall.",
        "Stall warning systems always have stick pushers, whereas stall protection systems use advanced computer algorithms.",
        "Stall protection systems are used on FBW aircraft whereas stall warning systems are used on conventional aircraft.",
        "Stall warning systems do not prevent a stall, whereas stall protection systems make stalling impossible."
      ],
      "answer": "Stall warning systems simply provide warnings; stall protection systems actively resist the aircraft entering a stall."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following conditions describes a self-induced oscillation (PIO)?",
      "choices": [
        "Deviations from the desired state which rapidly decrease in magnitude.",
        "Any small deviation in pitch causes the aircraft to 'porpoise'.",
        "Control inputs result in stable or unstable deviations from the desired state.",
        "The air speed continues to decrease after a pitch-down control input."
      ],
      "answer": "Control inputs result in stable or unstable deviations from the desired state."
    },
    {
      "question": "A yaw damper:",
      "choices": [
        "Is a rudder damper and its purpose is to prevent Dutch roll.",
        "Is an elevator augmentation system.",
        "Is an elevator augmentation system which counteracts the nose-down effect if the Mach number is higher than 0.8.",
        "Is a trim tab for roll control."
      ],
      "answer": "Is a rudder damper and its purpose is to prevent Dutch roll."
    },
    {
      "question": "Is this a characteristics of a yaw damper or of other rudder control systems: Low frequency.",
      "choices": [
        "Yaw Damper",
        "Rudder control",
        "Elevator control",
        "Aileron control"
      ],
      "answer": "Rudder control"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify which FEP functions are exclusive to FBW aircraft. Bank Limitation.",
      "choices": [
        "All Systems",
        "Fly-By-Wire Only",
        "Conventional Only",
        "None"
      ],
      "answer": "Fly-By-Wire Only"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the level of alert matching each description: Short aural alert.",
      "choices": [
        "Instant",
        "Advisory",
        "Caution",
        "Warning"
      ],
      "answer": "Caution"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the AP mode phase relating to this statement: The aircraft's trajectory is based on the rate of closure and difference between the original parameter and the new parameter.",
      "choices": [
        "Holding Phase",
        "Initial Phase",
        "Capture Phase",
        "Transition Phase"
      ],
      "answer": "Initial Phase"
    },
    {
      "question": "Manual thrust adjustments should not be too aggressive.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only on takeoff",
        "Only on approach"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "An autothrust system reduces pilot workload and\u2026",
      "choices": [
        "Maintains air speed under all changes of environmental conditions and autoflight modes.",
        "Improves thrust stability in vertical speed mode, and airspeed stability in level change.",
        "Either improves airspeed stability, or maintains predetermined thrust in changing environmental conditions.",
        "Improves situational awareness."
      ],
      "answer": "Either improves airspeed stability, or maintains predetermined thrust in changing environmental conditions."
    },
    {
      "question": "You are flying an aircraft at FL350 with the autopilot engaged in VNAV and LNAV modes. What are the consequences of an auto-trim failure in these conditions?",
      "choices": [
        "The autopilot will disconnect and the pilot flying should take the controls.",
        "The abnormal rudder jam checklist should be performed.",
        "The company should be notified and advice should be seen from MCC.",
        "An emergency descent should be initiated."
      ],
      "answer": "The autopilot will disconnect and the pilot flying should take the controls."
    },
    {
      "question": "Maximum thrust for the ambient conditions is set.",
      "choices": [
        "TOGA",
        "Retard/Arm",
        "%MCT%Speed",
        "Thrust"
      ],
      "answer": "TOGA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify which FEP functions are exclusive to FBW aircraft. 'G' Limitation.",
      "choices": [
        "Fly-By-Wire Only",
        "All Systems",
        "Conventional Only",
        "None"
      ],
      "answer": "Fly-By-Wire Only"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which is the correct sequence of events for a CAT IIIB autoland?",
      "choices": [
        "LOC engaged, G/S engaged, 1500 FT RA, LAND3, FLARE armed, FLARE engaged, A/T RETARD.",
        "LOC engaged, G/S armed, G/S engaged, LAND2, 1500 FT RA, FLARE armed, FLARE engaged, A/T RETARD.",
        "G/S engaged, LOC engaged, 1500 FT RA, LAND3, FLARE armed, FLARE engaged, A/T RETARD.",
        "LOC and G/S armed, LOC engaged, G/S engaged, LAND3, 1500 FT RA, FLARE armed, A/T RETARD, FLARE engaged."
      ],
      "answer": "LOC engaged, G/S engaged, 1500 FT RA, LAND3, FLARE armed, FLARE engaged, A/T RETARD."
    },
    {
      "question": "Self-induced oscillations most commonly involve deviations in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "pitch",
        "roll",
        "yaw",
        "bank"
      ],
      "answer": "pitch"
    },
    {
      "question": "Manual thrust control is always necessary to correct turbulence-induced oscillation.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Sometimes",
        "Not applicable"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "In flight level change, 300 kt climb with 15 degrees pitch up, MCP set speed 320 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "Right",
        "Up",
        "Central",
        "Down"
      ],
      "answer": "Down"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ loop control systems use feedback from an action or state to compare the actual state with the intended state.",
      "choices": [
        "Closed",
        "Open",
        "Centre",
        "Engaged"
      ],
      "answer": "Closed"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following is an example of a warnings, cautions or advisory: Single hydraulic or electrical fault.",
      "choices": [
        "Warning",
        "Advisory",
        "Caution",
        "Memo"
      ],
      "answer": "Caution"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Yaw Damper system is designed to increase the damping ratio of:",
      "choices": [
        "pitch oscillation.",
        "Dutch roll.",
        "phugoid roll.",
        "aileron roll."
      ],
      "answer": "Dutch roll."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the green band/area on a pitch trim indicator?",
      "choices": [
        "The range within which the stabiliser should be set for landing.",
        "The maximum range of trim that can be set by the autopilot.",
        "The allowable range for normal operation.",
        "The range within which the stabiliser trim should be set for take-off."
      ],
      "answer": "The range within which the stabiliser trim should be set for take-off."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Yaw Damper system: 1. Counters any wrong pilot action on the rudder pedals. 2. Counters Dutch roll. 3. Is active only when autopilot is engaged. The combination of all the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2.",
        "2",
        "2, 3.",
        "1, 2, 3."
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which autothrust modes/sub-modes are described by this statement: Associated with AP/FD modes which maintain trajectory.",
      "choices": [
        "Thrust",
        "Retard/Idle",
        "Speed",
        "%MCT%TOGA"
      ],
      "answer": "Speed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Red alert lights, captions and messages.",
      "choices": [
        "Advisory",
        "Caution",
        "Warning",
        "Instant"
      ],
      "answer": "Warning"
    },
    {
      "question": "Depending on aircraft type, the following parameters cause a take-off configuration warning to activate: The flaps/slats not in the normal range for take-off.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only if slats are down",
        "Not applicable"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify which FEP functions are exclusive to FBW aircraft. Pitch Limitation.",
      "choices": [
        "Fly-By-Wire Only",
        "All Systems",
        "Conventional Only",
        "None"
      ],
      "answer": "Fly-By-Wire Only"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following is an example of a warnings, cautions or advisory: Slightly low oil pressure or hydraulic quantity.",
      "choices": [
        "Caution",
        "Advisory",
        "Warning",
        "Information"
      ],
      "answer": "Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the autopilot roll-out mode control do during an autoland?",
      "choices": [
        "Maintains the localiser centreline by controlling rudder/nose wheel steering.",
        "Carries out an automatic go-around if speed is excessive.",
        "It applies full reverse thrust once on the ground.",
        "Roll-out mode stays engaged until turning off the runway."
      ],
      "answer": "Maintains the localiser centreline by controlling rudder/nose wheel steering."
    },
    {
      "question": "The aircraft's attitude is changed to change trajectory to achieve a new parameter.",
      "choices": [
        "Initial Phase",
        "Capture Phase",
        "Holding Phase",
        "Transition Phase"
      ],
      "answer": "Initial Phase"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sequences modes during autoland.",
      "choices": [
        "Speed",
        "Retard/Idle",
        "Thrust",
        "Retard/Arm"
      ],
      "answer": "Retard/Idle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is this a characteristics of a yaw damper or of other rudder control systems: Small magnitude.",
      "choices": [
        "Rudder control",
        "Yaw Damper",
        "Elevator trim",
        "Pitch trim"
      ],
      "answer": "Yaw Damper"
    },
    {
      "question": "Depending on aircraft type, the following parameters cause a take-off configuration warning to activate: The speedbrake is stowed.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only if armed",
        "Only if deployed"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "Closed-loop control systems can enter a state of self-induced oscillation if:",
      "choices": [
        "The feedback loop has very low latency.",
        "The amplitude of the system output signals is too low.",
        "The system overcompensates for deviations from the desired state.",
        "The flight control actuators aren't properly tuned to be counter-resonant"
      ],
      "answer": "The system overcompensates for deviations from the desired state."
    },
    {
      "question": "The AFDS will automatically disengage from the LNAV mode if:",
      "choices": [
        "The pre-programmed route is altered.",
        "LVL CHG mode is selected.",
        "A new desired altitude is selected.",
        "HDG SEL is selected."
      ],
      "answer": "HDG SEL is selected."
    },
    {
      "question": "There must be no deviation from the intended flight path following the failure of an autopilot.",
      "choices": [
        "FOALS",
        "FPALS",
        "FOHLS",
        "CAT IIIA"
      ],
      "answer": "FPALS"
    },
    {
      "question": "A mode disengages and a basic mode replaces it by default.",
      "choices": [
        "Armed",
        "Reversion",
        "Engaged",
        "Selected"
      ],
      "answer": "Reversion"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary purpose of the AFCS is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Provide the crew with the correct flight parameters for each flight phase (speed, attitude, heading etc).",
        "Reduce pilot workload and aircraft fatigue, and increase passenger comfort",
        "Automate all phases of flight, including the take-off.",
        "Optimise the fuel efficiency of the flight by using gentle control inputs."
      ],
      "answer": "Reduce pilot workload and aircraft fatigue, and increase passenger comfort"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of the Dutch-roll filter is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Filter yaw input signals to prevent the yaw damper from resisting the pilots' or autopilot's rudder control inputs, while responding to the higher frequency Dutch Roll oscillations.",
        "Ensure the yaw damper system reacts to all manual or automatic inputs as well as Dutch Roll oscillations.",
        "Ensure the yaw damper only reacts to the pilot's or autopilot's rudder inputs, while filtering out Dutch Roll oscillations.",
        "Send low frequency signals into the yaw damper computer."
      ],
      "answer": "Filter yaw input signals to prevent the yaw damper from resisting the pilots' or autopilot's rudder control inputs, while responding to the higher frequency Dutch Roll oscillations."
    },
    {
      "question": "Alert height is the point on approach after which downgrades from fail-__________ to fail-__________ are not annunciated.",
      "choices": [
        "passive; operational",
        "passive; passive",
        "operational; operational",
        "operational; passive"
      ],
      "answer": "operational; passive"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode in small font (Boeing) and a different colour.",
      "choices": [
        "Engaged",
        "Armed",
        "Reversion",
        "Inactive"
      ],
      "answer": "Armed"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of a yaw damper is to counteract the __________ aerodynamic __________ known as dutch-roll.",
      "choices": [
        "cyclical; accelerations",
        "vertical; stagnations",
        "linear; stagnations",
        "cyclical; oscillations"
      ],
      "answer": "cyclical; oscillations"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following is an example of a warnings, cautions or advisory: Fire.",
      "choices": [
        "Warning",
        "Caution",
        "Advisory",
        "Information"
      ],
      "answer": "Warning"
    },
    {
      "question": "How does the yaw damper detect dutch roll?",
      "choices": [
        "Using a rate gyro that measures angular rate.",
        "Using a gyro and Inputs from the IRS, depending on the aircraft type.",
        "Using inputs from the IRS.",
        "Using accelerometers and inputs from the IRS only, depending on the aircraft type."
      ],
      "answer": "Using a gyro and Inputs from the IRS, depending on the aircraft type."
    },
    {
      "question": "Maximum thrust without time limit is the target.",
      "choices": [
        "Speed",
        "Thrust",
        "MCT",
        "%Retard/Arm%TOGA"
      ],
      "answer": "MCT"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pilots must monitor the FMAs during a CAT III approach to ensure:",
      "choices": [
        "A/T RETARD mode doesn't arm before LAND3 extinguishes.",
        "FLARE mode does not arm above 500 FT RA.",
        "Modes are armed and engaged by the trigger radio heights or other parameters.",
        "A/T RETARD mode engages before FLARE mode engages."
      ],
      "answer": "Modes are armed and engaged by the trigger radio heights or other parameters."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the purpose of the TCS (Touch Control Steering)?",
      "choices": [
        "assist the flare during the autoland.",
        "steering of the aircraft via a touch screen.",
        "disengagement of the autopilot to make a flight path change, before reengaging it back.",
        "temporary manual flying while the autopilot ls still engaged."
      ],
      "answer": "temporary manual flying while the autopilot ls still engaged."
    },
    {
      "question": "VNAV (or in Airbus aircraft: CLB/DES) captures and maintains the vertical flight path __________",
      "choices": [
        "selected on the UP DN thumbwheel",
        "programmed in the FMC",
        "of the ILS glideslope",
        "set in the MCP"
      ],
      "answer": "programmed in the FMC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens if, during an automatic approach and landing, the radio altimeter fails?",
      "choices": [
        "The automatic landing system will not be able to perform the flare phase.",
        "The automatic landing system will be fully operational.",
        "The Glide Slope mode will NOT be operational.",
        "The automatic braking sequence will be impacted."
      ],
      "answer": "The automatic landing system will not be able to perform the flare phase."
    },
    {
      "question": "Among the following functions of an autopilot, those related to the aeroplane stabilization are: 1. Pitch attitude holding...",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 4.",
        "1, 3, 4, 5.",
        "1, 3.",
        "1, 3, 4."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3."
    },
    {
      "question": "The usual measure of engine speed is:",
      "choices": [
        "RPM is used for turbofan engines, and percentage of maximum RPM is used for piston engines.",
        "RPM for piston engines, and percentage of maximum RPM for turbofan engines.",
        "For all engine types, RPM.",
        "For all engine types, the percentage of maximum RPM."
      ],
      "answer": "RPM for piston engines, and percentage of maximum RPM for turbofan engines."
    },
    {
      "question": "A GPWS is able to alert the crew of excessive sink rate (rate of descent) while below a certain height above terrain. Where does the GPWS derive the sink rate from?",
      "choices": [
        "The rate of change of GPS altitude.",
        "The air data computer rate of descent.",
        "The IRS vertical speed.",
        "The rate of change of radar altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "The air data computer rate of descent."
    },
    {
      "question": "The disadvantages of a float type fuel gauge are: 1. The design is complex. 2. The indications are influenced by the aircraft attitude variations. 3. The indications are influenced by the accelerations. 4. The indications are influenced by temperature variations. The combination of correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3, 4.",
        "2, 3, 4.",
        "1",
        "2, 3."
      ],
      "answer": "2, 3, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "Terrain between 2000 ft above and 500 ft below the aircraft is shown in yellow or amber.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only above 10000 ft",
        "Only below 10000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Can be used to sense the difference in pressure between two pressure sources.",
      "choices": [
        "Aneroid Capsule",
        "Bellows",
        "Bourdon Tube",
        "Diaphragm"
      ],
      "answer": "Diaphragm"
    },
    {
      "question": "ACAS II systems use the Mode C transponder to receive other traffics' Mode S broadcasts.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only for TAs",
        "Only for RAs"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "RA data is used to inhibit aural warnings below set heights.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only for GPWS",
        "Only for stall warning"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an aircraft NOT fitted with an EFIS the master caution light illuminates and an audible alarm is triggered. How does the crew find information about the cause of the caution indication?",
      "choices": [
        "This can only be distinguished from the audible alert.",
        "Only from a message on the ECAM.",
        "The master caution will indicate the nature of the problem.",
        "From the annunciator lights on the central warning panel."
      ],
      "answer": "From the annunciator lights on the central warning panel."
    },
    {
      "question": "The flight data recorder must automatically stop data recording when the:",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft clears the runway.",
        "Landing gear is extended and locked.",
        "Aircraft cannot any longer move by its own power.",
        "Main gear shock strut compresses when touching the runway."
      ],
      "answer": "Aircraft cannot any longer move by its own power."
    },
    {
      "question": "Measures a wide range of pressure, but sensitivity is inversely proportional to range of operation.",
      "choices": [
        "Diaphragm",
        "Aneroid Capsule",
        "Bellows",
        "Bourdon Tube"
      ],
      "answer": "Diaphragm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Acquired data from the Aircraft Condition Monitoring System (ACMS) may be used:",
      "choices": [
        "As part of an FDM and safety programme.",
        "For the EGPWS terrain display.",
        "In place of the FWS to generate alerts.",
        "By the EFB for performance calculations."
      ],
      "answer": "As part of an FDM and safety programme."
    },
    {
      "question": "The direction of intruders is found using direction-finding antennae.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only for TA",
        "Only for RA"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "GPWS visual warnings can be:",
      "choices": [
        "Red 'PULL, UP, PULL UP' on the PFD, ND and CDU, or red warning lights on the glareshield.",
        "Red 'PULL UP' or 'WIND SHEAR' on PFD, and/or red warning lights on the glareshield.",
        "Amber 'PULL UP, PULL UP on the ND, and/or amber warning lights on the glareshield.",
        "Amber captions on the PFD and red warning lights on the glareshield."
      ],
      "answer": "Red 'PULL UP' or 'WIND SHEAR' on PFD, and/or red warning lights on the glareshield."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to CS 25, a CVR (Cockpit Voice Recorder) must record... The combination of the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3, 4.",
        "1, 3.",
        "1, 2.",
        "2, 4."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 3, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "The indication of a fuel float gauge varies with... The combination of correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "1, 2, 4.",
        "1, 2.",
        "1, 2, 3, 4."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "At a high angle of attack, dependent on the type of airplane, the stall protection system can... The combination of the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "1, 2, 3.",
        "1, 2.",
        "1, 3."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3."
    },
    {
      "question": "A system which measures the temperature of the air in the tank and the time taken for transmissions to travel to and from the surface of the fuel.",
      "choices": [
        "Ultrasound gauge",
        "Float gauge",
        "Capacitance gauge",
        "Dripstick"
      ],
      "answer": "Ultrasound gauge"
    },
    {
      "question": "The terrain awareness display is visible on the ND whenever terrain is detected.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only when selected",
        "Always on"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "You need 4000 kg of fuel for your flight. As you arrive at the aircraft, the refueller hands you a receipt for 2000 L of fuel showing s.g. 0.78. He says he used 4000 kg to set the aircraft's automatic refuelling system. Which of the following is an acceptable figure for the fuel remaining, after the previous flight, in the aircraft technical log?",
      "choices": [
        "1500 kg",
        "3000 kg",
        "2200 kg",
        "2500 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "2500 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct as regards a synchroscope on a multi-engine aircraft? A synchroscope ls used to:",
      "choices": [
        "1 ls correct, 2 ls Incorrect.",
        "Both 1 and 2 are correct.",
        "Both 1 and 2 are Incorrect .",
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "1 ls correct, 2 ls Incorrect."
    },
    {
      "question": "The types of tachometer found on aircraft include: Rotating __________ : A flexible shaft connects the engine and the instrument, and drives a drag cup by magnetism. They are found on smaller and older aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "magnet",
        "impulse",
        "tacho",
        "phonic"
      ],
      "answer": "magnet"
    },
    {
      "question": "No RA can be generated below 1000 ft above the ground.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only TA",
        "Depends on mode"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "An approximately accurate system only used in small aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Capacitance gauge",
        "Float gauge",
        "Ultrasound gauge",
        "Dripstick"
      ],
      "answer": "Float gauge"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: An aural 'TERRAIN, TERRAIN alert and a visual 'TERRAIN' on the PFD.",
      "choices": [
        "5",
        "2",
        "1",
        "6"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "FWC data is used to inhibit RAs during wind shear and GPWS warnings.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only for wind shear",
        "Only for GPWS"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "At high altitudes, aircraft performance is taken into account to inhibit 'climb' and 'increase climb' RAs.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only for descent RAs",
        "This is false"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to CS25, a CVR (Cockpit Voice Recorder) must record... The combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3, 4.",
        "1, 3.",
        "2, 4.",
        "1, 2."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 3, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "Terrain >2000 ft amsl is shown in red on the ND.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Shown in Amber",
        "Shown in Magenta"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "A training aircraft is approaching an intended stall. No aural or visual indication of the impending stall is given; you feel aerodynamic buffet. Then, the stick pusher activates. What do you enter into the technical log book?",
      "choices": [
        "Stall warning and stall protection working.",
        "Stall warning and stall protection inoperative.",
        "Stall warning inoperative, stall protection working.",
        "Stall warning working, stall protection inoperative."
      ],
      "answer": "Stall warning inoperative, stall protection working."
    },
    {
      "question": "The cockpit voice recorder must preserve the conversation and aural warnings of the last:",
      "choices": [
        "30 minutes of operation.",
        "25 hours of operation.",
        "48 hours of operation.",
        "Flight."
      ],
      "answer": "30 minutes of operation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Aural alert 'CAUTION WIND SHEAR' and a visual 'WIND SHEAR' on PFD.",
      "choices": [
        "5",
        "6",
        "4",
        "7"
      ],
      "answer": "7"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the description to the correct TCAS output: Will draw red areas on the EVSI or PFD VSI.",
      "choices": [
        "Proximate Traffic",
        "Resolution Advisory",
        "Traffic Advisory",
        "Other Traffic"
      ],
      "answer": "Resolution Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "Total fuel consumption is calculated by:",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel flow \u00f7 time",
        "Fuel flow + time",
        "Fuel flow x time",
        "Fuel flow x time squared"
      ],
      "answer": "Fuel flow x time"
    },
    {
      "question": "The outputs of the GPWS are: 1. Pitch up command to the AFCS 2. Aural alert 3. Aural Warning 4. Aural Klaxon Alert 5. Terrain shown on ND The combination regrouping all correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "2 and 3 only",
        "1, 2, 3 and 5",
        "2, 4 and 5",
        "2, 3, and 4"
      ],
      "answer": "2 and 3 only"
    },
    {
      "question": "When a TCAS RA is generated, the required vertical speed:",
      "choices": [
        "Is displayed on the VSI.",
        "Is not displayed separately.",
        "Takes account of stall speed.",
        "Shows a red arc on the VSI as your target rate of climb/ descent."
      ],
      "answer": "Is displayed on the VSI."
    },
    {
      "question": "The terrain awareness display is shown on the ND when selected; this prevents weather radar information from being displayed.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Sometimes",
        "Only in MAP mode"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Torque sensors may be: Mechanical. The axial load of a helical gear drives a piston compressing oil in a cylinder. The oil __________ is proportional to the torque. This system is relatively heavy, expensive and maintenance intensive.",
      "choices": [
        "pressure",
        "height",
        "depth",
        "viscosity"
      ],
      "answer": "pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "The disadvantages of a float type fuel gauge are: 1... 2... 3... 4... The combination of correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3, 4.",
        "1",
        "2, 3, 4.",
        "2, 3."
      ],
      "answer": "2, 3, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Aural 'WIND SHEAR, WIND SHEAR' warning and a visual 'WIND SHEAR' on PFD.",
      "choices": [
        "6",
        "5",
        "7",
        "4"
      ],
      "answer": "7"
    },
    {
      "question": "An external pressure source is fed to the interior, causing the unit to expand when pressure increases.",
      "choices": [
        "Bellows",
        "Aneroid Capsule",
        "Diaphragm",
        "Bourdon Tube"
      ],
      "answer": "Bellows"
    },
    {
      "question": "An Aeroplane Condition Monitoring System (ACMS) makes use of aircraft input data and also:",
      "choices": [
        "an erase button, a data management unit, and a headset jack.",
        "a headset jack, a data management unit, and outputs (e.g. a printer or ACARS).",
        "a data management unit, a recording unit, and outputs (e.g. a printer or ACARS).",
        "an area microphone, a recording unit, and an erase button."
      ],
      "answer": "a data management unit, a recording unit, and outputs (e.g. a printer or ACARS)."
    },
    {
      "question": "After a Radio Altimeter failure, which of the following systems are affected? 1. Autobrake system 2. EGPWS 3. Autothrottle 4. ISIS",
      "choices": [
        "2025-02-03 00:00:00",
        "2025-02-04 00:00:00",
        "2025-03-04 00:00:00",
        "2025-01-02 00:00:00"
      ],
      "answer": "2025-02-03 00:00:00"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fuel flow meters measure the volume or __________ of fuel per unit of time. They are normally measured in the __________ fuel line and represent the rate at which the engines are consuming fuel.",
      "choices": [
        "density; HP",
        "density; LP",
        "mass; HP",
        "mass; LP"
      ],
      "answer": "mass; LP"
    },
    {
      "question": "ACAS II is:",
      "choices": [
        "An ICAO standard for anti-collision systems.",
        "A device which helps aircraft avoid collisions with other traffic.",
        "A computer system in ATC centres which coordinates traffic automatically to avoid collisions.",
        "The brand name of the system developed by Honeywell which automatically deconflicts traffic."
      ],
      "answer": "An ICAO standard for anti-collision systems."
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of GPWS is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Warn of potential controlled flight into terrain.",
        "Prevent excessive rates of descent, within predefined parameters.",
        "Prevent closure with terrain below predefined limits.",
        "Prevent controlled flight into terrain."
      ],
      "answer": "Warn of potential controlled flight into terrain."
    },
    {
      "question": "Is a device in the CVR control panel which captures cockpit noises and conversations.",
      "choices": [
        "The test panel",
        "The cockpit area microphone (CAM).",
        "The flight data recorder",
        "The headset microphone"
      ],
      "answer": "The cockpit area microphone (CAM)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: An alert is triggered by excessive deviation below the ILS glide slope.",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "6",
        "5",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "question": "Summarise benefits of IHUMS:",
      "choices": [
        "Improved rotor track & balance giving lower vibration levels, increasing maximum operating altitude, accurate recording of flight exceedances.",
        "Accurate recording of flight exceedances;, cockpit voice recorder/flight data recorder allows accurate accident /incident investigation & HOMP, higher airspeeds possible.",
        "Reduced risk of catastrophic failure of rotor or gearbox, improved rotor track & balance giving lower vibration levels, accurate recording of flight exceedances.",
        "Reduced risk of catastrophic failure of rotor or gearbox, accurate recording of flight exceedances & cockpit voice recorder/flight data recorder allows accurate accident /incident investigation & HOMP but also maintenance costs increase."
      ],
      "answer": "Reduced risk of catastrophic failure of rotor or gearbox, improved rotor track & balance giving lower vibration levels, accurate recording of flight exceedances."
    },
    {
      "question": "A TCAS RA:",
      "choices": [
        "May require a reversal of the initial commands if ATC override the RA.",
        "May not require any change of pitch; no manoeuvre should be started until the required control inputs needed are understood.",
        "Must only be complied with if no conflict with ATC instructions exists.",
        "Always requires a change of pitch of 3 to 4 degrees only."
      ],
      "answer": "May not require any change of pitch; no manoeuvre should be started until the required control inputs needed are understood."
    },
    {
      "question": "The airline you are working for has a FDM system in operation. What is true about the acquired Information? 1. If the pilot purposely and recklessly exceeds stated parameters and limitations, the company can put him/her under Investigation. 2. The data will be used to find reoccurring adverse safety trends. 3. The Information will be used to improve crew training.",
      "choices": [
        "2 and 3.",
        "1 and 2.",
        "All of the above.",
        "1 and 3."
      ],
      "answer": "All of the above."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a multi-engine aircraft, a synchroscope provides an indication of the difference in:",
      "choices": [
        "low engine speed.",
        "vibration (Hz) between the engines.",
        "voltage (V) between the electrical generators.",
        "speed (RPM) between the engines."
      ],
      "answer": "speed (RPM) between the engines."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Visual and aural alerts can be 'TOO LOW GEAR' or 'TOO LOW FLAP' or 'TOO LOW TERRAIN'.",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "1",
        "3",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "4"
    },
    {
      "question": "The relative position of intruders is determined from their GNSS position.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Sometimes",
        "For RAs only"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "Measures high pressure sources.",
      "choices": [
        "Diaphragm",
        "Aneroid Capsule",
        "Bellows",
        "Bourdon Tube"
      ],
      "answer": "Bourdon Tube"
    },
    {
      "question": "A stall warning system (1)_____ and the stall protection system (2)_____.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) Alerts the pilot (2) Prevents the stall",
        "(1) Prevents the stall (2) Alerts the pilot",
        "(1) Prevents the stall (2) Prevents the stall",
        "(1) Alerts the pilot (2) Alerts the pilot"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) Alerts the pilot (2) Prevents the stall"
    },
    {
      "question": "The enhanced GPWS terrain display uses the following colours:",
      "choices": [
        "Green, Amber, Red, Blue.",
        "Green, Amber, Magenta, Blue.",
        "Green, Amber, Red, White.",
        "Cyan, Amber, Red, Blue."
      ],
      "answer": "Green, Amber, Red, Blue."
    },
    {
      "question": "Contains test and erase buttons, a headset jack, and a status light or gauge.",
      "choices": [
        "The headset microphone",
        "The cockpit area microphone (CAM).",
        "The recorder.",
        "The control unit."
      ],
      "answer": "The control unit."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following are main components of a CVR? 1... 2... 3... 4... 5... 6...",
      "choices": [
        "2, 3, 4, 6.",
        "1, 2, 4.",
        "1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.",
        "2, 3, 4, 5, 6."
      ],
      "answer": "2, 3, 4, 6."
    },
    {
      "question": "ACAS II systems use the Modes S transponder to interrogate traffic.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only for TAs",
        "Only for RAs"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Aural alert 'BANK ANGLE' when the bank angle is excessive.",
      "choices": [
        "6",
        "3",
        "4",
        "5"
      ],
      "answer": "6"
    },
    {
      "question": "Terrain between 500 ft and 2000 ft below the aircraft is shown in green.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Shown in white",
        "Shown in blue"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Cockpit Voice Recorder must record:",
      "choices": [
        "voice or audio signals identifying navigation or approach aids introduced into a headset or speaker and data recording flight and engine parameters.",
        "flight data, voice or audio signals identifying navigation or approach aids introduced into a headset or speaker and voice communications: transmitted from or received in the aeroplane by radio, and of flight-crew members on the flight deck.",
        "voice or audio signals identifying navigation or approach aids introduced into a headset or speaker and voice communications, transmitted from or received ln the aeroplane by radio, of flight-crew members on the flight deck, of flight-crew members on the flight deck using the aeroplane's Interphone system, and of flight-crew members on the flight-deck using the public address system (If installed).",
        "voice or audio signals identifying navigation or approach aids introduced into a headset or speaker and voice communications: transmitted from or received in the aeroplane by radio, of flight-crew members on the flight deck, of flight-crew members on the flight deck using the aeroplane's interphone system including calls between cabin crew stations (if installed), and of flight-crew members on the flight-deck using the public address system (if installed)."
      ],
      "answer": "voice or audio signals identifying navigation or approach aids introduced into a headset or speaker and voice communications, transmitted from or received ln the aeroplane by radio, of flight-crew members on the flight deck, of flight-crew members on the flight deck using the aeroplane's Interphone system, and of flight-crew members on the flight-deck using the public address system (If installed)."
    },
    {
      "question": "An engine vibration meter is indicating '4'. What is the unit of this indication?",
      "choices": [
        "Hz",
        "m/s",
        "hPa",
        "No units are specified"
      ],
      "answer": "No units are specified"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: A visual 'DON'T SINK' on the PFD, and an aural 'DON'T SINK, DON'T SINK'.",
      "choices": [
        "2",
        "1",
        "4",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct as regards a synchroscope on a multi-engine aircraft? A synchroscope ls used to: 1. reduce structural vibration and noise 2. achieve symmetrical thrust and fuel consumption.",
      "choices": [
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct.",
        "Both 1 and 2 are correct.",
        "1 ls correct, 2 ls Incorrect.",
        "Both 1 and 2 are Incorrect ."
      ],
      "answer": "1 ls correct, 2 ls Incorrect."
    },
    {
      "question": "Concerning a fuel gauge system, the most relevant fuel parameter is:",
      "choices": [
        "volume.",
        "mass.",
        "permittivity.",
        "density."
      ],
      "answer": "mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following are main features of IHUMS?",
      "choices": [
        "Monitoring & trending",
        "GBAS & SBAS",
        "Cockpit voice recorder & rotor system adjustment",
        "Flight management system & monitoring"
      ],
      "answer": "Monitoring & trending"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of a Flight Data Monitoring (FDM) programme is to collect flight data:",
      "choices": [
        "individually, to measure each pilot's performance.",
        "anonymously, to improve safety.",
        "to measure all crew member's performance.",
        "individually, for the safety evaluation of each pilot."
      ],
      "answer": "anonymously, to improve safety."
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the description to the correct TCAS output: Displayed as a hollow diamond.",
      "choices": [
        "Resolution Advisory",
        "Traffic Advisory",
        "Proximate Traffic",
        "Other Traffic"
      ],
      "answer": "Other Traffic"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of GPWS is:",
      "choices": [
        "to alert the pilots of hazardous terrain in front of and below the aircraft.",
        "to alert the crew if there are deviations from certain aerodynamic parameters like altitude, airspeed and angle of attack.",
        "to provide information and alert the pilots of a potentially hazardous terrain situation.",
        "to avoid the aircraft having a CFIT."
      ],
      "answer": "to provide information and alert the pilots of a potentially hazardous terrain situation."
    },
    {
      "question": "FDM is a safety programme which normally protects the anonymity of pilots.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Sometimes",
        "Never"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about cockpit voice recorders is/are accurate?",
      "choices": [
        "You are permitted to erase the CVR recording after flight.",
        "The CVR only records words spoken in the cockpit.",
        "The CVR may be mounted anywhere in the airframe.",
        "Tampering with the CVR system or its data is an offence."
      ],
      "answer": "You are permitted to erase the CVR recording after flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Visual 'GLIDE SLOPE' on the PFD and an aural 'GLIDE SLOPE' alert.",
      "choices": [
        "5",
        "4",
        "2",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "question": "They are determined by comparing GNSS/ADIRU position and geometric altitude with the terrain/obstructions database.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only geometric altitude",
        "Only GNSS position"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Torque sensors may be: Electronic. Solid state __________ gauges use a metal which changes __________ with changing strain. 4 sensors mounted at right angles are mounted on the side of a drive shaft. The system is cheap, light and simple. It can have multiple channels for redundancy. It __________ suitable for FADEC engines.",
      "choices": [
        "strain; resistance; is",
        "diode; resistance; is",
        "piezoelectric; capacitance; is",
        "piezoelectric; capacitance; is not"
      ],
      "answer": "strain; resistance; is"
    },
    {
      "question": "ADC data is used to calculate the relative altitude of intruders and to inhibit 'climb' RAs when performance is limited.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only to calculate altitude",
        "Only to inhibit RAs"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the description to the correct TCAS output: Displayed as a solid yellow circle.",
      "choices": [
        "Resolution Advisory",
        "Other Traffic",
        "Traffic Advisory",
        "Proximate Traffic"
      ],
      "answer": "Traffic Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "Has an impact-resistant housing, capable of surviving in deep water, and an underwater locator beacon.",
      "choices": [
        "The cockpit area microphone (CAM).",
        "The flight data recorder",
        "The recorder.",
        "The control unit."
      ],
      "answer": "The recorder."
    },
    {
      "question": "If crew awareness is required and subsequent crew action may be required, the flight warning system (FWS) generates:",
      "choices": [
        "A caution message.",
        "A warning message.",
        "A call message.",
        "An advisory message."
      ],
      "answer": "An advisory message."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Flight Data Recorder makes use of:",
      "choices": [
        "a recording system, an \"event\u2022 button, and an underwater locating device.",
        "an erase button, a recording system, and an area microphone.",
        "an area microphone, a headset jack and an \"event\" button.",
        "an underwater locating device, an erase button, and a headset jack."
      ],
      "answer": "a recording system, an \"event\u2022 button, and an underwater locating device."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Inhibited close to the ground to avoid nuisance warnings during landing.",
      "choices": [
        "2",
        "1",
        "3",
        "4"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Altitude call-outs when preset radio altitudes are passed.",
      "choices": [
        "6",
        "5",
        "3",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "6"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the description to the correct TCAS output: Associated with multiple aural alerts e.g. 'climb, climb'.",
      "choices": [
        "Traffic Advisory",
        "Other Traffic",
        "Resolution Advisory",
        "Proximate Traffic"
      ],
      "answer": "Resolution Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "The indication of a fuel float gauge varies with...The combination of correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 4.",
        "1, 2, 3, 4.",
        "4",
        "1, 2."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "Has a partly evacuated capsule, expanding and contracting when the pressure around it changes.",
      "choices": [
        "Diaphragm",
        "Bellows",
        "Bourdon Tube",
        "Aneroid Capsule"
      ],
      "answer": "Aneroid Capsule"
    },
    {
      "question": "In case of impending stall, the flight warning system (FWS) generates:",
      "choices": [
        "An urgency message.",
        "An advisory message.",
        "A warning message.",
        "A caution message."
      ],
      "answer": "A warning message."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Excessive terrain closure rate, even if not descending.",
      "choices": [
        "6",
        "1",
        "4",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of FDM is to identify adverse safety trends and tailor subsequent training programmes to enhance operational safety.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Sometimes",
        "Never"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Measures low to medium pressures.",
      "choices": [
        "Bellows",
        "Diaphragm",
        "Aneroid Capsule",
        "Bourdon Tube"
      ],
      "answer": "Bellows"
    },
    {
      "question": "The flight warning system (FWS) generates a caution message if:",
      "choices": [
        "Crew awareness is required and subsequent crew action may be required.",
        "Immediate recognition and corrective or compensatory action by the crew is required.",
        "Immediate crew awareness is required and subsequent crew action will be required.",
        "Crew awareness is required and corrective or compensatory action by the crew is immediately required."
      ],
      "answer": "Immediate crew awareness is required and subsequent crew action will be required."
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider the 2 statements below: 1. 15\u00b0 Celsius = 273 Kelvin. 2. 15\u00b0 Celsius = 59\u00b0 Fahrenheit. Which combination of answers matches the statements?",
      "choices": [
        "1 is correct, 2 is incorrect.",
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is incorrect",
        "1 is correct, 2 is correct.",
        "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "1 is incorrect, 2 is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following are factors that determine the type and number of parameters to be recorded by a FDR (flight data recorder)?",
      "choices": [
        "Recording duration and reliability of the FDR.",
        "Recording capacity and number of flight crew members.",
        "Recording capacity and applicable operational requirements.",
        "Recording duration and the maximum flight time of the aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "Recording capacity and applicable operational requirements."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: A high rate of descent at low altitude triggers an alert.",
      "choices": [
        "5",
        "7",
        "3",
        "1"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "When TAWS is fitted it must be connected to a:",
      "choices": [
        "4-dimensional FMS.",
        "2-dimensional terrain model.",
        "3-dimensional position sensor.",
        "1-dimensional VSI."
      ],
      "answer": "4-dimensional FMS."
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the description to the correct TCAS output: Displayed as a solid red square.",
      "choices": [
        "Other Traffic",
        "Traffic Advisory",
        "Resolution Advisory",
        "Proximate Traffic"
      ],
      "answer": "Resolution Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "EGPWS/TAWS relies on accurate position data. Consequently:",
      "choices": [
        "Excessive position accuracy commonly generates spurious warnings. In this case, obtain clearance from ATC before climbing.",
        "There is a risk of no warning, or false warnings, of potential impact with terrain. Terrain function should be inhibited if position accuracy is downgraded.",
        "Warnings should be disregarded if position accuracy is in doubt, or if the EPU is greater than 2 nm.",
        "The system won't generate alerts or warnings if the EPU/EPE/ANP is greater than 2 nm."
      ],
      "answer": "There is a risk of no warning, or false warnings, of potential impact with terrain. Terrain function should be inhibited if position accuracy is downgraded."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is correct regarding the FDM? A Flight Data Monitoring (FDM) programme collects and analyses aircraft flight data for the purpose of:",
      "choices": [
        "Displaying to the crew any adverse safety trend.",
        "Identifying adverse safety trends and tailoring training programmes.",
        "Displaying to the crew any exceeded parameter.",
        "Identifying adverse safety trends and automatic reporting to the Competent Authority."
      ],
      "answer": "Identifying adverse safety trends and tailoring training programmes."
    },
    {
      "question": "By what means are messages from an Aeroplane Condition Monitoring System (ACMS) transmitted to the maintenance base?",
      "choices": [
        "Digital datalink, without crew notification.",
        "Conventional analogue radios, with crew notification.",
        "The Flight Data Recorder, when the aircraft 1s on the ground.",
        "The commander, through VHF or HF voice communication."
      ],
      "answer": "Digital datalink, without crew notification."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Altitude loss after take-off or go-around triggers an alert.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "3",
        "4",
        "6"
      ],
      "answer": "3"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following is/are terrain display alerts of the EGPWS: 1. Runway overrun protection 2. Conflicting traffic on the ground 3. Excessive deviation from the localiser 4. Terrain clearance floor 5. Wind shear during take-off",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 4 and 5.",
        "4 only.",
        "3 and 5.",
        "1, 2, and 3."
      ],
      "answer": "4 only."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the type of TCA's aural alert: Climb, crossing climb'.",
      "choices": [
        "Traffic Advisory",
        "Corrective Advisory",
        "Preventive Advisory",
        "Information Advisory"
      ],
      "answer": "Corrective Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "A CVR consists of:",
      "choices": [
        "an Event Mark Device, Emergency Locator Transmitter, test button, and erase button.",
        "a tape recorder, Underwater Locating Device, area microphone, and control unit.",
        "a Digital Flight Data Acquisition Unit, area microphone, erase button, and tape recorder.",
        "an Underwater Locating Device, illuminating light, speakers, tape recorder, and control unit."
      ],
      "answer": "a tape recorder, Underwater Locating Device, area microphone, and control unit."
    },
    {
      "question": "Classify the following sensors by order of increasing pressure for which they are suitable. 1. Bellows type 2. Bourdon tube type 3. Aneroid capsule type",
      "choices": [
        "2, 1, 3.",
        "3, 1, 2.",
        "1, 2, 3.",
        "3, 2, 1."
      ],
      "answer": "3, 1, 2."
    },
    {
      "question": "An EGPWS warning alert is heard in the cockpit. The time left for the pilot to respond before hitting terrain is:",
      "choices": [
        "25 to 35 seconds.",
        "40 to 60 seconds.",
        "10 to 20 seconds.",
        "20 to 30 seconds."
      ],
      "answer": "20 to 30 seconds."
    },
    {
      "question": "When must the flight data recorder automatically stop data recording?",
      "choices": [
        "When the aeroplane clears the runway.",
        "When the main gear shock strut compresses when touching the runway.",
        "When the landing gear is extended and locked.",
        "When the aeroplane cannot any longer move by its own power."
      ],
      "answer": "When the aeroplane cannot any longer move by its own power."
    },
    {
      "question": "Components of a CVR system - match the components to a description: Contains test and erase buttons, a headset jack, and a status light or gauge.",
      "choices": [
        "The recorder.",
        "The cockpit area microphone (CAM).",
        "The control unit.",
        "The headset microphone"
      ],
      "answer": "The control unit."
    },
    {
      "question": "The distance of intruders is calculated from the time taken to receive replies.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only for Mode S",
        "Only for Mode C"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The time limit to CPA depends on the aircraft's altitude and the system's sensitivity level (SL). The value to trigger an RA is between 15 and 35 seconds.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "The value is fixed",
        "The value is 10 to 20 seconds"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The electromotive force of a thermocouple is not modified if one or several intermediate metals are inserted in the circuit provided that:",
      "choices": [
        "Contact points are maintained at equal temperature between these different metals.",
        "These metals are not the same as those constituting the thermocouple.",
        "These metals are maintained at a temperature higher than that of the cold source.",
        "These metals are maintained at a temperature lower than that of the cold source."
      ],
      "answer": "Contact points are maintained at equal temperature between these different metals."
    },
    {
      "question": "An electronic torque meter senses:",
      "choices": [
        "Twisting of the engine output shaft.",
        "Torsion on the propellers or rotors.",
        "Angular velocity of the propellers or rotors.",
        "Oil pressure from the reduction gearbox."
      ],
      "answer": "Twisting of the engine output shaft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Grave exceedances of parameters may warrant further investigation by the operator.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Only if damage is suspected",
        "Never"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The relationship between torque, RPM and power is:",
      "choices": [
        "Power x RPM = torque",
        "Torque x power = RPM",
        "Torque \u00f7 RPM = power",
        "RPM x torque = power"
      ],
      "answer": "RPM x torque = power"
    },
    {
      "question": "What should a takeoff warning provide, as a minimum requirement?",
      "choices": [
        "An aural warning after V1.",
        "An aural warning in the initial take-off roll.",
        "A visual warning after V1.",
        "A visual warning in the initial take-off roll."
      ],
      "answer": "An aural warning in the initial take-off roll."
    },
    {
      "question": "Electronic: An impulse or __________ wheel has a magnetic sensor close to the fan blades or to teeth on a rotating gear. These generate a series of electrical pulses. A computer measures the pulses and converts to RPM. Requires electrical power to function.",
      "choices": [
        "magnet",
        "phonic",
        "drive",
        "tacho"
      ],
      "answer": "phonic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Visual 'SINK RATE' on PFD, aural 'SINK RATE, SINK RATE' alert.",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "1",
        "4",
        "7"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Your aircraft has 2000 kg of fuel on board, and your flight plan requires that you have a fuel quantity on board of 5000 kg. How many U.S. gallons of fuel (s.g. 0.8) do you need to load?",
      "choices": [
        "3000",
        "3750",
        "975",
        "780"
      ],
      "answer": "975"
    },
    {
      "question": "When using electronic checklists, it's important to:",
      "choices": [
        "Carry out as quickly as possible any non-normal or emergency checklist actions to stabilise the situation.",
        "Acknowledge, but then delete, any non-critical, non-normal checklist actions if your workload is currently too high.",
        "First consider the consequences of actions commanded by the electronic checklist before actioning them.",
        "Follow the recommended actions exactly and completely at all times."
      ],
      "answer": "First consider the consequences of actions commanded by the electronic checklist before actioning them."
    },
    {
      "question": "Comprises a curved metal tube, open at one end, which straightens slightly when internal pressure rises.",
      "choices": [
        "Bellows",
        "Diaphragm",
        "Bourdon Tube",
        "Aneroid Capsule"
      ],
      "answer": "Bourdon Tube"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the Mode associated this description of conventional GPWS: Excessive rate of descent at low altitude triggers a warning.",
      "choices": [
        "7",
        "3",
        "5",
        "1"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Measures only low pressures.",
      "choices": [
        "Bellows",
        "Diaphragm",
        "Aneroid Capsule",
        "Bourdon Tube"
      ],
      "answer": "Aneroid Capsule"
    },
    {
      "question": "Movement of traffic symbols on the horizontal display:",
      "choices": [
        "Does not indicate the relative bearing of proximate traffic.",
        "Should not be interpreted as tracks because the system's design makes this unreliable.",
        "Is a reliable indicator of aircraft tracks, but only at low altitudes.",
        "Are accurately displayed tracks because the directional antennae are carefully calibrated."
      ],
      "answer": "Should not be interpreted as tracks because the system's design makes this unreliable."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is, in computer terminology, an operating system?",
      "choices": [
        "The bus structure that allows data communication.",
        "The central processing unit's control unit.",
        "The programme that controls a computer's basic functions.",
        "The control display unit that allows computer control."
      ],
      "answer": "The programme that controls a computer's basic functions."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the type of TCA's aural alert: 'Climb, climb'.",
      "choices": [
        "Traffic Advisory",
        "Corrective Advisory",
        "Preventive Advisory",
        "Warning Advisory"
      ],
      "answer": "Corrective Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "A TCAS II resolution advisory is displayed as:",
      "choices": [
        "a white or cyan solid lozenge.",
        "a white or cyan empty lozenge.",
        "a red full square.",
        "an amber solid circle."
      ],
      "answer": "a red full square."
    },
    {
      "question": "When the flight warning system (FWS) identifies an overspeed condition (airspeed exceeding VMO/MMO), it generates:",
      "choices": [
        "A caution message.",
        "A warning message.",
        "A call message.",
        "An advisory message."
      ],
      "answer": "A warning message."
    },
    {
      "question": "Data from the ACMS can be used as part of the flight data monitoring (FDM) programme.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Never",
        "Only with crew consent"
      ],
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Electrical: using 3-phase __________-generators. A small generator is driven by the engine shaft. This outputs 3-phase AC to drive a small motor in the gauge, which drives a drag cup by magnetism. The AC signal can be fed to EFIS displays on later aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "impulse",
        "tacho",
        "magnet",
        "phonic"
      ],
      "answer": "tacho"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the description to the correct TCAS output: Associated with aural alert 'traffic, traffic'.",
      "choices": [
        "Other Traffic",
        "Resolution Advisory",
        "Proximate Traffic",
        "Traffic Advisory"
      ],
      "answer": "Traffic Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "A mechanical fuel flowmeter uses:",
      "choices": [
        "A hydraulic driver turning a drum with magnetic pick-offs.",
        "A synchronous motor driving an impeller against a spring.",
        "A spring-loaded vane.",
        "An impeller with magnetic inserts."
      ],
      "answer": "A spring-loaded vane."
    },
    {
      "question": "GPWS audio and visual __________ are triggered when the inner envelope is encroached. This requires immediate action to achieve a maximum__________ climb until terrain clearance is assured.",
      "choices": [
        "warnings; rate",
        "warnings; angle",
        "alerts; angle",
        "alerts; rate"
      ],
      "answer": "warnings; angle"
    },
    {
      "question": "This component, and the test/erase button, are the only controls on the flight deck.",
      "choices": [
        "The cockpit area microphone (CAM).",
        "The test panel",
        "The headset microphone",
        "The auto/on switch."
      ],
      "answer": "The auto/on switch."
    },
    {
      "question": "A millivoltmeter measuring the electromotive force between the hot junction and the cold junction of a thermocouple can be directly graduated in temperature values provided that the temperature of the:",
      "choices": [
        "Hot junction is maintained at 15\u00b0C.",
        "Hot junction is maintained constant.",
        "Cold junction is maintained at 15\u00b0C.",
        "Cold junction is maintained constant."
      ],
      "answer": "Cold junction is maintained constant."
    },
    {
      "question": "The quantity of fuel may be measured by:",
      "choices": [
        "Flow rate or temperature.",
        "Volume or mass.",
        "Mass or flow rate.",
        "Volume or flow rate."
      ],
      "answer": "Volume or mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the type of TCA's aural alert: 'Monitor vertical speed'.",
      "choices": [
        "Corrective Advisory",
        "Preventive Advisory",
        "Traffic Advisory",
        "Information Advisory"
      ],
      "answer": "Preventive Advisory"
    },
    {
      "question": "Management can use FDM data to discipline pilots for any parameter exceedances.",
      "choices": [
        "True",
        "False",
        "Always",
        "With union agreement"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "GPWS produces audio and visual __________ when the outer envelope is encroached. You must __________.",
      "choices": [
        "warnings; press the master caution twice",
        "alerts; adjust the flight path",
        "warnings; adjust the flight path",
        "alerts; press the master caution twice"
      ],
      "answer": "alerts; adjust the flight path"
    }
  ],
  "M&B": [
    {
      "question": "What happens if the CG is aft of the rear limit?",
      "choices": [
        "Controllability decreases.",
        "Stability increases.",
        "Stability decreases.",
        "Control forces will increase."
      ],
      "answer": "Stability decreases."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the boundaries of the MAC?",
      "choices": [
        "FwdMAC to RearMAC",
        "LeMAC to TeMAC",
        "MACMin to MACMax",
        "MinMAC to MaxMAC"
      ],
      "answer": "LeMAC to TeMAC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the smallest pallet which can support a 800 lb crate on a floor with a maximum area load of 68 lb per square foot.",
      "choices": [
        "3 ft 9 in x 3 ft 1 in.",
        "4 ft 4 in x 2 ft 9 in.",
        "3 ft 6 in x 3 ft 4 in.",
        "4 ft x 3 ft 3 in."
      ],
      "answer": "4 ft 4 in x 2 ft 9 in."
    },
    {
      "question": "If the weight acting through the nose wheel, left main wheel and right main wheel is determined to be 280 kg, 7278 kg and 7287 kg respectively, and the distance between the nose and main wheels is 6.7 m, where is the aeroplane's CG?",
      "choices": [
        "0.13 m aft of the main wheels.",
        "0.17 m aft of the main wheels.",
        "6.53 m aft of the nose wheel.",
        "6.57 m aft of the nose wheel."
      ],
      "answer": "6.57 m aft of the nose wheel."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is MAC numerically presented?",
      "choices": [
        "As a standard deviation.",
        "As a modal value.",
        "As a median value.",
        "As a percentage."
      ],
      "answer": "As a percentage."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the RTOM that you would enter in the load sheet for the MRJT aircraft, given the following limitations and information? MSTOM: 61 700 kg, PLTOM: 68 200 kg, MZFM: 51 500 kg, MRM: 64 050 kg, Taxi fuel: 320 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "61 700 kg",
        "63 370 kg",
        "68 200 kg",
        "51 500 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "61 700 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The effect of the centre of gravity (CG) being close to the forward limit is:",
      "choices": [
        "decreased induced drag.",
        "reduced specific fuel consumption.",
        "a reduced rate of climb capability.",
        "an improved rate of climb capability."
      ],
      "answer": "a reduced rate of climb capability."
    },
    {
      "question": "The centre of gravity is the:",
      "choices": [
        "Centre of thrust along the longitudinal axis, in relation to a datum line.",
        "Neutral point along the longitudinal axis, in relation to a datum line.",
        "Point where all the aircraft mass is considered to be concentrated.",
        "Focus along the longitudinal axis, in relation to a datum line."
      ],
      "answer": "Point where all the aircraft mass is considered to be concentrated."
    },
    {
      "question": "Loads must be adequately secured in order to:",
      "choices": [
        "avoid any Centre of Gravity (CG) movement during flight.",
        "prevent excessive 'g' loading during the landing flare.",
        "avoid unplanned Centre of Gravity (CG) movement and aircraft damage.",
        "allow steep turns."
      ],
      "answer": "avoid unplanned Centre of Gravity (CG) movement and aircraft damage."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information what is the allowed take-off mass and maximum traffic load for the B737? MRM 63 060 kg, start up and taxi 300 kg, RTOM 62 800 kg, RLM 54 900 kg, MZFM 51 300 kg, DOM 34 300 kg, Block fuel 11 500 kg trip fuel 8700 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "62 500 kg and 16 700 kg respectively.",
        "62 800 kg and 17 000 kg respectively.",
        "62 500 kg and 17 000 kg respectively.",
        "62 800 kg and 17 300 kg respectively."
      ],
      "answer": "62 500 kg and 17 000 kg respectively."
    },
    {
      "question": "The AFM or POH or company operations manual contains a weighing schedule pertaining to the: __________ and balance arm data.",
      "choices": [
        "Moment",
        "Traffic Load",
        "Variable Load",
        "Datum"
      ],
      "answer": "Datum"
    },
    {
      "question": "What value is given to the Earth\u2019s gravitational field (g) on and close to the Earth\u2019s surface?",
      "choices": [
        "9.91 m/s\u00b3",
        "8.91 m/s\u00b2",
        "8.81 m/s\u2074",
        "9.81 m/s\u00b2"
      ],
      "answer": "9.81 m/s\u00b2"
    },
    {
      "question": "You uplift 4400 Imp Gall of fuel with SG of 0.80, what is the weight of the fuel?",
      "choices": [
        "156 980 kg",
        "156 980 N",
        "130 700 N",
        "16 002 N"
      ],
      "answer": "156 980 N"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a given configuration, the stall speed of an aeroplane will be highest when loaded:",
      "choices": [
        "to the maximum allowable mass with the most aft CG.",
        "to a low total mass with the most aft CG.",
        "to the maximum allowable mass with the most forward CG.",
        "to a low total mass with the most forward CG."
      ],
      "answer": "to the maximum allowable mass with the most forward CG."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following formulae best describes the ratio method for adjusting CG?",
      "choices": [
        "(m \u00f7 M)\u00b2 = d \u00f7 D",
        "m \u00f7 M = d \u00f7 D",
        "m \u00f7 M = d x D",
        "m x M = d x D"
      ],
      "answer": "m \u00f7 M = d \u00f7 D"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which two components comprise the Useful Load?",
      "choices": [
        "Basic Empty Mass and Variable Load",
        "Traffic Load and Variable Load",
        "Basic Empty Mass and Traffic Load",
        "Traffic Load and Fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "Traffic Load and Fuel"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following may result from an out-of-limits CG?",
      "choices": [
        "Reduced service ceiling.",
        "Loss of control, or reduced control effectiveness.",
        "Over-responsive control forces.",
        "Inability to descend from the cruise."
      ],
      "answer": "Loss of control, or reduced control effectiveness."
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the statement below with the correct words. The Final Reserve fuel is the remaining fuel which must be on board at the planned landing at the planned destination. It allows for a further period of holding at __________ ft above the alternate destination. The periods are __________ minutes for turbine engined aircraft and __________ minutes for piston engined aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "1000; 30; 45",
        "1500; 45; 60",
        "1500; 30; 45",
        "1000; 45; 60"
      ],
      "answer": "1500; 30; 45"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the allowed take-off mass for an A320 given the following information: RTOM 73 500 kg, RLM 60 500 kg, MZFM 59 000 kg, take-off fuel 12 000 kg and trip fuel 8500 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "73 500 kg",
        "67 500 kg",
        "69 000 kg",
        "71 000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "69 000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using the cargo data from CAP 696, what is the maximum mass that can be placed in a container, length 62.7 in, in the aft part of the forward compartment of the MRJT?",
      "choices": [
        "822 kg",
        "823 kg",
        "820 kg",
        "821 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "822 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a component of All Up Mass?",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel",
        "Reference Load",
        "Variable Load",
        "Basic Empty Mass"
      ],
      "answer": "Reference Load"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum running load of the aft cargo hold of an aeroplane is 1650 kg/m. Assume the standard mass of the proposed pallet is 120 kg and 2299 kg of baggage have to be loaded in the aft cargo hold. Which of the following pallets (length x width) should be used in order to comply with the running load limit and to optimise best the space in the cargo hold?",
      "choices": [
        "1 .45 m x 1 .44 m",
        "1.48 m x 1.46 m",
        "1.50m x 1.47m",
        "1.43 m x 1.40 m"
      ],
      "answer": "1.48 m x 1.46 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the mass in kilograms of 15 000 litres of fuel with an SG of 0.82?",
      "choices": [
        "18 292 kg",
        "1230 kg",
        "12 300 kg",
        "27 200 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "12 300 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the usual term (in aviation) given to the tendency of a force to rotate an object around an axis:",
      "choices": [
        "Turning Force.",
        "Moment.",
        "CG.",
        "Turning Effect."
      ],
      "answer": "Moment."
    },
    {
      "question": "Exceeding the forward CG limit during landing may result in: __________ control forces.",
      "choices": [
        "lower",
        "higher",
        "decreased",
        "minimum"
      ],
      "answer": "higher"
    },
    {
      "question": "Exceeding the forward CG limit may result in: __________ range and endurance.",
      "choices": [
        "maximum",
        "increased",
        "reduced",
        "minimum"
      ],
      "answer": "reduced"
    },
    {
      "question": "Exceeding the forward CG limit may result in: __________ fuel flow.",
      "choices": [
        "reduced",
        "increased",
        "minimum",
        "maximum"
      ],
      "answer": "increased"
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens to the CG if load is added forward of the original CG?",
      "choices": [
        "CG moves forward",
        "CP moves forward",
        "CP moves aft",
        "CG remains unmoved"
      ],
      "answer": "CG moves forward"
    },
    {
      "question": "After pre-flight planning but before dispatch a pilot accepts an additional 3000 kg of the traffic load, but in error does not recalculate the aircraft's performance. Assuming that the take- off phase is achieved safely, subsequent effects of this error would include:",
      "choices": [
        "a reduction in the rate of climb and the range.",
        "a reduction in the fuel flow and endurance.",
        "an improved angle of climb and increased obstacle clearance.",
        "an increase in the fuel flow and specific range."
      ],
      "answer": "a reduction in the rate of climb and the range."
    },
    {
      "question": "What effect does the CG on the aft limit have on the fuel consumption of an aeroplane?",
      "choices": [
        "Marginal increase",
        "Decreases",
        "No effect",
        "Increase"
      ],
      "answer": "Decreases"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following describes a possible handling and performance problem encountered with a CG too far aft?",
      "choices": [
        "Improvement in nose-wheel steering.",
        "Degradation or loss of nose-wheel steering.",
        "No likelihood of a nose-up overbalance (on a tricycle gear aircraft) on the ground resulting in tail damage.",
        "Decreased tendency to skid."
      ],
      "answer": "Degradation or loss of nose-wheel steering."
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens if you overload your helicopter with 3000kg?",
      "choices": [
        "Reduced range and manoeuvrability",
        "Increased endurance",
        "Reduced endurance and less drag",
        "Reduced endurance and increased range"
      ],
      "answer": "Reduced range and manoeuvrability"
    },
    {
      "question": "For an aircraft to be in equilibrium: The sum of all __________ must be zero.",
      "choices": [
        "datums",
        "arms",
        "weights",
        "moments"
      ],
      "answer": "moments"
    },
    {
      "question": "For an aircraft to be in equilibrium: The forces in any direction must be equal and __________.",
      "choices": [
        "zero",
        "balanced",
        "datums",
        "opposite"
      ],
      "answer": "opposite"
    },
    {
      "question": "The CG of a B737 aeroplane mass 52 000 kg must move aft by 1 ft. If the original CG is at a BA of 621 in and the centroid of the compartment is at BA 1046.5, what is the minimum mass that must be added or removed?",
      "choices": [
        "1509 kg must be added.",
        "1773 kg must be added.",
        "1714 kg must be removed.",
        "1714 kg must be added."
      ],
      "answer": "1509 kg must be added."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum fuel that can be loaded at the ramp for the MEP sample aircraft, given the following limitations and information? RTOM: 4820 lb, RLM: 4610 lb, MZFM: 4510 lb, Trip fuel: 260 lb, DOM: 3660 lb, Traffic load: 840 lb, Start-up and taxi fuel: 35 lb, Max (long range) fuel tank capacity: 880 lb.",
      "choices": [
        "260 lb",
        "880 lb",
        "225 lb",
        "355 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "355 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "Exceeding the forward CG limit may result in: increased __________ speeds (and related take-off and landing speeds).",
      "choices": [
        "stall",
        "maximum",
        "drag",
        "minimum"
      ],
      "answer": "stall"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft, for a given AUM, taking-off at a hot or high aerodrome requires a longer distance than taking off at sea level in ISA conditions, is an example of?",
      "choices": [
        "Altitude Limited Take-Off Mass",
        "Maximum Structural Take-off Mass",
        "Performance Limited Take-Off Mass",
        "Altitude Limited Landing Mass"
      ],
      "answer": "Performance Limited Take-Off Mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "The CG of a B737 aeroplane mass 52 000 kg must move aft by 1 ft. If the original CG is at a BA of 621 in and the centroid of the compartment is at BA 257, what is the minimum mass that must be added or removed?",
      "choices": [
        "1714 kg must be added.",
        "1714 kg must be removed.",
        "1660 kg must be added.",
        "1660 kg must be removed."
      ],
      "answer": "1660 kg must be removed."
    },
    {
      "question": "What types of limits are imposed on maximum masses?",
      "choices": [
        "Balance and Mass",
        "Gravity and Mass",
        "Performance and Structural",
        "Structural and Gravitational"
      ],
      "answer": "Performance and Structural"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is bulk cargo restrained within the aircraft's cargo holds?",
      "choices": [
        "By arranging them carefully so that they don't fall over in flight.",
        "By strapping it down to pallets, locked into place using restraining straps.",
        "By using restraining nets, attached to attachment points and tie-down points.",
        "By placing it inside ULDs, latched onto roller tracks."
      ],
      "answer": "By using restraining nets, attached to attachment points and tie-down points."
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the maximum mass that can be loaded on a pallet sized 1.2 m x 1.2 m, to comply with a maximum running load of 1915 kg/m.",
      "choices": [
        "2757 kg",
        "4596 kg",
        "1596 kg",
        "2298 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "2298 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum traffic load for the MRJT aircraft, given the following limitations and information? RTOM: 65 400 kg, RLM: 53 400 kg (performance limited), MZFM: 50 200 kg, Trip fuel: 4200 kg, T/O fuel: 5 500 kg, DOM: 32 800 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "22 900 kg",
        "27 100 kg",
        "19 300 kg",
        "17 400 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "17 400 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the RTOM of a B747-400, with an MSTOM of 385 000 kg operating off a given runway with a PLTOM of 357 500 kg? Block Fuel = 122 500 kg",
      "choices": [
        "357 500 kg",
        "385 000 kg",
        "262 500 kg",
        "235 000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "357 500 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The formula for calculating %MAC is:",
      "choices": [
        "%MAC = (LeMAC to CG x MAC) \u00f7 100",
        "%MAC = (LeMAC to CG \u00f7 MAC) x 100",
        "%MAC = 100 \u00f7 (LeMAC to CG \u00f7 MAC)",
        "%MAC = (LeMAC to CG \u00f7 MAC) x 60"
      ],
      "answer": "%MAC = (LeMAC to CG \u00f7 MAC) x 100"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is/are used to secure ULDs inside the aircraft fuselage?",
      "choices": [
        "Male/female and bayonet type locking points on the cargo hold floor",
        "Latches within rollers and tracks, or straps at tie-down points",
        "Locking points at strategic positions along the aircraft fuselage bulkheads",
        "ULD containers which fit tightly into channels"
      ],
      "answer": "Latches within rollers and tracks, or straps at tie-down points"
    },
    {
      "question": "The floor limit of an aircraft cargo hold is 5 000 N/m\u00b2. It is planned to load-up a cubic container measuring 0.4 m of side. It's maximum gross mass must not exceed (assume g = 10 m/s\u00b2):",
      "choices": [
        "320 kg",
        "800 kg",
        "80 kg",
        "32 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "80 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "A moment is:",
      "choices": [
        "The point in the horizontal plane from which all masses are referenced.",
        "The point through which the force of gravity is said to act.",
        "The distance from datum to the CG of the mass.",
        "The product of the mass and the balance arm."
      ],
      "answer": "The product of the mass and the balance arm."
    },
    {
      "question": "By what term is the origin of the aerodynamic forces known?",
      "choices": [
        "Centre of Pressure",
        "Moment Arm",
        "Mean Aerodynamical Chord",
        "Centre of Gravity"
      ],
      "answer": "Centre of Pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given : Actual mass 116 500 lb, Original CG station 435.0, Compartment A station 285.5, Compartment B station 792.5. If 390 lb of cargo is moved from compartment B (aft) to compartment A (forward), what is the station number of the new CG?",
      "choices": [
        "433.3",
        "423.3",
        "506.3",
        "463.7"
      ],
      "answer": "433.3"
    },
    {
      "question": "The term _________ describes the quantity of matter a solid body possesses.",
      "choices": [
        "weight",
        "mass",
        "specific gravity",
        "density"
      ],
      "answer": "mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the DOM plus the traffic load known as?",
      "choices": [
        "The zero fuel mass.",
        "The operating mass.",
        "The useful load.",
        "The all up mass."
      ],
      "answer": "The zero fuel mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum allowed mass of a container (66 in x 59.4 in x 64 in high) that can be loaded into the aft part of the forward compartment of the MRJT specimen aircraft? (Maximum distribution load 66 kg/ft\u00b2)",
      "choices": [
        "1792 kg",
        "1797 kg",
        "1796 kg",
        "1790 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "1796 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum crate mass that can be placed on a 30 lb spreader 4 ft x 2 ft 9 in, if the maximum area distribution load is 84 lb per sq ft?",
      "choices": [
        "974 lb.",
        "924 lb.",
        "944 lb.",
        "894 lb."
      ],
      "answer": "894 lb."
    },
    {
      "question": "Exceeding the forward CG limit may result in: decreased __________ speed (because of the increased drag).",
      "choices": [
        "stall",
        "drag",
        "minimum",
        "maximum"
      ],
      "answer": "maximum"
    },
    {
      "question": "Moving the CG forward and aft changes the amount of tail down force and lift required for stable flight: An aft CG requires less tail down force = less lift = __________ induced drag = __________ performance.",
      "choices": [
        "less; reduced",
        "more; reduced",
        "more; improved",
        "less; improved"
      ],
      "answer": "less; improved"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following formulae describes the ratio of masses to balance arms for determining the new CG?",
      "choices": [
        "m x MN = d x DarmCGN",
        "m \u00f7 MO = d \u00f7 DarmCGO",
        "m \u00f7 MN = d \u00f7 DarmCGN",
        "m \u00f7 MN = d \u00f7 DarmCGO"
      ],
      "answer": "m \u00f7 MN = d \u00f7 DarmCGO"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the distance that the CG moves if bag mass 27 lb is moved from the aft baggage zone (165.5 in) to the forward baggage zone (18.5 in) in a light twin mass 2000 kg?",
      "choices": [
        "2.2 in.",
        "1.3 in.",
        "2.4 in.",
        "0.9 in."
      ],
      "answer": "0.9 in."
    },
    {
      "question": "The chord of an imaginary, equivalent, rectangular wing, which has the same pitching characteristics as the actual wing, is called:",
      "choices": [
        "Mean Aerodynamical Chord (MAC)",
        "Minimum Aerodynamical Chord (MAC)",
        "Maximum Average Chord (MAC)",
        "Mean Average Chord (MAC)"
      ],
      "answer": "Mean Aerodynamical Chord (MAC)"
    },
    {
      "question": "The point in the horizontal plane from which all masses are referenced is:",
      "choices": [
        "The datum.",
        "The aircraft's nose.",
        "The CG position.",
        "The CG point."
      ],
      "answer": "The datum."
    },
    {
      "question": "On an aeroplane with its wing tanks filled with fuel and only its centre tank empty, when is the wing load at its maximum?",
      "choices": [
        "On landing.",
        "During cruise.",
        "At the brake release point.",
        "On take-off."
      ],
      "answer": "On landing."
    },
    {
      "question": "Comparing a forward CG position with an aft one, the forward cg position will cause a:",
      "choices": [
        "decrease of the stalling speed.",
        "tendency to yaw to the right on take-off.",
        "decrease in range.",
        "decrease in the landing speed."
      ],
      "answer": "decrease in range."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following, what is the traffic load? BEM 15 000 kg, OM 22 000 kg, variable load 1000 kg, ZFM 24 000 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "6000 kg",
        "4000 kg",
        "9000 kg",
        "8000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "8000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the statement below with the correct words. Landing Mass = __________ Mass - __________ Fuel.",
      "choices": [
        "Ramp; Taxi",
        "Take-off; Trip",
        "Start-up; Taxi",
        "Ramp; Trip"
      ],
      "answer": "Take-off; Trip"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name of the point through which the force of gravity is said to act?",
      "choices": [
        "Centre of Balance",
        "Centre of Gravity",
        "Centre of Gravitational Force",
        "Centre of Pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "Centre of Gravity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is correct? I. Stall speeds are determined with the CG at the forward limit. II. Minimum control speeds are determined with the CG at the aft limit.",
      "choices": [
        "I is incorrect, II is correct.",
        "I is correct, II is incorrect.",
        "I is correct, II is correct.",
        "I is incorrect, II is incorrect."
      ],
      "answer": "I is correct, II is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum fuel that can be loaded at the ramp for the MEP sample aircraft, given the following limitations and information? RTOM: 4780 lb, RLM: 4505 lb, MZFM: 4470 lb, Trip fuel: 225 lb, DOM: 3390 lb, Traffic load: 610 lb, Start-up and taxi fuel: 25 lb, Max (long range) fuel tank capacity: 820 lb.",
      "choices": [
        "570 lb",
        "755 lb",
        "730 lb",
        "820 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "755 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "2 planks of wood, 4 ft 6 in x 12 in, are available and can be used as load spreaders to carry a crate of mass 400 lb. Each plank has a mass of 12.5 lb. What is the area load limit carried?",
      "choices": [
        "94.44 lb/ft\u00b2",
        "47.22 lb/ft\u00b2",
        "49.66 lb/ft\u00b2",
        "7.87 lb/ft\u00b2"
      ],
      "answer": "47.22 lb/ft\u00b2"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the leading edge of MAC is at -0.92 m and the trailing edge at +3.46m, what is the %MAC if the CG is at -0.08 m?",
      "choices": [
        "8.9%.",
        "0.219",
        "19.2%.",
        "36.8%."
      ],
      "answer": "19.2%."
    },
    {
      "question": "The floor of the main cargo hold is limited to 4 000 N/m\u00b2. It is planned to load a cubic container each side of which measures 0.5m. Its maximum gross mass must not exceed: (assume g=10m/s\u00b2)",
      "choices": [
        "1000 kg",
        "500 kg",
        "5000 kg",
        "100 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "100 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The distance from the datum to the aircraft's CG is:",
      "choices": [
        "The moment.",
        "The centre of pressure",
        "The centre of gravity.",
        "The moment arm."
      ],
      "answer": "The moment arm."
    },
    {
      "question": "The PLLM is:",
      "choices": [
        "The maximum permitted take-off mass.",
        "The maximum permitted landing mass.",
        "The maximum permissible aeroplane mass with no useable fuel.",
        "The maximum mass due to landing runway limitations."
      ],
      "answer": "The maximum mass due to landing runway limitations."
    },
    {
      "question": "How many Imperial Gallons are there in 265 US Gallons?",
      "choices": [
        "280",
        "320",
        "220",
        "165"
      ],
      "answer": "220"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the effects of a CG in front of the forward limit? Range:",
      "choices": [
        "and absolute ceiling decrease.",
        "decreases and absolute ceiling increases.",
        "and absolute ceiling increase.",
        "increases and absolute ceiling decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "and absolute ceiling decrease."
    },
    {
      "question": "Operating Mass is a combination of:",
      "choices": [
        "Basic Empty Mass, Variable Load and Fuel",
        "Dry Operating Mass and Useful Load",
        "Basic Empty Mass, Traffic Load and Variable Load",
        "Basic Empty Mass, Traffic Load and Fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "Basic Empty Mass, Variable Load and Fuel"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the take-off mass? AUM on the Ramp (Ramp mass): 220 000 kg, DOM: 145 000 kg, Traffic load: 35 000 kg, Useful load: 75 000 kg, Start-up and taxi fuel 600 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "144 400 kg",
        "109 400 kg",
        "219 400 kg",
        "220 600 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "219 400 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "CG positions are usually shown in operational aircraft documents:",
      "choices": [
        "As a bar chart.",
        "Using an aeroplane pictogram.",
        "As tabular data.",
        "In graphical form."
      ],
      "answer": "In graphical form."
    },
    {
      "question": "You uplift 3000 US Gallons of fuel, how many litres is this?",
      "choices": [
        "660 litres",
        "9840 litres",
        "11 355 litres",
        "13 638 litres"
      ],
      "answer": "11 355 litres"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which two components comprise the Dry Operating Mass?",
      "choices": [
        "Traffic Load and Fuel",
        "Traffic Load and Variable Load",
        "Basic Empty Mass and Variable Load",
        "Basic Empty Mass and Traffic Load"
      ],
      "answer": "Basic Empty Mass and Variable Load"
    },
    {
      "question": "A container has a base area of 1.44 m\u00b2. The container is loaded on two ground supports (of negligible mass), each having floor-contact dimensions of 0.2 m x 1.2 m. Given that the maximum permissible floor load of the cargo compartment, which is 732 kg/m\u00b2, must be respected, what is the maximum mass that can be loaded in the container?",
      "choices": [
        "1054 kg",
        "351 kg",
        "175 kg",
        "1525 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "351 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum traffic load for the MRJT aircraft, given the following limitations and information? RTOM: 62 900 kg, RLM: 51 400 kg (performance limited), MZFM: 51 800 kg, Trip fuel: 4100 kg, T/O fuel: 6 600 kg, DOM: 33 600 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "22 700 kg",
        "18 200 kg",
        "19 900 kg",
        "15 300 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "15 300 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is used to prevent cargo from shifting during flight?",
      "choices": [
        "The cargo hold must be filled (using empty containers if necessary)",
        "A secure restraint system",
        "Latches and locks",
        "Maintaining the aircraft flight envelope within CG limitations"
      ],
      "answer": "A secure restraint system"
    },
    {
      "question": "Exceeding the forward CG limit during landing may result in: __________ nose wheel loads.",
      "choices": [
        "minimum",
        "excessive",
        "higher",
        "reduced"
      ],
      "answer": "excessive"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the statement below with the correct words. __________ fuel allows for small changes in fuel burn caused by unexpected routing, changes of cruise level and/or changes in the forecast wind.",
      "choices": [
        "Contingency",
        "Block",
        "Emergency",
        "Trip"
      ],
      "answer": "Contingency"
    },
    {
      "question": "The AFM or POH or company operations manual contains a weighing schedule pertaining to the: __________ of the empty aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "BEM",
        "DOM",
        "OM",
        "Traffic Load"
      ],
      "answer": "BEM"
    },
    {
      "question": "The length of a B737-400 is 36.45 m, what is its length in feet?",
      "choices": [
        "109 ft 4 in",
        "119 ft 5 in",
        "11 ft 1 in",
        "119 ft 7 in"
      ],
      "answer": "119 ft 7 in"
    },
    {
      "question": "Zero Fuel Mass is a combination of:",
      "choices": [
        "Basic Empty Mass, Variable Load and Fuel",
        "Basic Empty Mass, Traffic Load and Variable Load",
        "Basic Empty Mass, Traffic Load and Fuel",
        "Dry Operating Mass and Useful Load"
      ],
      "answer": "Basic Empty Mass, Traffic Load and Variable Load"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the leading edge of MAC is at -0.92 m and the trailing edge at +3.64m, what is the %MAC if the CG is at -0.08 m?",
      "choices": [
        "36.8%.",
        "18.4%.",
        "0.192",
        "21.9%."
      ],
      "answer": "18.4%."
    },
    {
      "question": "The allowed take-off mass may be defined as which of the following?",
      "choices": [
        "The MZFM + Trip Fuel",
        "The RTOM + Trip Fuel",
        "The RLM + Take-off Fuel",
        "The MZFM + Take-off Fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "The MZFM + Take-off Fuel"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is best defined as \"the aircraft mass before the crew, fuel, passengers, baggage, cargo and necessary equipment to support them are added.\"",
      "choices": [
        "Traffic Load",
        "Fuel",
        "Basic Empty Mass",
        "Variable Load"
      ],
      "answer": "Basic Empty Mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 15 kg mass is placed on the left hand end of a 2 m beam and a 25 kg on the right hand end. The centre of gravity is:",
      "choices": [
        "1.25 m left of the 25 kg mass.",
        "1.3 m right of the 15 kg mass.",
        "0.7 m left of the 25 kg mass.",
        "1.25 m right of the 15 kg mass."
      ],
      "answer": "1.25 m right of the 15 kg mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these following statements is INCORRECT?",
      "choices": [
        "The regulated landing mass is the maximum permitted landing mass, which complies with both structural and performance landing mass limitations.",
        "The regulated take-off mass is the maximum permitted take-off mass, which complies with both structural and performance take-off mass limitations.",
        "The regulated landing mass is the lower of the MSLM and PLLM.",
        "The regulated landing mass is the greater of the MSLM and PLLM."
      ],
      "answer": "The regulated landing mass is the greater of the MSLM and PLLM."
    },
    {
      "question": "The AFM or POH or company operations manual contains a weighing schedule pertaining to the: Centre of gravity __________ and limits.",
      "choices": [
        "moment",
        "datum",
        "BEM",
        "envelope"
      ],
      "answer": "envelope"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum permissible floor loading for a cargo compartment in an aircraft is given as 170 kg per square metre. A package with a mass of 374 kg is to be loaded. Assuming the pallet base is entirely in contact with the floor, which of the following is the minimum size pallet that can be used?",
      "choices": [
        "1.6 m x 1.5 m",
        "1.45 m x 1.45 m",
        "1.8 m x 1.4 m",
        "1.6 m x 1.4 m"
      ],
      "answer": "1.6 m x 1.4 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the main types of ULD used?",
      "choices": [
        "Flight cases and aircraft loading containers.",
        "Containers and flight cases.",
        "Flight cases and pallets.",
        "Containers and pallets."
      ],
      "answer": "Containers and pallets."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the listed types of cargo can be found in a bulk cargo compartment?",
      "choices": [
        "Containerised cargo.",
        "Live animals.",
        "Late-arrival and crew baggage.",
        "Palletised cargo."
      ],
      "answer": "Late-arrival and crew baggage."
    },
    {
      "question": "If the centre of gravity is outside the forward limit in level and forward flight, the drag :",
      "choices": [
        "decreases, and the fuel consumption decreases.",
        "increases, and endurance decreases.",
        "increases, and endurance increases.",
        "decreases, and the range decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "increases, and endurance decreases."
    },
    {
      "question": "The useful load is:",
      "choices": [
        "The gross mass of the aeroplane ready for flight but excluding fuel.",
        "The gross mass of the aeroplane ready for flight but excluding traffic load.",
        "The combined mass of the passengers, baggage, cargo and non-revenue load.",
        "The mass of the traffic load and fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "The mass of the traffic load and fuel."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information what is the allowed take-off mass and maximum traffic load for the B737? MRM 63 060 kg, start up and taxi 300 kg, RTOM 62 800 kg, RLM 48 900 kg, MZFM 51 300 kg, DOM 34 300 kg, Block fuel 11 500 kg trip fuel 8700 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "57 300 kg and 11 800 kg respectively.",
        "57 600 kg and 12 100 kg respectively.",
        "57 600 kg and 12 400 kg respectively.",
        "57 600 kg and 11 800 kg respectively."
      ],
      "answer": "57 600 kg and 12 100 kg respectively."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following what is the fuel load? BEM 14 000 kg, traffic load 9000 kg, variable load 2000 kg, useful load 15 000 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "5000 kg",
        "3000 kg",
        "6000 kg",
        "7000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "6000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The term _________ _________ is the ratio of the density of a liquid to the density of water at +4\u00b0C.",
      "choices": [
        "weight",
        "Nautical miles",
        "specific gravity",
        "mass"
      ],
      "answer": "specific gravity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following units are not used to calculate area load limits?",
      "choices": [
        "Kilograms per square foot - kg/ft\u00b2",
        "Pounds per square foot - lb/ft\u00b2",
        "Kilograms per cubic metre - kg/m\u00b3",
        "Kilograms per square metre - kg/m\u00b2"
      ],
      "answer": "Kilograms per cubic metre - kg/m\u00b3"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is distance to the new CG (CGN) calculated using the \u2018Moment Method'?",
      "choices": [
        "Distance to New CG (CGN) = Moment\u00b2 x \u00bdMass",
        "Distance to New CG (CGN) = \u221a(Moment x Mass)",
        "Distance to New CG (CGN) = Moment \u00f7 Mass",
        "Distance to New CG (CGN) = Moment x Mass"
      ],
      "answer": "Distance to New CG (CGN) = Moment \u00f7 Mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens if an existing load is moved aft?",
      "choices": [
        "CG moves aft",
        "CG remains unmoved",
        "CG moves forward",
        "CP moves aft"
      ],
      "answer": "CG moves aft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Moving the CG forward and aft changes the amount of tail down force and lift required for stable flight: A forward CG requires more tail down force = more lift = __________ induced drag = __________ performance.",
      "choices": [
        "more; improved",
        "less; reduced",
        "more; reduced",
        "less; improved"
      ],
      "answer": "more; reduced"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following, what is the AUM? BEM 15 000 kg, OM 22 000 kg, variable load 1000 kg, ZFM 25 000 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "37 000 kg",
        "31 000 kg",
        "32 000 kg",
        "29 000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "31 000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "If during flight a considerable amount of fuel was transferred from a fuel tank located in the forward fuselage section to a fuel tank located at the rear section of the fuselage, what effect would this have on the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "increase in range and stall speed.",
        "increase in range and decrease in stall speed.",
        "increase in stability and trim drag.",
        "Increase in stability and decrease in trim drag."
      ],
      "answer": "increase in range and decrease in stall speed."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is %MAC usually shown in operational aircraft documents?",
      "choices": [
        "Tabular data",
        "Computerised graph only",
        "Graphical form",
        "Airplane pictogram"
      ],
      "answer": "Graphical form"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many US Gallons are there in 340 Imperial Gallons?",
      "choices": [
        "320",
        "220",
        "408",
        "283"
      ],
      "answer": "408"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Max Traffic Load = ATOM + DOM \u2013 Take-Off Fuel",
        "Max Traffic Load = ATOM \u2013 DOM \u2013 Take-Off Fuel",
        "Max Traffic Load = ATOM \u2013 DOM + Take-Off Fuel",
        "Max Traffic Load = ATOM + DOM + Take-Off Fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "Max Traffic Load = ATOM \u2013 DOM \u2013 Take-Off Fuel"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is moved by shifting an existing load to a new position?",
      "choices": [
        "The CP position.",
        "The %MAC.",
        "The datum position.",
        "The CG position."
      ],
      "answer": "The CG position."
    },
    {
      "question": "If an aeroplane is at a higher mass than anticipated, for a given airspeed the angle of attack will:",
      "choices": [
        "Remain constant, drag will decrease and endurance will decrease.",
        "Be greater, drag will increase and endurance will decrease.",
        "Be decreased, drag will decrease and endurance will increase.",
        "Remain constant, drag will increase and endurance will increase."
      ],
      "answer": "Be greater, drag will increase and endurance will decrease."
    },
    {
      "question": "The range of permissible CG positions is limited by:",
      "choices": [
        "Maximum and minimum forward (fore) and rearward (aft) CG limits",
        "Maximum forward (fore) and rearward (aft) CG limits",
        "Maximum forward (fore), lateral and rearward (aft) CG limits",
        "Maximum and minimum forward (fore), lateral and rearward (aft) CG limits"
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum forward (fore) and rearward (aft) CG limits"
    },
    {
      "question": "Exceeding the forward CG limit during landing may result in: __________ performance.",
      "choices": [
        "increased",
        "decreased",
        "minimum",
        "higher"
      ],
      "answer": "decreased"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum intensity floor loading for an aeroplane is given in the Flight Manual as 650 kg per square metre. What is the maximum mass of a package which can be safely supported on a pallet with dimensions of 80 cm by 80 cm?",
      "choices": [
        "41.6 kg",
        "1015.6 kg",
        "416.0 kg",
        "101.6 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "416.0 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following formulae describes the minimum ballast mass (m) to be loaded?",
      "choices": [
        "m \u00f7 MN = d \u00f7 DarmCGO",
        "m \u00f7 MN = d \u00f7 DarmCGN",
        "m x MO = d x DarmCGO",
        "m \u00f7 MO = d \u00f7 DarmCGN"
      ],
      "answer": "m \u00f7 MO = d \u00f7 DarmCGN"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the effect of a forward CG on the time to reach cruising altitude?",
      "choices": [
        "A forward CG decreases the maximum Rate of Climb and increases the time to reach cruising altitude.",
        "A forward CG increases the maximum Rate of Climb and decreases the time to reach cruising altitude.",
        "The CG position has no impact on the Rate of Climb.",
        "A forward CG allows the selection of a higher cruising altitude, therefore increases the time to reach cruising altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "A forward CG decreases the maximum Rate of Climb and increases the time to reach cruising altitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following formulae is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Moment = Distance \u00f7 Force",
        "Moment = Force x Distance",
        "Moment = Force \u00f7 Distance",
        "Moment = (Force x Distance)\u00b2"
      ],
      "answer": "Moment = Force x Distance"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mass is measured in __________ or pounds.",
      "choices": [
        "kilograms",
        "gallons",
        "litres",
        "metres"
      ],
      "answer": "kilograms"
    },
    {
      "question": "The structural limitation of a baggage compartment is 50 lb/ft\u00b2. load has a mass of 320 kg and has to be distributed over an area of at least:",
      "choices": [
        "1.31 m\u00b2",
        "6.4 m\u00b2",
        "0.76 m\u00b2",
        "14.11 m\u00b2"
      ],
      "answer": "1.31 m\u00b2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the allowed (maximum) take-off mass for a light MEP aircraft given the following limitations and information. MSTOM: 4750 lb, PLTOM: 4690 lb, MZFM: 4470 lb, MSLM: 4510 lb, PLLM: 4750 lb, Trip fuel: 380 lb, T/O fuel: 460 lb",
      "choices": [
        "4970 lb",
        "4930 lb",
        "4690 lb",
        "4510 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "4690 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "When in equilibrium:",
      "choices": [
        "The forces acting on an aircraft are reduced to zero.",
        "The forces acting on an aircraft are equal.",
        "The aircraft must be in straight, steady, unaccelerated flight.",
        "The sum of the moments of the forces are zero."
      ],
      "answer": "The sum of the moments of the forces are zero."
    },
    {
      "question": "The fuel load before APU start is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Block Fuel",
        "Trip Fuel",
        "Taxi Fuel",
        "All-Up Fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "Block Fuel"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the statement below with the correct words. Take-Off Mass = __________ Mass - __________ Fuel.",
      "choices": [
        "Ramp; Taxi",
        "Ramp; Trip",
        "Start-up; Taxi",
        "Take-off; Trip"
      ],
      "answer": "Ramp; Taxi"
    },
    {
      "question": "The stalling speed of an aeroplane will be highest when it is loaded with a:",
      "choices": [
        "high gross mass and aft centre of gravity.",
        "high gross mass and forward centre of gravity.",
        "low gross mass and forward centre of gravity.",
        "low gross mass and aft centre of gravity."
      ],
      "answer": "high gross mass and forward centre of gravity."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the allowed take-off mass for an A340-600 given the following information: MSTOM 380 000 kg, PLTOM 390 000 kg, MSLM 262 000 kg, PLM 254 000 kg, MZFM 246 000 kg, take-off fuel 149 000 kg and trip fuel 128 000 kg, MRM 381 200 kg and start up and taxi 1500 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "382 000 kg",
        "380 000 kg",
        "395 000 kg",
        "379 700 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "379 700 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Exceeding the forward CG limit during landing may result in: __________ stalling speeds.",
      "choices": [
        "decreased",
        "lower",
        "minimum",
        "higher"
      ],
      "answer": "higher"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the effects of modifications on mass and CG are not, or cannot be, accurately calculated:",
      "choices": [
        "The aircraft must be re-weighed.",
        "The manufacturer must be notified.",
        "The aircraft must be withdrawn from service.",
        "The aircraft must be operated within the previously defined parameters."
      ],
      "answer": "The aircraft must be re-weighed."
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the table below, what is the CG for the Landing Mass?",
      "choices": [
        "88.92",
        "86.79",
        "86.31",
        "85.28"
      ],
      "answer": "86.79"
    },
    {
      "question": "In calculations with respect to the position of the centre of gravity a reference is made to a datum. The datum is:",
      "choices": [
        "A reference plane which is chosen by the aircraft manufacturer. Its position is given in the Aircraft Flight or Loading Manual.",
        "Calculated from the data derived from the weighing procedure carried out on the aircraft after any major modification.",
        "An arbitrary reference chosen by the pilot which can be located anywhere on the aircraft.",
        "Calculated from the loading manifest."
      ],
      "answer": "A reference plane which is chosen by the aircraft manufacturer. Its position is given in the Aircraft Flight or Loading Manual."
    },
    {
      "question": "At which flap setting(s) can the stabiliser trim (stab trim) setting for take-off be extracted directly from the trim sheet?",
      "choices": [
        "2\u00b0",
        "15\u00b0",
        "5\u00b0",
        "30\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "5\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Individual aircraft, which are part of a fleet average programme, must be re-weighed:",
      "choices": [
        "At intervals not exceeding 2 years",
        "Re-weighing not required if no significant amendments made to aircraft",
        "At intervals not exceeding 4 years",
        "At intervals not exceeding 9 years"
      ],
      "answer": "At intervals not exceeding 9 years"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot is taking-off from an airport with a light aircraft which has a maximum structural take-off mass of 3250 lb and 25 lb of taxi fuel can be added. It is a hot summer day and the maximum all up mass (MAUM) ls 3100 lb. What is the maximum ramp mass in these conditions?",
      "choices": [
        "3125 lb",
        "3275 lb",
        "3250 lb",
        "3100 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "3100 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "An Airbus A380 is loaded with cargo including a series of sports cars. The total mass is 100 000kg. The CG is 10 m from the datum and is 25% of Mac. The Mac is 7m long. Lamborghini weighs 1,000kg Range Rover sport weighs 2,000kg The Lamborghini is 5m behind the CG, and the Range Rover is 10m behind the Lamborghini. If the Lamborghini and the Range Rover are stolen, where is the new position of the CG?",
      "choices": [
        "CG = 9.7m",
        "CG = 9.9m",
        "CG = 10.5",
        "CG unchanged (10m)"
      ],
      "answer": "CG = 9.7m"
    },
    {
      "question": "When a significant number of passengers and/or checked baggage appears to exceed the standard mass allowances, what action must be taken by an operator?",
      "choices": [
        "Determine the actual masses by weighing OR apply an adequate mass increment.",
        "Multiply standard masses by a reduction factor AND remove fuel or baggage",
        "Remove those passengers exceeding the standard mass allowance by 1.2 or more.",
        "Determine the actual masses by weighing AND apply an adequate mass increment."
      ],
      "answer": "Determine the actual masses by weighing OR apply an adequate mass increment."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft has a total mass of 3927 kg with a CG of 4.28 m aft of the datum line. Determine the amount of additional load to be loaded at station 5.8 m aft of the datum line, to establish a new CG of 4.37 m aft of the datum line:",
      "choices": [
        "81 kg.",
        "233 kg.",
        "62 kg.",
        "247 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "247 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the standard mass for checked baggage within Europe for all aircraft having 20 or more passengers seats?",
      "choices": [
        "15 kg",
        "11 kg",
        "13 kg",
        "17 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "13 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Dry Operating Index (DOI)?",
      "choices": [
        "An index for the aft and forward CG limits at Dry Operating Mass.",
        "An index for the position of the centre of gravity at Dry Operating Mass.",
        "An index for the average CG at Dry Operating Mass.",
        "An index for the %MAC at Dry Operating Mass."
      ],
      "answer": "An index for the position of the centre of gravity at Dry Operating Mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "The basic empty mass of an aircraft is 30 000 kg. The masses of the following items are: Catering 300 kg, Safety and rescue material nil, Fly away kit nil, Crew (inclusive crew baggage) 365 kg, Fuel at take-off 3000 kg, Unusable fuel 120 kg, Passengers, baggage, cargo 8 000 kg. The Dry Operating Mass is:",
      "choices": [
        "30 785 kg",
        "30 300 kg",
        "30 665 kg",
        "38 300 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "30 665 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Take-off Mass of an aeroplane is 66 700 kg which includes a traffic load of 14 200 kg and a usable fuel load of 10 500 kg. If the standard mass for the crew is 545 kg the Dry Operating Mass is:",
      "choices": [
        "42 000 kg",
        "42 425 kg",
        "41 500 kg",
        "45 000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "42 000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "For the SEP1 in CAP 696 the CG forward and aft limits at a mass of 3500 lb are respectively:",
      "choices": [
        "82.5 in to 94.6 in",
        "74.0 in to 87.7 in",
        "78.65 in to 87.7 in",
        "80.4 in to 87.7 in"
      ],
      "answer": "78.65 in to 87.7 in"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assuming a baggage compartment with a structural limitation of 32 lb/sq ft, a mass of 200 kg has to be distributed over an area of:",
      "choices": [
        "1.28 m\u00b2",
        "0.58 m\u00b2.",
        "6.25 m\u00b2.",
        "13.77 m\u00b2 ."
      ],
      "answer": "1.28 m\u00b2"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is underload defined?",
      "choices": [
        "The maximum amount of extra variable load that can be accepted without exceeding any of the mass limitations.",
        "The minimum amount of extra traffic load that can be accepted without exceeding any of the mass limitations.",
        "The maximum amount of extra load that can be accepted without exceeding any of the CG limitations.",
        "The maximum amount of extra traffic load that can be accepted without exceeding any of the mass limitations."
      ],
      "answer": "The maximum amount of extra traffic load that can be accepted without exceeding any of the mass limitations."
    },
    {
      "question": "To measure the mass and CG-position of an aircraft, it should be weighed with a minimum of:",
      "choices": [
        "4 point of support",
        "2 points of support",
        "3 points of support",
        "1 point of support"
      ],
      "answer": "3 points of support"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Underload?",
      "choices": [
        "Underload = Allowed Variable Load - Fuel",
        "Underload = Allowed All-up Mass - Actual Traffic Load",
        "Underload = Allowed Traffic Load - Actual Traffic Load",
        "Underload = Allowed All-up Mass + Fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "Underload = Allowed Traffic Load - Actual Traffic Load"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Traffic Load?",
      "choices": [
        "Allowed Traffic Load = ATOM - DOM",
        "Allowed Traffic Load = ATOM - LM",
        "Allowed Traffic Load = ATOM - ZFM",
        "Allowed Traffic Load = ATOM - OM"
      ],
      "answer": "Allowed Traffic Load = ATOM - OM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the maximum amount of Extra Fuel that can be uploaded for this Commercial Air Transport flight? MTOM 2050 lb, MLM 1910 lb, ZFM 1727 lb, Planned T/O Fuel 32 US gal, Trip Fuel 25 US gal, Fuel tank capacity 54.5 US gal, Specific gravity 0.72",
      "choices": [
        "23 US gal",
        "7 US gal",
        "21.8 US gal",
        "22.5 US gal"
      ],
      "answer": "21.8 US gal"
    },
    {
      "question": "What may be used by operators to allow for daily changes in basic equipment and crew?",
      "choices": [
        "An Aircraft Prepared for Service (APS) CG report.",
        "An Aircraft Prepared for Service (APS) weighing schedule.",
        "An Aircraft Prepared for Service (APS) mass and index.",
        "An Aircraft Prepared for Service (APS) CP report."
      ],
      "answer": "An Aircraft Prepared for Service (APS) mass and index."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following data, what ls the additional traffic load that the crew could accept for take-off? Dry Operating Mass: 12 445 lb, Traffic Load: 241 lb, Fuel loaded: 5000 lb, Trip Fuel: 3000 lb, Taxi Fuel: 100 lb, MTOM: 18 386 lb",
      "choices": [
        "700 lb",
        "941 lb",
        "800 lb",
        "1041 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "800 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "A container with a base area of 5 x 5 ft2 is loaded into a cargo compartment. The maximum running load of the compartment is 85 lb/feet. The maximum possible weight of the container is:",
      "choices": [
        "850 lb",
        "85 lb",
        "2125 lb",
        "425 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "425 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane has a mean aerodynamic chord (MAC) of 134.5 inches. The leading edge of this chord is at a distance of 625.6 inches aft of the datum. Define the location of the centre of gravity of the aeroplane in terms of percentage MAC if the mass of the aeroplane is acting vertically through a balance arm located 650 inches aft of the datum.",
      "choices": [
        "0.105",
        "0.181",
        "0.765",
        "0.855"
      ],
      "answer": "0.181"
    },
    {
      "question": "During weighing, what items are included?",
      "choices": [
        "Only those forming part of the DOM.",
        "Only those forming part of the AUM.",
        "Only those forming part of the BEM.",
        "Only those forming part of the OM."
      ],
      "answer": "Only those forming part of the BEM."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Zero Fuel Mass (ZFM) of an aeroplane is always:",
      "choices": [
        "The Take-off Mass minus the Take-off Fuel Mass.",
        "The Take-off Mass minus the wing fuel mass.",
        "The Take-off Mass minus the fuselage fuel mass.",
        "The Maximum Take-off Mass minus the Take-off Fuel Mass."
      ],
      "answer": "The Take-off Mass minus the Take-off Fuel Mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the Take-off Mass for the following single engine aeroplane. Given : Basic Empty Mass 1799 lb, Pilot + Front seat passenger 300 lb, Cargo Mass 350 lb, Ramp Fuel = Block Fuel 60 Gal, Trip Fuel 35 Gal, Fuel density 6 lb/Gal, Taxi Fuel 10 lb",
      "choices": [
        "2449 lb",
        "2799 lb",
        "2534 lb",
        "2809 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "2799 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is the fuel index determined?",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel Index = Fuel Mass x SG x Fuel Index Correction Factor.",
        "Using fuel index scales.",
        "Using a \u2018fuel index correction table\u2019.",
        "%MAC = Fuel Mass x SG x Fuel Index."
      ],
      "answer": "Using a \u2018fuel index correction table\u2019."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which equation is correct in order to calculate the centre of gravity? The sum of the:",
      "choices": [
        "Moments multiplied by the sum of the masses.",
        "Masses multiplied by the sum of the moments.",
        "Moments divided by the sum of the masses.",
        "Masses divided by the sum of the moments."
      ],
      "answer": "Moments divided by the sum of the masses."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Maximum Zero Fuel Mass (MZFM) is the mass of the aeroplane with no usable fuel on board. It is a limitation which is:",
      "choices": [
        "Governed by the Traffic Load to be carried. It also provides protection from excessive \"wing bending\".",
        "Governed by the Traffic Load to be carried. It also provides protection from excessive wing bending.",
        "Listed in the Flight Manual as a fixed value. It is a structural limit.",
        "Tabulated in the Flight Manual against arguments of airfield elevation and temperature."
      ],
      "answer": "Listed in the Flight Manual as a fixed value. It is a structural limit."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is the CG Moment Arm calculated for the Basic Empty Mass?",
      "choices": [
        "CG Moment Arm = Total Moment \u00f7 Total Mass",
        "CG Moment Arm = Total Moment x Total Mass",
        "CG Moment Arm = Total Mass x Total Moment",
        "CG Moment Arm = Total Mass \u00f7 Total Moment"
      ],
      "answer": "CG Moment Arm = Total Moment \u00f7 Total Mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the statement which best defines the Datum.",
      "choices": [
        "Is a fixed point from which all balance arm distances are measured.",
        "Is a fixed vertical plane from which all distances are measured.",
        "Is a vertical plane through which all the forces of gravity are said to act.",
        "Is the point through which all the forces of gravity are said to act."
      ],
      "answer": "Is a fixed point from which all balance arm distances are measured."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the standard mass for checked baggage for a flight on an aircraft having 20 or more passengers seats, originating in London, UK and terminating in Casablanca, Morocco?",
      "choices": [
        "15 kg",
        "17 kg",
        "11 kg",
        "13 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "13 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The fleet mass is:",
      "choices": [
        "The average Dry Operating Mass and average CG position for all aircraft in the fleet.",
        "The average Operating Mass and CG position for all aircraft in the fleet.",
        "The average Dry Operating Mass and average CG position for at least 76% of aircraft in the fleet.",
        "The average Dry Operating Mass and average CG position for at least 51% of aircraft in the fleet."
      ],
      "answer": "The average Dry Operating Mass and average CG position for all aircraft in the fleet."
    },
    {
      "question": "The operator can determine (1) ____ to the Centre-of-Gravity limits, to be (2) _____.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) an additional 15 % margin; (2) more restrictive.",
        "(1) own limitations; (2) less restrictive.",
        "(1) own limitations; (2) more restrictive.",
        "(1) an additional 15 % margin; (2) less restrictive."
      ],
      "answer": "(1) own limitations; (2) more restrictive."
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the table below, what is the CG for the Ramp Mass?",
      "choices": [
        "87.29",
        "84.67",
        "88.92",
        "86.28"
      ],
      "answer": "86.28"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Zero Fuel Mass (ZFM)?",
      "choices": [
        "79 000 kg",
        "78 000 kg",
        "65 200 kg",
        "93 000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "79 000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "For the B737 as loaded in Figure 4.13 of CAP 696 what is the new landing mass and %MAC if an extra 500 kg of cargo is loaded into compartment 4?",
      "choices": [
        "55 400 kg and 20.1%",
        "55 400 kg and 21.75%",
        "54 170 kg and 20.1%",
        "54 170 kg and 21.75%"
      ],
      "answer": "54 170 kg and 21.75%"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is produced during weighing, and used to compile a weighing schedule?",
      "choices": [
        "CP report",
        "CG report",
        "Weighing list",
        "Weighing report"
      ],
      "answer": "Weighing report"
    },
    {
      "question": "A tri-wheel aircraft has its datum 25 inches aft of the nose wheel and 180 inches forward of the main wheels. If the nose jack shows 125 lb and each main wheel jack shows 3400 lb, determine the BEM and the CG position.",
      "choices": [
        "6925 lb and 201.3 inches from the nose wheel of the aircraft.",
        "3525 lb and 172.7 inches from the datum.",
        "6925 lb and 176.3 inches from the nose wheel of the aircraft.",
        "6925 lb and 177.2 inches from the datum."
      ],
      "answer": "6925 lb and 201.3 inches from the nose wheel of the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the stabiliser trim setting for flaps 15 if the CG is 14%.",
      "choices": [
        "4.4 units",
        "4.3 units",
        "5.6 units",
        "3.7 units"
      ],
      "answer": "3.7 units"
    },
    {
      "question": "Individual aircraft, not part of a fleet average programme, must be re-weighed:",
      "choices": [
        "At intervals not exceeding 4 years.",
        "At intervals not exceeding 2 years.",
        "Re-weighing not required if no significant amendments made to aircraft.",
        "At intervals not exceeding 9 years."
      ],
      "answer": "At intervals not exceeding 4 years."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane with one nose landing gear and two main landing gears is weighed on jacks. Determine the aircraft BEM and CG position, using the following readouts: Nose landing gear, located at 161 inches from datum reading: 2300 kg Each main landing gear, located at 775 inches from datum reading: 19300 kg",
      "choices": [
        "21600 kg and 709.6 inches from datum.",
        "40900 kg and 722.3 inches from datum.",
        "40900 kg and 740.5 inches from datum.",
        "21600 kg and 0.71 inches from datum."
      ],
      "answer": "40900 kg and 740.5 inches from datum."
    },
    {
      "question": "The moment for an item is:",
      "choices": [
        "The square of the distance the item is from the datum divided by its mass.",
        "The distance the item is from the datum divided by its mass.",
        "The mass of the item multiplied by its distance from the datum.",
        "The mass of the item divided by its distance from the datum."
      ],
      "answer": "The mass of the item multiplied by its distance from the datum."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Operating Mass?",
      "choices": [
        "Operating Mass = DOM + Take-off Fuel",
        "Operating Mass = DOM - Take-off Fuel",
        "Operating Mass = DOM + Ramp Fuel",
        "Operating Mass = DOM + Trip Fuel - Alternate Fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "Operating Mass = DOM + Take-off Fuel"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the Flight Manual, the Maximum Structural Mass of your aircraft is 3200 lb, which may be increased by 25 lb for taxiing. It is a hot day and the performance charts restrict the Maximum All Up Mass (MAUM) to 3100 lb. What is the value of the Regulated Take-Off Mass (RTOM)?",
      "choices": [
        "3225 lb",
        "3100 lb",
        "3125 lb",
        "3200 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "3100 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the context of weighing regulations, a fleet of aircraft is:",
      "choices": [
        "An operator's group of aircraft of the same model and configuration.",
        "A group of 9 or fewer aircraft of the same model and configuration.",
        "A group of 4 or fewer aircraft of the same model and configuration.",
        "A group of 19 or fewer aircraft of the same model and configuration."
      ],
      "answer": "An operator's group of aircraft of the same model and configuration."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which document will standard masses for flight crew, passengers and luggage be found?",
      "choices": [
        "Part-FCL",
        "ICAO Annex 19",
        "IR-OPS",
        "Part-M&B"
      ],
      "answer": "IR-OPS"
    },
    {
      "question": "The actual Zero Fuel Mass (ZFM) is equal to the:",
      "choices": [
        "Basic Empty Mass plus the fuel loaded.",
        "Actual Landing Mass plus Trip Fuel.",
        "Dry Operating Mass plus the Traffic Load.",
        "Operating Mass plus all the Traffic Load."
      ],
      "answer": "Dry Operating Mass plus the Traffic Load."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum quantity of fuel that can be loaded into an aircraft's tanks is given as 400 US gallons. If the fuel density (specific gravity) is given as 0.79 the mass of fuel which may be loaded is:",
      "choices": [
        "2302 kg",
        "1916 kg",
        "1437 kg",
        "1196 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "1196 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "How can you calculate the Dry Operating Index (DOI)?",
      "choices": [
        "DOM + constant",
        "DOM x CG arm + constant",
        "OM x constant",
        "DOM x CG arm / constant"
      ],
      "answer": "DOM x CG arm / constant"
    },
    {
      "question": "When considering the mass of a fuel load to be carried, what must be applied to the fuel volume to calculate its actual mass?",
      "choices": [
        "Standard Gravity",
        "Specified Factor",
        "Standard Deviation",
        "Specific Gravity"
      ],
      "answer": "Specific Gravity"
    },
    {
      "question": "CG Arm is calculated as follows:",
      "choices": [
        "CG x Mass",
        "Moment x Mass",
        "Moment / Mass",
        "Mass / Moment"
      ],
      "answer": "Moment / Mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fleet average mass programmes require an operator to weigh a certain proportion of a fleet:",
      "choices": [
        "At least every 4 years",
        "At least every 9 years",
        "At least every 2 years",
        "At least every 19 years"
      ],
      "answer": "At least every 4 years"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane, with its CG limits from 638 inches to 658 inches aft of the datum, should have been loaded so as to give a calculated Take-Off Mass of 64 200 kg and the CG located at 640 inches aft of the datum, with 750 kg loaded into the front cargo hold and 500 kg into the rear cargo hold. Unfortunately, the ground staff incorrectly loaded all the cargo into the forward cargo hold. If the distance between the cargo holds ls 517 inches, is the aeroplane's CG within limits?",
      "choices": [
        "Yes, it moves rearwards but is within limits.",
        "Yes, it is within limits.",
        "No, it is out of the forward limit.",
        "No, it is out of the rear lilt."
      ],
      "answer": "No, it is out of the forward limit."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane weighing schedule indicates that: The Empty Mass is 57 320 kg. The nominal Dry Operating Mass (DOM) is 60 120 kg. The Maximum Zero Fuel Mass (MZFM) is given as 72 100 kg. Which of the following is a correct statement in relation to this aeroplane?",
      "choices": [
        "Operational items have a mass of 2800 kg and the maximum Useful Load is 11 980 kg.",
        "Operational items have a mass of 2800 kg and the maximum Traffic Load for this aeroplane is 14 780 kg.",
        "Operational items have a mass of 2800 kg and the maximum Traffic Load for this aeroplane is 11 980 kg.",
        "Operational items have a mass of 2800 kg and the maximum Useful Load is 14 780 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "Operational items have a mass of 2800 kg and the maximum Traffic Load for this aeroplane is 11 980 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is weighed before it enters service:",
      "choices": [
        "To establish its maximum mass.",
        "To establish its CG position at maximum mass.",
        "To establish the minimum required take-off distance at maximum all-up mass.",
        "To establish its mass and CG."
      ],
      "answer": "To establish its mass and CG."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following shipments can be loaded in a cargo compartment with a floor loading of 70 kg/m2? Shipment W: 500 kg on a pallet sized 2 m x 2 m Shipment X: 500 kg on a pallet sized 1 m x 1 m Shipment Y: 600 kg on a pallet sized 2 m x 2 m Shipment Z: 600 kg on a pallet sized 3 m x 3 m (All pallets are in direct contact with the cargo floor).",
      "choices": [
        "Shipment X",
        "Shipment Y",
        "Shipment W",
        "Shipment Z"
      ],
      "answer": "Shipment Z"
    },
    {
      "question": "For the B737 as loaded in Figure 4.13 of CAP 696 what is the new landing mass and %MAC if an extra 500 kg of cargo is loaded into compartment 1?",
      "choices": [
        "55 400 kg and 17.8%",
        "55 400 kg and 20.1%",
        "54 170 kg and 18.0%",
        "54 170 kg and 17.8%"
      ],
      "answer": "54 170 kg and 18.0%"
    },
    {
      "question": "The trim sheet displays: -Forward CGs (smaller %MACs) to the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "left",
        "bottom",
        "right",
        "top"
      ],
      "answer": "left"
    },
    {
      "question": "IR-OPS states that __________ must determine that the mass of all operating items and crew members (and their effect on aircraft CG), are included in the aircraft\u2019s DOM by weighing or using standard masses.",
      "choices": [
        "an operator",
        "the ground handlers",
        "the aircraft commander",
        "the flight crew"
      ],
      "answer": "an operator"
    },
    {
      "question": "An additional baggage container is loaded into the aft cargo compartment but is not entered into the load and trim sheet. The aeroplane will be heavier than expected and calculated take-off safety speeds:",
      "choices": [
        "Will give reduced safety margins",
        "Are unaffected but V1 will increase",
        "Will be greater than required",
        "Will not be achieved"
      ],
      "answer": "Will give reduced safety margins"
    },
    {
      "question": "Considering only structural limitations, on very short legs with minimum take-off fuel, the traffic load is normally limited by:",
      "choices": [
        "Actual landing mass.",
        "Maximum Take-off Mass.",
        "Maximum Zero Fuel Mass.",
        "Maximum Landing Mass."
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum Zero Fuel Mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "The centre of gravity of an aircraft is that point through which the total mass of the aircraft is said to act. The weight acts in a direction:",
      "choices": [
        "Governed by the distribution of the mass within the aircraft.",
        "Always parallel to the aircraft's vertical axis.",
        "At right angles to the flight path.",
        "Parallel to the gravity vector."
      ],
      "answer": "Parallel to the gravity vector."
    },
    {
      "question": "At which masses must the CG position be within the CG envelope, including any LMC?",
      "choices": [
        "PLTOM and PLLM",
        "AUM and MRM",
        "ZFM and TOM",
        "MTOM and ZFM"
      ],
      "answer": "ZFM and TOM"
    },
    {
      "question": "The weighing of an aircraft must be performed:",
      "choices": [
        "Whenever there is a modification applied to the aircraft.",
        "Whenever the cumulative change to the DOM exceeds plus/minus 0.5% of the MSLM.",
        "Whenever the cumulative mass changes to the DOM exceeds plus/minus 5% of the MSTOM.",
        "At the intervals of nine years if individual aircraft masses are used."
      ],
      "answer": "Whenever the cumulative change to the DOM exceeds plus/minus 0.5% of the MSLM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to the table below, what is the CG for the Take-Off Mass?",
      "choices": [
        "85.28",
        "86.31",
        "88.92",
        "87.29"
      ],
      "answer": "86.31"
    },
    {
      "question": "What changes must be recorded during a re-weighing?",
      "choices": [
        "Basic equipment only.",
        "All in-flight equipment, plus the accumulated effects of modifications and repairs.",
        "Basic equipment and accumulated effects of modifications and repairs.",
        "Basic equipment or accumulated effects of modifications and repairs."
      ],
      "answer": "Basic equipment and accumulated effects of modifications and repairs."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Maximum Zero Fuel Mass (MZFM): 1. Is a regulatory limitation. 2. Is calculated for a maximum load factor of +3.5 g. 3. Is based on the maximum permissible bending moment at the wing root. 4. Is defined under the assumption that fuel is consumed from the outer wing tanks first. 5. Is defined under the assumption that fuel is consumed from the inner wing tanks first. Which combination of statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "2004-02-03 00:00:00",
        "2005-01-03 00:00:00",
        "2005-02-03 00:00:00",
        "2003-01-02 00:00:00"
      ],
      "answer": "2005-01-03 00:00:00"
    },
    {
      "question": "For the MEP1 in CAP 696 the CG forward and aft limits at a mass of 3600 lb are respectively:",
      "choices": [
        "82.0 in to 94.6 in.",
        "83.15 in to 94.6 in.",
        "90.5 in to 94.6 in.",
        "79.8 in to 87.7 in."
      ],
      "answer": "83.15 in to 94.6 in."
    },
    {
      "question": "For the B737 as loaded in Figure 4.13 of CAP 696 what is the new landing mass and %MAC if an extra 500 kg of cargo is off loaded from compartment 1?",
      "choices": [
        "54 400 kg and 22.2%",
        "53 170 kg and 20.2%",
        "53 170 kg and 22.2%",
        "54 400 kg and 20.1%"
      ],
      "answer": "53 170 kg and 22.2%"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the stabiliser trim setting for flaps 5 if the CG is 14%.",
      "choices": [
        "4.3 units",
        "5.6 units",
        "3.7 units.",
        "4.4 units."
      ],
      "answer": "4.4 units."
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to CAP 696 Section 2 SEP1, what is the full range of distance between the forward and aft CG limits at BEM?",
      "choices": [
        "87.7 in",
        "10 in",
        "6.4 in",
        "77.7 in"
      ],
      "answer": "10 in"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which document requires the operator to ensure that the loading, mass and aircraft CG comply with limitations specified in the AFM, POH or the Operations Manual.",
      "choices": [
        "ICAO Annex 4",
        "IR-OPS",
        "Part-FCL",
        "Part-MED"
      ],
      "answer": "IR-OPS"
    },
    {
      "question": "The trim sheet displays: -Aft CGs (larger %MACs) to the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "right",
        "left",
        "top",
        "bottom"
      ],
      "answer": "right"
    },
    {
      "question": "By adding to the Basic Empty Mass the mass of crew, crew baggage, catering, and operational equipment for a specific flight, we get the:",
      "choices": [
        "Dry Operating Mass.",
        "Take-off Mass.",
        "Zero Fuel Mass.",
        "Landing Mass."
      ],
      "answer": "Dry Operating Mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum load per running metre of an aircraft is 350 kg/m. The width of the floor area is 2 metres. The floor strength limitation is 300 kg per square metre. Which one of the following crates (length x width x height) can be loaded directly on the floor?",
      "choices": [
        "A load of 500 kg in a crate with dimensions 1.5 m x 1 m x 1 m.",
        "A load of 400 kg in a crate with dimensions 1.4 m x 0.8 m x 0.8 m.",
        "A load of 400 kg in a crate with dimensions 1.2 m x 1.2 m x 1.2 m.",
        "A load of 700 kg in a crate with dimensions 1.8 m x 1.4 m x 0.8 m."
      ],
      "answer": "A load of 400 kg in a crate with dimensions 1.2 m x 1.2 m x 1.2 m."
    },
    {
      "question": "The term 'Maximum Zero Fuel Mass' (MZFM) consists of:",
      "choices": [
        "The maximum mass authorized for a certain aeroplane not including the fuel load and operational items.",
        "The maximum mass for some aeroplanes including the fuel load and the Traffic Load.",
        "The maximum mass authorized for a certain aeroplane not including Traffic Load and fuel load.",
        "The maximum permissible mass of an aeroplane with no usable fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "The maximum permissible mass of an aeroplane with no usable fuel."
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the Basic Empty Mass and CG position of the aircraft given the following data: Reference point situated 60 inches from the Datum. Nosewheel load of 1275 kg situated -27 inches from the reference point. Left mainwheel load of 5383 kg situated +105 inches from the reference point. Right mainwheel load of 5287 kg situated +105 inches from the reference point. Ballast of 96 kg situated +112 inches from the reference point.",
      "choices": [
        "BEM 11945 kg. CG 150.91 inches aft of the datum.",
        "BEM 12043 kg. CG 80 inches aft of the datum",
        "BEM 10862kg. CG 80 inches aft of the structural reference point",
        "BEM 12041 kg CG 151.02 inches aft of the structural reference point"
      ],
      "answer": "BEM 11945 kg. CG 150.91 inches aft of the datum."
    },
    {
      "question": "The captain has received a calculated load sheet with his pre-flight package. The ground handler now hands over a final load sheet. ln this scenario, which one does the captain have to use?",
      "choices": [
        "The final load sheet provided by the ground handler.",
        "The load sheet he has received with his pre-flight package.",
        "It depends on the operator's SOPs which one the captain has to use.",
        "Neither one. It is his responsibility to calculate the load sheet himself."
      ],
      "answer": "The final load sheet provided by the ground handler."
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete figure 2.4 in CAP 696 to determine the take-off mass and CG for the SEP1 aeroplane (BEM 2415 lb and CG 77.7 in) with one pilot mass 165 lb, with 2 passengers mass 200 lb and 220 lb in seats 3 and 4 and a crate mass 150 lb in area B. Block fuel 30 US Gall.",
      "choices": [
        "3317 lb and 85.9 in",
        "3167 lb and 83.1 in",
        "3317 lb and 86.5 in",
        "3330 lb and 86.1 in"
      ],
      "answer": "3317 lb and 85.9 in"
    },
    {
      "question": "A location in the aircraft which is identified by a number designating its distance from the datum is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Station.",
        "Index.",
        "MAC.",
        "Moment."
      ],
      "answer": "Station."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: The Take-off Mass (TOM) of an aeroplane is 141 000 kg. Total fuel on board is 63 000 kg including 14 000 kg reserve fuel and 1 000 kg of unusable fuel. The Traffic Load (TL) is 12 800 kg. What is the Zero Fuel Mass (ZFM)?",
      "choices": [
        "78 000 kg",
        "79 000 kg",
        "93 000 kg",
        "65 200 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "79 000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft has a total mass of 5430 kg with a CG of 5.43 m aft of the datum line. Minutes before despatch an additional load of 210 kg was loaded onto the aircraft. The aircraft's new CG is 5.56 m aft of the datum. The additional load was placed:",
      "choices": [
        "9.05 m aft of the datum line.",
        "3.49 m aft of the datum line.",
        "8.92 m aft of the datum line.",
        "1.94 m aft of the datum line."
      ],
      "answer": "8.92 m aft of the datum line."
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the ramp mass in the following conditions: Basic empty mass (BEM) 3 210 lb Arm for BEM 88.5 in One pilot 160 lb Front seat passenger 200 lb Centre seat passengers 290 lb One passenger rear seat 110 lb Baggage in zone 1 - 100 lb Baggage in zone 4 - 50 lb Block fuel 100 US Gal Trip fuel 55 US Gal Fuel for start up and taxi 3 US Gal Fuel density 6 lb/US Gal.",
      "choices": [
        "4120 lb",
        "4720 lb",
        "4372 lb",
        "4390 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "4720 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to variations in the actual passenger distribution, cargo loading, or fuel distribution in comparison with the data used during the pre-flight preparation of the mass and balance documentation, the Operator (1) ___ which is/are (2) ___ restrictive than the certified CG limits.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) defines operational limits; (2) less.",
        "(1) applies a CG margin of 15%; (2) more",
        "(1) applies a CG margin of 15%; (2) less.",
        "(1) defines operational CG limits; (2) more."
      ],
      "answer": "(1) defines operational CG limits; (2) more."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the \"Regulated Landing Mass'?\"",
      "choices": [
        "The Maximum Landing Mass as determined by the aircraft manufacturer.",
        "The greatest of the Performance Limited Landing Mass and Structural Limited Landing Mass.",
        "The Maximum Landing Mass as approved by the aircraft's State of Registration.",
        "The lowest of the Performance Limited Landing Mass and Structural Limited Landing Mass."
      ],
      "answer": "The lowest of the Performance Limited Landing Mass and Structural Limited Landing Mass."
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the centre of gravity in % MAC (mean aerodynamic chord) with following data: Distance datum - centre of gravity: 12.53 m Distance datum - leading edge: 9.63 m Length of MAC: 8 m",
      "choices": [
        "47.0% MAC",
        "23.1% MAC",
        "36.3 % MAC",
        "63.4% MAC"
      ],
      "answer": "36.3 % MAC"
    },
    {
      "question": "A mass of 600 kg is loaded at a station which is located 12 metres behind the present centre of gravity and 18 metres behind the datum. (Assume g=10 m/s2) The moment for that mass used in the loading manifest is:",
      "choices": [
        "10 800 Nm",
        "108 kNm",
        "72 kNm",
        "115 200 Nm"
      ],
      "answer": "108 kNm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The basic empty mass of an aircraft is 30 000 kg The masses of the following items are: Catering 300 kg Safety and rescue material nil Fly away kit nil Crew (inclusive crew baggage) 365 kg Fuel at take-off 3000 kg Unusable fuel 120 kg Passengers, baggage, cargo 8 000 kg The Dry Operating Mass is:",
      "choices": [
        "38 300 kg",
        "30 785 kg",
        "30 665 kg",
        "30 300 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "30 665 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the CG of an aircraft is close to its forward limit, what will be achieved if fuel is transferred from the wing tanks to the aeroplane's fin or horizontal stabiliser tanks?",
      "choices": [
        "Best fuel economy, by repositioning the CG forward.",
        "Efficient stability control, by repositioning the CG aft.",
        "Best range, by repositioning the CG forward.",
        "Efficient fuel consumption, by repositioning the CG aft."
      ],
      "answer": "Efficient fuel consumption, by repositioning the CG aft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the length of the MAC, given: Leading edge at wing root: STA 235 Trailing edge at wing root: STA 250 Leading edge at wing tip: STA 148 Trailing edge at wing tip: STA 212 Leading edge of MAC: STA 192 Trailing edge of MAC: STA 224 Note: Body stations are distances from the aircraft nose in 10 -1 m.",
      "choices": [
        "640 cm",
        "320 cm",
        "400 cm",
        "150 cm"
      ],
      "answer": "320 cm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Maximum Zero Fuel Mass (MZFM) is:",
      "choices": [
        "Tabulated in the Flight Manual against arguments of airfield elevation and temperature.",
        "Governed by the Traffic Load to be carried.",
        "A structural limit listed in the Flight Manual as a fixed value.",
        "Governed by the CG limits."
      ],
      "answer": "A structural limit listed in the Flight Manual as a fixed value."
    },
    {
      "question": "In mass and balance calculations which of the following describes the datum?",
      "choices": [
        "It is the most aft position of the centre of gravity.",
        "It is the point on the aircraft designated by the manufacturers from which all centre of gravity measurements and calculations are made.",
        "It is the most forward position of the centre of gravity.",
        "It is the distance from the centre of gravity to the point through which the weight of the component acts."
      ],
      "answer": "It is the point on the aircraft designated by the manufacturers from which all centre of gravity measurements and calculations are made."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 696 figure 4.12. The ZFM of an aeroplane is equal to 48 000 kg and the CG position is at 25 % MAC. Which one of the statements below is correct ?",
      "choices": [
        "The graph does not provide enough information to assess compliance with the CG limit.",
        "The Index at ZFM is outside the allowed CG range.",
        "The Index at ZFM is within limits and in an aft position.",
        "A ZFM of 48 000 kg is not allowed for this aircraft type."
      ],
      "answer": "The Index at ZFM is within limits and in an aft position."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Fuel volume: 3800 US Gallons Fuel density: 0.79 kg/l. The fuel mass ls:",
      "choices": [
        "13 647 kg.",
        "14 383 kg.",
        "18 206 kg.",
        "11 364 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "11 364 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given : Actual mass 116 500 lb Original CG station 435.0 Compartment A station 285.5 Compartment B station 792.5 If 390 lb of cargo is moved from compartment B (aft) to compartment A (forward), what is the station number of the new CG?",
      "choices": [
        "423.3",
        "506.3",
        "433.3",
        "463.7"
      ],
      "answer": "433.3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Dry operating mass is the take-off mass of the aircraft less:",
      "choices": [
        "All usable fuel, portable water and chemicals.",
        "Traffic load, portable water and lavatory chemicals.",
        "All usable fuel and traffic load.",
        "All usable Fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "All usable fuel and traffic load."
    },
    {
      "question": "If all the moments are positive when calculating mass (weight) and balance, the position of the datum would be at the:",
      "choices": [
        "Trailing edge of the wing.",
        "Main wheels centreline.",
        "Nose, or forward of the aircraft.",
        "Centre line of the nose or tail wheel depending on the aircraft type."
      ],
      "answer": "Nose, or forward of the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which equation represents a conversion of 1 US gallon AVGAS into lbs?",
      "choices": [
        "1 USG = 3.8 lbs",
        "1 USG = 6 lbs",
        "1 USG = 6.8 lbs",
        "1 USG = 4 lbs"
      ],
      "answer": "1 USG = 6 lbs"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Dry Operating Mass includes:",
      "choices": [
        "crew and crew baggage, catering, removable passenger service equipment, potable water and lavatory chemicals.",
        "passengers baggage and cargo.",
        "fuel and passengers baggage and cargo.",
        "unusable fuel and reserve fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "crew and crew baggage, catering, removable passenger service equipment, potable water and lavatory chemicals."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Take-off Mass (TOM) of an aircraft is 8470 kg Total fuel on board is 1 600 kg including 450 kg reserve fuel and 29 kg of unusable fuel The Traffic Load (TL) is 770 kg What is the Zero Fuel Mass (ZFM)?",
      "choices": [
        "6420 kg",
        "6870 kg",
        "6899 kg",
        "6129 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "6899 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What effect does a CG outside the aft limit have on aircraft longitudinal stability and controllability?",
      "choices": [
        "Decreases both",
        "Decreases stability and increases controllability",
        "No change",
        "Increases both"
      ],
      "answer": "Decreases stability and increases controllability"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Mass on nose wheel: 285 kg Mass on left main wheels: 1465 kg Mass on right main wheels: 1395 kg Distance between the nose and main wheels: 7 ft 8 in Calculate the aircraft's CG position.",
      "choices": [
        "83.7 in aft of the nose wheel.",
        "18.3 in forward of the main gear.",
        "9.2 in forward of the main gear.",
        "7.1 ft aft of the nose wheel."
      ],
      "answer": "83.7 in aft of the nose wheel."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Maximum Zero Fuel Mass (MZFM) is a mass limitation for the:",
      "choices": [
        "Strength of the fuselage.",
        "Strength of the wing root.",
        "Total load of the fuel imposed upon the wing.",
        "Allowable load exerted upon the wing considering a margin for fuel tanking."
      ],
      "answer": "Strength of the wing root."
    },
    {
      "question": "A baggage weighing 50 kg is tied down on the baggage zone of the aircraft and the moment is -5000 KG mm The arm of the baggage zone is:",
      "choices": [
        "-10 nm and is located forward of the datum.",
        "+100 nm and is located aft of the datum.",
        "+10 nm and is located aft of the datum.",
        "-100 nm and is located forward of the datum."
      ],
      "answer": "-100 nm and is located forward of the datum."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to OPS regulations, standard masses for checked baggage may be used if the aircraft:",
      "choices": [
        "Has 30 or more seats.",
        "Is carrying 30 or more passengers.",
        "Has 6 or more seats.",
        "Has 20 or more seats."
      ],
      "answer": "Has 20 or more seats."
    },
    {
      "question": "A mass of 500 kg is loaded at a station which is located 10 metres behind the present Centre of Gravity and 16 metres behind the datum. (Assume g = 10 m/s2). The moment for that mass used in the loading manifest is:",
      "choices": [
        "13 0000 Nm",
        "30 000 Nm",
        "80 000 Nm",
        "50 000 Nm"
      ],
      "answer": "80 000 Nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "The arm is the ___ distance of a load as measured from the aircraft ___ .",
      "choices": [
        "Horizontal; datum",
        "Vertical; aft limit",
        "Lateral; datum",
        "Horizontal; forward limit"
      ],
      "answer": "Horizontal; datum"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following data applies to an aircraft which is about to take-off. MSTOM 8600 kg, PLTOM 8470 kg, DOM 5110 kg, Crew and special operating equipment 290 kg, Take-off fuel 1460 kg. Calculate the traffic load.",
      "choices": [
        "2360 kg",
        "1900 kg",
        "3650 kg",
        "3200 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "1900 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The floor of the main cargo hold is limited to 4000 N/ms2. It is planned to load a cubic container each side of which measures 0.5 m. The maximum gross mass must not exceed (assume g = 10 m/s2):",
      "choices": [
        "1000 kg",
        "5000 kg",
        "100 kg",
        "500 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "100 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is underload?",
      "choices": [
        "Underload = Allowed Traffic Load - Actual Traffic Load",
        "Underload = Allowed Variable Load - Fuel",
        "Underload = Allowed All-up Mass + Fuel",
        "Underload = Allowed All-up Mass - Actual Traffic Load"
      ],
      "answer": "Underload = Allowed Traffic Load - Actual Traffic Load"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is used for Commercial Air Transport. Since the aircraft's initial entry into service, 3 years ago, several repairs and modifications have been executed. These changes were accurately documented. The Operator uses individual aircraft masses. Does the aircraft need to be re-weighed now?",
      "choices": [
        "No, but it must be re-weighed within the next 12 months.",
        "No, but it must be re-weighed with in the next 6 years.",
        "Yes, because the applicable EU regulation requires a re-weighing every 3 years.",
        "Yes, because re-weighting should be done after every repair and/or modification."
      ],
      "answer": "No, but it must be re-weighed within the next 12 months."
    },
    {
      "question": "Moment (balance) arms are measured from a specific point to the body station at which the mass is located. That point is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "The datum",
        "The centre of gravity of aeroplane",
        "The focal point.",
        "The axis"
      ],
      "answer": "The datum"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using the standard mass figure from CAP 696 Page 5. You are about to depart for a commercial flight, with an aircraft having a flight crew of 7 members and 115 passengers. As part of your pre-flight calculations and given the following information, you need to calculate the Traffic Load in accordance with the standard passenger and baggage masses, as defined in the annex. Flight crew: 4 male & 3 female, Male passengers: 70, Female passengers: 35, Children: 10, Baggage: 62 items, Standard mass for a flight crew member: 85 kg, Non-revenue load: 500 kg",
      "choices": [
        "9766 kg",
        "10 826 kg",
        "10 366 kg",
        "10 476 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "10 476 kg"
    }
  ],
  "OPS": [
    {
      "question": "A Low Visibility Take-Off (LVTO) is defined as a take-off with an RVR less than ____ m",
      "choices": [
        "550",
        "400",
        "800",
        "125"
      ],
      "answer": "550"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the definition for a microburst? A microburst lasts for about 1 minute to 5 minutes and is a highly concentrated and powerful:",
      "choices": [
        "up draught of air, typically less than 5 km across.",
        "down draught of air, typically less than 5 km across.",
        "up draught of air, typically more than 5 km across.",
        "down draught of air, typically more than 5 km across."
      ],
      "answer": "down draught of air, typically less than 5 km across."
    },
    {
      "question": "When taking-off after a wide body aircraft which has just landed, you should take-off:",
      "choices": [
        "beyond the point where the aircraft's wheels have touched down.",
        "in front of the point where the aircraft's wheels have touched down.",
        "at the point where the aircraft's wheels have touched the ground and on the down wind side of the runway.",
        "at the point where the aircraft's wheels have touched down and on the wind side of the runway."
      ],
      "answer": "beyond the point where the aircraft's wheels have touched down."
    },
    {
      "question": "Any localised treatment to the aircraft must be carried out __________ otherwise, a difference in lift could cause uncommanded roll immediately after take-off.",
      "choices": [
        "symmetrically",
        "completely",
        "quickly",
        "by certified personnel"
      ],
      "answer": "symmetrically"
    },
    {
      "question": "Procedures applied by an aerodrome for the purpose of ensuring safety during low-visibility operations (LVOs)' \u00a0is the definition applied to:",
      "choices": [
        "Low Visibility Procedures (LVP)",
        "Low Visibility Approach Operation Procedures (LVAOP)",
        "Low Visibility Take-off Procedures (LVTOP)",
        "Local Visibility Procedures (LVP)"
      ],
      "answer": "Low Visibility Procedures (LVP)"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft having undertaken an anti-icing procedure and having exceeded the holdover time of the anti-icing fluid:",
      "choices": [
        "does not require a new anti-icing procedure before take-off.",
        "must only undertake a de-icing procedure before take-off.",
        "must only undertake a new anti-icing procedure before take-off.",
        "must undertake a de-icing procedure before a new application of anti-icing fluid before take-off."
      ],
      "answer": "must undertake a de-icing procedure before a new application of anti-icing fluid before take-off."
    },
    {
      "question": "The highest risk of bird strikes occurs:",
      "choices": [
        "above 5000 ft.",
        "under 2500 ft.",
        "between 3500 and 5000 ft.",
        "between 2500 and 3500 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "under 2500 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a manual approach, the aeroplane is subjected to wind shear with a decreasing headwind. ln the absence of a pilot action, the aeroplane: 1. flies above the intended approach path 2. flies below the intended approach path 3. has an increasing true airspeed 4. has a decreasing true airspeed The combination of correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1 and 4.",
        "2 and 4.",
        "2 and 3.",
        "1 and 3."
      ],
      "answer": "2 and 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "After a commercial passenger flight, the flight crew awaits by the baggage carousel for their luggage. Their hold luggage is delivered last, when all the passengers have already left. The flight crew notices that there is a piece of luggage remaining on the carousel which has NOT been claimed. According to ICAO Annex 17 and for security reasons, the definition of such baggage would be:",
      "choices": [
        "Unidentified baggage.",
        "Rejected baggage.",
        "Abandoned baggage.",
        "Lost baggage."
      ],
      "answer": "Unidentified baggage."
    },
    {
      "question": "An emergency landing is required when there is an immediate risk to the aircraft or passengers. In this case declare a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "PAN PAN",
        "MAYDAY",
        "Emergency.",
        "Incident."
      ],
      "answer": "MAYDAY"
    },
    {
      "question": "Water is not displaced from under the tyres fast enough to allow the tyre to make pavement contact'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Viscous hydroplaning.",
        "Anti-skid failure.",
        "Dynamic hydroplaning.",
        "Reverted rubber hydroplaning."
      ],
      "answer": "Dynamic hydroplaning."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ landing may be necessary when there is no immediate danger to the aeroplane, but a reduction in system redundancy, or a reduction in safety margins make it necessary to land rather than continue flight.",
      "choices": [
        "An emergency",
        "A precautionary.",
        "An immediate.",
        "A forced."
      ],
      "answer": "A precautionary."
    },
    {
      "question": "Whenever a potential bird hazard is observed, the commander shall:",
      "choices": [
        "inform immediately the bird control unit (BCU) directly by radio.",
        "immediately inform the local ATS unit.",
        "inform other aircraft in the vicinity by radio.",
        "submit a written hazard bird strike report upon arrival and within 48 hours."
      ],
      "answer": "immediately inform the local ATS unit."
    },
    {
      "question": "In case of a cargo compartment fire, the system which should be switched off, is generally the:",
      "choices": [
        "trim air",
        "pressurisation",
        "total air-conditioning",
        "ventilation of the cargo compartment"
      ],
      "answer": "ventilation of the cargo compartment"
    },
    {
      "question": "During an explosive decompression at flight level 370 (FL 370), your first action will be:",
      "choices": [
        "to set the transponder to 7700",
        "to warn the ATC",
        "to put on the oxygen mask",
        "to comfort your passengers"
      ],
      "answer": "to put on the oxygen mask"
    },
    {
      "question": "ln case of a serious threat based on the presence of a bomb on board a pressurised aircraft and disregarding any fuel considerations:",
      "choices": [
        "you carry out an emergency descent to reach the safety altitude.",
        "you go down to the level corresponding to the indicated cabin altitude and keep the aircraft in a clean configuration until the final approach.",
        "you descend to the flight level corresponding to the indicated cabin altitude or the safety altitude if higher and take preventive steps by putting yourself in a landing approach configuration.",
        "you climb to the maximum flight level which does not need the use of pressurisation."
      ],
      "answer": "you descend to the flight level corresponding to the indicated cabin altitude or the safety altitude if higher and take preventive steps by putting yourself in a landing approach configuration."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statements accurately describes the CS-25 requirement for fuel jettison systems?",
      "choices": [
        "Fuel jettison systems are required to ensure that, within 15 minutes, the aircraft's mass can be reduced to a point where the aircraft will meet the approach climb gradient performance requirements.",
        "Fuel jettison systems are required to ensure that, within 15 minutes, the aircraft's mass can be reduced to a point where the aircraft will meet the maximum structural landing weight requirements.",
        "Fuel jettison systems are required to ensure that, within 30 minutes, the aircraft's mass can be reduced to a point where the aircraft will meet the approach climb gradient performance requirements.",
        "Fuel jettison systems are required to ensure that, within 30 minutes, the aircraft's mass can be reduced to a point where the aircraft will meet the maximum structural landing weight requirement."
      ],
      "answer": "Fuel jettison systems are required to ensure that, within 15 minutes, the aircraft's mass can be reduced to a point where the aircraft will meet the approach climb gradient performance requirements."
    },
    {
      "question": "Friction generates heat, and the temperature rise turns residual water into high pressure steam. The steam causes the rubber to \u2018revert\u2019, becoming soft and gummy, which traps steam within the tyre's footprint'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Dynamic hydroplaning.",
        "Reverted rubber hydroplaning.",
        "Emergency braking.",
        "Viscous hydroplaning."
      ],
      "answer": "Reverted rubber hydroplaning."
    },
    {
      "question": "A runway designated as 'compacted or rolled snow' is given a SNOWTAM code of:",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "8",
        "7",
        "6"
      ],
      "answer": "8"
    },
    {
      "question": "The visual phase of an instrument approach to bring an aircraft into position for landing on a runway not suitably located for a straight-in approach'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "A visual approach.",
        "A circling approach.",
        "A go-around.",
        "A turning approach."
      ],
      "answer": "A circling approach."
    },
    {
      "question": "Whenever practicable, what transponder code shall be used to provide recognition of an aircraft which is being subjected to unlawful interference:",
      "choices": [
        "A 7500",
        "A 7600",
        "A 7700",
        "A 2000"
      ],
      "answer": "A 7500"
    },
    {
      "question": "To avoid wake turbulence, when flying behind and close to a large aeroplane, the pilot should manoeuvre whenever possible:",
      "choices": [
        "below and downwind from the large aeroplane.",
        "below and upwind from the large aeroplane.",
        "above and upwind from the large aeroplane.",
        "above and downwind from the large aeroplane."
      ],
      "answer": "above and upwind from the large aeroplane."
    },
    {
      "question": "Two aeroplanes are arriving from the same direction to land at an airport where making a straight-in approach and landing with a tailwind (within operational limits) will shorten the flight time by a few minutes. One of the aeroplanes has carbon brakes and the other steel brakes.",
      "choices": [
        "The aeroplane with steel brakes should use the runway with a headwind as steel brakes are more efficient at absorbing energy at higher brake temperatures, making them less susceptible than carbon brakes to brake fading.",
        "The aeroplane with steel brakes should NOT land with a tailwind as steel brakes are NOT approved for hard braking because steel brakes cannot absorb large amounts of energy.",
        "The aeroplane with carbon brakes are more likely to suffer from brake overheat if landing with a tailwind as carbon brakes are sensitive to heat and will NOT absorb the energy as efficiently as steel brakes.",
        "There can be a benefit in landing with a tailwind using carbon brakes as carbon brakes remain efficient at high temperatures and the wear is mainly determined by the number of applications."
      ],
      "answer": "There can be a benefit in landing with a tailwind using carbon brakes as carbon brakes remain efficient at high temperatures and the wear is mainly determined by the number of applications."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the definition for horizontal windshear?",
      "choices": [
        "The change of the horizontal wind vector with horizontal distance, as might be determined by two or more anemometers mounted at the same height along a runway.",
        "The change of vertical wind vector with height, as might be determined by two or more anemometers at different heights on a mast.",
        "The change of horizontal wind vector with height, as might be determined by two or more anemometers at different heights on a mast.",
        "The change of the vertical wind vector with horizontal distance, as might be in a SNOWTAM, a runway condition code of 5 means: determined by two or more anemometers mounted at the same height along a runway."
      ],
      "answer": "The change of the horizontal wind vector with horizontal distance, as might be determined by two or more anemometers mounted at the same height along a runway."
    },
    {
      "question": "For each aircraft type, CS-25 requires the manufacturer to:",
      "choices": [
        "Demonstrate that all passengers and crew can be evacuated within 60 seconds with 40% of the emergency exits available. Conducted in darkness with a representative cross-section of \u2018passengers\u2019.",
        "Demonstrate that all passengers and crew can be evacuated within 90 seconds with all of the emergency exits available. Conducted in darkness with a representative cross-section of \u2018passengers\u2019.",
        "Demonstrate that all 50% of passengers and crew can be evacuated within 90 seconds with half of the emergency exits available.",
        "Demonstrate that all passengers and crew can be evacuated within 90 seconds with half of the emergency exits available. Conducted in darkness with a representative cross-section of \u2018passengers\u2019."
      ],
      "answer": "Demonstrate that all passengers and crew can be evacuated within 90 seconds with half of the emergency exits available. Conducted in darkness with a representative cross-section of \u2018passengers\u2019."
    },
    {
      "question": "An application of heated anti-icing fluid to de-ice the aeroplane which then remains on the surface to provide anti-icing for a limited period'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "A 1-step de-icing/anti-icing treatment.",
        "A 2-step de-icing/anti-icing treatment.",
        "De-icing.",
        "A holdover application."
      ],
      "answer": "A 1-step de-icing/anti-icing treatment."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Certification Specifications for Large Aeroplanes (CS 25), when an aeroplane needs to show compliance with the Emergency Evacuation requirements with an actual demonstration:",
      "choices": [
        "at least 10 infants, 2 years old or younger, must be carried by female passengers.",
        "not more than 50% of the emergency exits in the sides of the fuselage may be used.",
        "a full briefing on the procedures to be followed in the demonstration must be given to the passengers.",
        "aisles and emergency exit access ways must be clear of all obstructions, to avoid injuries."
      ],
      "answer": "not more than 50% of the emergency exits in the sides of the fuselage may be used."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an aircraft to operate in icing conditions at night, it must be equipped with a means to illuminate __________.",
      "choices": [
        "the wing leading edges",
        "the entire wing",
        "the entire aircraft",
        "the engine inlets"
      ],
      "answer": "the wing leading edges"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a SNOWTAM, a runway condition code of 5 means:",
      "choices": [
        "The pilot report of braking action is POOR.",
        "The pilot report of braking action is GOOD.",
        "The pilot report of braking action is GOOD to MEDIUM.",
        "The pilot report of braking action is MEDIUM to POOR."
      ],
      "answer": "The pilot report of braking action is GOOD."
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the main characteristics of windshear is:",
      "choices": [
        "it occurs only at a low altitude (2000 ft) and never in the horizontal plane.",
        "it occurs only at a low altitude (2000 ft) and never in the vertical plane.",
        "it can occur at any altitude in both the vertical and horizontal planes.",
        "it can occur at any altitude and only in the horizontal plane."
      ],
      "answer": "it can occur at any altitude in both the vertical and horizontal planes."
    },
    {
      "question": "De-icing followed by anti-icing to provide maximum possible protection'. This a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "De-icing.",
        "A 2-step de-icing/anti-icing treatment.",
        "Anti-icing.",
        "A 1-step de-icing/anti-icing."
      ],
      "answer": "A 2-step de-icing/anti-icing treatment."
    },
    {
      "question": "What equipment is required for determination of DH in CAT II and CAT III approaches?",
      "choices": [
        "GNSS SBAS",
        "GNSS VNAV",
        "Air Data Computer",
        "Radio altimeter"
      ],
      "answer": "Radio altimeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to OPS regulations, what is the planning flight preparation minima for a destination alternate with a CAT Il approach available?",
      "choices": [
        "CAT 1 RVR + 200 m.",
        "CAT 1 RVR.",
        "CAT 1 + 50 ft / 200 m.",
        "Non-precision minima plus 200 ft/1000 m."
      ],
      "answer": "CAT 1 RVR."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which 1 of the following statements accurately describes the security precautions at an airport?",
      "choices": [
        "The landside area of an airport is more tightly controlled than the airside because the passengers have not yet been screened.",
        "It's not possible to secure an airfield because of the very large perimeter boundary.",
        "For the purposes of security, airport areas are usually divided into topside, airside, landside, and runways. Appropriate security measures are put in place for each area.",
        "Areas of the airside of an airport are identified as priority risk areas where, in addition to access control, other security controls are applied."
      ],
      "answer": "Areas of the airside of an airport are identified as priority risk areas where, in addition to access control, other security controls are applied."
    },
    {
      "question": "The correct definition of a safe forced landing is:",
      "choices": [
        "an inevitable landing on land or sea from which one may reasonably expect no injuries on board.",
        "a landing on land or sea from which it is guaranteed no injuries will result to the occupants.",
        "an unavoidable landing or ditching with a reasonable expectancy of no injuries to persons in the aircraft or on the surface.",
        "a voluntary landing on land or sea carried out by the crew in order to protect the aircraft and its occupants."
      ],
      "answer": "an unavoidable landing or ditching with a reasonable expectancy of no injuries to persons in the aircraft or on the surface."
    },
    {
      "question": "A fast decompression is recognisable by the following elements: 1. mist in the cabin 2. air streaming out of the aircraft 3. expansion of body gases 4. blast of air released violently from the lungs The combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "2025-01-04 00:00:00",
        "2003-01-02 00:00:00",
        "2004-02-03 00:00:00",
        "1, 2, 3, 4"
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 3, 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "The inability of a tyre to penetrate a very thin residual fluid film left on the pavement after most trapped water has been displaced'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "A contaminated runway.",
        "Reverted rubber hydroplaning.",
        "Viscous hydroplaning.",
        "Dynamic hydroplaning."
      ],
      "answer": "Viscous hydroplaning."
    },
    {
      "question": "An inspection of an aircraft interior after passenger access, and of the hold, checking for suspicious objects'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "An emergency check, following an IED telephone threat.",
        "An aircraft security check.",
        "A routine pre-flight safety check.",
        "Screening."
      ],
      "answer": "An aircraft security check."
    },
    {
      "question": "A braking action of 0.25 and below reported on a SNOWTAM is:",
      "choices": [
        "poor",
        "good",
        "medium",
        "unreliable"
      ],
      "answer": "poor"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct line which maybe seen in a SNOWTAM when the estimated surface friction is reported.",
      "choices": [
        "H) GOOD/GOOD/GOOD",
        "H)5/4/4",
        "H) 5/GOOD/36",
        "H)0.37 /0.39/0.32"
      ],
      "answer": "H)5/4/4"
    },
    {
      "question": "The estimated time that anti-icing fluid will prevent ice and frost formation and accumulation of snow on treated surfaces'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "The maximum time for flight in severe icing conditions.",
        "The failure time.",
        "The holdover time.",
        "The anti-icing decision time."
      ],
      "answer": "The holdover time."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct presentation of friction measurement or calculated coefficient in a SNOWTAM:",
      "choices": [
        "H) 0.46/0.39/0.44",
        "H) 46/39/44 SFH",
        "H) 4/4/5 SFH",
        "H) GOOD/GOOD/GOOD"
      ],
      "answer": "H) 46/39/44 SFH"
    },
    {
      "question": "The dynamic hydroplaning spin-up speed (for a non-rotating tyre) is:",
      "choices": [
        "7.7P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt.",
        "9.7P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt.",
        "7.9P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt.",
        "9P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt."
      ],
      "answer": "7.7P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft has been flying with one of its two transponders defective and the failure has been deferred in accordance with the MEL. During a 30 minute turnaround, an engineer replaces the defective transponder with a new one. Prior to commencing the next commercial air transport flight, what must the commander ensure?",
      "choices": [
        "NO additional documentation is required. When the engineer performing the deferral in accordance with the MEL signed for the pending change of the transponder, this included clearance for the maintenance release at a later point.",
        "The engineer must certify to have changed the transponder in accordance with the prescribed procedures and maintenance release must be signed for by an authorised person.",
        "There is NO requirement for any additional documentation since the defective transponder was deferred according to the MEL and needed to be changed at the first opportunity.",
        "The commander must visually inspect to ensure that the transponder has been changed in accordance with the prescribed procedure prior to signing the maintenance release."
      ],
      "answer": "The engineer must certify to have changed the transponder in accordance with the prescribed procedures and maintenance release must be signed for by an authorised person."
    },
    {
      "question": "A light aircraft is landing in a busy airport which operates multiple runways. Which runway should the pilot choose as preferential to avoid wake turbulence after a heavy aircraft landing?",
      "choices": [
        "RWY 25R, 3 kt headwind",
        "RWY 18, 13 kt crosswind",
        "RWY 25C, wind calm",
        "RWY 25L, wind variable 5 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "RWY 18, 13 kt crosswind"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum validity of a SNOWTAM is:",
      "choices": [
        "8 hours",
        "24 hours",
        "3 hours",
        "12 hours"
      ],
      "answer": "8 hours"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aerodrome observation reports the following runway contamination: 02170135 09L 5/2/2 100/50/75 NR/06/06 WET/SLUSH/SLUSH Which of the following would be the correct SNOWTAM Performance Calculation Section when ATIS reports the following winds: 260/15",
      "choices": [
        "02170135 27R 2/2/5 75/50/100 NR/06/06 WET/SLUSH/SLUSH",
        "02170135 09L 5/2/2 100/50/75 NR/06/06 WET/SLUSH/SLUSH",
        "02170135 27R 2/2/5 75/50/100 06/06/NR SLUSH/SLUSH/WET",
        "02170135 27L 2/2/5 75/50/100 06/06/NR SLUSH/SLUSH/WET"
      ],
      "answer": "02170135 27R 2/2/5 75/50/100 06/06/NR SLUSH/SLUSH/WET"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who is responsible for establishing the procedures for inspecting an aircraft when ground de-icing and anti-icing make this necessary?",
      "choices": [
        "The Competent Authority.",
        "The State of Registry.",
        "The operator.",
        "Maintenance."
      ],
      "answer": "The operator."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to CS 25, if a fuel jettisoning system is required, it must be capable of jettisoning enough fuel within:",
      "choices": [
        "30 minutes",
        "45 minutes",
        "15 minutes",
        "60 minutes"
      ],
      "answer": "15 minutes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following best describes Runway Visual Range?",
      "choices": [
        "The range at which the pilot of an aircraft on the extended centre line of a runway during an approach to land can see the runway surface markings; or the lights delineating the runway or its centre line.",
        "The range at which the pilot of an aircraft on the extended centre line of a runway during an approach to land is able to see the centre line of a runway.",
        "The range over which the pilot of an aircraft on the centre line of a runway can see the runway surface markings; or the lights delineating the runway or identifying its centre line.",
        "The range over which the pilot of an aircraft on the centre line of a runway can see either the runway surface markings, including the runway centre line; or the runway centre line lights and runway edge lights."
      ],
      "answer": "The range over which the pilot of an aircraft on the centre line of a runway can see the runway surface markings; or the lights delineating the runway or identifying its centre line."
    },
    {
      "question": "A runway designated 'wet or water patches' is given a SNOWTAM code of:",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "7",
        "2",
        "NIL"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "An Operator is carrying out Commercial Air Transport with aeroplanes and helicopters, including Low Visibility Operations. Which annexes of the European Regulations on Air Operations contain the requirements applicable to this Operator?",
      "choices": [
        "Annexes 1, Ill (Part-ORO), IV (Part-CAT) and V (Part-SPA).",
        "Annexes Ill (Part-ORO) and IV (Part-CAT) only.",
        "Annexes 1, IV (Part-CAT) and V (Part-SPA) only.",
        "Annexes 1, Ill (Part-ORO), IV (Part-CAT) and VIII (Part-SPO)."
      ],
      "answer": "Annexes 1, Ill (Part-ORO), IV (Part-CAT) and V (Part-SPA)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding the establishment of noise abatement procedures by the operator?",
      "choices": [
        "NADP 1 or NADP 2 must be chosen for an airport, either by the commander or by the operator.",
        "The same procedure must be applied for all airports.",
        "The operator should establish its own NADPs by complying with the NADPs published by the authority.",
        "The operator must establish NADP 1 and NADP 2."
      ],
      "answer": "The operator should establish its own NADPs by complying with the NADPs published by the authority."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying from London, Heathrow, UK to New York, JFK, USA and is within the NAT High Level Airspace at FL 360. A hydraulic warning light has come on, which may necessitate a change of level. The in-flight contingency procedure requires an offset from the assigned route. If prior clearance cannot be obtained, what would be the initial action?",
      "choices": [
        "A turn to the left or right of track by at least 45\u00b0 and immediately initiate a descent to a lower level.",
        "Turn to the right of track in order to avoid any nearby traffic, which would follow the Strategic Offset Procedure (SLOP).",
        "A turn to the right of track of at least 45\u00b0 towards the nearest alternate, which is Keflavik, Iceland.",
        "A turn to the right of track of at least 30\u00b0 towards the nearest alternate, which is Keflavik, Iceland."
      ],
      "answer": "A turn to the right of track of at least 30\u00b0 towards the nearest alternate, which is Keflavik, Iceland."
    },
    {
      "question": "The dynamic hydroplaning spin-down speed (for a rotating tyre) is:",
      "choices": [
        "9P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt.",
        "9.7P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt.",
        "7P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt.",
        "7.7P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt."
      ],
      "answer": "9P\u200b (P= Pressure in psi) kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "Commanders must report bird activity to __________ using an ASR.",
      "choices": [
        "the Authority.",
        "ATC.",
        "the Operator.",
        "EASA."
      ],
      "answer": "ATC."
    },
    {
      "question": "A runway where braking coefficients are reported as 31 /30/29 would have an estimated braking action of:",
      "choices": [
        "Medium to poor, with the last third being poor.",
        "Medium to good, with the last third being medium.",
        "Medium, with the last third being medium to poor.",
        "First third medium and the two remaining thirds medium to poor."
      ],
      "answer": "Medium, with the last third being medium to poor."
    },
    {
      "question": "A precautionary procedure which protects clean surfaces against ice formation for a limited period of time'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "De-icing.",
        "A 2-step de-icing/anti-icing treatment.",
        "Anti-icing.",
        "A 1-step de-icing/anti-icing."
      ],
      "answer": "Anti-icing."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a given ambient temperature and type of anti-icing fluid, in which of the following conditions will the holdover (protection) time be the shortest?",
      "choices": [
        "Steady snow",
        "Frost",
        "Freezing fog",
        "Freezing rain"
      ],
      "answer": "Freezing rain"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refuelling or de-fuelling with Avgas or wide-cut fuel _________ permitted while passengers are embarking, on board, or disembarking.",
      "choices": [
        "is",
        "may be",
        "is not",
        "is sometimes"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    },
    {
      "question": "The global air-to-air frequency, for use when out of range of VHF ground stations, for exchange of operationally significant information is:",
      "choices": [
        "23.45 MHz.",
        "2.8 GHz",
        "123.45 MHz.",
        "123.45 GHz."
      ],
      "answer": "123.45 MHz."
    },
    {
      "question": "For 3- or 4-engined aeroplanes, at an AEO cruising speed, according to the FCOM, in ISA, still-air conditions and based on actual take-off mass, the maximum distance for a take-off alternate aerodrome should not be farther from the departure aerodrome than:",
      "choices": [
        "2 hours flight time",
        "1.5 hours flight time",
        "1 hour flight time",
        "30 minutes flight time"
      ],
      "answer": "2 hours flight time"
    },
    {
      "question": "The NAT track message is typically published at:",
      "choices": [
        "Day-time 1200 UTC - Night-time 0000 UTC.",
        "Day-time 0800 UTC - Night-time 2000 UTC.",
        "Day-time 1400 UTC - Night-time 2200 UTC.",
        "Day-time 2200 UTC - Night-time 1400 UTC."
      ],
      "answer": "Day-time 2200 UTC - Night-time 1400 UTC."
    },
    {
      "question": "For single-engined turbine aeroplane operations at night or in IMC, at normal cruising speed in still-air conditions, based on actual take-off mass, the maximum distance for a take-off alternate aerodrome should not be farther from the departure aerodrome than:",
      "choices": [
        "45 minutes flight time",
        "1.5 hours flight time",
        "30 minutes flight time",
        "1 hour flight time"
      ],
      "answer": "30 minutes flight time"
    },
    {
      "question": "Items capable of posing a risk to health, safety, property or the environment and listed in the TIs or classified according to the TIs'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Dangerous goods which must never be carried on aircraft.",
        "Dangerous goods in excepted quantities.",
        "Dangerous goods.",
        "Dangerous goods which can only be carried by an Operator with a permanent approval to carry DGs."
      ],
      "answer": "Dangerous goods."
    },
    {
      "question": "Planning minima for all IFR flights should comply with which of the following criteria?",
      "choices": [
        "Plan for at least 1 destination aerodrome + 1 destination alternate aerodrome so that no fewer than 2 safe-landing options are available during normal operations when reaching the destination aerodrome.",
        "Plan for at least 1 aerodromes so that no fewer than 1 safe-landing option is available during normal operations when reaching the destination aerodrome.",
        "Plan for at least 2 aerodromes so that 2 safe-landing options are available during normal operations when reaching the destination aerodrome.",
        "Plan for at least 1 aerodrome so that 2 safe-landing options are available during normal operations when reaching the destination aerodrome."
      ],
      "answer": "Plan for at least 1 aerodrome so that 2 safe-landing options are available during normal operations when reaching the destination aerodrome."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following criteria are applicable to the departure aerodrome planning minima?",
      "choices": [
        "The commander should not commence take-off unless weather conditions at the departure aerodrome are no less than the applicable landing minima at that aerodrome, unless a weather-permissible take-off alternate aerodrome is available.",
        "The commander may commence take-off provided weather conditions at a suitable take-off alternate aerodrome are forecast to be no less than the applicable landing minima at that aerodrome within 1.5 hours of take-off.",
        "The commander should not commence take-off unless the RVR and DH for a non-precision approach at the departure aerodrome are no less than the applicable landing minima at that aerodrome.",
        "The commander may commence take-off provided weather conditions at the departure aerodrome are forecast to be no less than the applicable landing minima at that aerodrome within 2 hours of take-off."
      ],
      "answer": "The commander should not commence take-off unless weather conditions at the departure aerodrome are no less than the applicable landing minima at that aerodrome, unless a weather-permissible take-off alternate aerodrome is available."
    },
    {
      "question": "2 destination alternates are needed when:",
      "choices": [
        "At the ETA +/- 2 hr the weather is such that, for a circling operation, ceiling \u2265DA.",
        "At the ETA +/- 1 hr the weather is such that safety margins cannot be met, or no meteorological information is available.",
        "At the ETA +/- 2 hr the weather is such that, for a circling operation, ceiling \u2265DH.",
        "At the ETA +/- 2 hr the weather is such that saefety margins cannot be met,, or no meteorological information available."
      ],
      "answer": "At the ETA +/- 1 hr the weather is such that safety margins cannot be met, or no meteorological information is available."
    },
    {
      "question": "Noise abatement procedures must not prohibit the use of _____ _____ during landing.",
      "choices": [
        "reverse thrust",
        "fuel dumping",
        "reduced thrust",
        "air brakes"
      ],
      "answer": "reverse thrust"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to ICAO, noise abatement procedures during landing:",
      "choices": [
        "prohibit the use of reverse thrust.",
        "apply in case of instrument approaches only.",
        "shall not prohibit the use of reverse thrust.",
        "apply in case of visual approaches only."
      ],
      "answer": "shall not prohibit the use of reverse thrust."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct, concerning precision approach minima for ETOPS ERA?",
      "choices": [
        "A CAT II approach DH at an ETOPS ERA will be no lower than 100 ft.",
        "The CAT I approach DH \u00a0at an ETOPS ERA will be no lower than 200 ft.",
        "Additional ceiling and visibility increments only apply to CAT I minima.",
        "The CAT I approach DH \u00a0at an ETOPS ERA will be no lower than 400 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "The CAT I approach DH \u00a0at an ETOPS ERA will be no lower than 400 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Noise abatement should not be the determining factor in the designation of a runway, under the following circumstances: 1. when crosswind component, including gusts, exceeds 15 kt. 2. when the tailwind component, including gusts, exceeds 5 kt. 3. when the runway surface conditions are adversely affected. The combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2.",
        "2, 3.",
        "1, 2, 3.",
        "1, 3."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 3."
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete this sentence regarding NAT HLA ATS Communications: \"NAT operations outside VHF range require 2 ____, one of which should be ____.\"",
      "choices": [
        "SATVOICE - CPDLC compliant",
        "LRCS - VHF",
        "LRNS - HF",
        "LRCS - HF"
      ],
      "answer": "LRCS - HF"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a manual approach, the aeroplane is subjected to wind shear with an increasing headwind. ln the absence of a pilot action, the aeroplane: 1. flies above the intended approach path 2. flies below the intended approach path 3. has an increasing true airspeed 4. has a decreasing true airspeed The combination of correct statements is:",
      "choices": [
        "1 and 3.",
        "2 and 3.",
        "2 and 4.",
        "1 and 4."
      ],
      "answer": "1 and 3."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the European Regulation on Air Operations, operations under IFR, or under VFR over routes NOT navigated by reference to visual landmarks:",
      "choices": [
        "aircraft are only required to be equipped with one VOR and one ADF when area navigation is required.",
        "only one radio communication system is necessary under normal operating conditions to communicate with an appropriate ground station at any point on the route, including diversions.",
        "aircraft shall be equipped with one short range and one long range communication system.",
        "aircraft shall be equipped with radio communication and navigation equipment in accordance with the applicable airspace requirements."
      ],
      "answer": "aircraft shall be equipped with radio communication and navigation equipment in accordance with the applicable airspace requirements."
    },
    {
      "question": "Who has the responsibility for establishing operating procedures for noise abatement purposes during instrument flight in compliance with ICAO PANS OPS 8168 the:",
      "choices": [
        "state of the operator",
        "commander",
        "state in which the aeroplane is operating",
        "operator"
      ],
      "answer": "operator"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft has departed from Dublin on a transoceanic flight to Montreal. Prior to entering NAT HLA (High Level Airspace) at level flight, the flight crew performs a final confirmation of the aircraft systems serviceability and checks the two primary altimeter readings. Unless otherwise specified, within how many feet of each other must the altimeter readings be?",
      "choices": [
        "300 ft.",
        "400 ft.",
        "200 ft.",
        "250 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "200 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aerodrome may be nominated as an ETOPS ERA aerodrome for flight planning and dispatch purposes, if available forecast weather conditions for a period lasting from the earliest potential landing time until 1 hour after the latest nominated time of use, equals or exceeds:",
      "choices": [
        "For a precision approach, a ceiling of DA/H +400 ft and visibility of VIS +1500 m.",
        "For a precision approach, a ceiling of DA/H +200 ft and visibility of VIS +800 m.",
        "For a circling approach, a ceiling of MDA/H +200 ft and visibility of VIS +800 m.",
        "For a non-precision approach, a ceiling of MDA/H +200 ft and visibility of VIS +800 m."
      ],
      "answer": "For a precision approach, a ceiling of DA/H +200 ft and visibility of VIS +800 m."
    },
    {
      "question": "A category I precision approach (CAT I) is an approach which may be carried out with a runway visual range of at least:",
      "choices": [
        "800 m",
        "500 m",
        "350 m",
        "550 m"
      ],
      "answer": "550 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about Blue Spruce routes is/are accurate?",
      "choices": [
        "The Blue Spruce routes are published twice daily.",
        "Blue Spruce routes are fixed routes across the northern part of the NAT HLA.",
        "Blue Spruce routes are special routes exempt from NAT HLA requirements.",
        "Blue Spruce routes are often used by aircraft with only 1 LRNS."
      ],
      "answer": "Blue Spruce routes are fixed routes across the northern part of the NAT HLA."
    },
    {
      "question": "If your ETA for an oceanic entry point changes (and the aircraft is not under ADS-C surveillance), you must pass a revised ETA to ATS if the change is greater than:",
      "choices": [
        "5 minutes.",
        "10 minutes.",
        "2 minutes.",
        "3 minutes."
      ],
      "answer": "3 minutes."
    },
    {
      "question": "Using the Basic Fuel/Energy Procedure with Variations, what is the minimum reduced contingency fuel that should be uplifted using the RCF 2 procedure? Cruise fuel consumption = 2400 kg/hr Hold fuel consumption = 1800 kg/hr Flight time = 4 hours",
      "choices": [
        "288 kg",
        "1088 kg",
        "150 kg",
        "800 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "800 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the abbreviation MOPSC refer to?",
      "choices": [
        "Maximum operational passenger seating configuration",
        "Maximum operational seating configuration",
        "Maximum operational passenger seating classification",
        "Minimum operational passenger seating configuration"
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum operational passenger seating configuration"
    },
    {
      "question": "The term decision height (DH) is used for:",
      "choices": [
        "a circling approach only.",
        "a precision approach.",
        "an indirect approach.",
        "a non-precision approach."
      ],
      "answer": "a precision approach."
    },
    {
      "question": "Thrust is reduced to climb thrust above 800 ft, the airspeed is kept constant at not less than V2 + 10 kt. Then, at not more than 3000 ft, accelerate with positive rate of climb for flap/slat retraction'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "NADP 2: distant noise abatement.",
        "The increased V2 procedure.",
        "NADP 1: close-in noise abatement.",
        "NADP 1: distant noise abatement."
      ],
      "answer": "NADP 1: close-in noise abatement."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to SLOP, it is recommended that flight crews of aircraft capable of programming automatic offsets:",
      "choices": [
        "Should select flying an offset to the left (ODD flight levels)or to the right (EVEN flight levels) of track up to 2 nm in 0.1 nm increments.",
        "Should select flying an offsetor to the left of track up to 2 nm n 0.1 nm increments.",
        "Should randomly select flying centreline or an offset to the right of track up to 2 nm in 0.1 nm increments.",
        "Should randomly select flying centreline or an offset to the left or to the right of track up to 2 nm in 0.1 nm increments."
      ],
      "answer": "Should randomly select flying centreline or an offset to the right of track up to 2 nm in 0.1 nm increments."
    },
    {
      "question": "Who is ultimately responsible for ensuring that all equipment and baggage is properly secured:",
      "choices": [
        "The SCCM.",
        "The dispatcher.",
        "The Commander.",
        "The Operator."
      ],
      "answer": "The Commander."
    },
    {
      "question": "The best method for preventing gross navigation errors is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Maintain an accurate list of waypoints.",
        "Re-read your clearance before oceanic entry.",
        "Plot your position accurately on a chart.",
        "Maintain Mach number +/- 0.2 or TAS +/- 20 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "Plot your position accurately on a chart."
    },
    {
      "question": "A departure alternate is required:",
      "choices": [
        "If the crosswind is out of limits for take-off",
        "When carrying DGs on a cargo aircraft.",
        "If, for performance or weather issues, it may not be possible to return to the departure aerodrome.",
        "If the RVR is less than 1500 m"
      ],
      "answer": "If, for performance or weather issues, it may not be possible to return to the departure aerodrome."
    },
    {
      "question": "MNPS is the abbreviation for:",
      "choices": [
        "Minimum Navigation Positioning System.",
        "Military Network Performance Structure.",
        "Minimum Navigation Performance Specification.",
        "Maximum North-Atlantic Precision System."
      ],
      "answer": "Minimum Navigation Performance Specification."
    },
    {
      "question": "A list of dangerous goods, which may not be transported by air, can be found in:",
      "choices": [
        "the shipper's declaration for dangerous goods.",
        "Annex 6 to the Chicago Convention.",
        "the Technical Instructions for the Safe Transport of Dangerous Goods by Air.",
        "Annex 18 to the Chicago Convention."
      ],
      "answer": "the Technical Instructions for the Safe Transport of Dangerous Goods by Air."
    },
    {
      "question": "In accordance with ICAO PANS OPS 8168, noise preferential routes are established to ensure that departing and arriving aeroplanes avoid overflying noise-sensitive areas in the vicinity of the aerodrome as far as practicable. In establishing noise preferential routes:",
      "choices": [
        "turns during take-off and climb should not be required unless the bank angle for turns is limited to 28\u00b0 (climbing at V2 + 10 to 20 kt)",
        "turns during take-off and climb should not be required unless the bank angle for turns is limited to 20\u00b0 (climbing at V2 + 10 to 20 kt)",
        "turns during take-off and climb should not be required unless the aeroplane has reached and can maintain throughout the turn a height of no less than 100 m above terrain and the highest obstacle.",
        "no turns should be required coincident with a reduction of power associated with a noise abatement procedure."
      ],
      "answer": "no turns should be required coincident with a reduction of power associated with a noise abatement procedure."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following best describes Mach Number Technique?",
      "choices": [
        "An in-flight technique whereby all participating aircraft operating along certain routes should maintain an assigned Mach number for the entire flight.",
        "An in-flight technique whereby successive aircraft operating along all NAT HLA routes are assigned a Mach number by ATC for all flight above FL300.",
        "An in-flight technique whereby successive aircraft operating along suitable routes are cleared by ATC to maintain a Mach number for a portion of the en-route phase of flight.",
        "An in-flight technique for accuratlely converting Mach number to TAS and thereafter to an accurate and reliable GS, to permit monitoring and accurate reporting of flight progress, thereby ensuring aircraft separation."
      ],
      "answer": "An in-flight technique whereby successive aircraft operating along suitable routes are cleared by ATC to maintain a Mach number for a portion of the en-route phase of flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is/are single-LRNS routes:",
      "choices": [
        "Certain designated OTS routes.",
        "PBCS routes.",
        "Most Blue Spruce routes and at least 1 Tango route.",
        "All the Blue Spruce and Tango routes."
      ],
      "answer": "Most Blue Spruce routes and at least 1 Tango route."
    },
    {
      "question": "Regarding all weather operations, if VAT is from 91 kt to 120 kt, the aeroplane is in:",
      "choices": [
        "Category B.",
        "Category D.",
        "Category C.",
        "Category E."
      ],
      "answer": "Category B."
    },
    {
      "question": "Whose responsibility is it to ensure that a suitable ETOPS en-route alternate is available within the approved, diversion time, at all points of any ETOPS segment(s)?",
      "choices": [
        "The Operator.",
        "ATS.",
        "ATC.",
        "The Authority."
      ],
      "answer": "The Operator."
    },
    {
      "question": "Who is responsible for developing procedures to ensure escape paths are unobstructed before taxi, take-off and landing?",
      "choices": [
        "The Operator.",
        "The Authority.",
        "The Commander.",
        "The State of Registry."
      ],
      "answer": "The Operator."
    },
    {
      "question": "In MNPS airspace, the speed reference for turbo-jet aircraft is the:",
      "choices": [
        "true airspeed.",
        "indicated airspeed.",
        "Mach number.",
        "ground speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Mach number."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refuelling or de-fuelling with Avgas or wide-cut fuel shall not take place:",
      "choices": [
        "\u2026unless passengers are embarking, on board or disembarking.",
        "\u2026if the operator has conducted a suitable and sufficient risk assessment, considering the high risk of using wide-cut fuel types.",
        "...if the operator has established appropriate procedures.",
        "...when passengers are embarking, on board or disembarking."
      ],
      "answer": "...when passengers are embarking, on board or disembarking."
    },
    {
      "question": "For 2-engined aeroplanes, at an OEI cruising speed according to the FCOM, in ISA, still-air conditions and based on actual take-off mass, the maximum distance for a take-off alternate aerodrome should not be farther from the departure aerodrome than:",
      "choices": [
        "2 hours flight time",
        "1.5 hours flight time",
        "30 minutes flight time",
        "1 hour flight time"
      ],
      "answer": "1 hour flight time"
    },
    {
      "question": "\"A DG-related occurrence resulting in fatal or serious injury or major damage\". This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "A dangerous goods incident.",
        "A dangerous goods accident.",
        "A dangerous goods situation.",
        "A dangerous goods violation."
      ],
      "answer": "A dangerous goods accident."
    },
    {
      "question": "Using the Basic Fuel/Energy Scheme, contingency fuel is the greater of either the fuel required for:",
      "choices": [
        "5% of planned trip fuel or 5% of trip fuel for remainder of flight; or 5 minutes at cruising speed at 1000 ft (300 m) above destination in standard conditions.",
        "5% of planned trip fuel or 5% of trip fuel for remainder of flight; or 5 minutes at OEI speed at 1500 ft (450 m) above destination in standard conditions, with the remaining engine set at maximum continuous power.",
        "5% of planned trip fuel or 5% of trip fuel for remainder of flight; or 5 minutes at holding speed at 1500 ft (450 m) above destination in standard conditions.",
        "5% of planned trip fuel or 10% of trip fuel for remainder of flight; or 10 minutes at holding speed at 1500 ft (450 m) above destination in standard conditions."
      ],
      "answer": "5% of planned trip fuel or 5% of trip fuel for remainder of flight; or 5 minutes at holding speed at 1500 ft (450 m) above destination in standard conditions."
    },
    {
      "question": "Communication using HF radio is still common in the NAT HLA. Which of the following statements about HF radio communication is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Even when VHF radio reception isn't available, HF reception always will be.",
        "At night, or when the sun is low, lower frequencies are used.",
        "HF radio reception is usually clearer and more reliable than VHF.",
        "Unlike VHF, HF radio reception is not significantly affected by the state of the ionosphere."
      ],
      "answer": "At night, or when the sun is low, lower frequencies are used."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a flight in NAT MNPS airspace at FL 390, if all long range navigation systems of an aircraft become unserviceable and if no instructions are received from the ATC within a reasonable delay, the pilot in command should consider, broadcasting on 121.5 MHz:",
      "choices": [
        "return to departure airport",
        "climbing or descending 500 feet",
        "land at the nearest airport",
        "set an offset of 5 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "climbing or descending 500 feet"
    },
    {
      "question": "Regarding Noise Abatement Procedures, the first procedure (NADP 1) is used for noise reduction:",
      "choices": [
        "Depending on the prevailing wind.",
        "Not applicable - there is no such procedure.",
        "Away from the airfield.",
        "Near the airfield."
      ],
      "answer": "Near the airfield."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying from Athens to Milan. The weather at the destination is below the applicable minima. The pilot may not take off unless the weather at the expected time of (1) _____ at (2) _____ is above the applicable minima.",
      "choices": [
        "(1) takeoff; (2) Athens",
        "(1) arrival; (2) the alternates.",
        "(1) takeoff; (2) the alternates",
        "(1) arrival; (2) Milan"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) arrival; (2) the alternates."
    },
    {
      "question": "Without ETOPS approval, twin-engined aeroplanes may not fly over a route which contains any point further from an adequate aerodrome than can be flown in the threshold time, OEI, in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "forecast wind conditions.",
        "still air.",
        "ISA conditions.",
        "actual wind conditions."
      ],
      "answer": "still air."
    },
    {
      "question": "The pre-flight check before a NAT HLA flight must include a check of the aircraft's __________ because waypoint ETAs are based on its information.",
      "choices": [
        "clock",
        "FMS",
        "FMC",
        "INS"
      ],
      "answer": "clock"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flights planning to operate outside VHF range may request HF exemption under certain circumstances. What condition is applied to any approval being issued?",
      "choices": [
        "2 alternative (non-HF) LRCS are carried",
        "3 alternative LRCS are carried",
        "2 alternative VHF LRCS are carried",
        "At least 1 alternative non-HF LRCS is carried"
      ],
      "answer": "2 alternative (non-HF) LRCS are carried"
    },
    {
      "question": "A DG-related occurrence resulting in injury, damage, fire, breakage, spillage, leakage of fluid or radiation or where the integrity of the packaging has failed, or seriously jeopardises the aircraft or its occupants\". This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "A dangerous goods accident.",
        "A dangerous goods leak.",
        "A dangerous goods non-containment event.",
        "A dangerous goods incident."
      ],
      "answer": "A dangerous goods incident."
    },
    {
      "question": "ETOPS approval is part of:",
      "choices": [
        "An Operator's AOC.",
        "The MEL.",
        "Long-haul operations.",
        "The Authority's EDTP approval."
      ],
      "answer": "An Operator's AOC."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is meant by \"reaching the destination aerodrome\"?",
      "choices": [
        "Arriving at the final approach fix at the destination aerodrome.",
        "Reaching the missed approach point at the destination aerodrome.",
        "Reaching DA/H or MDA/H at the destination aerodrome.",
        "Landing at the destination aerodrome."
      ],
      "answer": "Reaching DA/H or MDA/H at the destination aerodrome."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refuelling or de-fuelling with Avgas or wide-cut fuel __________ permitted while passengers are embarking, on board, or disembarking.",
      "choices": [
        "may be",
        "is",
        "is not",
        "is sometimes"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to ICAO Doc 4444, a wake turbulence non-radar separation minima of 2 minutes shall be applied to:",
      "choices": [
        "LIGHT aircraft landing behind a MEDIUM aircraft.",
        "MEDIUM aircraft taking-off behind a HEAVY aircraft from an intermediate part of a parallel runway separated by less than 760 m.",
        "MEDIUM aircraft landing behind a HEAVY aircraft.",
        "LIGHT aircraft taking-off behind a MEDIUM aircraft from an intermediate part of the same runway."
      ],
      "answer": "MEDIUM aircraft landing behind a HEAVY aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "The European Regulation on Air Operations states that for operations under IFR, or under VFR over routes NOT navigated by reference to visual landmarks, additional VOR or ADF systems are required on any route, or part thereof, where navigation is based on these respective signals. If neither of these are available, can the route still be flown?",
      "choices": [
        "No, because the propagation characteristics of each system are different.",
        "No, the carriage of VOR and ADF is mandatory.",
        "Yes, provided position reporting with an appropriate ATC station can be performed.",
        "Yes, if safe navigation can be performed with alternative equipment."
      ],
      "answer": "Yes, if safe navigation can be performed with alternative equipment."
    },
    {
      "question": "ICAO Annex 18 is a document dealing with:",
      "choices": [
        "the safety of the air transport of dangerous goods.",
        "the air transport of live animals.",
        "the technical operational use of aircraft.",
        "the noise pollution of aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "the safety of the air transport of dangerous goods."
    },
    {
      "question": "The (ETA +/-1 hr) planning minima for an isolated destination, a destination alternate, or en-route alternate aerodromes, for Type B approach operations, are:",
      "choices": [
        "DA/H +200 ft and RVR/VIS +800 m",
        "DA/H +200 ft and RVR/VIS +400 m",
        "DA/H +400 ft and RVR/VIS +1000 m",
        "DA/H +200 ft and RVR/VIS +1500 m"
      ],
      "answer": "DA/H +200 ft and RVR/VIS +800 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "What class of dangerous goods is represented by the label shown here?",
      "choices": [
        "Explosives",
        "Corrosive",
        "Gases",
        "Flammable Liquid"
      ],
      "answer": "Explosives"
    },
    {
      "question": "Recency, training and checking requirements must be met for each type/variant operated by an individual crew member, except where the __________ approves credit(s) across types or variants.",
      "choices": [
        "Operator",
        "ICAO",
        "Authority",
        "Manufacturer"
      ],
      "answer": "Authority"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a conversion course, flight crew may not operate other types or classes of aircraft. This rule doesn't apply to flight crew who are exclusively operating Performance Class __________ aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "D",
        "C",
        "B",
        "A"
      ],
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider the applicable operational requirements on task specialists' responsibilities. Task specialists' duties shall be specified:",
      "choices": [
        "In the TSC (Task Specialists' Checklist).",
        "In the SOPs (Standard Operating Procedures).",
        "On the AOC (Air Operator Certificate).",
        "In the TM (Training Manual)."
      ],
      "answer": "In the SOPs (Standard Operating Procedures)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the true and false statements. Personnel must have access to parts of the OM related to their duties.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "False",
        "Only if they are flight crew",
        "Only the digital version"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "When a pilot has an OML licence restriction, the other pilot must be:",
      "choices": [
        "No OML, less than 60 years old.",
        "Fully qualified on type, no OML, less than 65 years old.",
        "Fully qualified on type, no OML, less than 59 years old.",
        "Fully qualified on type, no OML, less than 60 years old."
      ],
      "answer": "Fully qualified on type, no OML, less than 60 years old."
    },
    {
      "question": "In unforeseen circumstances, the aircraft can operate with reduced crew if passenger numbers are reduced to ensure the rules are met. In such cases a report must be made to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "ICAO",
        "the Authority",
        "the Operator",
        "EASA"
      ],
      "answer": "the Authority"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the true and false statements. Crew members must have personal copies of the OM Part A and Part B.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "False",
        "Only the Captain",
        "Only if flying internationally"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cabin crew can operate on up to __________ different aeroplane types. This number may be increased if the procedures are similar. In this context a 'different type\u2019 means that equipment locations, exits or procedures are different.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "3",
        "4",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pilots operating both aeroplanes and helicopters may only operate __________ type(s) of each.",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "4",
        "1",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the true and false statements. Flight crew must have personal copies of the OM Parts A, B and C.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "False",
        "Only Part A",
        "Only if required by the Authority"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "A non-technical crew member assigned to perform in-flight duties related to the safety of passengers' is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Flight crew.",
        "Cabin crew.",
        "Handling staff.",
        "Check-in staff."
      ],
      "answer": "Cabin crew."
    },
    {
      "question": "Operators must not permit the use of portable electronic devices:",
      "choices": [
        "Of any type at any time.",
        "That can adversely affect aeroplane systems or equipment.",
        "Between taxi-out and taxi-in.",
        "While the engines are running."
      ],
      "answer": "That can adversely affect aeroplane systems or equipment."
    },
    {
      "question": "The location from where the crew member normally starts and ends a series of FDPs and where crew accommodation is not required'. This is a definition of:",
      "choices": [
        "On-airport standby duty.",
        "Home base.",
        "En-route location.",
        "Dead-heading'."
      ],
      "answer": "Home base."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a night flight, an observer located in the cockpit, seeing an aircraft coming from front left on approximate opposite parallel track, will first see the:",
      "choices": [
        "red steady light",
        "white steady light",
        "green steady light",
        "green and white flashing light"
      ],
      "answer": "red steady light"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a minimum the flight safety documentation system comprises the __________ manual and the __________ control manual.",
      "choices": [
        "Training; ground",
        "operations; maintenance",
        "operations; ground",
        "Training; maintenance"
      ],
      "answer": "operations; maintenance"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ICAO document applicable to operations by operators authorised to conduct international CAT operations is:",
      "choices": [
        "ICAO Annex 6, Part 1.",
        "ICAO Annex 6, Part Int.",
        "ICAO Annex 18, Part CAT.",
        "Regulation 965/2001."
      ],
      "answer": "ICAO Annex 6, Part 1."
    },
    {
      "question": "The commander or operator must submit an ASR to __________ for any incident that endangered, or could have endangered, safety.",
      "choices": [
        "the Authority",
        "IATA",
        "EASA",
        "the Manufacturer"
      ],
      "answer": "the Authority"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ training is appropriate when 2 variants of the same aircraft type have very similar equipment and handling characteristics.",
      "choices": [
        "Differences",
        "Familiarisation",
        "Accurate",
        "Conversion"
      ],
      "answer": "Familiarisation"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is due to be operated with 160 passengers. The aircraft has not yet been assigned a required minimum number of cabin crew by the competent authority. For this trip, ___ cabin crews are required.",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "4",
        "5",
        "6"
      ],
      "answer": "4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Before conducting CAT operations, the operator must:",
      "choices": [
        "Apply for an AOC from EASA.",
        "Apply for an AOC from the relevant Authority.",
        "Obtain approval from IATA.",
        "Obtain an AOC issued by the relevant Authority."
      ],
      "answer": "Obtain an AOC issued by the relevant Authority."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to ICAO Annex 6, what shall the Operator establish for the use and guidance of operational personnel, as part of its safety management system?",
      "choices": [
        "A flight document assembly system.",
        "A flight safety documents system.",
        "A security documentation system.",
        "An operational guidance system."
      ],
      "answer": "A flight safety documents system."
    },
    {
      "question": "Life rafts are required for flight over water at \u2018long distances\u2019 from land. For an aeroplane capable of continuing OEI to an aerodrome this means the lesser of:",
      "choices": [
        "120 min at cruising speed and 300 nm.",
        "120 min at cruising speed and 400 nm.",
        "180 min at cruising speed and 200 nm.",
        "90 min at cruising speed and 400 nm."
      ],
      "answer": "120 min at cruising speed and 400 nm."
    },
    {
      "question": "Sole authority as to whether an 'acceptable deferred defect' is acceptable for the flight rests with:",
      "choices": [
        "The commander.",
        "The Operator.",
        "The dispatcher.",
        "The Authority."
      ],
      "answer": "The commander."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify if this is a true or false statement. Digital flight data monitoring programmes use data from operations for safety and disciplinary purposes.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "False",
        "Only for safety purposes",
        "Only for training purposes"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "First-aid oxygen is required for any aeroplane which:",
      "choices": [
        "Requires cabin crew and is pressurised and which operates at a pressure altitude > 19 000 ft.",
        "Requires cabin crew and is pressurised and which operates at a pressure altitude > 25 000 ft.",
        "Requires cabin crew and is pressurised and which operates at a pressure altitude > 10 000 ft.",
        "Requires cabin crew or is pressurised or which operates at a pressure altitude > 25 000 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "Requires cabin crew and is pressurised and which operates at a pressure altitude > 25 000 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "TAWS is required:",
      "choices": [
        "For all turbine-powered aircraft, but not piston-engined aircraft.",
        "Only for aircraft certified to operate under IFR.",
        "For all aircraft with a MCTOM > 5700 kg or a MOPSC > 9",
        "For all aircraft with a MCTOM > 5700 kg or MOPSC > 19."
      ],
      "answer": "For all aircraft with a MCTOM > 5700 kg or a MOPSC > 9"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft must have cabin crew, when there are passengers on board, if its MOPSC is greater than:",
      "choices": [
        "9",
        "3",
        "15",
        "19"
      ],
      "answer": "19"
    },
    {
      "question": "An ATC service appropriate to airspace and rules of the air:",
      "choices": [
        "Must be used for all flights when possible.",
        "Must be used by all aircraft with a MCTOM > 27 000 kg.",
        "Must be used by all aircraft with a MCTOM > 20 000 kg.",
        "Is not essential for a flight in which no passengers are carried."
      ],
      "answer": "Must be used for all flights when possible."
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider the applicable operational requirements on task specialist's responsibilities. The task specialist shall report any fault, failure, malfunction or defect, which is believed to affect the safe operation of the aircraft, to:",
      "choices": [
        "The pilot in command.",
        "EASA.",
        "The Operator.",
        "The competent authority."
      ],
      "answer": "The pilot in command."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the true and false statements. Copies of all parts of the OM must be kept in the aircraft library.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "False",
        "Only Part B",
        "Only if required by the operator"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "ln accordance with OPS regulations, an operator must ensure that the MDH for a VOR approach is not lower than:",
      "choices": [
        "200 ft.",
        "250 ft.",
        "300 ft.",
        "350 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "300 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "The MEL (Minimum Equipment List) shall be established by:",
      "choices": [
        "the aircraft state of registry",
        "the state of the operator",
        "the operator",
        "the manufacturer"
      ],
      "answer": "the operator"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is true about required equipment?",
      "choices": [
        "All required flight equipment is not subjected to an equipment approval.",
        "All flight equipment is subject to an equipment approval.",
        "Accurate time pieces can be used without an equipment approval.",
        "Child-restraint devices are subject to an equipment approval."
      ],
      "answer": "Accurate time pieces can be used without an equipment approval."
    },
    {
      "question": "The correct statement concerning extinguishing agents onboard aircraft is:",
      "choices": [
        "Water may only be used for minor fires.",
        "A powder extinguisher is suitable for extinguishing a cockpit fire.",
        "Carbon dioxide is only used in the cargo hold.",
        "Halon is an effective extinguishing agent for use in aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "Halon is an effective extinguishing agent for use in aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "An emergency medical kit required for any aircraft with a:",
      "choices": [
        "MOPSC > 30 and which intends to fly > 60 minutes from an aerodrome with medical assistance available.",
        "MOPSC > 30 and which intends to fly > 30 minutes from an aerodrome with medical assistance available.",
        "MOPSC > 20 and which intends to fly > 45 minutes from an aerodrome with medical assistance available.",
        "MOPSC > 20 and which intends to fly > 60 minutes from an aerodrome with medical assistance available."
      ],
      "answer": "MOPSC > 30 and which intends to fly > 60 minutes from an aerodrome with medical assistance available."
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot is performing the pre-flight preparations on an aircraft whose first Certificate of Airworthiness was issued in 2010. This is the first time the pilot is operating an aircraft where a Flight Data Recorder (FDR) is required. The following is a requirement about the operation of the FDR:",
      "choices": [
        "The FDR sensors must be switched on, as data are recorded from sensors that are independent from the information shown to the flight crew, to improve integrity of the recording.",
        "Regardless of pilot action, recording will start and stop automatically to ensure the FOR can record data at all times when the aeroplane is capable of moving under its own power.",
        "Regardless of pilot action, the FDR automatically records at any time when there are persons on board the aeroplane to determine liability in the event of a failure of any system.",
        "The FDR must be manually started when the flight crew begin the pre-flight preparations and then manually stopped when the doors are opened after landing, to preserve the data."
      ],
      "answer": "Regardless of pilot action, recording will start and stop automatically to ensure the FOR can record data at all times when the aeroplane is capable of moving under its own power."
    },
    {
      "question": "The commander must produce all required documents within a reasonable time if asked by a representative of:",
      "choices": [
        "The Operator",
        "ICAO",
        "IATA",
        "The Authority."
      ],
      "answer": "The Authority."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following correctly states the requirement for spare fuses?",
      "choices": [
        "10% (min 3) of each rating in use.",
        "25% (min 3) of each rating in use.",
        "25% (min 2) of each rating in use.",
        "10% (min 2) of each rating in use."
      ],
      "answer": "10% (min 3) of each rating in use."
    },
    {
      "question": "Before exercising Commander\u2019s discretion the commander must:",
      "choices": [
        "Obtain the permission of the Operator.",
        "Obtain the permission of all the crew members.",
        "Obtain the permission of the majority of the crew members.",
        "Consult the crew on their alertness levels before deciding on extension."
      ],
      "answer": "Consult the crew on their alertness levels before deciding on extension."
    },
    {
      "question": "How many battery-powered accessible megaphones are required on an aircraft with a MOPSC of 61-99?",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "2",
        "NONE",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "The MMEL (Master Minimum Equipment List) is drawn up by:",
      "choices": [
        "the manufacturer",
        "the operator.",
        "the aircraft state of registry.",
        "the aircraft manufacturer's list."
      ],
      "answer": "the manufacturer"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ training is required when the variants are broadly similar but have some significant differences that justify time in the simulator or aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "Differences",
        "Accurate",
        "Familiarisation",
        "Conversion"
      ],
      "answer": "Differences"
    },
    {
      "question": "The term 'CAT operations' describes:",
      "choices": [
        "The carriage of passengers or mail in any circumstances.",
        "The carriage of passengers, cargo or mail across international borders.",
        "The transport of passengers, cargo or mail for remuneration or valuable reward.",
        "Any flight operated by the holder of a commercial pilot's licence."
      ],
      "answer": "The transport of passengers, cargo or mail for remuneration or valuable reward."
    },
    {
      "question": "During __________ phases of flight, cabin crew must be seated at assigned station and must not perform any duties other than those required for safety.",
      "choices": [
        "difficult",
        "turbulent",
        "critical",
        "essential"
      ],
      "answer": "critical"
    },
    {
      "question": "An item which does not consistently accomplish its intended purpose, or function within its design limits or tolerances is most properly classed as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "dysfunctional",
        "an acceptable deferred defect",
        "inoperative",
        "unserviceable"
      ],
      "answer": "inoperative"
    },
    {
      "question": "CAT operations are only legal if the operator has an:",
      "choices": [
        "air operations certificate",
        "air operator's certificate",
        "airline operations certificate",
        "air transport license"
      ],
      "answer": "air operator's certificate"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first aid oxygen equipment must be capable of a mass flow of at least __________ litres STPD per minute.",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "1",
        "3",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight time specification schemes must specify recurrent extended recovery rest periods to compensate for cumulative fatigue. Such periods must be a minimum of __________ hours, including __________ local night(s).",
      "choices": [
        "36; 2",
        "36;1",
        "36;3",
        "24;2"
      ],
      "answer": "36; 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Annex 6, what is the definition of an Air Operator Certificate?",
      "choices": [
        "A certificate needed to carry out specified commercial international air transport operations, but not for domestic commercial flights.",
        "A certificate the crew will present to immigration officers, stating that all passengers on board fulfil the visa requirements needed.",
        "A certificate automatically authorising an operator to carry out domestic air services in any ICAO contracting State.",
        "A certificate authorising an operator to carry out specified commercial air transport operations."
      ],
      "answer": "A certificate authorising an operator to carry out specified commercial air transport operations."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft with 29 passengers requires how many fire extinguishers?",
      "choices": [
        "2",
        "1",
        "4",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "You have recently passed your initial training and line check for an operator and it is only your 6th flight as an inexperienced pilot. During the briefing, you realise that the captain you're scheduled to fly with has also recently passed his/her command upgrade and it is only his/her 3rd flight. Can you fly together?",
      "choices": [
        "Yes, since both of you have completed your respective training, you count as experienced crew.",
        "Yes, you have passed your supernumerary flights therefore you can fly with an inexperienced captain.",
        "Yes, as long as the dispatcher is aware and allows it.",
        "No, there are too many inexperienced flight crew."
      ],
      "answer": "No, there are too many inexperienced flight crew."
    },
    {
      "question": "What area of operations is covered by Regulation 965/2012 Annex VIII?",
      "choices": [
        "Aeroplane Maintenance",
        "Specialised Operations",
        "Specific Approvals",
        "Non-Complex Aircraft"
      ],
      "answer": "Specialised Operations"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the true and false statements. All personnel must have personal access to the OM Parts A, B and C.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "False",
        "Only flight crew",
        "Only management"
      ],
      "answer": "False"
    },
    {
      "question": "A captain may be assigned to operate from the co-pilot's position for training or checking a __________ or when designated by the operator to act as co-pilot.",
      "choices": [
        "new first officer",
        "commander",
        "senior cabin crew",
        "flight engineer"
      ],
      "answer": "commander"
    },
    {
      "question": "For passenger oxygen systems, the required minimum supply is the amount of oxygen needed for a constant rate descent from the aeroplane\u2019s maximum certificated operating altitude to 15 000 ft in __________ minutes.",
      "choices": [
        "7",
        "15",
        "10",
        "5"
      ],
      "answer": "10"
    },
    {
      "question": "Any task a crew member performs for the operator'. This is a definition of:",
      "choices": [
        "Duty period.",
        "Rotation.",
        "Duty",
        "Reserve."
      ],
      "answer": "Duty"
    },
    {
      "question": "The regulatory green navigation light is located on the starboard side with a coverage angle of:",
      "choices": [
        "140\u00b0.",
        "110\u00b0.",
        "220\u00b0.",
        "70\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "110\u00b0."
    },
    {
      "question": "As a flight crew member, you are to report for a period of airport standby. When does the airport standby period commence?",
      "choices": [
        "30 minutes before arriving at the airport.",
        "From arriving at the airport.",
        "From reporting at the reporting point.",
        "45 minutes before arriving at the airport."
      ],
      "answer": "From reporting at the reporting point."
    },
    {
      "question": "If a crew member is working for more than one operator the responsibility for flight, duty and rest records rests with:",
      "choices": [
        "The operator.",
        "The crew member.",
        "The Commander.",
        "The Authority."
      ],
      "answer": "The crew member."
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight crew must not operate on more than __________ type(s) or variant(s) unless competent to do so. The Operator must assess the differences, similarities, SOPs and handling characteristics of the aircraft to ensure that such an operation is justified.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "3",
        "4",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot working for a CAT operator has performed 105 duty hours in the last 13 consecutive days. On the 14th day, the operator's crewing department calls, asking the pilot to operate a flight with a total duty of 8 hours later that same day. According to the EU-OPS regulations, what is the correct decision?",
      "choices": [
        "NOT operate the flight, since duty shall NOT exceed 110 duty hours in any 14 consecutive days.",
        "Operate the flight, since the limit for duty is 115 duty hours in any 14 consecutive days.",
        "Operate the flight, since the limit for duty is 120 duty hours in any 14 consecutive days.",
        "NOT operating the flight, since duty shall NOT exceed 105 duty hours in any 14 consecutive days."
      ],
      "answer": "NOT operate the flight, since duty shall NOT exceed 110 duty hours in any 14 consecutive days."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to OPS regulations, for a pressurised aeroplane, following an emergency descent, the maximum pressure altitude at which each member of the flight crew on flight deck duty are not required to be supplied with supplemental oxygen, without flight time limitation is:",
      "choices": [
        "15 000 ft",
        "13 000 ft",
        "8000 ft",
        "10 000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "10 000 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "To act as commander in commercial air transport on a single-pilot aeroplane, how many hours must the holder of a CPL(A) fly on a multi-engine type under IFR?",
      "choices": [
        "400 h + 100 h PIC",
        "700 h + 200 h PIC",
        "200 h + IR",
        "700 h + 400 h PIC"
      ],
      "answer": "700 h + 400 h PIC"
    },
    {
      "question": "The point when the aircraft first moves under its own power for the purpose of preparing for take-off'. This is a definition of:",
      "choices": [
        "Commencement of flight.",
        "Start of a flight duty period.",
        "Taxiing.",
        "Push back."
      ],
      "answer": "Commencement of flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "The average flow rate of first aid oxygen must be __________ litres per minute per person at standard temperature and pressure, dry (STPD).",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "4",
        "1",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "3"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a turnaround, the pilots get a visit from a competent authority who requests to see the aircraft's documents. What should the commander do in this situation?",
      "choices": [
        "The commander must not provide such documents,. the inspector should contact the operator.",
        "Cali his/her superior and ask before showing these documents.",
        "Provide to that person the documentation required to be carried on board.",
        "Comply because anybody is allowed to see those documents."
      ],
      "answer": "Provide to that person the documentation required to be carried on board."
    },
    {
      "question": "You are the pilot of a calibration flight requiring a task specialist to be on board. The task specialist is aware of an incident that could endanger the safety of the operation. Who must he/she report this to?",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft Operator",
        "Airport load controller",
        "Senior Cabin Crew Member",
        "Pilot-in-command"
      ],
      "answer": "Pilot-in-command"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft with 42 passengers requires how many fire extinguishers?",
      "choices": [
        "2",
        "3",
        "1",
        "4"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify if this is a true or false statement. A flight data monitoring programme must exist for aircraft with MCTOM > 27 000 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "False",
        "Only for passenger flights",
        "Only if required by the state of registry"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "When operating an in-flight relief (heavy) crew at or above FL 200, the commander can be relieved by:",
      "choices": [
        "A commander, or a CPL/ATPL-holding co-pilot who is type-rated, satisfies the recency requirements and is in date with recurrent training.",
        "Any CPL-holding co-pilot who is type-rated, satisfies the recency requirements and is in date with recurrent training.",
        "A commander, or an ATPL-holding co-pilot who is type-rated, satisfies the recency requirements and is in date with recurrent training.",
        "Any flight crew member."
      ],
      "answer": "A commander, or an ATPL-holding co-pilot who is type-rated, satisfies the recency requirements and is in date with recurrent training."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify if this is a true or false statement. A flight data monitoring programme should exist for aircraft with MCTOM > 20 000 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "False",
        "Only for cargo flights",
        "Only if operating internationally"
      ],
      "answer": "True"
    },
    {
      "question": "The minimum CVR loop recording time is:",
      "choices": [
        "25 hrs if the aircraft's MCTOM > 5700 kg and its C of A was issued after 1 Jan 2021 and 1 hr for all other aeroplanes.",
        "25 hrs if the aircraft's MCTOM > 27 000 kg and its C of A was issued after 1 Jan 2021 and 2 hrs for all other aeroplanes.",
        "10 hrs if the aircraft's MCTOM > 27 000 kg and individual C of A after 1 Jan 2021 and 2 hrs for all other aeroplanes.",
        "25 hrs if the aircraft's MCTOM > 5700 kg and its C of A was issued after 1 Jan 2021 and 2 hrs for all other aeroplanes."
      ],
      "answer": "25 hrs if the aircraft's MCTOM > 27 000 kg and its C of A was issued after 1 Jan 2021 and 2 hrs for all other aeroplanes."
    }
  ],
  "PER": [
    {
      "question": "What is the screen height for take off from a wet runway for a Class B aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "100",
        "75",
        "50",
        "25"
      ],
      "answer": "50"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 3.7. Why is wind omitted from the graph?",
      "choices": [
        "Wind is automatically incorporated into the graph.",
        "Wind is only considered when climbing in certain directions.",
        "The data is measured with reference to the air.",
        "The data is measured with reference to the ground."
      ],
      "answer": "The data is measured with reference to the air."
    },
    {
      "question": "The stalling speed or the minimum steady flight speed at which the aeroplane is controllable in landing configuration is abbreviated as:",
      "choices": [
        "VS1.",
        "VMC.",
        "VSO.",
        "VS."
      ],
      "answer": "VSO."
    },
    {
      "question": "Compared with clean configuration, a take off with a 10\u00b0 flaps setting will result in:",
      "choices": [
        "A decreased field length limited TOM and a decreased climb limited TOM.",
        "An increased field length limited TOM and a decreased climb limited TOM.",
        "A decreased field length limited TOM and a increased climb limited TOM.",
        "An increased field length limited TOM and a increased climb limited TOM."
      ],
      "answer": "An increased field length limited TOM and a decreased climb limited TOM."
    },
    {
      "question": "What conditions allow the \"increase V1\" technique to increase the allowable take-off mass? The take off mass is:",
      "choices": [
        "Limited by both the field & length and the maximum tyre speed.",
        "Not limited by the field nor by the maximum tyre speed.",
        "Limited by structural restrictions MTOM.",
        "Limited either by the runway length or by the maximum tyre speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Not limited by the field nor by the maximum tyre speed."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 3.10. Given the following information, calculate the barrier speed for a multi-engine piston airplane. Pressure altitude: 4000 ft Outside air temp: 10\u00b0C Aircraft mass: 3450 lb",
      "choices": [
        "76 kt",
        "74 kt",
        "75 kt",
        "72 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "72 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Class B aeroplane has a wingspan of 10 metres. 1000 metres from the start of the departure sector, the width of the sector is __________ metres.",
      "choices": [
        "185",
        "125",
        "190",
        "250"
      ],
      "answer": "190"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the effect of excess thrust on a climb at constant angle?",
      "choices": [
        "Converts excess thrust to increase flight path angle.",
        "Accelerates and rate of climb increases.",
        "Accelerates and climb gradient decreases.",
        "Accelerates and climb gradient increases."
      ],
      "answer": "Accelerates and rate of climb increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "You are in a single engine piston aircraft with a stall speed of 68 kt. What is the minimum value of VR for this aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "71 kt",
        "75 kt",
        "82 kt",
        "68 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "68 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 698 Figure 4.1. For a maximum allowable tailwind of 10 kt calculate the maximum wind strength that can be accepted for a take off from runway 06 with wind from 180 degrees.",
      "choices": [
        "10",
        "20",
        "15",
        "25"
      ],
      "answer": "20"
    },
    {
      "question": "The critical engine inoperative:",
      "choices": [
        "Decreases the power required and increases the total drag due to the additional drag of the windmilling engine and the compensation of the yaw moment.",
        "Increases the power required and the total drag due to the additional drag of the windmilling engine and the compensation of the yaw moment.",
        "Does not affect the aeroplane performance since it is independent of the power plant.",
        "Increases the power required and decreases the total drag due to the windmilling engine."
      ],
      "answer": "Increases the power required and the total drag due to the additional drag of the windmilling engine and the compensation of the yaw moment."
    },
    {
      "question": "Assume a normal approach and landing with a class B aircraft on a wet runway. Which of the following values shows the corresponding screen height?",
      "choices": [
        "35 ft",
        "60 ft",
        "50 ft",
        "100 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "50 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The rotation speed VR for normal utility single-engined landplanes (MTOM 5700 kg or less) must be the same as or faster than:",
      "choices": [
        "1.20 VS1",
        "1.10 VMC or 1.20 VS1, whichever is the greater.",
        "VS1",
        "1.05 VMC or 1.10 VS1, whichever is the greater."
      ],
      "answer": "VS1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The reference speed of the aeroplane, in a specified landing configuration, at the point where it descends through the landing screen height in the determination of the landing distance for manual landings is:",
      "choices": [
        "VSR0",
        "VREF",
        "VR",
        "VS0"
      ],
      "answer": "VREF"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following provides maximum obstacle clearance during climb?",
      "choices": [
        "The speed for maximum rate of climb.",
        "1.2Vs.",
        "The speed for maximum climb angle Vx.",
        "The speed, at which the flaps may be selected one position further UP."
      ],
      "answer": "The speed for maximum climb angle Vx."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Performance Class B take-off flight path:",
      "choices": [
        "Begins at 50 ft above the surface at the end of the TODR and ends at approximately 1000 ft above the surface.",
        "Begins at the point of lift-off and ends at the 50 ft screen height.",
        "Begins at the start of the take-off and ends at approximately 1500 ft above the surface.",
        "Begins at 50 ft above the surface at the end of the TODR and ends at approximately 1500 ft above the surface."
      ],
      "answer": "Begins at 50 ft above the surface at the end of the TODR and ends at approximately 1500 ft above the surface."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which factor must be applied, if not stated differently in AFM, for a Performance Class B aeroplane when taking-off on a runway with 1% upslope?",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "1.1",
        "0.95",
        "1.05"
      ],
      "answer": "1.05"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assume a normal approach and landing with a class B airplane on a dry runway. Which of the following values shows the corresponding screen height?",
      "choices": [
        "50 ft",
        "35 ft",
        "100 ft",
        "60 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "50 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The speed at which the pilot starts to apply back pressure to initiate rotation on take-off is:",
      "choices": [
        "VR",
        "VSR0",
        "VREF",
        "V1"
      ],
      "answer": "VR"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the effect on performance when the outside air pressure is low:",
      "choices": [
        "Decreases the take off roll due to a lower TAS.",
        "Increases the take-off roll due to reduced lift available on the wing.",
        "Increases take-off roll due to decrease in thrust available.",
        "Decreases take-off roll due to increase in thrust available."
      ],
      "answer": "Increases take-off roll due to decrease in thrust available."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP 698 as required. Determine the required headwind given: OAT+30\u00b0C, Pressure altitude: 2000 ft, TODA 1900 ft, Mass 3200 lbs, Flaps at Approach, Dry asphalt runway.",
      "choices": [
        "15 kt.",
        "10 kt.",
        "22 kt.",
        "20 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "22 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "The departure sector begins at the point where the aircraft reaches __________ ft above the surface. At this point the width of the departure sector is half the aeroplane's wingspan plus __________ metres.",
      "choices": [
        "60; 60",
        "50; 60",
        "60; 50",
        "50; 50"
      ],
      "answer": "50; 60"
    },
    {
      "question": "For multi-engine Class B aeroplanes, the operator must ensure that the aircraft is capable of continuing flight, at or above the relevant minimum altitudes for safe flight stated in the Operations Manual, to a point __________ft above the aerodrome.",
      "choices": [
        "1500",
        "1000",
        "2000",
        "500"
      ],
      "answer": "1000"
    },
    {
      "question": "The stall speed or the minimum steady flight speed obtained in a specified configuration is:",
      "choices": [
        "VS1",
        "VS",
        "VS1G",
        "VS0"
      ],
      "answer": "VS1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum angle of bank permitted after take-off below 50 ft for an aeroplane in Performance Class B is:",
      "choices": [
        "5\u00b0",
        "0\u00b0",
        "15\u00b0",
        "10\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "0\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "The stall speed or the minimum steady flight speed in the landing configuration is:",
      "choices": [
        "VS1",
        "VS",
        "VS0",
        "VSR"
      ],
      "answer": "VS0"
    },
    {
      "question": "The operator must ensure that the aircraft, in the meteorological conditions expected for the flight, and in the event of engine failure, is capable of reaching a place at which a safe forced landing can be made.",
      "choices": [
        "This requirement applies only to single-engine Class B aeroplanes.",
        "This requirement applies to all Class B aeroplanes.",
        "This requirement applies to single-engine Class B aeroplanes taking-off in IMC.",
        "This requirement applies to all multi-engine Class B aeroplanes."
      ],
      "answer": "This requirement applies only to single-engine Class B aeroplanes."
    },
    {
      "question": "The 1g stall speed at which the aeroplane can develop a lift force (normal to the flight path) equal to its weight is:",
      "choices": [
        "VSR0",
        "VS1G",
        "VS1",
        "VS0"
      ],
      "answer": "VS1G"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is correct concerning fuel consumption change, at altitude, of a propeller driven aeroplane?",
      "choices": [
        "It increases before VMP.",
        "It decreases before VMP.",
        "It increases after VMP.",
        "It decreases after VMP."
      ],
      "answer": "It increases after VMP."
    },
    {
      "question": "The reference stall speed in the landing configuration is:",
      "choices": [
        "VR",
        "VSR0",
        "VREF",
        "VS0"
      ],
      "answer": "VSR0"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a Performance Class B, multi-engined aeroplane, in order to eliminate any problems associated with a critical engine failure:",
      "choices": [
        "engines are mounted away from the aeroplane's centreline.",
        "propellers with a minimum of three blades are used.",
        "counter rotating propellers are installed.",
        "all propellers turn ln the same direction."
      ],
      "answer": "counter rotating propellers are installed."
    },
    {
      "question": "The stall speed or the minimum steady flight speed at which the aeroplane is controllable is:",
      "choices": [
        "VS",
        "VS0",
        "VS1",
        "VMC"
      ],
      "answer": "VS"
    },
    {
      "question": "The effect of increasing the flap setting, from zero to the recommended take-off setting, on the length of the Take-off Distance Required (TODR) and the Field Length Limited Take-off mass (TOM) is:",
      "choices": [
        "Increased TOD required and increased field length limited TOM.",
        "Decreased TOD required and decreased field length limited TOM.",
        "Decreased TOD required and increased field length limited TOM.",
        "Increased TOD required and decreased field length limited TOM."
      ],
      "answer": "Decreased TOD required and increased field length limited TOM."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an MEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP698 as required. Determine the TOD for an aircraft, mass 4500 lb, flaps up, 1000 ft pressure altitude, 20\u00b0C and 10 kt headwind component.",
      "choices": [
        "1900 ft.",
        "1400 ft.",
        "1700 ft.",
        "2000 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "1700 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "What percentages of the head wind and tail wind component are taken into account when calculating the take off field length required?",
      "choices": [
        "50% head wind and 100% tail wind.",
        "50% head wind and 150% tail wind.",
        "100% head wind and 100% tail wind.",
        "150% head wind and 50% tail wind."
      ],
      "answer": "50% head wind and 150% tail wind."
    },
    {
      "question": "The gradient of the take-off flight path from 50 ft to the engine failure height is the average all-engine gradient multiplied by a factor of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "1.3",
        "0.77",
        "2.1",
        "1"
      ],
      "answer": "0.77"
    },
    {
      "question": "The minimum power required speed VMP is __________ VMD.",
      "choices": [
        "equal to",
        "greater than",
        "less than",
        "sometimes greater than"
      ],
      "answer": "less than"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the minimum width of a clearway?",
      "choices": [
        "1000 ft",
        "500 ft",
        "250 ft",
        "750 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "500 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the cruise, optimum range and endurance is most likely to be achieved when the CG position is slightly __________.",
      "choices": [
        "forward",
        "aft",
        "neutral",
        "at the limit"
      ],
      "answer": "aft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The speed at which an aircraft achieves its maximum rate of climb is known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "VX",
        "VY",
        "VNE",
        "VFE"
      ],
      "answer": "VY"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the effect of increased mass on the performance of a gliding aeroplane?",
      "choices": [
        "The lift/drag ratio decreases.",
        "There is no effect.",
        "The gliding angle decreases.",
        "The speed for best angle of descent increases."
      ],
      "answer": "The speed for best angle of descent increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a steady unaccelerated descent:",
      "choices": [
        "The thrust steadily reduces with altitude.",
        "Thrust and a component of weight are balanced by the drag.",
        "The lift must be less than the combined components of weight.",
        "The lift steadily reduces with altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Thrust and a component of weight are balanced by the drag."
    },
    {
      "question": "Wet and contaminated runways increase the take-off distance because of the twin influences of displacement drag and __________ drag.",
      "choices": [
        "induced",
        "impingement",
        "stiction",
        "parasite"
      ],
      "answer": "impingement"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 10% increase in the speed at the screen height, results in a __________% increase in the landing distance. Answer as a number.",
      "choices": [
        "20",
        "5",
        "10",
        "15"
      ],
      "answer": "20"
    },
    {
      "question": "Climb gradient is the __________ divided by the __________ times 100.",
      "choices": [
        "vertical height gained; horizontal distance flown",
        "horizontal distance flown; horizontal distance flown",
        "horizontal distance flown; vertical height gained",
        "vertical height gained; vertical height gained"
      ],
      "answer": "vertical height gained; horizontal distance flown"
    },
    {
      "question": "Lowering flaps __________ the rate of climb and __________ VY.",
      "choices": [
        "reduces; increases.",
        "increases; reduces.",
        "reduces; reduces.",
        "increases; increases."
      ],
      "answer": "reduces; reduces."
    },
    {
      "question": "A decrease in the turbojet aeroplane's mass __________ Vx and __________ the excess thrust.",
      "choices": [
        "reduces; increases.",
        "reduces; reduces.",
        "increases; increases.",
        "increases; reduces."
      ],
      "answer": "reduces; increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "The initial part of the descent is flown at a constant __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Mach",
        "CAS",
        "IAS",
        "TAS"
      ],
      "answer": "Mach"
    },
    {
      "question": "Aeroplanes powered by reciprocating engines with an MOPSC of more than 9 or a maximum take-off mass exceeding 5700 kg are in Performance Class:",
      "choices": [
        "B",
        "D",
        "C",
        "A"
      ],
      "answer": "C"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a turbojet engine fuel flow = SFC x __________.",
      "choices": [
        "thrust",
        "power",
        "drag",
        "lift"
      ],
      "answer": "thrust"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the demonstrated crosswind is considered to be limiting, then it\u2019s entered as an operating limitation in:",
      "choices": [
        "The Abnormal Procedures section of the training manual.",
        "The aircraft flight manual (AFM).",
        "CS-25",
        "EU OPS 1"
      ],
      "answer": "The aircraft flight manual (AFM)."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the specific range (SAR)?",
      "choices": [
        "TAS/Fuel flow",
        "Endurance / Speed",
        "Fuel flow / TAS",
        "Speed / Endurance"
      ],
      "answer": "TAS/Fuel flow"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary purpose of a continuous descent to final approach is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Maximise fuel savings.",
        "Reduce crew workload.",
        "Increase safety.",
        "Minimise noise disturbance to people under the flight path."
      ],
      "answer": "Maximise fuel savings."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane is taking off on Runway 18. The reported wind is 210/40 kt. The headwind component is __________ kt. The crosswind component is __________ kt.",
      "choices": [
        "35; 10",
        "35; 20",
        "40; 20",
        "20; 35"
      ],
      "answer": "35; 20"
    },
    {
      "question": "How does an increase in mass affect VY and VX?",
      "choices": [
        "Increase & Decrease",
        "Increase and Increase",
        "Decrease & Decrease",
        "Decrease & Increase"
      ],
      "answer": "Increase and Increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ is the angle of the aircraft\u2019s flight path (in degrees) measured with respect to the Earth\u2019s horizontal.",
      "choices": [
        "Flight path angle",
        "climb angle",
        "flight path vector",
        "climb gradient"
      ],
      "answer": "Flight path angle"
    },
    {
      "question": "The flight path angle is the angle between the:",
      "choices": [
        "path of the aircraft relative to True North.",
        "longitudinal axis and the path of the aircraft.",
        "longitudinal axis and the horizon.",
        "path of the aircraft relative to the horizon."
      ],
      "answer": "path of the aircraft relative to the horizon."
    },
    {
      "question": "The intersections of the thrust available and the drag curve are the operating points of the aeroplane:",
      "choices": [
        "In unaccelerated level flight.",
        "In accelerated level flight.",
        "In descent with constant IAS.",
        "In unaccelerated climb."
      ],
      "answer": "In unaccelerated level flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ an aerodrome\u2019s pressure altitude, the longer the TOD.",
      "choices": [
        "higher",
        "lower",
        "same as",
        "inverse of"
      ],
      "answer": "higher"
    },
    {
      "question": "The take-off distance available (TODA) is normally:",
      "choices": [
        "The runway plus stopway. The TODA is the lesser of: TORA plus stopway, or 1.5 times TORA.",
        "The runway plus stopway and clearway.",
        "The runway plus the clearway. The TODA is the lesser of: TORA plus clearway, or 1.5 times TORA.",
        "The runway plus the clearway. The TODA is the lesser of: TORA plus clearway, or 0.5 times TORA."
      ],
      "answer": "The runway plus the clearway. The TODA is the lesser of: TORA plus clearway, or 1.5 times TORA."
    },
    {
      "question": "Other factors remaining constant, the effect an increase of altitude, in a standard atmosphere, has on the value of Vx and Vv in terms of TAS is:",
      "choices": [
        "Both will decrease.",
        "Both will remain the same.",
        "Vx will decrease and Vv will increase.",
        "Both will increase."
      ],
      "answer": "Both will increase."
    },
    {
      "question": "With regard to turbo jet aeroplanes, wind (1) ____ endurance and (2) ____ the maximum endurance speed. Which option is the correct one?",
      "choices": [
        "(1) does not affect, (2) affects",
        "(1) does not affect, (2) does not affect",
        "(1) affects, (2) does not affect",
        "(1) affects, (2) affects"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) does not affect, (2) does not affect"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Europe CS-23 covers:",
      "choices": [
        "The operation of aeroplanes in the Normal category, with a passenger seating configuration up to 19 or less and a MCTOM of 8618 kg (or less).",
        "Piston propeller aeroplanes only.",
        "The operation of aeroplanes in the Normal category, with a passenger seating configuration up to 19 or less and a Mass of 8618 kg (or less).",
        "Covers large aeroplanes with a MCTOM greater than 5700 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "The operation of aeroplanes in the Normal category, with a passenger seating configuration up to 19 or less and a MCTOM of 8618 kg (or less)."
    },
    {
      "question": "The specific air range (SAR) __________ affected by wind, because it depends on NAM/kg of fuel or TAS/fuel flow.",
      "choices": [
        "is not",
        "is",
        "is sometimes",
        "is always"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    },
    {
      "question": "In steady, unaccelerated, straight-and-level flight:",
      "choices": [
        "L = W and T = L.",
        "T must be greater than D.",
        "L = W and T = D.",
        "W cos\u03b8 is parallel to the flight path."
      ],
      "answer": "L = W and T = D."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a given air gradient, a headwind __________ the ground gradient; a tailwind __________ it.",
      "choices": [
        "increases; reduces",
        "reduces; increases",
        "increases; increases",
        "reduces; reduces"
      ],
      "answer": "increases; reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "Endurance is maximised when the fuel flow is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "maximised",
        "minimised",
        "constant",
        "variable"
      ],
      "answer": "minimised"
    },
    {
      "question": "Gross Performance diminished by a safety factor (margin), laid down by the appropriate authority is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Net performance.",
        "Operational performance.",
        "Safety performance.",
        "Measured performance."
      ],
      "answer": "Net performance."
    },
    {
      "question": "A decrease in atmospheric pressure has, among other things, the following consequences on take-off performance:",
      "choices": [
        "A reduced take-off distance and improved initial climb performance.",
        "An increased take-off distance and degraded initial climb performance.",
        "An increased take-off distance and improved initial climb performance.",
        "A reduced take-off distance and degraded initial climb performance."
      ],
      "answer": "An increased take-off distance and degraded initial climb performance."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum operating CAS is __________",
      "choices": [
        "VMO",
        "VMM",
        "MMO",
        "CMO"
      ],
      "answer": "VMO"
    },
    {
      "question": "Aeroplanes powered by propeller engines with an MOPSC of 9 or less and a maximum take-off mass of 5700 kg or less are in Performance Class:",
      "choices": [
        "B",
        "D",
        "C",
        "A"
      ],
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "When not flat-rated, thrust reduces with altitude because:",
      "choices": [
        "The temperature reduces, thus reducing the mass flow through both turbojet engines and propellers.",
        "The temperature reduces, thus reducing the thermal efficiency of engines.",
        "The air density reduces, thus reducing the mass flow through both turbojet engines and propellers.",
        "Altitude reduces the velocity of flow through the propeller or turbojet engine."
      ],
      "answer": "The air density reduces, thus reducing the mass flow through both turbojet engines and propellers."
    },
    {
      "question": "The theoretical altitude at which the rate of climb is zero is called the__________ ceiling.",
      "choices": [
        "absolute",
        "operational",
        "service",
        "aerodynamic"
      ],
      "answer": "absolute"
    },
    {
      "question": "Extending flap __________ excess thrust.",
      "choices": [
        "has no effect",
        "reduces",
        "increases",
        "sometimes increases"
      ],
      "answer": "reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is the minimum speed that ensures you can retain sufficient control of the aircraft when in the approach and landing configuration.",
      "choices": [
        "VREF",
        "VMCL",
        "VMCA",
        "VFE"
      ],
      "answer": "VMCL"
    },
    {
      "question": "The average performance that a fleet of aircraft can be expected to achieve, when satisfactorily maintained and flown in accordance with the techniques described in the flight manual' is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Measured performance.",
        "Net performance.",
        "Operational performance.",
        "Gross performance."
      ],
      "answer": "Gross performance."
    },
    {
      "question": "MECON __________ as the cost index increases.",
      "choices": [
        "decreases",
        "has no effect",
        "increases",
        "is not related"
      ],
      "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "The cost index is the cost of time/the cost of fuel. A lower cost index weights the flight towards __________ savings. A higher cost index weights the flight towards __________ savings.",
      "choices": [
        "fuel; fuel",
        "fuel; time",
        "time; time",
        "time; fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "fuel; time"
    },
    {
      "question": "Along with aeroplane mass, which other factors have an influence on the service ceiling?",
      "choices": [
        "Airspace capacity and clear air turbulence.",
        "Winds and pressure.",
        "Maximum differential pressure and winds.",
        "Air temperature and the position of the CG."
      ],
      "answer": "Air temperature and the position of the CG."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a turbojet aircraft, VX occurs at __________.",
      "choices": [
        "VMD",
        "VMP",
        "VY",
        "VNE"
      ],
      "answer": "VMD"
    },
    {
      "question": "With regard to the effect of altitude on the speed for maximum endurance for a propeller-driven aeroplane, as altitude increases, the speed for maximum endurance will:",
      "choices": [
        "decrease, because the power required decreases with altitude.",
        "increase, because the power required increases with altitude.",
        "decrease, because aeroplane drag decreases with altitude.",
        "increase, because aeroplane drag increases with altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "increase, because the power required increases with altitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "When a turbojet aeroplane climbs using a climb schedule, the initial part of the climb is flown at constant __________ and subsequently at constant __________.",
      "choices": [
        "CAS; CAS.",
        "Mach; Mach.",
        "CAS; Mach.",
        "Mach; CAS."
      ],
      "answer": "CAS; Mach."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is descending at 193 kt TAS in still air with a vertical speed of 1000 ft/min. The descent gradient is:",
      "choices": [
        "0.054",
        "0.048",
        "0.051",
        "0.065"
      ],
      "answer": "0.051"
    },
    {
      "question": "The point during the climb at which the designated climb CAS and designated climb Mach number coincide is known as the __________altitude.",
      "choices": [
        "crossover",
        "constraint",
        "optimum",
        "absolute"
      ],
      "answer": "crossover"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a turbojet engine, SFC is lowest (best) when:",
      "choices": [
        "The aircraft is flying at VMD.",
        "The engine is running at its design RPM (approximately 90 to 95% maximum).",
        "The engine is running at VMP.",
        "The air temperature is high."
      ],
      "answer": "The engine is running at its design RPM (approximately 90 to 95% maximum)."
    },
    {
      "question": "The net flight path climb gradient after take-off compared to the gross climb gradient is:",
      "choices": [
        "Depends on type of aircraft.",
        "Smaller.",
        "Greater.",
        "The same."
      ],
      "answer": "Smaller."
    },
    {
      "question": "The \"Density altitude\" is:",
      "choices": [
        "the height obtained by setting the subscale of an altimeter to QNE.",
        "the height in the standard atmosphere at which the prevailing density occurs.",
        "the altitude in the standard atmosphere at which the prevailing density occurs.",
        "the altitude obtained by setting the subscale of an altimeter to QNH."
      ],
      "answer": "the altitude in the standard atmosphere at which the prevailing density occurs."
    },
    {
      "question": "Turbojet range is greatest at __________ altitude because this is where SFC is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "low; highest.",
        "high; highest.",
        "low; lowest.",
        "high; lowest."
      ],
      "answer": "high; lowest."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a propeller-driven, twin-engined aircraft, VXSE is __________ than VX.",
      "choices": [
        "faster",
        "slower",
        "the same as",
        "unrelated to"
      ],
      "answer": "faster"
    },
    {
      "question": "An increase in atmospheric pressure has, among other things, the following consequences on landing performance:",
      "choices": [
        "An increased landing distance and improved go-around performance.",
        "An increased landing distance and degraded go-around performance.",
        "A reduced landing distance and improved go-around performance.",
        "A reduced landing distance and degraded go-around performance."
      ],
      "answer": "A reduced landing distance and improved go-around performance."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a turbojet-powered aeroplane, the lowest SFC occurs:",
      "choices": [
        "At the altitude where the engine is running at full throttle (full throttle height).",
        "Whenever the engine is running at the lowest RPM needed to sustain straight and level flight.",
        "At the altitude where the thrust required requires the engine core to run at its optimum design RPM.",
        "Whenever the engine is running at its optimum design RPM (90-95% of maximum)."
      ],
      "answer": "At the altitude where the thrust required requires the engine core to run at its optimum design RPM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Turns __________ climb performance.",
      "choices": [
        "increase",
        "reduce",
        "has no effect",
        "improves then reduces"
      ],
      "answer": "reduce"
    },
    {
      "question": "Multi-engined aeroplanes powered by turbo-propeller engines with an MOPSC of more than 9 or a maximum take-off mass exceeding 5700 kg, and all multi-engined turbo-jet powered aeroplanes are in Performance Class:",
      "choices": [
        "A",
        "B",
        "C",
        "D"
      ],
      "answer": "A"
    },
    {
      "question": "The optimum altitude for range is __________ for a propeller-driven aeroplane compared with a turbojet-driven aeroplane.",
      "choices": [
        "lower",
        "same",
        "higher",
        "sometimes lower"
      ],
      "answer": "lower"
    },
    {
      "question": "If you don\u2019t let the automatics manage the descent:",
      "choices": [
        "Set a target CAS or Mach number to avoid the risk of any speed exceedance.",
        "The aeroplane will descend at the minimum rate of descent.",
        "Select a target CAS to avoid the risk of a MMO exceedance.",
        "Select a target CAS to avoid the risk of a VMO exceedance."
      ],
      "answer": "Select a target CAS to avoid the risk of a VMO exceedance."
    },
    {
      "question": "With regard to the CG and its effect on performance select the correct statement.",
      "choices": [
        "A forward CG increases stability and increases fuel consumption.",
        "An aft CG decreases stability and increases fuel consumption.",
        "An aft CG increases stability and decreases fuel consumption.",
        "A forward CG increases stability and decreases fuel consumption."
      ],
      "answer": "A forward CG increases stability and increases fuel consumption."
    },
    {
      "question": "A tailwind __________ the range (SGR).",
      "choices": [
        "has no effect",
        "reduces",
        "increases",
        "sometimes reduces"
      ],
      "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum operating Mach number is known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "VMO",
        "MMO",
        "VNE",
        "VFE"
      ],
      "answer": "MMO"
    },
    {
      "question": "Compared with still-air, the effect a headwind has on the values of the maximum range speed and the maximum gradient climb speed respectively is that:",
      "choices": [
        "The maximum range speed decreases and the maximum gradient climb speed increases.",
        "The maximum range speed decreases and the maximum gradient climb speed decreases.",
        "The maximum range speed increases and the maximum gradient climb speed is not affected.",
        "The maximum range speed decreases and the maximum gradient climb speed is not affected."
      ],
      "answer": "The maximum range speed increases and the maximum gradient climb speed is not affected."
    },
    {
      "question": "A tailwind increases the landing distance because:",
      "choices": [
        "It increases the aeroplane's ground speed.",
        "A tailwind increases VMCL.",
        "It increases the aeroplane's CAS.",
        "A tailwind requires a higher VREF."
      ],
      "answer": "It increases the aeroplane's ground speed."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a given aircraft mass, the climb gradient:",
      "choices": [
        "Increases with increasing flap angle and increasing temperature.",
        "Decreases with increasing flap angle and increasing temperature.",
        "Decreases with increasing flap angle and decreasing temperature.",
        "Increases with increasing flap angle and decreasing temperature."
      ],
      "answer": "Decreases with increasing flap angle and increasing temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "How does a change in Pressure Altitude affect the climb performance with regard to the Rate Of Climb and the Climb Angle? lncreasing Pressure Altitude results in:",
      "choices": [
        "an increased Rate Of Climb but the Climb Angle remains the same.",
        "a decreased Climb Angle but the Rate Of Climb remains the same.",
        "an increased Rate Of Climb and an increased Climb Angle.",
        "a decreased Rate Of Climb and a decreased Climb Angle."
      ],
      "answer": "a decreased Rate Of Climb and a decreased Climb Angle."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following combinations adversely affects take-off and initial climb performance?",
      "choices": [
        "High temperature and high relative humidity",
        "Low temperature and low relative humidity",
        "High temperature and low relative humidity",
        "Low temperature and high relative humidity"
      ],
      "answer": "High temperature and high relative humidity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Considering a climb gradient of 5.1% to 2000 ft, with a TAS of 100 kt and a tailwind component of 12 kt. Find the rate of climb in feet per minute.",
      "choices": [
        "450",
        "437",
        "500",
        "517"
      ],
      "answer": "517"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ is the maximum permissible mass at the start of the take-off run.",
      "choices": [
        "MLM",
        "MTOM",
        "MSLM",
        "MZFM"
      ],
      "answer": "MTOM"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a propeller engine fuel flow = SFC x __________.",
      "choices": [
        "thrust",
        "power required",
        "TAS",
        "drag"
      ],
      "answer": "power required"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement about the clearway is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Minimum semi-width is 90m.",
        "Minimum clearway gradient is 1.5%",
        "The clearway is part of ASDA.",
        "The airport authority has control over the clearway."
      ],
      "answer": "The airport authority has control over the clearway."
    },
    {
      "question": "During climb with all engines, the altitude where the rate of climb reduces to 100 ft/min is called:",
      "choices": [
        "Absolute ceiling.",
        "Thrust ceiling.",
        "Service ceiling.",
        "Aerodynamic ceiling."
      ],
      "answer": "Service ceiling."
    },
    {
      "question": "The ratio of the vertical height lost divided by the horizontal distance flown over the ground is known as the _________ gradient.",
      "choices": [
        "air",
        "ground",
        "descent",
        "flight path"
      ],
      "answer": "ground"
    },
    {
      "question": "When the aircraft climbs at a constant CAS, the TAS and Mach number . When a climb is flown at a constant Mach number, the CAS (and TAS).",
      "choices": [
        "decrease; increase.",
        "increase; increase.",
        "increase; reduce.",
        "decrease; reduce."
      ],
      "answer": "increase; reduce."
    },
    {
      "question": "The distance between the point on the surface of the aerodrome at which an aeroplane can begin its take-off run to the nearest point...at which the surface... is incapable of bearing the weight... is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "TORA",
        "TODA",
        "LDA",
        "ASDA"
      ],
      "answer": "TORA"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a turbo-propeller aeroplane, endurance __________ with altitude.",
      "choices": [
        "does not vary significantly",
        "varies significantly",
        "increases",
        "decreases"
      ],
      "answer": "does not vary significantly"
    },
    {
      "question": "To achieve the maximum range over ground with headwind the airspeed should be:",
      "choices": [
        "reduced to the gust penetration speed.",
        "equal to the speed for maximum range cruise with no wind.",
        "higher compared to the speed for maximum range cruise with no wind.",
        "lower compared to the speed for maximum range cruise with no wind."
      ],
      "answer": "higher compared to the speed for maximum range cruise with no wind."
    },
    {
      "question": "VY is the speed at which the difference between __________ available and __________ required is greatest.",
      "choices": [
        "thrust; thrust.",
        "power; thrust.",
        "power; power.",
        "thrust; power."
      ],
      "answer": "power; power."
    },
    {
      "question": "The specific ground range (SGR) depends on NGM/kg fuel or groundspeed/fuel flow. A headwind __________ range (SGR).",
      "choices": [
        "reduces",
        "has no effect",
        "increases",
        "sometimes reduces"
      ],
      "answer": "reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Europe, turbine-powered large aeroplanes (Performance Class A aeroplanes) are certified under:",
      "choices": [
        "CS-25",
        "EU OPS 1",
        "FAR-25",
        "CS-23"
      ],
      "answer": "CS-25"
    },
    {
      "question": "An obstacle-free rectangular area on the ground at the end of the runway, at least the same width as the associated runway and centred along the runway\u2019s centreline' is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Stopway.",
        "ASDA",
        "TORA",
        "Clearway."
      ],
      "answer": "Stopway."
    },
    {
      "question": "The formula for calculating the percentage gradient is:",
      "choices": [
        "T-W/W",
        "(T-D)/W",
        "T x D/W",
        "(T-D) x 100/W"
      ],
      "answer": "(T-D) x 100/W"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the difference between climb angle and climb gradient?",
      "choices": [
        "The variation of the angle is represented by the gradient.",
        "The gradient is based on mass, the angle is not.",
        "The value of the gradient is always higher than the value of the angle.",
        "The gradient considers wind, the angle does not."
      ],
      "answer": "The value of the gradient is always higher than the value of the angle."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following conditions: Still air climb gradient 7.5% TAS 140 kt Wind component 25 kt head What is the effective wind climb gradient?",
      "choices": [
        "0.061",
        "0.085",
        "0.091",
        "0.058"
      ],
      "answer": "0.091"
    },
    {
      "question": "Study this diagram. The crosswind component is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "25 kt.",
        "20 kt.",
        "9 kt.",
        "13 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "20 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "A marked speed acceleration along the flight path results in __________ climb performance during the acceleration event.",
      "choices": [
        "reduced",
        "has no effect",
        "increased",
        "initially improves"
      ],
      "answer": "reduced"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the effect of an upslope on the ASDR, it:",
      "choices": [
        "Decreases.",
        "Only decreases if the TOM decreases.",
        "Only increases if the TOM increases.",
        "Increases."
      ],
      "answer": "Increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "The decrease of altitude to horizontal air distance expressed as a percentage is one way of describing the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "descent angle",
        "descent gradient",
        "descent rate",
        "descent path"
      ],
      "answer": "descent gradient"
    },
    {
      "question": "The runway limited take-off mass on a dry runway is the maximum take-off mass for the given airport/runway conditions, considering:",
      "choices": [
        "TORA and Flap position.",
        "TODA, TORA, ASDA use of available reverse thrust and flap setting.",
        "TODA, TORA, ASDA and flap setting.",
        "TODA, ASDA, use of available reverse thrust and flap setting."
      ],
      "answer": "TODA, TORA, ASDA and flap setting."
    },
    {
      "question": "The average for the aeroplane achieved by experienced and highly skilled test pilots' is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Ideal performance.",
        "Net performance.",
        "Measured performance.",
        "Gross performance."
      ],
      "answer": "Measured performance."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary purpose of the step climb is to __________ by staying as close as operationally possible to the optimum __________ as the flight progresses.",
      "choices": [
        "increase range; speed",
        "increase range; altitude",
        "reduce flight time; speed",
        "reduce flight time; altitude"
      ],
      "answer": "increase range; altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "A forward CG position __________ trim drag.",
      "choices": [
        "reduces",
        "has no effect",
        "increases",
        "sometimes reduces"
      ],
      "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which speed represents the maximum endurance speed for a propeller driven aeroplane?",
      "choices": [
        "1.32 VMP",
        "VMD",
        "1.32 VMD",
        "VMP"
      ],
      "answer": "VMP"
    },
    {
      "question": "How will the power required vary with IAS for increasing density altitude for a propeller aeroplane in the climb?",
      "choices": [
        "It is unrelated to density.",
        "Power required will remain unchanged.",
        "Power required will increase.",
        "Power required will decrease."
      ],
      "answer": "Power required will increase."
    },
    {
      "question": "The available thrust minus the drag is known as excess__________.",
      "choices": [
        "thrust",
        "power",
        "lift",
        "energy"
      ],
      "answer": "thrust"
    },
    {
      "question": "Take-off with the air conditioning packs ON __________ the thrust to weight ratio and __________ the take-off run.",
      "choices": [
        "reduces; increases.",
        "increases; reduces",
        "increases; increases.",
        "reduces; reduces."
      ],
      "answer": "reduces; increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which (valid) type of propeller maintains constant thrust over the speed range encountered during take-off?",
      "choices": [
        "A fixed pitch propeller.",
        "A constant speed propeller.",
        "A cruise propeller.",
        "A climb propeller."
      ],
      "answer": "A constant speed propeller."
    },
    {
      "question": "Study the diagram then identify the correct answer:",
      "choices": [
        "B is VMP",
        "A is VMD",
        "B is 0.76 VMD",
        "A is VMP"
      ],
      "answer": "A is VMP"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ CG position increases range because it produces less trim drag.",
      "choices": [
        "Forward",
        "Aft",
        "Neutral",
        "Variable"
      ],
      "answer": "Aft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Endurance is greatest when the __________ is lowest.",
      "choices": [
        "power available",
        "SFC",
        "SR",
        "drag"
      ],
      "answer": "SFC"
    },
    {
      "question": "The landing distance available is best described as:",
      "choices": [
        "The distance between the point of touch down on the runway and the point on the runway where the aeroplane has come to a complete stop.",
        "The length of the runway from threshold to threshold.",
        "The distance between the point on the surface of the aerodrome at which an aeroplane can begin its take-off run to the nearest point...",
        "The runway plus the clearway."
      ],
      "answer": "The length of the runway from threshold to threshold."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum rate of climb that can be maintained at the absolute ceiling is:",
      "choices": [
        "0 ft/min",
        "100 ft/min",
        "500 ft/min",
        "125 ft/min"
      ],
      "answer": "0 ft/min"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is accelerating in level flight:",
      "choices": [
        "At speeds above VMD the induced drag steadily reduces, causing even greater acceleration.",
        "Thrust must be greater than drag.",
        "The induced drag steadily reduces, causing even greater acceleration.",
        "Lift must be less than weight."
      ],
      "answer": "Thrust must be greater than drag."
    },
    {
      "question": "The performance associated with contaminated runways is to be found in:",
      "choices": [
        "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Normal Procedures.",
        "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Limitations",
        "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Performance.",
        "Part A of the Operations Manual \u2014 Performance."
      ],
      "answer": "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Performance."
    },
    {
      "question": "The minimum control speed for the take-off climb is:",
      "choices": [
        "VMU",
        "VMCG",
        "V2MIN",
        "VMCA"
      ],
      "answer": "VMCA"
    },
    {
      "question": "The accelerate-stop distance on a dry runway is the __________ of the all-engine ASD and critical-engine-out ASD (ASDN-1).",
      "choices": [
        "greater",
        "same as",
        "lesser",
        "average"
      ],
      "answer": "greater"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a Class A aircraft the net take-off flight path is subdivided into various segments. Which of the following statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "The third segment is completed at the normal flap retraction height and is flown at max continuous thrust.",
        "The first segment starts at the end of TODA where the aircraft should be at 50 ft and V2. This segment is flown at V2 whilst the landing gear is retracted.",
        "The second segment is flown at V3 up to a height of 400 ft (Flap retraction height).",
        "The final segment starts at the end of segment 3 with the aircraft in a clean configuration, at the final segment climb speed with maximum continuous power set, ending at 1500 ft or higher if there are distant obstacles to clear."
      ],
      "answer": "The final segment starts at the end of segment 3 with the aircraft in a clean configuration, at the final segment climb speed with maximum continuous power set, ending at 1500 ft or higher if there are distant obstacles to clear."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: airfield pressure altitude of 4000 ft, temperature +37\u00b0C, field length available 5500 ft, 1% downslope, 10 kt tailwind, and Flaps 15\u00b0 find the field length limiting mass.",
      "choices": [
        "47 000 kg.",
        "42 400 kg.",
        "50 000 kg.",
        "42 000 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "42 400 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Gross gradients are reduced by safety factors of __________ % for 2-engined aeroplanes; __________ % for 3-engined aeroplanes; and __________ % for 4-engined aeroplanes.",
      "choices": [
        "0.8; 1.0; 1.2.",
        "1.0; 1.1; 1.2.",
        "0.7; 08; 0.9.",
        "0.8; 0.9; 1.0."
      ],
      "answer": "0.8; 0.9; 1.0."
    },
    {
      "question": "The relationship of the reference landing speed (VREF) to the reference stalling speed ln the landing configuration (VSR0) is that VREF may not be below:",
      "choices": [
        "1.32 VSR0",
        "1.1 VSR0",
        "1.23 VSR0",
        "VSR0"
      ],
      "answer": "1.23 VSR0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Regarding take-off distances and speeds for take-off, which of the following is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "For a balanced field, the balanced V1 would result in the same ASD, one engine out TOD and one engine out TOR.",
        "At the runway limited take off mass for balanced field there is a single speed for V1.",
        "The balanced V1 is the maximum speed at which neither the one engine out TOD nor TOR are exceeded.",
        "For a balanced field, the balanced V1 would result in the same ASD, all engine TOD and all engine TOR."
      ],
      "answer": "At the runway limited take off mass for balanced field there is a single speed for V1."
    },
    {
      "question": "Take-off on a runway with standing water, with a depth of 0.5 cm, compared to a dry runway, field length limited mass will:",
      "choices": [
        "Increase, with a reduced V1.",
        "Remain the same, with a reduced V1.",
        "Decrease, with a decreased V1.",
        "Decrease, with an increased V1."
      ],
      "answer": "Increase, with a reduced V1."
    },
    {
      "question": "The landing mass for the estimated time of landing must allow a full stop landing from __________ ft above the threshold.",
      "choices": [
        "35",
        "100",
        "50",
        "25"
      ],
      "answer": "50"
    },
    {
      "question": "Reference CAP 698 Figure 4.23. Given the following Information, calculate the highest aircraft mass that allows a safe net level-off altitude. MSA: 12 000 ft Anti-ice: OFF A/C: AUTO (HIGH) ISA deviation: +15\u00b0C",
      "choices": [
        "60 750 kg",
        "58 500 kg",
        "58 250 kg",
        "62 850 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "58 250 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "VMAX TYRE, must be __________ than VLOF.",
      "choices": [
        "equal to or faster",
        "equal to or slower",
        "faster",
        "slower"
      ],
      "answer": "equal to or faster"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which combination of answers reflects the reason for using reduced thrust? 1. Save engine life. 2. Reduced fuel consumption. 3. V1 can be less than VMCG. 4. Noise abatement. 5. Allows contaminated runway operations. 6. PMC inoperative.",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 4.",
        "1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.",
        "1, 2, 3, 4",
        "1, 4."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "The procedures associated with take-off and landing on contaminated runways are to be found in:",
      "choices": [
        "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Performance.",
        "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Limitations",
        "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Normal Procedures.",
        "Part A of the Operations Manual \u2014 Normal Procedures."
      ],
      "answer": "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Normal Procedures."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a contaminated runway, the LDA must be __________% of the dry landing distance or the determined contaminated landing distance. Whichever is the greater.",
      "choices": [
        "125",
        "115",
        "135",
        "110"
      ],
      "answer": "115"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the climb limited take-off mass for an airfield at a pressure altitude of 4000 ft, with an OAT of +37\u00b0C, when using Flaps 15\u00b0.",
      "choices": [
        "52 200 kg.",
        "50 000 kg.",
        "48 200 kg.",
        "54 200 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "48 200 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the factors that affect the drift-down flight path during a descent with OEI?",
      "choices": [
        "Mass at start of drift down, Pressure Altitude, Fuel remaining.",
        "Mass difference, Pressure Altitude, OAT.",
        "Mass at start of drift down, Pressure altitude, OAT.",
        "Mass difference, Pressure Altitude, Fuel remaining."
      ],
      "answer": "Mass at start of drift down, Pressure altitude, OAT."
    },
    {
      "question": "When is the latest a pilot can take the first action to abort?",
      "choices": [
        "2 seconds before V1.",
        "When in a stable steady climb.",
        "At V1.",
        "At VR."
      ],
      "answer": "At V1."
    },
    {
      "question": "The requirements of the take-off net flight path for a Class A aeroplane assume:",
      "choices": [
        "The failure of the critical engine of a multi-engined aeroplane at VEF.",
        "The failure of any engine of a multi-engined aeroplane at VEF.",
        "The failure of any engine of a multi-engined aeroplane at VR.",
        "The failure of two engines of a three-engined or four-engined aeroplane at VEF."
      ],
      "answer": "The failure of the critical engine of a multi-engined aeroplane at VEF."
    },
    {
      "question": "The minimum dynamic hydroplaning speed for a rotating tyre is 9\u221a P. For a locked-up tyre it is 7.7 \u221a P. The higher value is most likely to be the most limiting __________. The lower value may be limiting __________.",
      "choices": [
        "on take-off; during landing before wheel spin-up.",
        "on take-off; on take-off.",
        "during an RTO; during an RTO.",
        "during an RTO; on take-off."
      ],
      "answer": "on take-off; during landing before wheel spin-up."
    },
    {
      "question": "Hot/high conditions __________ the maximum permissible landing mass.",
      "choices": [
        "has no effect.",
        "increase.",
        "reduce.",
        "sometimes increase"
      ],
      "answer": "reduce."
    },
    {
      "question": "V2MIN is more likely to be limited by __________ at cold, low altitude airports and by __________ at hot, high altitude airports.",
      "choices": [
        "VMC; VMC",
        "VMC; VSR",
        "VSR; VMC",
        "VSR; VSR"
      ],
      "answer": "VMC; VSR"
    },
    {
      "question": "The TODR for a wet runway is the __________ of TODdry and TODN-1wet.",
      "choices": [
        "lesser",
        "same as",
        "greater",
        "average"
      ],
      "answer": "greater"
    },
    {
      "question": "For jet-propelled aeroplanes, the maximum endurance speed corresponds with the:",
      "choices": [
        "Maximum rate of climb speed.",
        "Mach maximum-range.",
        "Mach long-range.",
        "Maximum climb-gradient speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum climb-gradient speed."
    },
    {
      "question": "A tailwind __________ the aeroplane\u2019s ground speed. This increases the LDR.",
      "choices": [
        "has no effect on.",
        "increases.",
        "decreases",
        "sometimes decreases"
      ],
      "answer": "increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.23. Given: Aircraft mass: 52 000 kg Temperature: ISA +20\u00b0C Engine Anti-Ice: ON Air Conditioning (AC): OFF Using the data above determine the net level off altitude.",
      "choices": [
        "17 000 ft",
        "17 400 ft",
        "14 800 ft",
        "15 400 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "15 400 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is true when calculating take-off data for a Class A aeroplane and if the reverse thrust is inoperative?",
      "choices": [
        "The ASDA will decrease in case of wet and dry runways.",
        "The ASD will increase if the runway is wet.",
        "The CLTOM will decrease.",
        "The TOD will increase."
      ],
      "answer": "The ASD will increase if the runway is wet."
    },
    {
      "question": "Increased mass __________ the landing distance.",
      "choices": [
        "increases.",
        "has no effect on.",
        "decreases",
        "sometimes decreases"
      ],
      "answer": "increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ hydroplaning can result from an excessive build-up of rubber on the runway surface. The tyres hydroplane on the partially melted rubber lying on the runway surface.",
      "choices": [
        "Reverted Rubber",
        "Contaminated",
        "Viscous",
        "Dynamic"
      ],
      "answer": "Viscous"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.7. Given the following information, what is the Maximum Take-Off Mass (MTOM) eventually limited by VMBE for the MRJT aeroplane? Airfield Elevation: 1998 ft Slope: 0.2% upslope QNH: 1013.25 hPa OAT: 38\u00b0C V1: 145 kt Tailwind: 5 kt",
      "choices": [
        "Approximately 68 000 kg.",
        "Significantly more than 68 000 kg.",
        "We do not have enough information to determine this.",
        "Below 68 000 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "Approximately 68 000 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the greatest mass that an MRJT can be, at the most critical point on the flight for obstacle clearance, if the OAT is ISA, with no icing conditions forecast and the highest obstacle within 5 nm either side of the planned track to the alternate aerodrome is 14 000 ft?",
      "choices": [
        "49 800 kg.",
        "60 000 kg.",
        "56 200 kg.",
        "58 200 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "58 200 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "When the aircraft descends, the margin between the high and low speed buffet progressively __________.",
      "choices": [
        "decreases.",
        "remains constant.",
        "increases.",
        "fluctuates."
      ],
      "answer": "increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "Assume a normal approach and landing with a class A airplane Which of the following values shows the corresponding screen height?",
      "choices": [
        "35 ft",
        "50 ft",
        "100 ft",
        "60 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "50 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the field-length-limited take-off mass and V1 were calculated using balanced field-lengths, the use of any additional clearway in the calculation would cause:",
      "choices": [
        "an increased obstacle-limited take-off mass and an increased V1.",
        "an increased field-length-limited take-off mass and a reduced V1.",
        "an increased field-length-limited take-off mass and an increased V1.",
        "an increased obstacle-limited take-off mass with the same V1."
      ],
      "answer": "an increased field-length-limited take-off mass and a reduced V1."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.28. Given: Airport PA: 1800 ft Runway: dry Field length: 1600 m Headwind: 20 kt Flaps: 30\u00b0 Automatic spoilers and anti-skid: operative Find the field length limit mass:",
      "choices": [
        "47 000 kg",
        "58 000 kg",
        "52 000 kg",
        "60 000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "58 000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the factor for Class A aeroplanes, when determining the take-off distance and when considering a take-off from a dry runway with all engines operating?",
      "choices": [
        "1.15",
        "1",
        "1.35",
        "0.7"
      ],
      "answer": "1.15"
    },
    {
      "question": "Reference CAP 698 Figure 4.4. Given the following: Runway 02, TORA 6400 ft, 1 % upslope, obstacle after departure, maximum 5\u00b0 flaps allowed. Runway 20, TORA 6400 ft, 1 % downslope, departure over the sea, maximum 15\u00b0 flaps allowed. Wind: 020\u00b0 /5 kt. The actual TOM is 58 800 kg, which is 600 kg beyond the limit for runway 02. Which of the following options is the best choice, from both a safety and commercial standpoint?",
      "choices": [
        "Take-off on RWY 20 despite tailwind, as useful load could be increased by 600 kg.",
        "Offload 600 kg of passengers or bags and take-off on RWY 02.",
        "Defuel by 600 kg and take-off on RWY 02.",
        "Take-off on RWY 20, after reducing the TOM."
      ],
      "answer": "Take-off on RWY 20 despite tailwind, as useful load could be increased by 600 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "The speed at which an engine fails, in time to be recognised by V1 is known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "VEF",
        "V2",
        "V1",
        "VE"
      ],
      "answer": "VEF"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 698 figure 4.31 What is the minimum brake cooling time required after a rejected take off, given the following: aircraft mass 55 tons; take-off rejected (brakes-on) at 135 kt; aerodrome pressure altitude 1000 ft; OAT +35\u00baC.",
      "choices": [
        "31 min.",
        "88 min.",
        "29 min.",
        "32 min."
      ],
      "answer": "88 min."
    },
    {
      "question": "Where are the procedures associated with take-off and landing on contaminated runways found?",
      "choices": [
        "Part B of the Operations Manual",
        "Part A of the Operations Manual",
        "Part C of the Operations Manual",
        "Part D of the Operations Manual"
      ],
      "answer": "Part B of the Operations Manual"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 698 figure 4.28. Determine the minimum LDA for the following conditions: aircraft mass 55 000 kg; aerodrome pressure altitude 2000 ft; wet runway; Flap 40; wind component +20 kt; anti-skid inoperative, manual spoilers.",
      "choices": [
        "8400 ft.",
        "5350 ft.",
        "9050 ft.",
        "9700 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "8400 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Balanced V1 is selected:",
      "choices": [
        "For a runway length limited take-off with a stopway to give the highest-mass.",
        "If the accelerate-stop distance is equal to the one engine out take-off distance.",
        "If it is equal to V2.",
        "For a runway length limited take-off with a clearway to give the highest mass."
      ],
      "answer": "If the accelerate-stop distance is equal to the one engine out take-off distance."
    },
    {
      "question": "The screen height for take-off from a wet runway is __________ ft.",
      "choices": [
        "50",
        "15",
        "35",
        "25"
      ],
      "answer": "15"
    },
    {
      "question": "Field length is balanced when:",
      "choices": [
        "All engine acceleration to V1 and braking distance for rejected take-off are equal.",
        "Calculated V2 is less than 110% VMCA and V1.",
        "One engine acceleration from V1 to VLOF plus flare distance between VLOF and 35 feet are equal.",
        "Take-off distance available equals accelerate stop distance available."
      ],
      "answer": "Take-off distance available equals accelerate stop distance available."
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot is planning a landing where the landing mass is greater then the maximum quick turnaround mass. Select the correct statement that the pilot should follow:",
      "choices": [
        "He should increase the VREF to avoid a tailstrike on flare.",
        "He must wait a certain amount of time before commencing another take-off.",
        "The autobrakes should not be selected.",
        "He must not use the rapid exit taxiway."
      ],
      "answer": "He must wait a certain amount of time before commencing another take-off."
    },
    {
      "question": "The RLTOM for flap 5\u00b0, 10\u00b0 and 15\u00b0 are 122 000 kg, 125 000 kg and 128 000 kg respectively. The CLTOM for Flap 5\u00b0, 10\u00b0 and 15\u00b0 are 132 000 kg, 130 000 kg and 128 000 kg respectively. Given a 10 kt tailwind (reduce by 600 kg per kt), what is the maximum take-off mass and at which flap setting?",
      "choices": [
        "131 000 kg/ Flap 10",
        "122 000 kg/ Flap 15",
        "128 000 kg/ Flap 15",
        "122 000 kg/ Flap 5"
      ],
      "answer": "122 000 kg/ Flap 15"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ the amount of take-off flap increases RLTOM and __________ the climb (and obstacle) limited masses.",
      "choices": [
        "reducing; reduces",
        "reducing; increases",
        "increasing; reduces",
        "increasing; increases"
      ],
      "answer": "increasing; reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "Occasional movements by aircraft with an ACN of 50 should not adversely affect the pavement if the reported PCN is at least:",
      "choices": [
        "60 / R / A / W / U",
        "45 / R /A/ W / U",
        "47 / F /A/ W / U",
        "65 / R / A / W / U"
      ],
      "answer": "47 / F /A/ W / U"
    },
    {
      "question": "Turbo-propeller aeroplanes, landing on a dry runway must plan to land within __________% of the LDA.",
      "choices": [
        "90",
        "60",
        "50",
        "70"
      ],
      "answer": "70"
    },
    {
      "question": "If your aeroplane can\u2019t climb with one engine inoperative, then your minimum obstacle clearance is __________ ft within 5 nm of your intended track (provided you have sufficient navigation accuracy).",
      "choices": [
        "1000",
        "150",
        "2000",
        "2500"
      ],
      "answer": "2000"
    },
    {
      "question": "VR is __________ by air density.",
      "choices": [
        "not affected",
        "indirectly affected",
        "directly affected",
        "only affected at high altitudes"
      ],
      "answer": "indirectly affected"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Class A take-off path extends from a standing start to a point in the take-off at which the aeroplane is__________ ft above the take-off surface.",
      "choices": [
        "1500",
        "50",
        "1000",
        "35"
      ],
      "answer": "1500"
    },
    {
      "question": "At what TOM would 225 mph tyres become limiting, at Flaps 15\u00b0, at an airfield pressure altitude of 4000 ft, an OAT of +37\u00b0C and 10 kt tailwind component?",
      "choices": [
        "73 600 kg.",
        "80 200 kg.",
        "70 450 kg.",
        "79 550 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "73 600 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the event of an engine failure take off, what is the purpose of the 2 second interval rule?",
      "choices": [
        "It is considered in the all engines take-off only.",
        "To recognise and react to the engine failure by V1.",
        "Permits the recognition of the engine failure.",
        "The pilot must apply the brakes one second before V1 to stop within the ASDA."
      ],
      "answer": "To recognise and react to the engine failure by V1."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.30. Given: Aerodrome Pressure altitude: 3000 ft Outside Air Temperature (OAT): +30\u00b0F Runway slope: 1.5% down Wind: 10 kt head Flaps: 40\u00b0 Using the data above, determine the Maximum Quick Turnaround Mass.",
      "choices": [
        "55 850 kg",
        "58 125 kg",
        "57 000 kg",
        "56 375 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "56 375 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not used by aircraft manufacturers to establish dry landing distances?",
      "choices": [
        "Reverse thrust",
        "Autobrakes",
        "Anti-skid",
        "Ground spoilers"
      ],
      "answer": "Reverse thrust"
    },
    {
      "question": "Good, medium to good, medium to poor' or 'poor' are descriptions used for __________ surface friction.",
      "choices": [
        "estimated",
        "measured",
        "calculated",
        "observed"
      ],
      "answer": "estimated"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.5. Consider the take-off performance for the twin jet aeroplane climb limit chart. Why has the wind been omitted from the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "There is a built-in safety measure.",
        "The effect of the wind must be taken from another chart.",
        "The climb limit performances are taken relative to the air.",
        "There is no effect of the wind on the climb angle relative to the ground."
      ],
      "answer": "The climb limit performances are taken relative to the air."
    },
    {
      "question": "The speed V2 is defined for jet aeroplanes as:",
      "choices": [
        "Lift off speed.",
        "Take-off decision speed.",
        "Take-off climb speed or speed at 35 ft.",
        "Critical engine failure speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Take-off climb speed or speed at 35 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "The increased V2 technique may be used when the runway length limiting mass __________ the climb or the obstacle limiting mass and the climb or obstacle mass is limiting the take-off mass.",
      "choices": [
        "is the same as",
        "exceeds",
        "is less than",
        "is not related to"
      ],
      "answer": "exceeds"
    },
    {
      "question": "The __________ is the lowest of the performance limited and structurally limited take-off masses.",
      "choices": [
        "RTOM",
        "PLTOM",
        "MTOM",
        "MLM"
      ],
      "answer": "RTOM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Your take-off mass is most likely to be climb-limited at an airport with a __________ density altitude.",
      "choices": [
        "high",
        "low",
        "standard",
        "zero"
      ],
      "answer": "high"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 698 Section 4. What are the V speeds for the MRJT for a TOM of 50 000 kg, Flaps 5\u00b0, at a 4000 ft pressure altitude and OAT of +37\u00b0C, 15 kt tailwind, no runway slope?",
      "choices": [
        "V1 130 kt VR 132 kt V2 142 kt.",
        "V1 126 kt VR 128 kt V2 138 kt.",
        "V1 132 kt VR 134 kt V2 141 kt.",
        "V1 128 kt VR 134 kt V2 141 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "V1 128 kt VR 134 kt V2 141 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "Select from the following list of conditions those that must prevail in the second segment of the take-off net flight path for a Class A aeroplane: ...",
      "choices": [
        "2, 3, 6 , 9.",
        "1, 4, 6, 9.",
        "1, 5, 8, 10.",
        "1, 4, 5, 10."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 4, 6, 9."
    },
    {
      "question": "A runway is deemed to be contaminated when more than __________% of the runway surface area is covered by greater than __________ mm of water or its equivalent depth in slush or loose snow, or compacted snow or ice.",
      "choices": [
        "35; 3",
        "25; 3",
        "50; 3",
        "25; 5"
      ],
      "answer": "25; 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Reference 698 CAP Figure 4. 7. Determine the brake release weight, given: V1: 149 kts Pressure altitude: 1487 ft OAT: +19\u00b0C Runway Slope: 0.5 % UP Wind: 10 kt headwind",
      "choices": [
        "The same as the MSTOM 62 800 kg.",
        "Cannot be determined.",
        "V1 can't be higher than VMBE.",
        "Excess of 68 000 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "Excess of 68 000 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "If your aeroplane can achieve a positive net gradient with one engine inoperative, then your minimum obstacle clearance is __________ ft within 5 nm of your intended track (provided you have sufficient navigation accuracy).",
      "choices": [
        "2000",
        "1000",
        "150",
        "500"
      ],
      "answer": "1000"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 698 figure 4.25. An aircraft with a mass of 55 tons descends from FL 340 having suffered an engine failure. There is a 30 kt tailwind. Anti-ice is not required. The OAT is ISA -15\u00baC. What is the horizontal distance covered, the time taken and the fuel burned, to descend to 20 000 ft ? ...",
      "choices": [
        "148 nm; 19 min; 750 kg",
        "150 nm; 20 min; 400 kg",
        "144 nm; 24 min; 750 kg",
        "120 nm; 25 min; 500 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "144 nm; 24 min; 750 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "V1WET is __________ than V1 because of the reduced ability to __________ on the runway.",
      "choices": [
        "lower; decelerate",
        "higher; accelerate",
        "lower; accelerate",
        "higher; decelerate"
      ],
      "answer": "lower; decelerate"
    },
    {
      "question": "If wind limitations apply in case of contaminated runways, these limitations are to be found in:",
      "choices": [
        "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Limitations.",
        "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Normal Procedures.",
        "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Performance.",
        "Part A of the Operations Manual."
      ],
      "answer": "Part B of the Operations Manual \u2014 Limitations."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane receives a late descent clearance from ATC due to opposite traffic, with all factors being equal and constant. Choose the correct statement. The pilot may:",
      "choices": [
        "Use speed brakes and maintain planned descent speed, however, the aeroplane will have a higher energy state when back on the planned profile.",
        "increase drag by increasing the airspeed and therefore increasing the descent angle, reducing the energy state of the aeroplane due to extra drag.",
        "Slow down and use speed brakes to increase the drag and increase the descent angle since the speed brakes are more effective at lower airspeed.",
        "increase the airspeed to regain the vertical profile, however, the aeroplane will have a higher energy state when back on the planned profile."
      ],
      "answer": "increase the airspeed to regain the vertical profile, however, the aeroplane will have a higher energy state when back on the planned profile."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following are valid consequences of an incorrectly calculated V1?",
      "choices": [
        "An incorrectly calculated V1 which is too high may mean that there is insufficient TODA to continue, but sufficient ASDA for a rejected take-off.",
        "An incorrectly calculated V1 which is too high should give you sufficient TODA to continue but there may be insufficient ASDA for a rejected take-off.",
        "An incorrectly calculated V1 which is too low should give you sufficient TODA to continue, and sufficient ASDA for a rejected take-off but a reduced RTOM.",
        "An incorrectly calculated V1 which is too low may mean that there is insufficient ASDA to continue, but sufficient TODA for a rejected take-off."
      ],
      "answer": "An incorrectly calculated V1 which is too high should give you sufficient TODA to continue but there may be insufficient ASDA for a rejected take-off."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to the attached image. Given: Runway: 23L Runway condition: wet Wind: 140\u00b0 / 14 kt OAT: 10\u00b0C QNH: 1008 hPa Engine anti-ice: ON Packs: OFF Take-off position: VB Using the chart provided, determine the RTOM given the above conditions without interpolation...",
      "choices": [
        "77 110 kg",
        "78 810 kg",
        "78 110 kg",
        "77 810 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "77 110 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the landing roll, when can the pilot apply the brakes? 1) When both main gears touch the ground ... 4) When all wheels are on the ground.",
      "choices": [
        "1 and 2.",
        "1, 3 and 4.",
        "1, 2 and 4.",
        "3 and 4."
      ],
      "answer": "3 and 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.28. Given: Airport PA: 1800 ft Runway: dry Field length: 1600 m Headwind: 20 kt Flaps: 30\u00b0_Automatic spoilers and anti-skid: operative Find the field length limit mass:",
      "choices": [
        "47 000 kg",
        "52 000 kg",
        "60 000 kg",
        "58 000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "58 000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a Class A aeroplane what is the all engines take-off distance safety factor?",
      "choices": [
        "1.3",
        "1",
        "1.15",
        "1.5"
      ],
      "answer": "1.15"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a dry runway the accelerate stop distance is increased by:",
      "choices": [
        "By headwind.",
        "An uphill slope.",
        "Low outside air temperature.",
        "By a lower take-off mass because the aeroplane accelerates faster to V1."
      ],
      "answer": "An uphill slope."
    },
    {
      "question": "The limiting mass for the landing climb is the maximum mass at which a gradient of __________% can be achieved.",
      "choices": [
        "2.8",
        "1",
        "3.2",
        "5"
      ],
      "answer": "3.2"
    },
    {
      "question": "The minimum speed during the take-off, following a failure of the critical engine at VEF, at which the pilot can continue the take-off and achieve the required height above the take-off surface within the take-off distance. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "VR",
        "V3",
        "V1",
        "V2"
      ],
      "answer": "V1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Reference CAP 698 Figure 4.7. Planned take-off mass is 64 000 kg Pressure altitude 4000 ft OAT +10\u00b0C. V1 - 151, 155, 161. Runway slope is -1% and tailwind 5 kt. What is the maximum permitted take-off mass?",
      "choices": [
        "63 400 kg",
        "64 000 kg",
        "63 700 kg",
        "64 900 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "63 400 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which procedure is likely to involve V1 being reduced?",
      "choices": [
        "When ASDA > TODA.",
        "Take-off with inoperative anti-skid.",
        "Reduced thrust take-off.",
        "Increased V2 technique."
      ],
      "answer": "Take-off with inoperative anti-skid."
    },
    {
      "question": "The take-off flight path:",
      "choices": [
        "Begins at the end of the runway.",
        "Begins at 35 ft above the take-off surface at the end of the take-off distance.",
        "Begins at lift-off.",
        "Begins at the start of the take-off roll."
      ],
      "answer": "Begins at 35 ft above the take-off surface at the end of the take-off distance."
    },
    {
      "question": "The optimum speed during drift-down is VMD or LRC depending on the circumstances. The optimum drift-down speed __________ with a reduction in the aeroplane's mass.",
      "choices": [
        "reduces.",
        "increases.",
        "remains constant.",
        "is not a factor."
      ],
      "answer": "reduces."
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight at altitudes higher or lower than the optimum:",
      "choices": [
        "Has no effect on fuel flow.",
        "Invariably results in reduced maximum range.",
        "May be beneficial if there is a more favourable wind at that altitude.",
        "May be beneficial if there is a more favourable temperature at that altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "May be beneficial if there is a more favourable wind at that altitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "The critical engine is the engine that, upon failing, results in thrust from the remaining engine(s) producing the __________ yawing moment.",
      "choices": [
        "greatest",
        "least",
        "average",
        "zero"
      ],
      "answer": "greatest"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which factors might cause V2 to be limited by VMCA? 1) large flap angles ... 6) low aircraft weights.",
      "choices": [
        "2, 3, 5.",
        "2, 4, 6.",
        "1, 3, 5.",
        "1, 3, 6."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 3, 6."
    },
    {
      "question": "An increasing headwind during the descent __________ your descent profile. To descend at your intended rate, you need to __________ thrust.",
      "choices": [
        "shallows; reduce.",
        "steepens; add.",
        "shallows; add.",
        "steepens; reduce."
      ],
      "answer": "steepens; add."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a Class A aircraft landing on a wet runway by how much must the landing distance be increased? Answer as a %.",
      "choices": [
        "0.15",
        "0.25",
        "0.05",
        "0.1"
      ],
      "answer": "0.15"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the flap setting is changed from 10\u00b0 to 20\u00b0, V2MIN will:",
      "choices": [
        "Increase.",
        "Remain the same.",
        "Decrease if not limited by VMCA.",
        "Increase or decrease depending on weight."
      ],
      "answer": "Decrease if not limited by VMCA."
    },
    {
      "question": "Extending flaps or reducing aircraft mass __________ the stall reference speed.",
      "choices": [
        "decreases",
        "has no effect",
        "increases",
        "doubles"
      ],
      "answer": "decreases"
    },
    {
      "question": "If you rotate too early:",
      "choices": [
        "The take-off distance reduces but the take-off run increases.",
        "The take-off run and take-off distance increases.",
        "The take-off run reduces but the take-off distance increases.",
        "The take-off run and take-off distance decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "The take-off run and take-off distance increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "Study the table. What is the maximum permissible take-off mass, and at what flap setting?",
      "choices": [
        "59 200 kg at Flap 10.",
        "57 000 kg at Flap 15.",
        "60 100 kg at Flap 5.",
        "55 500 kg at Flap 5."
      ],
      "answer": "57 000 kg at Flap 15."
    },
    {
      "question": "The screen height, for a class A aircraft, for take-off from a dry runway is __________ ft.",
      "choices": [
        "50",
        "15",
        "35",
        "100"
      ],
      "answer": "35"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the runway is forecast to be wet at the estimated time of arrival, the landing distance must be increased by __________% unless a lower factor is specified in the Aircraft Flight Manual.",
      "choices": [
        "10",
        "15",
        "20",
        "25"
      ],
      "answer": "15"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.31. Using the environmental data below and the attached figure, calculate the required brake cooling period for the rejected take-off. ... Abort speed: 100 kt (Max braking and reverse thrust used).",
      "choices": [
        "40 minutes",
        "55 minutes",
        "20 minutes",
        "30 minutes"
      ],
      "answer": "55 minutes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Turbojet aeroplanes, landing on a dry runway must plan to land within __________% of the LDA.",
      "choices": [
        "60",
        "50",
        "90",
        "70"
      ],
      "answer": "60"
    },
    {
      "question": "The minimum dynamic hydroplaning speed for a rotating tyre is __________ \u221a P. For a locked-up tyre it is __________ \u221a P.",
      "choices": [
        "9.7; 7",
        "9; 7",
        "9.7; 7.7",
        "9; 7.7"
      ],
      "answer": "9; 7.7"
    },
    {
      "question": "The aeroplane must be able to have some climb performance (a positive gradient) by the time it reaches __________ ft above the intended landing aerodrome.",
      "choices": [
        "500",
        "1000",
        "1500",
        "2000"
      ],
      "answer": "1500"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are flying to a destination with limited fuel services and a short runway. To minimise fuel uplift requirements at the destination you plan to land with the maximum amount of fuel possible. What factor might limit your landing mass?",
      "choices": [
        "A runway downslope as it leads to a reduced landing distance.",
        "High OAT as it leads to a higher groundspeed.",
        "A runway upslope as it increases landing distance.",
        "Low OAT as it leads to a lower groundspeed."
      ],
      "answer": "High OAT as it leads to a higher groundspeed."
    },
    {
      "question": "The engine thrust and therefore the yawing moment are __________ when the air is dense. Consequently, VMC __________ with decreasing air density.",
      "choices": [
        "least; decreases",
        "greatest; increases",
        "greatest; decreases",
        "least; increases"
      ],
      "answer": "greatest; decreases"
    },
    {
      "question": "The NTOFP, determined from the data provided in the AFM, must clear all relevant obstacles by a vertical distance of 35 ft and by a horizontal distance of at least __________ m (for a wingspan exceeding 60 m) plus __________ x D",
      "choices": [
        "90; 0.125.",
        "90; 1.25",
        "60; 12.5",
        "60; 0.125."
      ],
      "answer": "90; 0.125."
    },
    {
      "question": "A measured surface friction value of __________ equates to 'good'. Any value less than __________ equates to 'poor'.",
      "choices": [
        "0.4; 0.5",
        "0.5; 0.25",
        "0.5; 0.5",
        "0.4; 0.25"
      ],
      "answer": "0.4; 0.25"
    },
    {
      "question": "When an aircraft manufacturer applies for approval for an aircraft type, it must demonstrate the type\u2019s landing performance over the course of __________ landings in standard temperatures, at each weight, altitude and wind within the operational limits of the aeroplane.",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "6",
        "10",
        "8"
      ],
      "answer": "6"
    },
    {
      "question": "The purpose of V1 WET is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Increase the safety margins when the runway is wet.",
        "Increase obstacle clearance in poor weather conditions.",
        "Prevent an excessively restricted RLTOM.",
        "Compel the operator to reduce the take-off mass."
      ],
      "answer": "Prevent an excessively restricted RLTOM."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ hydroplaning occurs when the contamination under the tyres is not displaced fast enough to allow the tyre to make contact with the runway surface over its total footprint area.",
      "choices": [
        "Dynamic",
        "Contaminated",
        "Reverted Rubber",
        "Viscous"
      ],
      "answer": "Dynamic"
    },
    {
      "question": "In high air density conditions, VR is limited by __________.",
      "choices": [
        "V1",
        "VLOF",
        "VMC",
        "VEFD"
      ],
      "answer": "VMC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 698 figure 4.28. Determine the runway length limiting landing mass at an aerodrome with a pressure altitude of 2000 ft, with 7250 ft runway length available, wind calm, runway wet and flaps 40\u00b0, anti-skid operative.",
      "choices": [
        "53 600 kg.",
        "63 600 kg.",
        "61 500 kg.",
        "67 000 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "63 600 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the event of engine failure below V1, the first action to be taken by the pilot in order to decelerate the aeroplane is to:",
      "choices": [
        "Reverse engine thrust.",
        "Reduce the engine thrust.",
        "Apply wheel brakes.",
        "Deploy airbrakes or spoilers."
      ],
      "answer": "Reduce the engine thrust."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ hydroplaning occurs when a wheel locks on a damp or wet runway. The superheated tyre generates high-pressure steam. This causes the surface rubber to revert to its uncured state, resulting in a hot fluid layer building up between the tyre and the runway surface.",
      "choices": [
        "Reverted Rubber",
        "Dynamic",
        "Viscous",
        "Contaminated"
      ],
      "answer": "Reverted Rubber"
    },
    {
      "question": "During driftdown, your rate of descent increases if you fly at any speed __________ the best L/D ratio.",
      "choices": [
        "below but not above",
        "above but not below",
        "above or below",
        "neither above nor below"
      ],
      "answer": "above or below"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.6. Given: Pressure Altitude: 85 ft OAT: +8\u00b0C Tailwind Component: 8 kt PMC: OFF Flaps: 5\u00b0 Find the FLAPS TYRE SPEED LIMIT MASS for your aircraft which is fitted with 225 mph tyres...",
      "choices": [
        "It is not possible to determine from the information provided.",
        "Below 84 000 kg.",
        "It is out of the aircraft structural MTOM limits.",
        "84 000 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "It is out of the aircraft structural MTOM limits."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum CAS at which the brakes can absorb all the energy from a take-off rejected at V1 is the v-speed known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "V1Max",
        "VMBE",
        "VTYRE",
        "V2"
      ],
      "answer": "VMBE"
    },
    {
      "question": "The commercial operations safety factor is __________% for the all-engine take-off distance requirement.",
      "choices": [
        "70",
        "115",
        "130",
        "100"
      ],
      "answer": "115"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following conditions, find VMBE. Pressure altitude 4000 ft. OAT +37\u00b0C, brake release mass 68 tons, 10 kt headwind, 1% downslope.",
      "choices": [
        "152 kt",
        "149 kt",
        "151 kt",
        "153 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "149 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the event of a rejected take-off in Class A, when is it assumed that the first action should be taken to stop the aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "When the engine fails.",
        "At V1.",
        "2 secs before V1.",
        "2 secs after V1."
      ],
      "answer": "At V1."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.31. Using the environmental data below and the attached figure, calculate whether a brake cooling period is required following a rejected take-off: Takeoff mass: 61 300 kg Elevation: 2000 ft OAT: +34\u00b0C Wind: calm Abort speed: 80 kt",
      "choices": [
        "Cooling is required and it will require approximately 45 min to achieve this.",
        "Cooling is required and it will require approximately 30 min to achieve this.",
        "Cooling is not required, reverse thrust is considered to have been used for rejected takeoff purposes.",
        "Cooling is required, it will require approximately 25 min to achieve this."
      ],
      "answer": "Cooling is required and it will require approximately 45 min to achieve this."
    },
    {
      "question": "Using the BOB chart, determine the Mach number for the onset of high speed buffet aircraft with a mass of 60 tons, at FL 330, with CG at 10% MAC at 1.3 g. Note: 1 Imperial ton is approximately 1000 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "0.75 M",
        "0.76 M",
        "0.74 M",
        "0.68 M"
      ],
      "answer": "0.75 M"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.28. What is the minimum field length required for the worst wind situation, landing a twin jet aeroplane with the anti-skid inoperative? Given: Elevation: 2000 ft QNH: 1013 hPa Landing Mass: 50 000 kg Flaps: as required for minimum landing distance Runway condition: dry Maximum allowable tailwind: 15 kts Maximum allowable headwind: 50 kts",
      "choices": [
        "2600 m",
        "2700 m",
        "2900 m",
        "3100 m"
      ],
      "answer": "3100 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to the RTOM table provided. What are the V speeds and RTOM for Runway 23L at airport 'VB', using the T/O 1 configuration. QNH 1003, OAT +37\u00b0C, 10 kt tailwind, no runway slope, Packs on?",
      "choices": [
        "72 170 kg, V1 is 137 kt, VR is 138 kt, V2 is 143 kt.",
        "73 100 kg, V1 is 137 kt, VR is 138 kt, V2 is 143 kt.",
        "72 170 kg, V1 is 138 kt, VR is 138 kt, V2 is 142 kt.",
        "72 170 kg, V1 is 139 kt, VR is 139 kt, V2 is 143 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "72 170 kg, V1 is 137 kt, VR is 138 kt, V2 is 143 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "What classification is given to a multi-engine turbo-jet aircraft with less than 9 passenger seats and a weight less than 5700 kg?",
      "choices": [
        "Class A",
        "Class B",
        "Class C",
        "Unclassified."
      ],
      "answer": "Class A"
    },
    {
      "question": "A downslope __________ the landing distance.",
      "choices": [
        "decreases",
        "increases.",
        "has no effect on.",
        "first increases, then decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.4. For a twin engine turbojet aeroplane two take-off flap settings (5\u00b0 and 15\u00b0) are certified. Using the attached chart, what is the maximum allowed Take-off Mass, given the following conditions: Airport PA: 7000 ft OAT: -10\u00b0C Field length available: 2400 m Slope: Level Wind: Calm PMC: ON A/C: AUTO",
      "choices": [
        "70 000 kg",
        "55 000 kg",
        "52 000 kg",
        "56 000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "56 000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the advantage of balancing V1, even in the event of a climb limited take-off?",
      "choices": [
        "The climb limited Take-off Mass is the highest.",
        "The accelerate stop distance required is the shortest.",
        "The safety margin with respect to the runway length is greatest.",
        "The take-off distance required with one engine out at V1 is the shortest."
      ],
      "answer": "The safety margin with respect to the runway length is greatest."
    },
    {
      "question": "V2 must be achieved no later than the screen height of __________ ft.",
      "choices": [
        "75",
        "35",
        "100",
        "50"
      ],
      "answer": "35"
    },
    {
      "question": "The reduction to be applied to the gross gradient (take-off climb) to obtain the net gradient for a twin-engined Class A aeroplane is:",
      "choices": [
        "0.009",
        "0.01",
        "0.007",
        "0.008"
      ],
      "answer": "0.008"
    },
    {
      "question": "In accordance to EASA CS-25 which of the following listed speeds are used for determination of V2 MIN?",
      "choices": [
        "V1, VR.",
        "VSR, VMCA.",
        "VSO, VMCA.",
        "VMCG, V2."
      ],
      "answer": "VSR, VMCA."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements, concerning the obstacle limited Take-off Mass for Performance Class A aeroplane, is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "It should be determined on the basis of a 35 ft obstacle clearance with respect to the net take-off flight path.",
        "It should not be corrected for 30\u00b0 bank turns in the take-off path.",
        "It should be calculated in such a way that there is a margin of 50 ft with respect to the net take-off flight path.",
        "It is not affected by wind conditions."
      ],
      "answer": "It should be determined on the basis of a 35 ft obstacle clearance with respect to the net take-off flight path."
    },
    {
      "question": "In low air density conditions VR may be limited by __________.",
      "choices": [
        "VEF",
        "VMU",
        "VFR",
        "VMV"
      ],
      "answer": "VMU"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 698 figure 4.25. An aircraft with a mass of 55 tons descends from FL 340 having suffered an engine failure. There is a 30 kt tailwind. Anti-ice is not required. The OAT is ISA -15\u00baC. What is the horizontal distance covered, the time taken and the fuel burned, to descend to 20 000 ft ? Note: 1 Imperial ton is approximately 1000 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "120 nm; 25 min; 500 kg",
        "144 nm; 24 min; 750 kg",
        "150 nm; 20 min; 400 kg",
        "148 nm; 19 min; 750 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "144 nm; 24 min; 750 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The take-off distance required on a dry runway is the greater of TODN-1dry and __________ x TODN dry.",
      "choices": [
        "1.1",
        "1.15",
        "1.3",
        "1.25"
      ],
      "answer": "1.15"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 4.28. What is the field length limiting mass for the below conditions? Flaps: 15\u00b0 Wind: 20 kt headwind Runway condition: dry Pressure altitude: 3000 ft Field length available: 5505 ft Anti-Skid: operative.",
      "choices": [
        "51 000 kg",
        "41 000 kg",
        "53 000 kg",
        "48 000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "51 000 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum CAS at which the brakes can absorb all the energy from a take-off rejected at V1 is the v-speed known as VMBE. It must be __________.",
      "choices": [
        "greater than V1",
        "less than V1",
        "equal to or greater than V1",
        "equal to V1"
      ],
      "answer": "equal to or greater than V1"
    },
    {
      "question": "During your approach, ATC asks you to perform a circle-to-land manoeuvre due to an unexpectedly strong tailwind. After the downwind leg, you make the last turn to the final approach with a strong headwind. ln comparison to an approach in still air, you should (1) ____ thrust to stay on the correct glide path, as the headwind will cause the aircraft's glide angle to (2) ____",
      "choices": [
        "(1) increase; (2) increase .",
        "(1) decrease; (2) increase.",
        "(1) increase; (2) decrease.",
        "(1) decrease; (2) decrease."
      ],
      "answer": "(1) increase; (2) increase ."
    },
    {
      "question": "The slope of the airborne part of the Class A take-off path must be __________ at each point.",
      "choices": [
        "positive",
        "not less than horizontal",
        "negative",
        "dependent on aircraft type"
      ],
      "answer": "positive"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 698 figure 4.31 What is the minimum brake cooling time after landing, given the following: landing mass 45 tons; brakes-on speed 130 kt; OAT +40\u00baC; MSL: wind calm; manual braking and no reverse thrust.",
      "choices": [
        "62 min.",
        "32 min.",
        "19 min.",
        "58 min."
      ],
      "answer": "62 min."
    },
    {
      "question": "The optimum altitude __________ as aircraft mass reduces.",
      "choices": [
        "reduces.",
        "increases.",
        "remains constant.",
        "is not a factor."
      ],
      "answer": "increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "A runway is covered over the total length with 5 mm depth of wet ice. ln terms of runway contamination, \"wet ice\" is:",
      "choices": [
        "ice with water on top of it or ice that is melting.",
        "water that has frozen or compacted snow that has transitioned into ice in cold and dry conditions.",
        "snow that has been compacted into a solid mass.",
        "ice crystals formed from airborne moisture on a surface on a surface whose temperature is at or below freezing."
      ],
      "answer": "ice with water on top of it or ice that is melting."
    },
    {
      "question": "If the aeroplane\u2019s navigational accuracy doesn\u2019t meet the 95% containment requirement, then you must increase the margin either side of your intended track to __________ nm",
      "choices": [
        "15",
        "20",
        "10",
        "5"
      ],
      "answer": "10"
    },
    {
      "question": "For an aeroplane in Performance Class B the following factors must be applied in determining the take-off distance from dry grass and wet pavement respectively:",
      "choices": [
        "1.2 and 1.15",
        "1.3 and 1.15",
        "1.2 and 1.0",
        "1.3 and 1.2"
      ],
      "answer": "1.2 and 1.0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Maximum endurance for a turbojet aeroplane is achieved at:",
      "choices": [
        "The speed that corresponds to the 1.32 x VMD",
        "The speed for maximum lift coefficient.",
        "The speed that corresponds to the speed for maximum climb angle.",
        "The speed that approximately corresponds to the maximum rate of climb speed"
      ],
      "answer": "The speed that corresponds to the speed for maximum climb angle."
    },
    {
      "question": "Ref to CAP 698 MEP 1 Figure 3.1. OAT: 24\u00b0C Pressure Altitude: 3000 ft RWY: 30R Wind: 060\u00b0/4 kt Take-off Mass: 3800 lb Other conditions are as associated in the header of the graph. Given the following information, what is the Take-Off Distance?",
      "choices": [
        "1550 ft",
        "2150 ft",
        "1670 ft",
        "2000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "2000 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider a Performance Class B aeroplane which is used for commercial transport and a runway where a clearway or a stopway is available. The take-off mass shall not exceed the maximum take-off mass specified in the AFM for the pressure altitude and the ambient temperature at the aerodrome of departure. The unfactored take-off distance, specified in the AFM, shall not exceed the accelerate stop distance available (ASDA), when multiplied by a factor of:",
      "choices": [
        "1.5",
        "1.3",
        "1.25",
        "1.15"
      ],
      "answer": "1.3"
    },
    {
      "question": "VREF for a Class B aircraft is defined as:",
      "choices": [
        "1.2 VSO",
        "1.2 VMC",
        "1.3 VSO",
        "1.3 VMC"
      ],
      "answer": "1.3 VSO"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 3.7. Given: OAT: -20\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 18 000 ft Gross mass: 4000 lbs Mixture: Leaned to 25\u00b0F Rich of peak EGT Other conditions as associated in the header of the graph. What is the two engine rate of climb for the conditions given?",
      "choices": [
        "870 ft/min.",
        "1050 ft/min.",
        "1370 ft/min.",
        "550 ft/min."
      ],
      "answer": "1050 ft/min."
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider a Performance Class B aeroplane which is used for commercial transport and a runway where a clearway or a stopway is available. The take-off mass shall not exceed the maximum take-off mass specified in the AFM for the pressure altitude and the ambient temperature at the aerodrome of departure. The unfactored take-off distance, specified in the AFM, shall not exceed the take-off distance available (TODA), when multiplied by a factor of:",
      "choices": [
        "1.25",
        "1.5",
        "1.15",
        "1.3"
      ],
      "answer": "1.15"
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP 698 as required. Calculate the obstacle clearance over an obstacle 900 ft high, 3 nm from the end of TODA given a climb gradient of 10%.",
      "choices": [
        "1875 ft.",
        "1825 ft.",
        "975 ft.",
        "2775 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "975 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is wind considered in the take-off performance data of the Aeroplane Operations Manuals?",
      "choices": [
        "Since take-offs with tailwind are not permitted, only headwinds are considered.",
        "Not more than 80% headwind and not less than 125% tailwind.",
        "Unfactored headwind and tailwind components are used.",
        "Not more than 50% of a headwind and not less than 150% of the tailwind."
      ],
      "answer": "Not more than 50% of a headwind and not less than 150% of the tailwind."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 3.6. Given the following data, determine the aircraft height gain after 2.5 NM. Mass: 4200 lbs PA: 4000 ft OAT: +30\u00b0C Wind: 20 kt headwind (All engines operating).",
      "choices": [
        "2550 ft",
        "1350 ft",
        "3300 ft",
        "2800 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "3300 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "For an MEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP698 as required. Calculate the planned clearance above an obstacle 700 ft high, 2 nm from reference zero. The aircraft\u2019s take-off mass is 4000 lb, flaps are UP, the aerodrome pressure altitude is 4000 ft and the temperature is +20\u00b0C. The cloud base is 500 ft and there is a 10 kt headwind.",
      "choices": [
        "386 ft.",
        "586 ft.",
        "186 ft.",
        "786 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "186 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an MEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP698 as required. What is the MTOM for a commercial flight conducting a normal take-off from a field length of 1870 ft, given the following conditions. MSL, OAT +18\u00b0C, wind calm, paved level dry surface. No stopway or clearway.",
      "choices": [
        "3550 lb",
        "4100 lb",
        "2500 lb",
        "3150 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "3550 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 698 Figure 2.4. Given the following information, determine the minimum or maximum wind component for the SEP aircraft to land: Pressure altitude: 10 000 ft Mass: 2860 lb Temperature: -2\u00b0 C Runway LDA: 2000 ft.",
      "choices": [
        "Maximum 6 kt tailwind.",
        "Minimum 19 kt headwind.",
        "Maximum 4 kt tailwind.",
        "Minimum 38 kt headwind."
      ],
      "answer": "Minimum 19 kt headwind."
    },
    {
      "question": "Following a take-off determined by the 50 ft (15 m) screen height, a light twin aircraft climbs on a 10% over-the-ground climb gradient. It will clear a 900 m high obstacle in relation to the runway (horizontally), situated at 10 000 m from the 50 ft clearing point with an obstacle clearance of:",
      "choices": [
        "100 m",
        "115 m",
        "85 m",
        "It will not clear the obstacle."
      ],
      "answer": "115 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "For an MEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP698 as required. You plan an approach to an airfield at a pressure altitude of 5000 ft and an OAT of +38\u00b0C. With the aeroplane at its AUM of 4513 lb, you must determine whether it can satisfy the balked landing climb gradient requirement. What is the achievable balked landing climb gradient? What is the minimum required balked climb gradient?",
      "choices": [
        "7.35% achievable and 1.43% required.",
        "7% achievable and 2.5% required.",
        "7.35% achievable and 2.5% required.",
        "2.6% achievable and 7.5% required."
      ],
      "answer": "7.35% achievable and 2.5% required."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP 698 as required. Determine MTOM with a TOD of 2500 ft, given: OAT+20\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 4000 ft Tailwind 5 kt Flaps at Approach Runway dry asphalt.",
      "choices": [
        "2750 lb.",
        "3250 kg.",
        "4000 lb.",
        "3250 lb."
      ],
      "answer": "3250 lb."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP698 as required. Determine the ground roll distance given: OAT+40\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 6000 ft QNH 973 hPa Mass 3400 lbs Tailwind 5 kt Flaps at Approach Dry asphalt runway.",
      "choices": [
        "2150 ft.",
        "3500 ft.",
        "3800 ft.",
        "2000 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "2150 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP 698 as required. Determine the required headwind given: OAT+30\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 2000 ft TODA 1900 ft Mass 3200 lbs Flaps at Approach Dry asphalt runway.",
      "choices": [
        "20 kt.",
        "15 kt.",
        "10 kt.",
        "22 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "22 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which factor must be applied, if not stated differently in AFM, for a Performance Class B aeroplane when landing on a runway with short grass?",
      "choices": [
        "1.05",
        "1.15",
        "0.95",
        "1.45"
      ],
      "answer": "1.15"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 3.2. Given: OAT: 20\u00b0C Pressure Altitude: 2000 ft RWY: 24L Wind: 120\u00b0/8 kts Take-off Mass: 4500 lbs Heavy Duty Brakes: installed Other conditions as associated in the header of the chart. What is the Accelerate and Stop Distance under the conditions given?",
      "choices": [
        "3400 ft",
        "3600 ft",
        "4200 ft",
        "4500 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "4200 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "A commercial air transport flight is to be conducted in a single-engined piston aircraft. At the most critical point during the flight, the distance to be travelled to a safe landing place is 10 NM. Given the following information, what is the lowest altitude the aircraft should fly over this critical point? Terrain elevation: 0 ft Gross glide gradient: 10% TAS: 110 kt Expected tailwind component: 20 kt 1 NM = 6080 ft Still air distance = (height difference / net gradient) x 100 Ground distance = Still Air Distance x (GS / TAS)",
      "choices": [
        "5100 ft",
        "5400 ft",
        "5800 ft",
        "6200 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "5400 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "For an MEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP698 as required. Determine the ASD for an aircraft, mass 4500 lb, flaps up, 1000 ft pressure altitude, 20\u00b0C and 10 kt headwind component.",
      "choices": [
        "3450 m.",
        "3800 ft.",
        "3450 ft.",
        "3750 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "3450 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP 698 as required. You have identified a suitable forced landing area 4 nm off route at an altitude of 2000 ft. Given the following conditions, calculate the minimum net glide height needed to make it to the forced landing site: OAT at forced landing site +30C, ISA pressure. Gross air gradient 10%. Glide speed 75 KIAS. Tailwind of 20 kt.\u201d",
      "choices": [
        "1800 ft.",
        "2430 ft.",
        "2550 ft.",
        "2055 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "2055 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 3.2. Given: OAT: 25\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 3000 ft RWY: 24L Wind: 310\u00b0/20 kts Take-off mass: 4400 lbs Heavy Duty Brakes: installed Other conditions as associated in the header of the chart. What is the Accelerate and Stop Distance under the conditions given?",
      "choices": [
        "4000 ft",
        "33750 ft",
        "3750 ft",
        "4300 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "3750 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP 698 as required. Determine the required headwind given: OAT+20\u00b0C Pressure altitude: sea level QNH 973 hPa TODA 1700 ft Mass 3450 lbs Flaps approach Dry asphalt runway",
      "choices": [
        "20 ft.",
        "26 kt.",
        "10 ft.",
        "14 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "26 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP 698 as required. Determine the distance to a height of 50 ft given: OAT+38\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 4000 ft QNH 973 hPa Mass 3400 lbs Tailwind 5 kt Flaps at Approach Firm, dry grass runway.",
      "choices": [
        "1700 ft.",
        "4050 ft.",
        "3900 ft.",
        "3250 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "3900 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP 698 as required. Determine the distance to a height of 50 ft given: OAT-7\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 5800 ft QNH 973 hPa Mass 2950 lbs Headwind 5 kt Flaps up Runway dry.",
      "choices": [
        "1750 ft.",
        "1000 ft.",
        "2050 ft.",
        "1900 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "1750 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 SEP 1 Figure 2.1. Given the following information, what is the required fuel to climb? Airport Pressure Altitude: 4000 ft Airport OAT: +10\u00b0C Climb to: FL100 OAT at FL100: -5\u00b0C Take-off Mass: 3400 lb Gear: up",
      "choices": [
        "4.2 gal",
        "2.8 gal",
        "16.0 gal",
        "8.0 gal"
      ],
      "answer": "2.8 gal"
    },
    {
      "question": "With reference to CAP 698 Figure 3.9. For a multi-engine piston aeroplane, calculate the maximum landing mass given the following conditions: Temperature: 10\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 2000 ft LDA: 2600 ft Headwind: 14 kt",
      "choices": [
        "2750 Ib",
        "3600 lb",
        "3350 Ib",
        "3000 Ib"
      ],
      "answer": "3350 Ib"
    },
    {
      "question": "For an MEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP698 as required. What is the FLL limited landing mass for a commercial MEP 1 flight given the following conditions: Pressure altitude sea level; OAT 0\u00b0C; LDA 2430 ft; 15 kt headwind on a dry runway.",
      "choices": [
        "3400 lb",
        "3450 lb",
        "3300 lb",
        "3000 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "3300 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "How does a downslope runway affect the take off and landing performance of an aeroplane? It:",
      "choices": [
        "decreases the take off distance, and increases the landing distance.",
        "decreases both the take off distance and the landing distance.",
        "increases the take-off distance, and decreases the landing distance.",
        "increases both the take off distance and the landing distance."
      ],
      "answer": "decreases the take off distance, and increases the landing distance."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an MEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP698 as required. The landing distance for a MEP 1 private flight was calculated as 3260 ft from the following data: Pressure altitude 3000 ft OAT +10\u00b0C Mass 4250 lb 5 kt tailwind. If this had been a commercial flight the landing distance would be:",
      "choices": [
        "3010 ft",
        "4660 ft",
        "2280 ft",
        "3260 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "4660 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "For a multi engined aircraft not certified under EASA CS 25 and in Performance Class B, service ceiling is defined as:",
      "choices": [
        "The altitude which at maximum power the rate of climb of an aircraft has fallen to 0 ft per minute.",
        "The altitude which at maximum power the rate of climb of an aircraft has fallen to 100 ft per minute for a piston engine and 500 ft per minute for a jet aircraft.",
        "The altitude which at maximum power the rate of climb of an aircraft has fallen to 500 ft per minute.",
        "The altitude which at maximum power the rate of climb of an aircraft has fallen to 100 ft per minute."
      ],
      "answer": "The altitude which at maximum power the rate of climb of an aircraft has fallen to 100 ft per minute."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an SEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP 698 as required. Determine the distance to a height of 50 ft, and the length of the take-off roll, given: OAT 30\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 1000 ft Mass 3400 lbs Tailwind 10 kt Flaps at Approach Dry, asphalt runway.",
      "choices": [
        "TOD 1800 ft TOR 900 ft.",
        "TOD 2750 ft TOR 145 ft.",
        "TOD 1300 ft TOR 2500 ft.",
        "TOD 2500 ft TOR 1300 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "TOD 2500 ft TOR 1300 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "For an MEP Aircraft. Using the data provided in CAP698 as required. Determine the landing distance, and speed at screen height, for a MEP 1 commercial air transport flight given the following data: Pressure altitude 3000 ft OAT +10\u00b0C Mass 4250 lb 5 kt tailwind.",
      "choices": [
        "88 kt and 1310 ft.",
        "89 kt and 3260 ft.",
        "88 kt and 1420 ft.",
        "88 kt and 3260 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "88 kt and 3260 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "A jet aeroplane is flying at the speed for maximum range, below the optimum altitude. How does the specific range change when altitude increases? The specific range :",
      "choices": [
        "increases only if there is no wind.",
        "decreases.",
        "first increases then decreases.",
        "does not change."
      ],
      "answer": "first increases then decreases."
    },
    {
      "question": "During the early part of the climb to cruise altitude, an a twin engine aircraft has a mass of 72 700 kg. Each engine is producing 90 000 N of thrust. The drag is estimated to be 45 400 N. What is the aircraft\u2019s percentage climb gradient? (Assume acceleration due to gravity is 10 m/s2)",
      "choices": [
        "0.185",
        "0.203",
        "0.181",
        "0.301"
      ],
      "answer": "0.185"
    },
    {
      "question": "Range is greatest at high altitude, both for engine and aerodynamic reasons. There is less drag for the same TAS at altitude. Most importantly, SFC is best at altitude. The optimum altitude is a balance between the savings achieved by cruising at high level and the time and fuel cost of climbing to altitude' This is a description of the considerations for:",
      "choices": [
        "turbojet-driven aeroplanes.",
        "propeller-driven aeroplanes.",
        "all aeroplanes.",
        "piston-engine aeroplanes."
      ],
      "answer": "turbojet-driven aeroplanes."
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens when flying at the \"backside of the power curve\"?",
      "choices": [
        "The altitude cannot be maintained.",
        "The speed is unstable.",
        "The aeroplane will not stall.",
        "The elevator must be pulled to lower the nose."
      ],
      "answer": "The speed is unstable."
    },
    {
      "question": "The cost index is the cost of time/the cost of fuel. A lower cost index (e.g. 0) weights the conduct of the flight towards __________ savings. A higher cost index (e.g. 100) weights the conduct of the flight towards __________ savings.",
      "choices": [
        "fuel; time",
        "time; fuel",
        "time; time",
        "fuel; fuel"
      ],
      "answer": "fuel; time"
    },
    {
      "question": "A climb gradient required is 3.3 %. For an aircraft maintaining 100 kt true airspeed, with no wind, this climb gradient corresponds to a rate of climb of approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "33.0 m/s",
        "3.30 m/s",
        "3300 ft/min",
        "330 ft/min"
      ],
      "answer": "330 ft/min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the one-engine-failed climb gradient of a four-engine-aeroplane, given the following information: Aeroplane mass: 358 000 kg Thrust per engine: 245 000 N Drag: 455 000 N (Assume the acceleration due to gravity is 10 m/s\u00b2)",
      "choices": [
        "0.147",
        "0.078",
        "0.127",
        "0.068"
      ],
      "answer": "0.078"
    },
    {
      "question": "The distance from the point on the surface of the aerodrome at which an aeroplane begins its take-off roll to the nearest point in the direction of take-off at which it can\u2019t roll over the surface of the aerodrome and be brought to rest in an emergency without risk of accident' is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "ASDA",
        "TORA",
        "TODR",
        "TODA"
      ],
      "answer": "ASDA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements concerning the range influenced by the CG is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "An aft CG increases range and increases stability.",
        "A forward CG decreases range and increases stability.",
        "A forward CG increases range and decreases stability.",
        "An aft CG decreases range and decreases stability."
      ],
      "answer": "A forward CG decreases range and increases stability."
    },
    {
      "question": "When descending after an engine failure in the cruise, the correct speed is?",
      "choices": [
        "Best ROC speed and add flap.",
        "VMD and add flap.",
        "Maximum L/D ratio and jettison fuel.",
        "Stall speed and jettison fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "Maximum L/D ratio and jettison fuel."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a turbojet aeroplane, maximum endurance is achieved at __________ at __________ altitude.",
      "choices": [
        "VMP; low",
        "VMD; high",
        "VMP; high",
        "VMD; low"
      ],
      "answer": "VMD; high"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ali other criteria being equal, what factor can reduce the landing distance?",
      "choices": [
        "The use of spoilers.",
        "A wet runway.",
        "A tailwind component.",
        "Landing on an airfield at a higher altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "The use of spoilers."
    },
    {
      "question": "The speed above maximum range cruise speed that results in a 1% decrease in nm/kg is known as the __________ speed.",
      "choices": [
        "long range cruise",
        "maximum cruise",
        "cost index 100",
        "economic cruise"
      ],
      "answer": "long range cruise"
    },
    {
      "question": "An obstacle is 5000 m from the end of the TODR and is 160 m high. The screen height is 50 ft and the ground climb gradient is 5%. Which of the following statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "The obstacle will be cleared by 295 ft.",
        "The obstacle will not be cleared.",
        "The obstacle will be cleared by 345 ft.",
        "The obstacle will be cleared by 710 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "The obstacle will be cleared by 345 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "The speed of the aeroplane, in a specified landing configuration, at the point where it descends through the landing screen height, used in the determination of the landing distance for manual landings' is the definition of:",
      "choices": [
        "VAP",
        "VMD",
        "VREF",
        "VFA"
      ],
      "answer": "VREF"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a climb at a constant Indicated Air Speed (IAS), what happens to the True Air Speed (TAS)?",
      "choices": [
        "Decreases due to the decreasing air density.",
        "Increases, and the aircraft might exceed MMO.",
        "Increases when switching to climb at a constant Mach number.",
        "Remains constant after the tropopause."
      ],
      "answer": "Increases, and the aircraft might exceed MMO."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft manufacturer constructs two aircraft. Aircraft 1 is a SEP with a 160 hp engine and a MTOM of 1300 kg. Aircraft 2 is a twin-engine piston aircraft with two of the same 160 hp engines, and a MTOM of 2000 kg. In the event of an engine failure on aircraft 2, which of the following statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "If both aircraft aeroplanes are operated at a same gross mass of 1250 kg then aircraft 1 will have a better power to weight ratio than aircraft 2.",
        "If both aircraft aeroplanes are operated at a same gross mass of 1250 kg then aircraft 2 will have a better power to weight ratio than aircraft 1.",
        "If both aeroplanes are operated at their maximum mass then aircraft 1 will have a better power to weight ratio than aircraft 2.",
        "If both aircraft aeroplanes are operated at their maximum mass then aircraft 2 will have a better power to weight ratio than aircraft 1."
      ],
      "answer": "If both aeroplanes are operated at their maximum mass then aircraft 1 will have a better power to weight ratio than aircraft 2."
    },
    {
      "question": "A lower density of air will result in an increased:",
      "choices": [
        "Performance-limited take-off mass.",
        "Take-off distance.",
        "Rate of climb.",
        "Climb gradient."
      ],
      "answer": "Take-off distance."
    },
    {
      "question": "From 500 ft above the destination aerodrome to FL50, a multi-engined piston (MEP) aeroplane performs a steady climb, maintaining a constant speed of 120 kt IAS. During this climb, the \"Power Required vs. TAS\" curve will move (1) ....... and the \"Power Available vs. TAS\" curve will move (2) .........",
      "choices": [
        "(1) up and right; (2) down and right",
        "(1) down and left; (2) up and left",
        "(1) up and left; (2) down and left",
        "(1) down and right; (2) up and right"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) up and right; (2) down and right"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane is taking off on Runway 18. The reported wind is 210/40 kt. The headwind component is __________ kt. The crosswind component is __________ kt. (Rounded up to a whole number).",
      "choices": [
        "40; 20",
        "35; 20",
        "35; 10",
        "20; 35"
      ],
      "answer": "35; 20"
    },
    {
      "question": "Your route of the day is London-Paris-London in a performance class 8 aeroplane. During your approach into London, the QNH has reduced considerably since your earlier departure, with a small increase in temperature. Vou expect your aircrafts performance to (1) _____ as the landing distance required will (2) _____ and the missed approach climb gradient will (3) _____ .",
      "choices": [
        "(1) increase; (2) reduce; (3) reduce.",
        "(1) reduce; (2) increase; (3) increase.",
        "(1) increase; (2) reduce; (3) increase.",
        "(1) reduce; (2) increase; (3) reduce."
      ],
      "answer": "(1) reduce; (2) increase; (3) reduce."
    },
    {
      "question": "If you want to follow a 3.25\u00b0 glideslope (ILS), when TAS is 130 kt and wind component is 15 kt tailwind, your rate of descend must be:",
      "choices": [
        "675 feet/min",
        "510 feet/min",
        "748 feet/min",
        "832 feet/min"
      ],
      "answer": "832 feet/min"
    },
    {
      "question": "The distance between the point on the surface of the aerodrome at which an aeroplane can begin its take-off run to the nearest point, in the direction of take-off, at which the surface of the aerodrome is incapable of bearing the weight of the aeroplane under normal operating conditions' is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "LDA",
        "TODA",
        "TORA",
        "ASDA"
      ],
      "answer": "TORA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Study this diagram, then identify the correct statement.",
      "choices": [
        "Best range for a propeller-driven aeroplane occurs at Point B.",
        "Best range for a propeller-driven aeroplane occurs at Point A.",
        "Best range for a turbojet aeroplane occurs at Point A.",
        "Best range for a turbojet aeroplane occurs at Point B."
      ],
      "answer": "Best range for a propeller-driven aeroplane occurs at Point B."
    },
    {
      "question": "The ground gradient __________ affected by wind.",
      "choices": [
        "is not",
        "is",
        "is only",
        "is never"
      ],
      "answer": "is"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum semi-width of the obstacle domain for an aircraft of wingspan 52 m that can maintain navigational accuracy and is not required to turn more than 15\u00b0 after take-off. The obstacle is 2200 m from the end of TODA.",
      "choices": [
        "365 m",
        "361 m",
        "600 m",
        "300 m"
      ],
      "answer": "300 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "What will be the effect on an aeroplane's performance if aerodrome pressure altitude is decreased?",
      "choices": [
        "It will decrease the take-off distance required.",
        "It will increase the accelerate stop distance.",
        "It will increase the take-off distance required.",
        "It will increase the take-off ground run."
      ],
      "answer": "It will decrease the take-off distance required."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a propeller aeroplane, maximum endurance is achieved at __________ at __________ altitude.",
      "choices": [
        "VMP; high",
        "VMD; high",
        "VMP; low",
        "VMD; low"
      ],
      "answer": "VMP; low"
    },
    {
      "question": "As speed is reduced from VMD to VMP:",
      "choices": [
        "Power required decreases, drag decreases.",
        "Power required increases, drag increases.",
        "Power required decreases, drag increases.",
        "Power required increases, drag decreases."
      ],
      "answer": "Power required decreases, drag increases."
    },
    {
      "question": "When the aircraft climbs at a constant CAS, the TAS and Mach number __________. When a climb is flown at a constant Mach number, the CAS (and TAS)__________.",
      "choices": [
        "increase; reduce.",
        "decrease; increase.",
        "increase; increase.",
        "decrease; reduce."
      ],
      "answer": "increase; reduce."
    },
    {
      "question": "Regarding a jet transport aeroplane, specific fuel consumption (SFC):",
      "choices": [
        "Is the TAS per unit of fuel flow.",
        "Is the nautical miles per unit mass of fuel.",
        "Is the nautical miles per unit of fuel flow.",
        "Is the fuel flow per unit of thrust."
      ],
      "answer": "Is the fuel flow per unit of thrust."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the image provided, which of the following situations shows the landing distance?",
      "choices": [
        "C",
        "A,B, and C",
        "A",
        "B"
      ],
      "answer": "A"
    },
    {
      "question": "The tangent from the origin to the power required against true airspeed curve, for a jet aeroplane, determines the speed for:",
      "choices": [
        "maximum endurance.",
        "maximum specific range.",
        "minimum power.",
        "critical angle of attack."
      ],
      "answer": "maximum endurance."
    },
    {
      "question": "During descent with idle power and assuming all other parameters remaining the same, how will an increased mass change the Minimum Angle of Descent and the corresponding speed? The Minimum Angle of Descent:",
      "choices": [
        "remains the same at an unchanged speed.",
        "decreases at an increased speed.",
        "remains the same at an increased speed.",
        "increases at an increased speed."
      ],
      "answer": "remains the same at an increased speed."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane with an L/D ratio of 1:12 is gliding at a TAS of 90 kt into a 30 kt headwind. What is its gross ground gradient of descent?",
      "choices": [
        "0.083",
        "0.052",
        "0.125",
        "0.091"
      ],
      "answer": "0.125"
    },
    {
      "question": "A multi-engined piston aeroplane is in straight and level flight. As fuel is burnt, the mass of the aeroplane reduces. Consequently, the Specific Range (SR) will (1) __ , and the optimum speed for maximum SR will (2) ___ .",
      "choices": [
        "(1) decrease; (2) increase.",
        "(1) increase; (2) increase.",
        "(1) decrease; (2) decrease.",
        "(1) increase; (2) decrease."
      ],
      "answer": "(1) increase; (2) decrease."
    },
    {
      "question": "A 4-engined aeroplane with a mass of 358 000 kg suffers an engine failure in the climb. Assuming acceleration of gravity 10 m/s\u00b2. Its drag is 455 000 N. Each engine produces a thrust of 245 000 N. What is the aeroplane\u2019s climb gradient following the engine failure?",
      "choices": [
        "0.076",
        "0.078",
        "0.102",
        "0.78"
      ],
      "answer": "0.078"
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens to the minimum rate of descent and gradient of descent when the aircraft mass is decreased, all other factors being constant?",
      "choices": [
        "Rate of Descent decreases, Gradient of Descent decreases.",
        "Rate of Descent increases, Gradient of Descent remains the same.",
        "Rate of Descent decreases, Gradient of Descent remains the same.",
        "Rate of Descent increases, Gradient of Descent increases."
      ],
      "answer": "Rate of Descent decreases, Gradient of Descent remains the same."
    },
    {
      "question": "What factors affect the level-off altitude?",
      "choices": [
        "Temperature & Drag.",
        "Drag & Power.",
        "Power & Lift.",
        "Temperature & Power."
      ],
      "answer": "Temperature & Power."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the rate of climb required for an aircraft to climb at 1800 ft with a TAS of 125 kt, a headwind component of 25 kt and a climb gradient of 4.6%?",
      "choices": [
        "527",
        "450",
        "500",
        "583"
      ],
      "answer": "583"
    },
    {
      "question": "The standard long range cruise Mach number (MMLC ) used by both Boeing and Airbus is about __________ faster than maximum range speed. This reduces the range by 1%, which means that at MMLC the aircraft achieves 99% of the SAR achieved at MMR.",
      "choices": [
        "0.15",
        "0.04",
        "0.1",
        "0.24"
      ],
      "answer": "0.04"
    },
    {
      "question": "A crosswind determined by the manufacturer when it first tests its new type. The limit depends on a number of factors, such as the amount of rudder authority, the yaw induced by engine failure, the state of the runway surface and the level of pilot skill required to maintain control'. This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "VMCG",
        "The gross crosswind.",
        "The net crosswind.",
        "The demonstrated crosswind."
      ],
      "answer": "The demonstrated crosswind."
    }
  ],
  "FPM": [
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Plate AMSTERDAM (Schipol) 10-2B. You recover via MOLIX, LUTEX and ROBVI and then hold for 20 mins. Expected fuel state at SUGOL after 20 mins holding? Usable Fuel at MOLIX 380 lbs, GS = 103 kts, Fuel flow at SUGOL 215 lbs/h, Holding fuel flow 140 lbs/h",
      "choices": [
        "255 lbs",
        "225 lbs",
        "455 lbs",
        "355 lbs"
      ],
      "answer": "255 lbs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to figure or CAP 697 Figure 4.5.3.2 for Pressure Altitude 35 000. What will be the change in air range available from 1000 kg of fuel for the following situation if the OAT increases from -55\u00b0 to -45\u00b0C? Aircraft mass at start of cruise leg: 50 000 kg, Cruise level: FL350, Cruise speed: Mach 0.74, Forecast OAT at FL350: -55\u00b0C, Wind component at FL350: -25 kt",
      "choices": [
        "A reduction of 1 NAM.",
        "A reduction of 11 NAM.",
        "An increase of 4 NAM.",
        "An increase of 10 NAM."
      ],
      "answer": "A reduction of 1 NAM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to a drive failure, the slats of a transport category aircraft do not retract properly after take-off. Based on the flight planning data given below, calculate the time penalty in per cent for the flight, based on endurance. Usable fuel 8540 kg, Fuel consumption 2600 kg/h, Final reserve fuel 1100 kg, (Note: consider 60% fuel penalty for flap/slat failure and 180% for gear retraction failure)",
      "choices": [
        "0.51",
        "0.37",
        "0.6",
        "0.64"
      ],
      "answer": "0.37"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the remaining fuel in litres : ETO ATO Planned Fuel (L) Actual 1. 10:02 10:00 133 137, 2. 10:10 10:08 126 130, 3. 10:32",
      "choices": [
        "109 L",
        "111 L",
        "105 L",
        "107 L"
      ],
      "answer": "111 L"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM 875 000 lbs, MLM 652 000 lbs, MZFM 555 100 lbs, DOM 394 100 lbs, Traffic Load 155 215 lbs, Trip Fuel 198 620 lbs, Planned T/O Fuel 226 195 lbs, Taxi Fuel 1600 lbs, Fuel burn correction per 1000 lb of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 470 lb and LDM: + 887 lbs",
      "choices": [
        "99 490 lbs",
        "75 110 lbs",
        "5785 lbs",
        "94 490 lbs"
      ],
      "answer": "99 490 lbs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, calculate the minimum required fuel for a Commercial Air Transport flight in accordance with the Reduced Contingency Fuel Procedure. Taxi Fuel: 230 kg, Trip Fuel to the Decision Point: 8355 kg, Trip Fuel from the Decision Point to the commercial destination: 2120 kg, Trip Fuel from the Decision Point to the optional refuel destination: 1860 kg, Final Reserve Fuel: 1200 kg, No Additional Fuel is required, No Extra Fuel is required, An en-route alternate for the optional refuel destination is available, No destination alternate requirements exist for both destination aerodromes.",
      "choices": [
        "12 429 kg",
        "11 952kg",
        "12 156 kg",
        "12 011 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "12 011 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the total fuel required for a VFR Commercial Air Transport flight with a multi-engine piston aircraft? Start up and Taxi Fuel: 2 gal, Climb Fuel: 6 gal, Cruise Fuel: 21 gal, Alternate Fuel: 3 gal, Fuel flow for Final Reserve Fuel: 16 gal/h",
      "choices": [
        "39 gal",
        "41 gal",
        "46 gal",
        "44 gal"
      ],
      "answer": "46 gal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following planning data, calculate the maximum possible extra fuel in kg, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. Max Ramp Mass 77 500 kg, MTOM 73 000 kg, MLM 66 360 kg, MZFM 62 720 kg, DOM 42 845 kg, Traffic Load 17 460 kg, Planned T/O fuel 10 365 kg, Trip Fuel 7890 kg, Taxi Fuel 195 kg, Fuel Penalty: 135 kg / 1000 kg extra fuel, Max Fuel tank capacity 21 000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "3580 kg",
        "4139 kg",
        "2330 kg",
        "2694 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "2330 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart E(LO)1. Which of the following is a correctly specified navaid from which you can get a bearing at KIRKWALL (EGPA, N58\u00b058' W002\u00b054')?",
      "choices": [
        "VOR/DME KWL, 118.3 MHz",
        "NDB KW, 395 kHz",
        "VOR channel 58 - 47",
        "VOR KW, 108.6 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "NDB KW, 395 kHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Chart E (LO)2. What is the DME Frequency of Lelystad DME?",
      "choices": [
        "121.0 MHz",
        "111.40 MHz",
        "109.25 MHz",
        "124.50 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "111.40 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen ALICANTE (LEAL) charts 11-1, 11-2, 13-1 and 13-2. An aircraft ls planned to fly to Alicante Elche aerodrome (LEAL) with the following entry ln the tech log \"ADF inoperative due broken frequency selector parts ordered\". How will this affect the availability of approaches to Runway 10 at Alicante?",
      "choices": [
        "All given approaches are available as none of them are based on the Al NOB.",
        "Both the VOR approaches are available. The ILS and LOC approaches are unavailable.",
        "Only the VOR Z approach is available.",
        "All given ILS and VOR approaches are available. The LOC A and LOC B approaches are unavailable."
      ],
      "answer": "Both the VOR approaches are available. The ILS and LOC approaches are unavailable."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen ALICANTE - Charts 13-3, 13-4 and 13-5. There is a NOTAM stating that ALTET VOR DME (ALT) is unserviceable at the time of arrival at ALICANTE. What VOR approaches are available from MAGAL to runway 28?",
      "choices": [
        "VOR X only",
        "VOR X and Y",
        "None of them",
        "VOR Z"
      ],
      "answer": "VOR X only"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Charts E(LO)1 & E(LO)2. You are flying on airway N560 from RIMOL (N57\u00b032' W004\u00b003') to when 24 nm before GOW you are on radial:",
      "choices": [
        "190\u00b0 GOW",
        "299\u00b0 GOW",
        "038\u00b0 GOW",
        "010\u00b0 GOW"
      ],
      "answer": "010\u00b0 GOW"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen STUTTGART (EDDS) charts 11-1 and 11-lA. An aircraft of approach category 'C' and approach capability LNAV/VNAV and CAT IIIB, expects to perform one of the two ILS approach procedures given onto Rwy 07 at Stuttgart airport (EDDS). What is the lowest RVR or minimum meteorological visibility required to commence any of the two approaches given?",
      "choices": [
        "An RVR of 300 m",
        "A meteorological visibility of 550 m",
        "An RVR of 200 m",
        "An RVR of 550 m"
      ],
      "answer": "An RVR of 200 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to Chart GSPRM E(LO) 1. You are flying from KIRKWALL (N59\u00b0 W003\u00b0) to ABERDEEN (N57\u00b020' W002\u00b015') via the airways. Which is your routing and tracks?",
      "choices": [
        "N560 198 then Y904 164\u00b0",
        "N560 192\u00b0 then Y904 158\u00b0",
        "N560 195\u00b0 then Y904 161\u00b0",
        "DCT 169\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "N560 195\u00b0 then Y904 161\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Alicante charts 10-3A. Using SID CATON 2C. What is the correct procedure?",
      "choices": [
        "3500 feet at D9.5. ALT not above FL80 at VILNA. Level at FL110 NARGO. FL230 at CATON.",
        "5000 feet at D9.5. ALT not above FL70 at VILNA. Level at FL110 NARGO. FL290 at CATON.",
        "3100 feet or higher at D9.5. FL80 or higher at VILNA. FL110 or higher at NARGO. Not above FL 230 at CATON.",
        "Runway heading to 4500 ft. Above FL80 at VILNA. Above FL110 at NARGO. Not above FL230 at CATON."
      ],
      "answer": "3100 feet or higher at D9.5. FL80 or higher at VILNA. FL110 or higher at NARGO. Not above FL 230 at CATON."
    },
    {
      "question": "How many feet do you have to climb to reach FL75? Given: Departure aerodrome elevation 1500 ft, QNH 1023 hPa, Temperature ISA (1hPa=30 ft)",
      "choices": [
        "6600 ft",
        "7800 ft",
        "6300 ft",
        "6000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "6300 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart Alicante 10-3A. Your departure is via CATON 3A and you are cleared to FL80. Due to a restriction you have to remain at 2000 FT until passing VOR/DME ALT. QNH is 1040 hPa, ROC is 800 Ft/min and GS is 133 KT. When are you going to reach the top of climb (ToC)?",
      "choices": [
        "1 NM After VILNA",
        "4 NM After VILNA",
        "1 NM before VILNA",
        "4 NM Before VILNA"
      ],
      "answer": "1 NM before VILNA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: MSA 8230 ft, QNH 995 hPa (measured at an airfield nearby at MSL), Temperature ISA -18\u00b0C, Track 123\u00b0M. Assume 30 ft / hPa. Calculate the minimum cruising flight level for a flight under under IFR.",
      "choices": [
        "FL100",
        "FL110",
        "FL90",
        "FL120"
      ],
      "answer": "FL110"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Charts Amsterdam 10-2, 10-2A, 10-2B, 10-2C. Flying from Paris approaching Amsterdam from the South, which STARS are appropriate?",
      "choices": [
        "DENUT 1A, HELEN 1A, PESAR 2A, PUTTY 1A (10 2A)",
        "EELDE 1A&B, NORKU 2A&B REKKEN 2A&B, (10-2)",
        "TOPPA 2A (10-2C)",
        "LAMSO 2A, MOLIX 2A, REDFA 1A (10 2B)"
      ],
      "answer": "DENUT 1A, HELEN 1A, PESAR 2A, PUTTY 1A (10 2A)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart Alicante 11-2. You are arriving to the airport, but when you are about to land, the tailwind changes above limits. What do you do?",
      "choices": [
        "Continue to land as normal.",
        "Carry out missed approach and circle South of the airport.",
        "Divert.",
        "Land with no flap."
      ],
      "answer": "Carry out missed approach and circle South of the airport."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)14. You are flying from Izmir, Turkey and are approaching Santorini, Greece along ATS route J62. The wind is from the south. Find the appropriate plates and identify the bearing and range from KORAX to SNI.",
      "choices": [
        "155\u00b0M - 9 nm",
        "335\u00b0T - 9 nm",
        "155\u00b0M - 9 km",
        "335\u00b0M - 9 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "155\u00b0M - 9 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Charts Alicante 10-2A, 10-2B, 10-2C, 10-2D. You are preparing for a flight from MANCHESTER to ALICANTE. To choose a likely STAR to ALICANTE, which of the following charts will you consider when choosing an arrival route to decide which STAR to load into your FMS route.",
      "choices": [
        "10-2D",
        "10-2B",
        "10-2C",
        "10-2A"
      ],
      "answer": "10-2A"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, when flying between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden ((EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006', what station and frequency should you contact for a flight information service on leaving Schw\u00e4bish Hall Information?",
      "choices": [
        "Langen Information 128.95 MHz",
        "Stuttgart Tower 119.05 MHz",
        "V\u00f6lkleshofen Lichtenberg 130.12 MHz",
        "Schw\u00e4bish Hall 108.05 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "Langen Information 128.95 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "A twin engine piston aircraft planning to fly VFR from A to B. Given the following data, what is the minimum block fuel? Flight Time 1hr 50 min, Dep Airfield is the Dest Alternate, Taxi 8 L, Fuel for Departure and Climb 30 L, Fuel Go around and Climb 30 L, App and Landing 14 L, Fuel Flow Cruise: 58 L / hr , Fuel Flow Holding 50 L / hr. Answer in Litres.",
      "choices": [
        "324 L",
        "354 L",
        "384 L",
        "404 L"
      ],
      "answer": "354 L"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. What is the distance between MUNICH 112.30 MUN and WALDA 112.8 WLD?",
      "choices": [
        "67 NM",
        "32 km",
        "39 NM",
        "67 km"
      ],
      "answer": "67 km"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are flying a heading of 020\u00b0 with a TAS of 180 kt. If the wind is from 060\u00b0 at 30 kt, what will your drift angle and ground speed be?",
      "choices": [
        "5\u00b0L; 155 kt",
        "5\u00b0R\u00b7 155 kt",
        "7\u00b0R; 158 kt",
        "7\u00b0L; 158 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "7\u00b0L; 158 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following Information, calculate the drift angle: TAS:179 kt, Wind: 330\u00b0(M)/25 kt, VAR: 20\u00b0W, Course: 210\u00b0(M)",
      "choices": [
        "12\u00b0 Left",
        "18\u00b0 Left",
        "10\u00b0 Left",
        "8\u00b0 Left"
      ],
      "answer": "8\u00b0 Left"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, when flying between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden ((EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006', what radio navigation aid could you use for distance and (nearly) accurate groundspeed to the first line feature, the A81 autobahn (motorway)?",
      "choices": [
        "SHD DME 108.05 MHz",
        "KBD DME 115.80 MHz",
        "KRH VOR/DME 115.95 MHz",
        "LBU VOR/DME 109.20 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "SHD DME 108.05 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, when flying between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden (EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006', what is the flight time between the line features formed by the A81 and A8 autobahns (motorways)?",
      "choices": [
        "19 min",
        "7.5 min",
        "9 min",
        "38 min"
      ],
      "answer": "9 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP workbook SEP Figure 2.4. Given: Aeroplane mass at start-up 3663 lbs, Aviation gasoline (density 6 lbs/gal, Take-off altitude sea level, Headwind 40 kt, Cruising altitude 8000 ft, Power setting full throttle 2300 RPM, 20 degrees celsius lean of peak EGT. Calculate the range.",
      "choices": [
        "844 NM",
        "633 NM",
        "730 NM",
        "547.5 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "633 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "GSPRM - Friedrichshafen VFR 19-1 Following a take-off on RWY 24, what is the track and maximum altitude for a departure via visual reporting point NOVEMBER ?",
      "choices": [
        "127\u00b0 - 4500 ft",
        "269\u00b0 - 2400 ft",
        "300\u00b0 - 2591 ft",
        "315\u00b0 - 3000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "315\u00b0 - 3000 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen VFR Chart ED-4. Find the highest obstacle or elevation, within a 10 NM wide corridor and considering a 5 NM radius around the aerodromes, when flying directly from Griesau (N48\u00b057', E12\u00b025') to Arnbruck (N49\u00b07', E12\u00b059').",
      "choices": [
        "4777 ft",
        "3717 ft",
        "3438 ft",
        "4055 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "4055 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following Information, at what distance should the pilot commence the descent in order to arrive overhead the airfield at 2000 ft? Cruise level: FL95, GS: 155 kt, TAS: constant, Wind component: negligible, Temperature: ISA, QNH: 1030 hPa, Rate of descent: 500 ft/min",
      "choices": [
        "45 NM",
        "38 NM",
        "48 NM",
        "41 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "41 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. ETSI INGOLSTADT MANCHING N48.42.9, E01132.0. You are in the CTR. Which Frequency would be the correct one to use?",
      "choices": [
        "125.25",
        "109.5",
        "115.05",
        "118.2"
      ],
      "answer": "125.25"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. SONNEN (EDPS) to STRAUBING (EDMS). What is the highest obstacle within 5 nm? Tip - EDMS is North East of Munich region.",
      "choices": [
        "1674 ft",
        "1900 ft",
        "3754 ft",
        "3333 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "3754 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Along the route the highest obstacle ls 13 421 feet AMSL. If the QNH is 989 hPa, the MT ls 311\u00b0 and the temperature is 10 degrees below ISA, the lowest appropriate VFR flight level that you could choose in order to clear this obstacle by a minimum of 2000 feet is:",
      "choices": [
        "FL 185",
        "FL 175",
        "FL 195",
        "FL 165"
      ],
      "answer": "FL 185"
    },
    {
      "question": "When calculating the fuel required to carry out a given flight, one must take into account: 1 - the wind 2 - foreseeable airborne delays 3 - other weather forecasts 4 - any foreseeable conditions which may delay landing The combination which provides the correct statement is:",
      "choices": [
        "2003-01-02 00:00:00",
        "2025-01-03 00:00:00",
        "1, 2, 3, 4",
        "2025-02-04 00:00:00"
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 3, 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight Planning Manual MRJT 1 Figure 4.3.5. For a flight of 2400 ground nautical miles, the following apply: Tailwind 25 kt Temperature ISA -10\u00b0C Brake release mass 66 000 kg The Trip Fuel and trip time respectively are:",
      "choices": [
        "15 800 kg, 6 hrs 20 min.",
        "14 600 kg, 5 hrs 45 min.",
        "15 000 kg, 6 hrs 00 min.",
        "14 000 kg, 5 hrs 35 min."
      ],
      "answer": "14 000 kg, 5 hrs 35 min."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance A to B 2346 NM Ground speed OUT 365 kt Ground speed BACK 480 kt The time from A to the point of equal time (PET) between A and B is:",
      "choices": [
        "260 min.",
        "197 min.",
        "219 min.",
        "167 min."
      ],
      "answer": "219 min."
    },
    {
      "question": "Use Flight Planning Manual MRJT 1 Figure 4.5.1 Given: Brake release mass: 58 000 kg Temperature: ISA + 15 The fuel required to climb from an aerodrome at elevation 4000 ft to FL300 is:",
      "choices": [
        "1450 kg",
        "1250 kg",
        "1400 kg",
        "1350 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "1250 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 165 NM True track 055\u00b0 W/V 360/20 TAS 105 kt What is the distance of the PET from the departure point?",
      "choices": [
        "132 NM",
        "92 NM",
        "83 NM",
        "73 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "92 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane with reciprocating engines is planning to depart for an isolated destination Aerodrome as a Commercial Air Transport operation. Calculate the minimum amount of fuel required (to the nearest 10 kg), when overhead the isolated aerodrome, considering the following details. Flight time: 2 hours and 30 minutes Top of climb to top of descent time: 2 hours Normal fuel consumption cruise: 780 kg per hour",
      "choices": [
        "1440 kg",
        "540 kg",
        "760 kg",
        "820 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "820 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM 233 000 kg MLM 182 000 kg MZFM 170 000 kg DOM 122 550 kg Traffic Load 41 936 kg Trip Fuel 52 139 kg Planned T/O Fuel 57 143 kg Taxi Fuel 300 kg Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 394 kg and LDM: + 650 kg Fuel tank capacity 110 000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "5514 kg",
        "12 510 kg",
        "11 371 kg",
        "11 071 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "11 371 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM 233 000 kg MLM 182 000 kg MZFM 170 000 kg DOM 122 550 kg Traffic Load 43 217 kg Trip Fuel 45 854 kg Planned T/O Fuel 51 616 kg Taxi Fuel 300 kg Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 394 kg and LDM: + 650 kg Fuel tank capacity 110 000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "15 617 kg",
        "4233 kg",
        "1047 kg",
        "14 596 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "15 617 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the ground speed of the aircraft? TAS: 300 kt Heading: 090\u00b0 Wind: 330\u00b0/46 kt",
      "choices": [
        "280 kt",
        "320 kt",
        "330 kt",
        "325 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "325 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 150 NM Safe Endurance 2.4 h True Track 250 W/V 280/15 TAS 120 kt What is the distance of the PSR from the departure point??",
      "choices": [
        "142 NM",
        "83 NM",
        "98 NM",
        "71 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "142 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given : Taxi Fuel = 150 kg Trip time = 2hrs Alternate = 1200 kg Extra Fuel = 350 kg Holding Fuel Flow = 2500 kg/hr Trip Fuel flow = 3100 kg/hr Find the Block Fuel.",
      "choices": [
        "9466 kg",
        "9640 kg",
        "9460 kg",
        "9115 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "9460 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. Maximum Ramp Mass 77 500 kg MTOM 77000 kg MLM 66 360 kg MZFM 62720 kg DOM 42 845 kg Traffic Load 17460 kg Planned T/O Fuel 10 365 kg Trip Fuel 7890 kg Taxi Fuel 195 kg Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 135 kg and LDM: + 156 kg Fuel tank capacity 21 000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "4139 kg",
        "3580 kg",
        "2415 kg",
        "6330 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "4139 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to IFR Chart E(HI)1. Your aircraft is routing from Newcastle, England (EGNT) to Keflavik, Iceland via route L602 - TLA VOR/DME - route UL613 - BAMRA - UP61. ETO TLA VOR/DME = 11.25 UTC ETO BAMRA = 12.15 UTC 5 nm before VADNO (N57\u00b0 27\u2019 W003\u00b0 38\u2019), ATC instructs a speed change: \u201cReduce speed, cross BAMRA not before 12.17 UTC\u201d. What is the required reduction in groundspeed?",
      "choices": [
        "25 kt",
        "20 kt",
        "10 kt",
        "15 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "20 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Plate AMSTERDAM (Schipol) 10-2B. You recover via MOLIX, LUTEX and ROBVI and then hold for 20 mins. TAS 250 kt Nil Wind Fuel flow in cruise 3000 kg /h Holding fuel flow 2400 kg / h How much fuel do you burn between MOLIX and leaving the hold to commence the procedure?",
      "choices": [
        "1160 kg",
        "1650 kg",
        "1250 kg",
        "1760 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "1250 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft was over A at 1435 hours flying direct to B. Given: Distance A to B 2900 NM True airspeed 470 kt Mean wind component OUT +55 kt Mean wind component BACK -75 kt The ETA for reaching the point of equal time (PET) between A and B is:",
      "choices": [
        "17:21:00",
        "18:46:00",
        "16:57:00",
        "17:44:00"
      ],
      "answer": "16:57:00"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 220 NM True track 175\u00b0 W/V 220/10 TAS 135 kts What is the distance of the PET from the departure point?",
      "choices": [
        "136 NM",
        "103 NM",
        "110 NM",
        "116 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "116 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 260 NM Safe Endurance 4.1 h True Track 150 W/V 100/30 TAS 110 kt What is the distance of the PSR from the departure point?",
      "choices": [
        "213 NM",
        "107 NM",
        "47 NM",
        "154 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "213 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Track 355\u00b0 (T) Wind velocity 340/30 kt TAS 140 kt Total distance A to B 350 NM What is the time and the distance to the point of equal time between A and B?",
      "choices": [
        "75 mins; 211 NM.",
        "114 mins; 211 NM.",
        "50 mins; 140 NM.",
        "75 mins; 140 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "114 mins; 211 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel to be uplifted, if the Commander wants to climb directly to the optimum altitude of 37 000 ft. Maximum Take-off Mass (MTOM) to climb at FL370: 68 000 kg Maximum Zero Fuel Mass (MZFM): 62 731 kg Actual Zero Fuel Mass (AZFM): 59 031 kg Regulated Take-Off Mass (RTOM): 76 000 kg Maximum Landing Mass (MLM): 66 360 kg Fuel Tank Capacity: 16 000 kg Taxi Fuel: 240 kg Trip Fuel: 4761 kg Minimum Block Fuel: 8000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "9209",
        "8000",
        "4330",
        "1209"
      ],
      "answer": "1209"
    },
    {
      "question": "Use Flight planning Manual SEP 1 Figure 2.2 Table 2.2.3 Using the Power Setting Table, for the single engine aeroplane, determine the cruise TAS and fuel flow (lbs/hr) with full throttle and cruise lean mixture in the following conditions: Given: OAT: 13\u00b0C Pressure altitude: 8000 ft RPM: 2300",
      "choices": [
        "160 kt and 71.1 lbs/hr",
        "158 kt and 74.4 lbs/hr",
        "160 kt and 69.3 lbs/hr",
        "159 kt and 71.7 lbs/hr"
      ],
      "answer": "160 kt and 69.3 lbs/hr"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 2450 NM Safe Endurance 7.5 h TAS 410 kt Ground Speed Out 360 kt Ground Speed Home 460 kt What is the time of the PSR from the departure point in minutes?",
      "choices": [
        "252 min",
        "156 min",
        "111 min",
        "198 min"
      ],
      "answer": "252 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight Planning Manual MRJT 1 Figure 4.3.5. What is the Trip Fuel? Given: Temperature ISA +15\u00b0C Brake release mass 62 000 kg Trip time 5 hrs 20 min",
      "choices": [
        "13 200 kg",
        "13 500 kg",
        "13 000 kg",
        "13 800 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "13 500 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following data is extracted from an aeroplane loading manifest. Take-off Mass (Performance Limited) 93 500 kg Expected Landing Mass at destination 81 700 kg Maximum Certificated Landing Mass 86 300 kg Take-off Fuel on board 16 500 kg During the flight a diversion is made to an en-route alternate which is not performance limited for landing. Fuel remaining at landing is 10 300 kg The Landing Mass:",
      "choices": [
        "Is 87 300 kg and excess structural stress could result.",
        "Must be reduced to 81 700 kg in order to avoid a high speed approach.",
        "Is 83 200 kg which is in excess of the regulated Landing Mass and could result in overrunning the runway.",
        "Is 87 300 kg which is acceptable in this case because this is a diversion and not a normal scheduled landing."
      ],
      "answer": "Is 87 300 kg and excess structural stress could result."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, assuming conditions stay the same, what is the ETA at DELTA? BETA to GAMMA distance: 60 NM Actual time en-route: 30 min Actual lime of arrival at GAMMA: 1240 UTC GAMMA to DELTA distance: 34 NM",
      "choices": [
        "12:37 UTC",
        "13:07 UTC",
        "12:57 UTC",
        "12:47 UTC"
      ],
      "answer": "12:57 UTC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following Information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel to be uplifted. Maximum Zero Fuel Mass MZFM: 2000 kg Actual Zero Fuel Mass AZFM: 2000 kg Regulated Take-Off Mass RTOM: 3000 kg Maximum Landing Mass MLM: 2200 kg Fuel Tank Capacity: 550 kg Trip Fuel TF: 190 kg Minimum Block Fuel (BF): 300 kg",
      "choices": [
        "Not able to carry Extra Fuel.",
        "60 kg.",
        "90 kg.",
        "250 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "90 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given A to B: 2050 NM Mean ground speed there 440 kt Mean ground speed back 540 kt The distance to the point of equal time PET between A & B is:",
      "choices": [
        "920 NM",
        "1130 NM",
        "1025 NM",
        "1153 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "1130 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Maximum allowable take-off mass: 64 400 kg Maximum landing mass: 56 200 kg Maximum zero fuel mass: 53 000 kg Dry operating mass: 35 500 kg Traffic load: 14 500 kg Trip fuel: 4900 kg Minimum Take-off Fuel: 7400 kg. Find maximum allowable take-off fuel:",
      "choices": [
        "11 400 kg",
        "11 100 kg",
        "8600 kg",
        "14 400 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "11 100 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the required fuel for an aircraft on a commercial VFR flight with reciprocating engines, given: Fuel Flow: 120 kg/h Trip Time: 4 h 39 min No alternate selected and good weather expected.",
      "choices": [
        "558 kg",
        "706 kg",
        "586 kg",
        "676 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "706 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the following NOTAM, what is the maximum height of the balloon involved? Q) EUAD/QWCLW/IV/M/W/000/004/5339N00135W001 A) EUAD B) FROM 15/12/14 1348C) TO 16/03/06 1830 E) UNMANNED CAPTIVE BALLOON IN LOW FLYING AREA AVOIDANCE AREA WI 1NM RADIUSMAX HEIGHT 200FT AGL/324FT AMSL15/12/06/0PSLFLOWER Surface, UPPER 324 Feet AMSL SCHEDULE DEC 14 1348-1600, DEC 15-31 0700-1600, JAN 01-31 0700-1630, FEB 01-29 0700-1730, MAR 01-06 0600-1830",
      "choices": [
        "324 feet AMSL.",
        "324 feet AGL.",
        "200 feet AMSL.",
        "The height is variable."
      ],
      "answer": "324 feet AMSL."
    },
    {
      "question": "For pre-flight planning purposes, what is the minimum Fuel required for the Commercial Air Transport flight in a Jet aircraft aeroplane, given the following information? Assume the Basic Fuel Scheme WITHOUT variations applies. Trip Fuel: 3740 kg Fuel to alternate: 936 kg Taxi Fuel: 140 kg Fuel flow at 1500 ft above destination aerodrome: 2132 kg/h Extra Fuel: 0 kg Discretionary Fuel: 0 kg",
      "choices": [
        "5882 kg",
        "6069 kg",
        "4816 kg",
        "6948 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "6069 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. Maximum Ramp Mass 63 060 kg MTOM 62 800 kg MLM 54 900 kg MZFM 51 300 kg DOM 33 200 kg Traffic Load 12 375 kg T/O Fuel 3575 kg Trip Fuel 2100 kg Taxi Fuel 195 kg Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 40 kg and LDM: + 42kg Fuel tank capacity 16 145 kg",
      "choices": [
        "13 650 kg",
        "8180 kg",
        "5725 kg",
        "7850 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "8180 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: True Air Speed: 135 kt True course: 270\u00b0 Wind: 340\u00b0 /20 kt Distance: 53 NM Determine ground speed (GS) and flight time for covering the given distance:",
      "choices": [
        "127 kt, 17 minutes",
        "115 kt, 28 minutes",
        "107 kt, 30 minutes",
        "127 kt, 25 minutes"
      ],
      "answer": "127 kt, 25 minutes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination: 950 NM Safe Endurance: 3.5 h TAS: 360 kt Ground Speed Out: 320 kt Ground Speed Home: 400 kt What is the distance and time of the PSR from the departure point?",
      "choices": [
        "Distance: 622 NM Time: 117 min",
        "Distance: 328 NM Time: 62 min",
        "Distance: 311 NM Time: 52 min",
        "Distance: 528 NM Time: 79 min"
      ],
      "answer": "Distance: 622 NM Time: 117 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to a drive failure, the slats of a transport category aircraft do not retract properly after take-off. Based on the flight planning data given below, calculate the time penalty in per cent for the flight, based on endurance. Usable fuel 8540 kg Fuel consumption 2600 kg/h Final reserve fuel 1100 kg (Note: consider 60% fuel penalty for flap/slat failure and 180% for gear retraction failure)",
      "choices": [
        "0.64",
        "0.6",
        "0.51",
        "0.37"
      ],
      "answer": "0.37"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM 85 000 kg MLM 75 500 kg MZFM 71 420 kg DOM 48 000 kg Traffic Load 15 464 kg Trip Fuel 2561 kg Planned T/O Fuel 5167 kg Taxi Fuel 200 kg Fuel tank capacity 23 500 kg Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 54 kg and LDM: + 57kg",
      "choices": [
        "9430 kg",
        "7956 kg",
        "9968 kg",
        "9940 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "9968 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using Flight Planning Manual MRJT 1 Figure 4.7.2 An aircraft on an extended range operation is required never to be more than 120 minutes from an alternate, based on 1 engine inoperative LRC conditions in ISA. Using the above table and a given mass of 40 000 kg at the most critical point, the maximum air distance to the relevant alternate is:",
      "choices": [
        "735 NM",
        "810 NM",
        "875 NM",
        "794 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "735 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following NOTAM, are you able to fly passengers into EUAD on a charter flight? Q) EGTT/QAZCA/IV/NBO/AE/000/022/5334N00021W003 A) EUAD B) FROM 15/12/08 0942 C) TO PERM E) AERODROME ATZ ACTIVE 0620-2115 DAILYAD OPEN, ATS AVBL, USE OF THE AD IS PRIOR PERMISSION REQUIRED 0620-0630 UTC FOR NON SKED MOVEMENTS EUAD AD 2.3 AND AD 2.17 REFER",
      "choices": [
        "Yes, but you need prior permission between 06:20-21:15.",
        "Yes, you can fly in at any time between 06:20-21:15 UTC daily.",
        "Yes, you can fly in at any time after 06:30 UTC, even though the airfield is open from 06:20.",
        "Yes, but you must file a flight plan before departing, at least two hours before the scheduled arrival time."
      ],
      "answer": "Yes, you can fly in at any time after 06:30 UTC, even though the airfield is open from 06:20."
    },
    {
      "question": "For pre-flight planning purposes what is the block fuel required? Assume the Basic Fuel Scheme WITHOUT variations applies. Taxi fuel: 350 kg Trip fuel: 85 000 kg Contingency fuel: 5% of the Trip fuel Final reserve fuel: 3000 kg Alternate fuel: 5500 kg Discretionary fuel: 1500 kg Extra fuel: 0 kg",
      "choices": [
        "98 100 kg",
        "99 600 kg",
        "99 250 kg",
        "95 350 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "99 600 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the ground speed? TAS: 150 kt Track: 090\u00b0 Wind: 050\u00b0/46 kt",
      "choices": [
        "128 kt",
        "160 kt",
        "188 kt",
        "112 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "112 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel to be uplifted. Maximum Zero Fuel Mass: 62731 kg Actual Zero Fuel Mass: 55031 kg Regulated Take-Off Mass: 76000 kg Maximum Landing Mass: 66360 kg Fuel Tank Capacity: 16000 kg Taxi Fuel: 240 kg Trip Fuel: 7931 kg Minimum Block Fuel: 16000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "4511 kg.",
        "4751 kg.",
        "Not able to carry Extra Fuel.",
        "7700 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "Not able to carry Extra Fuel."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the following NOTAM, what is the safe distance for a civilian aircraft? Q) EUAD/QSPLT/IV/BO/AE/000/021/5212N00011E003 A) EUAD B) FROM 16/02/09 0830 C) TO 16/02/09 1430 E) E BAND HIGH INTENSITY RADAR TRANSMISSION AREA (HIRTA) IN D304 RADIUS 1NMMAX HEIGHT 472FT AGLSAFE DISTANCES CIVILIAN ACFT 0.011NM 11FT AGL MIL ACFT VERY LOW 0.011NM 11FT AGL LOW 0.053NM 157FT AGL MEDIUM 0.077NM 242FT AGL HIGH 0.143NM 472FT AGL",
      "choices": [
        "0.011 NM",
        "0.143 NM",
        "472 ft",
        "1 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "0.011 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies from airport A to airport B, covering a total distance of 460 NM. After 1 h 11 min, it has covered a distance of 183 NM, and its remaining fuel is equal to 780 lb plus reserves. Determine the remaining fuel at airport B, assuming conditions remain the same and given: TAS: 185 kt Headwind: 30 kt Trip fuel: 1098 lb Fuel flow: 370 lb/h",
      "choices": [
        "235 lb + reserves",
        "385 lb + reserves",
        "119 lb + reserves",
        "299 lb + reserves"
      ],
      "answer": "299 lb + reserves"
    },
    {
      "question": "How much useable fuel should be on board at start-up given the following planning information: APU fuel flow 150 kg/h Taxi fuel flow 11 kg / minute APU time 38 minutes Taxi. 13 minutes Trip fuel (including contingency) 4250 kg Alternate and Final Reserve fuel 3730 kg",
      "choices": [
        "8100 kg",
        "7980 kg",
        "6568 kg",
        "8218 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "8218 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the time and distance given: FF 9.6 USG TAS 100 Wind 15 kts tail Actual fuel 50 USG",
      "choices": [
        "5:13 @ 598 NM",
        "5:20 @ 599 NM",
        "5:20 @ 512 NM",
        "5:13 @ 512 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "5:13 @ 598 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM 233 000 kg MLM 182 000 kg MZFM 170 000 kg DOM 122 550 kg Traffic Load 35 367 kg Trip Fuel 62 332 kg Planned T/O Fuel 67 885 kg Taxi Fuel 300 kg Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 394 kg and LDM: + 650 kg Fuel tank capacity 110 000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "12 751 kg",
        "6898 kg",
        "7198 kg",
        "18 530 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "7198 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM: 87 5000 lbs MLM: 65 2000 lbs MZFM: 55 5100 lbs DOM: 39 4100 lbs Traffic Load: 10 9350 lbs Trip Fuel: 28 9750 lbs Planned T/O Fuel: 31 5315 lbs Taxi Fuel: 1600 lbs Fuel burn correction per 1000lb of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 470lb and LDM: + 887lb Tank capacity: 37 7750 lbs",
      "choices": [
        "56 235 lbs",
        "54 635 lbs",
        "54 255 lbs",
        "72 235 lbs"
      ],
      "answer": "56 235 lbs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel to be uplifted. Maximum Zero Fuel Mass: 62731 kg, Actual Zero Fuel Mass: 55031 kg, Regulated Take-Off Mass: 76000 kg, Maximum Landing Mass: 66360 kg, Fuel Tank Capacity: 16000 kg, Taxi Fuel: 240 kg, Trip Fuel: 7931 kg, Minimum Block Fuel: 16000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "4511 kg.",
        "4751 kg.",
        "Not able to carry Extra Fuel.",
        "8000 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "Not able to carry Extra Fuel."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following NOTAM information, when can RWY 07R/25L be expected to be in operation? >>> EDDF FRANKFURT MAIN<<< SCHEDULE: DAILY 2200-0400 RWY 07R/25L CLSD.: NOTAM ED/A0675/16 RWY 25L TDZ SLIPPERY WHEN WET.: NOTAM ED/A0588/16 >>> END OF BULLETIN<<<",
      "choices": [
        "From the 22nd of the month to the 4th of the next month.",
        "Daily from 04:00 to 22:00.",
        "Daily from 22:00 to 04:00.",
        "From the 4th of the month to the 22nd of the month."
      ],
      "answer": "Daily from 04:00 to 22:00."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the following NOTAM, when can you expect the HENTON DVOR to come back into service? Q) EUAD/QNVAS/IV/BO/E/000/999/5221N00140W025 B) FROM 16/02/09 1130 C) TO 16/02/09 1530 E) HENTON DVOR/DME HEN FREQ 113.65 MHZ/CH 083Y, DVOR U/S",
      "choices": [
        "11:30 on the 9th February 2016.",
        "15:30 on the 9th February 2016.",
        "15:30 on the 2nd September 2016.",
        "11:30 on the 2nd September 2016."
      ],
      "answer": "15:30 on the 9th February 2016."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the following NOTAM, what is the safe distance for a civilian aircraft? Q) EUAD/QSPLT/IV/BO/AE/000/021/5212N00011E003 A) EUAD B) FROM 16/02/09 0830C) TO 16/02/09 1430 E) E BAND HIGH INTENSITY RADAR TRANSMISSION AREA (HIRTA) IN D304 RADIUS 1NMMAX HEIGHT 472FT AGLSAFE DISTANCES CIVILIAN ACFT 0.011NM 11FT AGL MIL ACFT VERY LOW 0.011NM 11FT AGL LOW 0.053NM 157FT AGL MEDIUM 0.077NM 242FT AGL HIGH 0.143NM 472FT AGL",
      "choices": [
        "0.011 NM",
        "0.143 NM",
        "472 ft",
        "1 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "0.011 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Trip Fuel for a jet aeroplane to fly from the departure aerodrome to the destination aerodrome is 5350 kg. Fuel consumption in holding mode is 6000 kg/hr The quantity of fuel which is needed to carry out one go-around and land on the alternate airfield is 4380 kg. The destination aerodrome has a single runway. What is the minimum quantity of fuel which should be on board at take-off?",
      "choices": [
        "11 730 kg",
        "13 000 kg",
        "14 730 kg",
        "13 230 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "13 230 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the ground speed of the aircraft? TAS: 300 kt, Heading: 090\u00b0, Wind: 330\u00b0/46 kt",
      "choices": [
        "330 kt",
        "320 kt",
        "325 kt",
        "280 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "325 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to Cap 697 Figure 4.6.1 Given a trip distance of 500 miles 50 kf tailwind, max cruising level of FL160, standard day and an estimated landing weight of 50 000 kg, what is the trip fuel and time for a gear-down ferry flight?",
      "choices": [
        "5250 kg - 1hr 36 min",
        "5350 kg - 1hr 26 min",
        "5900 kg - 1hr 26 min",
        "8900 kg - 2hr 24 min"
      ],
      "answer": "5250 kg - 1hr 36 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies from airport A to airport B, covering a total distance of 460 NM. After 1 h 11 min, it has covered a distance of 183 NM, and its remaining fuel is equal to 780 lb plus reserves. Determine the remaining fuel at airport B, assuming conditions remain the same and given: TAS: 185 kt, Headwind: 30 kt, Trip fuel: 1098 lb, Fuel flow: 370 lb/h",
      "choices": [
        "235 lb + reserves",
        "385 lb + reserves",
        "119 lb + reserves",
        "299 lb + reserves"
      ],
      "answer": "299 lb + reserves"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2. Routing from London Gatwick Airport, England to Paris Charles de Gaulle Airport, France via, GWC and DVL along route UN859 at FL250, what frequency would you contact, in the vicinity of DVL?",
      "choices": [
        "129.005 MHz",
        "134.410 MHz",
        "132.185 MHz",
        "128.870 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "129.005 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Use Flight planning Manual SEP 1 Figure 2.2 Table 2.2.3 Using the Power Setting Table, for the single engine aeroplane, determine the cruise TAS and fuel flow (lbs/hr) with full throttle and cruise lean mixture in the following conditions: Given: OAT: 13\u00b0C, Pressure altitude: 8000 ft, RPM: 2300",
      "choices": [
        "158 kt and 74.4 lbs/hr",
        "160 kt and 69.3 lbs/hr",
        "159 kt and 71.7 lbs/hr",
        "160 kt and 71.1 lbs/hr"
      ],
      "answer": "160 kt and 69.3 lbs/hr"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the time and distance given: FF 9.6 USG, TAS 100, Wind 15 kts tail, Actual fuel 50 USG",
      "choices": [
        "5:13 @ 598 NM",
        "5:20 @ 599 NM",
        "5:20 @ 512 NM",
        "5:13 @ 512 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "5:13 @ 598 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, assuming conditions stay the same, what is the ETA at DELTA? BETA to GAMMA distance: 60 NM, Actual time en-route: 30 min, Actual lime of arrival at GAMMA: 1240 UTC, GAMMA to DELTA distance: 34 NM",
      "choices": [
        "12:57 UTC",
        "12:37 UTC",
        "13:07 UTC",
        "12:47 UTC"
      ],
      "answer": "12:57 UTC"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft at FL 120, IAS 200 kt, OAT -5\u00b0C and wind component +30 kt, is required to reduce speed in order to cross a reporting point 5 MIN later than planned. Assuming flight conditions do not change, when 100 NM from the reporting point IAS should be reduced to:",
      "choices": [
        "165 kt",
        "169 kt",
        "174 kt",
        "159 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "159 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following NOTAM information, what RADAR and TOWER frequency should be used by departing aircraft at 2100 UTC? >>> EGLF (FARNBOROUGH) <<< DUE TO WIP TAXIWAY ZULU IS CLOSED NOTAM EG/C0697/16 SCHEDULE MON-FRI 0700-0800 2000- 2200, SAT-SUN 0800-0900,1830-2200 FARNBOROUGH RADAR AND TOWER MAY BE PROVIDED AS A COMBINED SERVICE WITH COUPLED FREQUENCIES INBOUND AIRCRAFT SHOULD CONTACT FARNBOROUGH RADAR ON 134.350MHZ OUTBOUND AIRCRAFT SHOULD CONTACT FARNBOROUGH TOWER ON 122.500MHZ NOTAM",
      "choices": [
        "122.500 MHz.",
        "RADAR frequency as specified on the chart.",
        "TOWER frequency as specified on the chart.",
        "134.350 MHz."
      ],
      "answer": "122.500 MHz."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM 233 000 kg, MLM 182 000 kg, MZFM 170 000 kg, DOM 122 550 kg, Traffic Load 35 367 kg, Trip Fuel 62 332 kg, Planned T/O Fuel 67 885 kg, Taxi Fuel 300 kg, Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 394 kg and LDM: + 650 kg, Fuel tank capacity 110 000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "12 751 kg",
        "6898 kg",
        "7198 kg",
        "18 530 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "7198 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft takes-off from an airport 2 hours before sunset. The pilot flies a track of 090\u00b0 (T), W/V 130\u00b0 /20 kt, TAS 100 kt. In order to return to the point of departure before sunset, the furthest distance which may be travelled is:",
      "choices": [
        "105 NM",
        "84 NM",
        "97 NM",
        "115 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "97 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the following NOTAM, what is the maximum height of the balloon involved? Q) EUAD/QWCLW/IV/M/W/000/004/5339N00135W001 A) EUAD B) FROM: 15/12/14 13:48C) TO: 16/03/06 18:30 E) UNMANNED CAPTIVE BALLOON IN LOW FLYING AREA AVOIDANCE AREA WI 1 NM RADIUS. MAX HEIGHT 200FT AGL/324FT AMSL. 15/12/06/0PSLF. LOWER: Surface, UPPER: 324 Feet AMSL SCHEDULE: DEC 14 1348-1600, DEC 15-31 0700-1600, JAN 01-31 0700-1630, FEB 01-29 0700-1730, MAR 01-06 0600-1830",
      "choices": [
        "324 feet AMSL.",
        "200 feet AMSL.",
        "The height is variable.",
        "324 feet AGL."
      ],
      "answer": "324 feet AMSL."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM: 87 5000 lbs, MLM: 65 2000 lbs, MZFM: 55 5100 lbs, DOM: 39 4100 lbs, Traffic Load: 10 9350 lbs, Trip Fuel: 28 9750 lbs, Planned T/O Fuel: 31 5315 lbs, Taxi Fuel: 1600 lbs, Fuel burn correction per 1000lb of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 470lb and LDM: + 887lb, Tank capacity: 37 7750 lbs",
      "choices": [
        "56 235 lbs",
        "54 635 lbs",
        "54 255 lbs",
        "72 235 lbs"
      ],
      "answer": "56 235 lbs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 165 NM, True track 055\u00b0, W/V 360/20, TAS 105 kt. What is the distance of the PET from the departure point?",
      "choices": [
        "132 NM",
        "73 NM",
        "83 NM",
        "92 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "92 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given : Taxi Fuel = 150 kg, Trip time = 2hrs, Alternate = 1200 kg, Extra Fuel = 350 kg, Holding Fuel Flow = 2500 kg/hr, Trip Fuel flow = 3100 kg/hr. Find the Block Fuel.",
      "choices": [
        "9466 kg",
        "9460 kg",
        "9640 kg",
        "9115 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "9460 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "How much useable fuel should be on board at start-up given the following planning information: APU fuel flow 150 kg/h, Taxi fuel flow 11 kg / minute, APU time 38 minutes, Taxi. 13 minutes, Trip fuel (including contingency) 4250 kg, Alternate and Final Reserve fuel 3730 kg",
      "choices": [
        "7980 kg",
        "8100 kg",
        "6568 kg",
        "8218 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "8218 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following data, what is the maximum extra fuel that may be uplifted? Maximum Zero Fuel Mass: 155 000 kg Maximum Take-off Mass: 210 000 kg Maximum Landing Mass: 175 000 kg Planned ZFM: 155 000 kg Take-off Fuel: 48 600 kg Trip Fuel: 42 500 kg Fuel tank capacity = 65 000 litres. Jet Fuel A-1 Specific Gravity = 0.82. Each 1000 kg extra in mass incurs fuel penalty values of: TOM: +260 kg LDM: +370 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "13 900 kg.",
        "4700 kg.",
        "6400 kg.",
        "5720 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "4700 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2 and the image above. You are due to fly a VVIP flight from Doncaster Sheffield Airport, England (EGCN) - N53 28 W001 00' - to Dublin Airport, Ireland ((EIDW), departing EGCN at 21.05 UTC and routing via UPTON, L975, L70, V14 and DUB. Planned ETO at UPTON is 21.10 UTC and average planned GS is 296 kt. Approach to landing from DUB to touchdown is 8 minutes. METAR W/V at EIDW = 290/40 (no forecast changes) Aircraft maximum crosswind component = 25 kt A take-off delay means your ETO at UPTON is 21.15. What is your best course of action (from the following options)?",
      "choices": [
        "Cancel the flight.",
        "Land on runway 28 (no distance limitations).",
        "Land on runway 34 (no distance limitations).",
        "Increase average GS to 325 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "Increase average GS to 325 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 150 NM, Safe Endurance 2.4 h, True Track 250, W/V 280/15, TAS 120 kt. What is the distance of the PSR from the departure point??",
      "choices": [
        "71 NM",
        "98 NM",
        "83 NM",
        "142 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "142 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following NOTAM information, what changes apply to NDB CF? NEW TODAY TIL 1603312359 NDB REMAINS CF 367KHZ FROM 0000 TO 0900 NDB CF 367KHZ BECOMES ASM 367KHZ FROM 0900 TO 2359 REF TRIGGER NOTAM PERM AIRAC AIP AMDT 04/16 : NOTAM LF/F0403/16 >>> END OF BULLETIN <<<",
      "choices": [
        "NDB CF identifier changes to \"ASM\u00b7 at 09:00 UTC, and changes back to \"CF\" after 00:00 UTC.",
        "NDB CF frequency changes to 367 kHz at 09:00 UTC on the given date.",
        "NDB CF identifier changes from \"CF\" to \"ASM\" at 23:59 UTC on the given date.",
        "NDB CF identifier changes from \"CF\" to \"ASM\" at 09:00 UTC on the given date."
      ],
      "answer": "NDB CF identifier changes from \"CF\" to \"ASM\" at 09:00 UTC on the given date."
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight Planning Manual MRJT 1 Figure 4.3.5. What is the Trip Fuel? Given: Temperature ISA +15\u00b0C, Brake release mass 62 000 kg, Trip time 5 hrs 20 min",
      "choices": [
        "13 000 kg",
        "13 800 kg",
        "13 500 kg",
        "13 200 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "13 500 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance A to B 2346 NM, Ground speed OUT 365 kt, Ground speed BACK 480 kt. The time from A to the point of equal time (PET) between A and B is:",
      "choices": [
        "260 min.",
        "197 min.",
        "219 min.",
        "167 min."
      ],
      "answer": "219 min."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 4.6.1. Given a trip distance of 500 miles, 50 kt tailwind, max cruising level of FL160, standard day and an estimated landing weight of 50 000 kg, what is the trip fuel and time for a gear-down ferry flight?",
      "choices": [
        "8900 kg - 2hr 24 min",
        "5900 kg - 1hr 26 min",
        "5250 kg - 1hr 26 min",
        "5350 kg - 1hr 39 min"
      ],
      "answer": "5350 kg - 1hr 39 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "With 3.5 hours total endurance on board, and a wind velocity of 270\u00b0/20 kt, a pilot has to travel over a distance of 200 NM on a track of 270\u00b0T. If the TAS is 100 kt and the pilot must land with 30 minutes worth of fuel on board, what is the distance to the Point of Safe Return PSR, and how long will it take to get there?",
      "choices": [
        "160 NM and 120 minutes.",
        "144 NM and 108 minutes.",
        "96 NM and 72 minutes.",
        "107 NM and 80 minutes."
      ],
      "answer": "144 NM and 108 minutes."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Plate AMSTERDAM (Schipol) 10-2B. You recover via MOLIX, LUTEX and ROBVI and then hold for 20 mins. TAS 250 kt Nil Wind, Fuel flow in cruise 3000 kg /h, Holding fuel flow 2400 kg / h. How much fuel do you burn between MOLIX and leaving the hold to commence the procedure?",
      "choices": [
        "1250 kg",
        "1160 kg",
        "1650 kg",
        "1760 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "1250 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following Information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel to be uplifted. Maximum Zero Fuel Mass MZFM: 2000 kg, Actual Zero Fuel Mass AZFM: 2000 kg, Regulated Take-Off Mass RTOM: 3000 kg, Maximum Landing Mass MLM: 2200 kg, Fuel Tank Capacity: 550 kg, Trip Fuel TF: 190 kg, Minimum Block Fuel (BF): 300 kg",
      "choices": [
        "Not able to carry Extra Fuel.",
        "250 kg.",
        "90 kg.",
        "60 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "90 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Distance from A to B is 1000 NM, All engine TAS is 400 kt, Engine failure TAS is 350 kt, Wind component between A and PET is a 50 kt tailwind and wind component between PET to B is a 30 kt tailwind. What is the distance and time to the engine failure PET from A?",
      "choices": [
        "479 NM, 64 min.",
        "441 NM, 66 min.",
        "441 NM, 59 min.",
        "427 NM, 57 min."
      ],
      "answer": "441 NM, 59 min."
    },
    {
      "question": "For pre-flight planning purposes what is the block fuel required? Assume the Basic Fuel Scheme WITHOUT variations applies. Taxi fuel: 350 kg, Trip fuel: 85 000 kg, Contingency fuel: 5% of the Trip fuel, Final reserve fuel: 3000 kg, Alternate fuel: 5500 kg, Discretionary fuel: 1500 kg, Extra fuel: 0 kg",
      "choices": [
        "98 100 kg",
        "99 600 kg",
        "99 250 kg",
        "95 350 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "99 600 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2 and any other relevant data, answer the following questions for an approach to land at Stuttgart Airport, Germany (EDDS): For a straight-in landing on RWY 07, what is the CAT II ILS DH?",
      "choices": [
        "91 ft",
        "1367 ft",
        "50 ft",
        "100 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "100 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot is calculating the Take-Off Distance for a Performance Class B multi-engined aeroplane. Specific factors must be applied to the AFM data to take into account variables that affect the takeoff performance. These factors have NOT been provided in the AFM and other performance and operating manuals from the manufacturer. For which variables must the pilot apply a factor greater than 1.0?",
      "choices": [
        "Surface type: grass, Condition: wet or dry.",
        "Surface type: paved or grass, Condition: wet.",
        "Surface type: paved, Condition: wet.",
        "Surface type: paved, Condition: dry."
      ],
      "answer": "Surface type: grass, Condition: wet or dry."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM 233 000 kg, MLM 182 000 kg, MZFM 170 000 kg, DOM 122 550 kg, Traffic Load 43 217 kg, Trip Fuel 45 854 kg, Planned T/O Fuel 51 616 kg, Taxi Fuel 300 kg, Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 394 kg and LDM: + 650 kg, Fuel tank capacity 110 000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "1047 kg",
        "4233 kg",
        "14 596 kg",
        "15 617 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "15 617 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "When calculating the fuel required to carry out a given flight, one must take into account: 1 - the wind, 2 - foreseeable airborne delays, 3 - other weather forecasts, 4 - any foreseeable conditions which may delay landing. The combination which provides the correct statement is:",
      "choices": [
        "1, 2, 3, 4",
        "2025-01-03 00:00:00",
        "2025-02-04 00:00:00",
        "2003-01-02 00:00:00"
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 3, 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following NOTAM information, when can the aerodrome be expected to be operating on Tuesday? >>> LKPD (PARDUBICE) <<< AD OPR HR CHANGED MON-FRI 0700-1830 SAT 0700-1800 SUN 0700-1830 NOTAM LK/B1453/15 >>> END-OF-BULLETIN <<<",
      "choices": [
        "07:00 \u2013 18:00 LT",
        "07:00 \u2013 18:00 UTC",
        "07:00 \u2013 18:30 UTC",
        "07:00 \u2013 18:30 LT"
      ],
      "answer": "07:00 \u2013 18:30 UTC"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are due to fly an METP freight aircraft from A to B. The aircraft requires each wing tank to be refuelled individually. Total usable fuel = 800 litres of JET-A1 in each wing tank. The aircraft fuel gauges are calibrated in US Gallons and show that there is already 45 US Gal in the port wing tank and 60 US Gal in the starboard wing tank. The moment arm in the aircraft mass & balance documentation is stated in lbs/in and the fuel bowser is calibrated in litres. What total fuel uplift must the crew request from the fueller and what mass of fuel must be entered into the mass & balance calculation? JET-A1 specific gravity = 0.80.",
      "choices": [
        "1200 ltr & 2120 lb",
        "1200 ltr & 960 lb",
        "1125 ltr & 2040 lb",
        "1125 ltr & 900 lb"
      ],
      "answer": "1200 ltr & 2120 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aeroplane with reciprocating engines is planning to depart for an isolated destination Aerodrome as a Commercial Air Transport operation. Calculate the minimum amount of fuel required (to the nearest 10 kg), when overhead the isolated aerodrome, considering the following details. Flight time: 2 hours and 30 minutes, Top of climb to top of descent time: 2 hours, Normal fuel consumption cruise: 780 kg per hour",
      "choices": [
        "540 kg",
        "760 kg",
        "1440 kg",
        "820 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "820 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flying at 7500 ft is cleared to descend to be level at 1 000 ft, 6 NM before reaching a beacon. If ground speed is 156 kt and Rate of Descent is 800 ft/min, how many miles before the beacon should descent begin?",
      "choices": [
        "11.1 NM",
        "27.1 NM",
        "15.0 NM",
        "30.2 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "27.1 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)1. A route is planned between FLESLAND VOR/DME (N60 20' E005 20') and MYGEGENAES NDB (N62 03' W007 16') along N623 and G3. TAS = 390 kt. ETO at FLS is 09.24 UTC, with a planned ETO at MY of 10.36 UTC. Reporting at VALDI at 09.52, what is the revised ETO at MY?",
      "choices": [
        "10.43 UTC",
        "10.35 UTC",
        "10.26 UTC",
        "10.30 UTC"
      ],
      "answer": "10.30 UTC"
    },
    {
      "question": "After flying for 16 min at 100 kt TAS with a 20 kt tailwind component, you have to return to the airfield of departure. You will arrive after (Note include a standard rate turn of 3\u00b0 /sec in your calculations):",
      "choices": [
        "21 min",
        "25 min",
        "17 min.",
        "11 min 40 sec"
      ],
      "answer": "25 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is in cruising flight at FL095, GS 155 kt. The pilot intends to descend at 500 ft/min to arrive overhead the MAN VOR at 2000 FT (QNH 1030 hPa). The TAS remains constant in the descent, wind is negligible, temperature standard. At what distance from MAN should the pilot commence the descent?",
      "choices": [
        "48 NM",
        "38 NM",
        "41 NM",
        "45 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "41 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. Maximum Ramp Mass 77 500 kg, MTOM 77000 kg MLM 66 360 kg, MZFM 62720 kg DOM 42 845 kg, Traffic Load 17460 kg, Planned T/O Fuel 10 365 kg, Trip Fuel 7890 kg, Taxi Fuel 195 kg, Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 135 kg and LDM: + 156 kg, Fuel tank capacity 21 000 kg",
      "choices": [
        "3580 kg",
        "6330 kg",
        "2415 kg",
        "4139 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "4139 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2 and CAP 697, Fig. 4.2. You are tasked with making an urgent freight delivery between Knock Airport, Republic of Ireland (EIKN) and Edinburgh Airport, Scotland (EGPH), routing via the BELFAST VOR/DME (BEL). The Brake Release Weight is 62 500 kg. Outside air temperature is ISA +25\u00b0C. What is the short distance cruise altitude?",
      "choices": [
        "30 000 ft.",
        "24 000 ft.",
        "28 000 ft.",
        "26 000 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "28 000 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "An MRJT aircraft is flying with its landing gear down. How will the aircraft's performance be affected?",
      "choices": [
        "There will be a medium reduction on performance owing to a limited increase in both lift and drag which has a medium effect on routes and altitudes.",
        "There will be a large reduction in performance owing to a significant increase in drag which has a negative effect on routes and altitudes.",
        "There will be no effect on performance as modern engines and airframes are designed to accommodate such events.",
        "There will be a small reduction on performance owing to a limited increase in drag which has a negligible effect on routes and altitudes."
      ],
      "answer": "There will be a large reduction in performance owing to a significant increase in drag which has a negative effect on routes and altitudes."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 4.6.1. Given a trip distance of 300 miles, 100 kt headwind, max cruising level of FL200, standard day and an estimated landing weight of 55 000 kg, what is the trip fuel and time for a gear-down ferry flight?",
      "choices": [
        "4100 kg - 1 hr 45 min",
        "5600 kg - 1 hr 45 min",
        "2500 kg - 0 hr 51 min",
        "6250 kg - 1 hr 45 min"
      ],
      "answer": "6250 kg - 1 hr 45 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination: 950 NM, Safe Endurance: 3.5 h, TAS: 360 kt, Ground Speed Out: 320 kt, Ground Speed Home: 400 kt. What is the distance and time of the PSR from the departure point?",
      "choices": [
        "Distance: 622 NM Time: 117 min",
        "Distance: 328 NM Time: 62 min",
        "Distance: 311 NM Time: 52 min",
        "Distance: 528 NM Time: 79 min"
      ],
      "answer": "Distance: 622 NM Time: 117 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)1 and CAP 697, Figure 4.5.1. An aircraft is departing Fagernes airport, Norway (N61\u00b000' E009\u00b015') and climbs to an initial cruising altitude of FL250. OAT = ISA -5\u00b0C. QNH = 1003 hPa. Given a brake release weight of 56 000 kg and a 40 kt tailwind component, what is the time, fuel, ground distance and TAS for the climb?",
      "choices": [
        "10 min, 925 kg, 56 NM, 349 kt.",
        "10 min, 1000 kg, 50 NM, 349 kt.",
        "9 min, 900 kg, 39 NM, 339 kt.",
        "9 min, 825 kg, 35 NM, 339 kt."
      ],
      "answer": "10 min, 925 kg, 56 NM, 349 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "During a VFR flight at a navigational checkpoint the remaining usable fuel in tanks is 60 US gallons. The reserve fuel is 12 US gallons. According to the flight plan the remaining flight time is 1h35min. Calculate the highest acceptable rate of consumption possible for the rest of the trip.",
      "choices": [
        "30.3 US gallons/hour",
        "33.0 US gallons/hour",
        "37.9 US gallons/hour",
        "21.3 US gallons/hour"
      ],
      "answer": "30.3 US gallons/hour"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given A to B: 2050 NM, Mean ground speed there 440 kt, Mean ground speed back 540 kt. The distance to the point of equal time PET between A & B is:",
      "choices": [
        "1025 NM",
        "1130 NM",
        "1153 NM",
        "920 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "1130 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. MTOM 85 000 kg, MLM 75 500 kg, MZFM 71 420 kg, DOM 48 000 kg, Traffic Load 15 464 kg, Trip Fuel 2561 kg, Planned T/O Fuel 5167 kg, Taxi Fuel 200 kg, Fuel tank capacity 23 500 kg, Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 54 kg and LDM: + 57kg",
      "choices": [
        "9430 kg",
        "7956 kg",
        "9968 kg",
        "9940 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "9968 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using Flight Planning Manual MRJT 1 Figure 4.7.2. An aircraft on an extended range operation is required never to be more than 120 minutes from an alternate, based on 1 engine inoperative LRC conditions in ISA. Using the above table and a given mass of 40 000 kg at the most critical point, the maximum air distance to the relevant alternate is:",
      "choices": [
        "735 NM",
        "810 NM",
        "875 NM",
        "794 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "735 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following NOTAM information, when can the aerodrome be expected to be operating on Tuesday? >>> LKPD PARDUBICE <<< AD OPR HR CHANGED: MON-FRI 0700-1830 SAT 0700-1800 SUN 0700-1830:NOTAM LK/B1453/15 >>> END OF BULLETIN<<<",
      "choices": [
        "07:00 - 18:00 UTC",
        "07:00 - 18:30 LT",
        "07:00 - 18:30 UTC",
        "07:00 - 18:00 UTC"
      ],
      "answer": "07:00 - 18:30 UTC"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying at Mach .84 at FL330. The static air temperature is -48 degrees Celsius and the headwind component 52 kt. At 13.38 UTC the controller requests the pilot to cross the meridian of 030W at 1500 UTC. The distance to go is 570 NM. What should be the reduced Mach number?",
      "choices": [
        "0.76",
        "0.74",
        "0.84",
        "0.8"
      ],
      "answer": "0.8"
    },
    {
      "question": "The commander decides to increase the Block Fuel by 1200 kg due to an expected holding at the destination aerodrome as this equates to approximately 30 minutes of holding. After take-off, the FMS indicates that there is only 27 minutes of extra holding fuel despite the payload being as originally planned. What is the reason for this?",
      "choices": [
        "The Extra Fuel has made the aeroplane heavier, thus the Trip fuel is increased.",
        "The Flight is NOT following its original route and shortcuts increase the Trip Fuel.",
        "The FMC gives inaccurate results of calculations and therefore it cannot be relied on.",
        "There is a stronger tailwind component than planned, leading to an increase of Trip Fuel."
      ],
      "answer": "The Extra Fuel has made the aeroplane heavier, thus the Trip fuel is increased."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 2450 NM, Safe Endurance 7.5 h, TAS 410 kt, Ground Speed Out 360 kt, Ground Speed Home 460 kt. What is the time of the PSR from the departure point in minutes?",
      "choices": [
        "198 min",
        "111 min",
        "252 min",
        "156 min"
      ],
      "answer": "252 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "With respect to the optimum altitude, which of the following statements is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "An aeroplane sometimes flies above or below the optimum altitude because optimum altitude increases continuously during flight.",
        "An aeroplane flies most of the time above the optimum altitude because this yields the most economic result.",
        "An aeroplane always flies below the optimum altitude, because Mach buffet might occur.",
        "An aeroplane always flies at the optimum altitude because this is economically seen as the most attractive altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "An aeroplane sometimes flies above or below the optimum altitude because optimum altitude increases continuously during flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)4 and CAP 697, Figure 4.5.3.1. An aircraft crosses NANTES ATLANTIQUE VOR/DME (NTS) (N42\u00b010' W001\u00b035') at FL 300 and at LRC speed, with an aircraft mass of 48 600 kg, en-route along A25 to BORDEAUX VOR/DME (BMC). Given a 50 kt tailwind and ISA +10\u00b0C, what is the fuel required between NTS and BMC?",
      "choices": [
        "795 kg.",
        "850 kg.",
        "1280 kg.",
        "705 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "705 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2 and any other relevant data, answer the following questions for an approach to land at Stuttgart Airport, Germany (EDDS): For the RNP RWY 07 approach. what is the minimum ground visibility for aircraft greater than 5.7 mt MTOW?",
      "choices": [
        "1500 m",
        "5000 ft",
        "4000 m",
        "2400 m"
      ],
      "answer": "4000 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "A jet aeroplane equipped with old engines has a specific fuel consumption of 0.06 kg per Newton of thrust and per hour and, in a given flying condition, a fuel mileage of 14 kg per Nautical Miles. In the same flying conditions, the same aeroplane equipped with modern engines with a specific fuel consumption of 0.035 kg per Newton of thrust and per hour, has a fuel mileage of:",
      "choices": [
        "11.7 kg/NM.",
        "14 kg/NM.",
        "10.7 kg/NM.",
        "8.17 kg/NM."
      ],
      "answer": "8.17 kg/NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the remaining fuel in litres : ETO ATO Planned Fuel (L) Actual 1. 10:02 10:00 133 137 2. 10:10 10:08 126 130 3. 10:32",
      "choices": [
        "111 L",
        "105 L",
        "109 L",
        "107 L"
      ],
      "answer": "111 L"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the ground speed? TAS: 150 kt, Track: 090\u00b0, Wind: 050\u00b0/46 kt",
      "choices": [
        "128 kt",
        "188 kt",
        "112 kt",
        "160 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "112 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to the LRJT 1 Integrated Cruise table. A turbojet aircraft is flying using the following data: TOM: 155 400 kg; Planned cruise at FL 330; LRC; Standard Atmosphere (ISA); CG: 37 %. What flight time will be required to cover an air distance of 2350 NM?",
      "choices": [
        "1 hr 28 min",
        "8 hr 51 min",
        "7 hr 23 min",
        "5 hr 58 min"
      ],
      "answer": "5 hr 58 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697, Fig. 4.1 Optimum Altitude. With a brake release weight of 52 000 kg, and using the M 0.74 cruise reference, what is the optimum pressure altitude?",
      "choices": [
        "37 000 ft.",
        "34 000 ft",
        "35 000 ft.",
        "36 000 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "36 000 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Maximum allowable take-off mass: 64 400 kg, Maximum landing mass: 56 200 kg, Maximum zero fuel mass: 53 000 kg, Dry operating mass: 35 500 kg, Traffic load: 14 500 kg, Trip fuel: 4900 kg, Minimum Take-off Fuel: 7400 kg. Find maximum allowable take-off fuel:",
      "choices": [
        "11 400 kg",
        "11 100 kg",
        "8600 kg",
        "14 400 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "11 100 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2 An aircraft crosses CRK VOR/DME at FL80 at 15.42 UTC, en-route along route P2 to STU VOR/DME, at a GS of 260 kt. The aircraft's ETO at NEXAT is 15.59 UTC. What is the revised GS to maintain the ETO overhead STU?",
      "choices": [
        "285 kt",
        "249 kt",
        "302 kt",
        "260 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "249 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)1. A route is planned between MYGEGENAES NDB (N62 03' W007 16') and FLESLAND VOR/DME (N60 20' E005 20') along N623 and G3. Mach No = 0.73 Pressure Altitude = FL 250 OAT = ISA-10\u00b0C Forecast W/V = 220\u00b0/80 Fuel flow is 1250 kg/hr Fuel SG = 0.82 Fuel cost = \u00a30.85 per litre What is the fuel cost difference, which results from accepting a higher flight level at FL290 (OAT = ISA -5\u00b0C) with a reported wind of 250/120?",
      "choices": [
        "-\u00a3127.00",
        "+\u00a385.00",
        "-\u00a385.00",
        "+\u00a3127.00"
      ],
      "answer": "-\u00a3127.00"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the pre flight preparation, the pilot calculates an amount of 27.5 US gallons for refuelling, which equals to:",
      "choices": [
        "104 litres.",
        "7 litres.",
        "125 litres.",
        "6 litres."
      ],
      "answer": "104 litres."
    },
    {
      "question": "The planned flight time between two waypoints is 25 minutes, and the distance is 30 NM. During the actual flight, the flight time between these waypoints is found to be 32 minutes. How much lower is the actual groundspeed compared to the one that has been used for planning?",
      "choices": [
        "26 kt",
        "19 kt",
        "10 kt",
        "16 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "16 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)14. Your charter holiday aircraft is routing from UK over Italy via ARA (Araxos) VOR/DME (N38\u00b0 10\u2019 E021\u00b0 26\u2019) along L612, via TRL (Tripolis) VOR/DME (N37\u00b0 25\u2019 E022\u00b0 20\u2019), along J65 via SUD (Souda) VOR/DME (N35\u00b0 32\u2019 E024\u00b0 10\u2019) to IRA (Iraklion) VOR/DME (N35\u00b0 21\u2019 E025\u00b0 12\u2019), to land at Nikos Kazantzakis International Airport, Crete. On approaching ARA along N604, Athens Control clears you \u201cdirect own navigation from TRL to IRA, maintain FL80 until advised\u201d. Given a CAS of 210 kt, and W/V of 260\u00b0/30 at FL80 (OAT ISA +30\u00b0C) calculate the revised magnetic heading, groundspeed and ETE from TRL to IRA.",
      "choices": [
        "132\u00b0M, 231 kt, 41 min",
        "140\u00b0M, 250 kt, 40 min",
        "132\u00b0M, 269 kt, 41 min",
        "136\u00b0M, 231 kt, 42 min"
      ],
      "answer": "132\u00b0M, 269 kt, 41 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 220 NM, True track 175\u00b0, W/V 220/10, TAS 135 kts. What is the distance of the PET from the departure point?",
      "choices": [
        "116 NM",
        "103 NM",
        "110 NM",
        "136 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "116 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP697 MRJT Figure 4.3.1c. Trip distance 1900 nm, 50 kt tailwind, estimated landing weight 50 000 kg, cruise at FL220, ISA -10\u00b0C. What is the trip fuel and time?",
      "choices": [
        "14 800 kg and 5 hrs 36 mins",
        "9500 kg and 4 hrs 6 mins",
        "12 000 kg and 4 hrs 27 mins",
        "12 000 kg and 4 hrs 45 mins"
      ],
      "answer": "12 000 kg and 4 hrs 27 mins"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following equations is correct for solving the relationship between nautical air miles and nautical ground miles?",
      "choices": [
        "GS = (TAS x NAM) \u00f7 NGM",
        "NGM = (TAS x NAM) \u00f7 GS",
        "TAS = GS x (NAM \u00f7 NGM)",
        "NAM = (NGM x GS) \u00f7 TAS"
      ],
      "answer": "TAS = GS x (NAM \u00f7 NGM)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Distance from departure to destination 260 NM, Safe Endurance 4.1 h, True Track 150 W/V 100/30, TAS 110 kt. What is the distance of the PSR from the departure point?",
      "choices": [
        "154 NM",
        "47 NM",
        "107 NM",
        "213 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "213 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are due to fly an MEP freight aircraft from X to Y. The aircraft requires each wing tank to be refuelled individually. Total fuel required is 148 US Gallons of Avgas. There is already 120 lb in the port wing tank and 140 lb in the starboard wing tank. What total fuel uplift must the crew request from the fueller? Avgas specific gravity = 0.72.",
      "choices": [
        "86.5 US Gals",
        "395 litres",
        "104 Imp Gals",
        "328 litres"
      ],
      "answer": "395 litres"
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to a drive failure, the slats of a transport category aircraft do not retract properly after take-off. Based on the flight planning data given below, calculate the time penalty in per cent for the flight, based on endurance. Usable fuel 8540 kg, Fuel consumption 2600 kg/h, Final reserve fuel 1100 kg (Note: consider 60% fuel penalty for flap/slat failure and 180% for gear retraction failure)",
      "choices": [
        "0.64",
        "0.6",
        "0.37",
        "0.51"
      ],
      "answer": "0.37"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft takes 14 minutes to climb to FL290 covering 71 NAM, what is the ground distanced covered in a 30 kt headwind?",
      "choices": [
        "64 NGM",
        "71 NGM",
        "57 NGM",
        "78 NGM"
      ],
      "answer": "64 NGM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the required fuel for an aircraft on a commercial VFR flight with reciprocating engines, given: Fuel Flow: 120 kg/h, Trip Time: 4 h 39 min, No alternate selected and good weather expected.",
      "choices": [
        "558 kg",
        "706 kg",
        "586 kg",
        "676 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "706 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "An MRJT aircraft is flying with its landing gear down. Complete the following: There will be _____ drag.",
      "choices": [
        "significant",
        "minor",
        "none",
        "moderate"
      ],
      "answer": "significant"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 4.7.3 Given, a distance of 800 nm from the diversion point to the alternate, a 50 kt headwind, a weight of 40 000 kg at the point of diversion, a stabilisation level of FL 260 and ISA+20\u00b0C conditions; what is the fuel required and the time to arrive at the diversion?",
      "choices": [
        "4500 kg & 2 hr 30 min",
        "6500 kg & 2 hr 30 min",
        "6500 kg & 2 hr 39 min",
        "5400 kg & 2 hr 39 min"
      ],
      "answer": "4500 kg & 2 hr 30 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "An MRJT aircraft is flying with its landing gear down. Complete the following: The _____ performance has a _____ effect on routes and altitudes.",
      "choices": [
        "reduced; negative",
        "reduced; positive",
        "improved; negative",
        "improved; possitive"
      ],
      "answer": "reduced; negative"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to IFR Chart E(HI)1. Your aircraft is routing from Newcastle, England (EGNT) to Keflavik, Iceland via route L602 - TLA VOR/DME - route UL613 - BAMRA - UP61. ETO TLA VOR/DME = 11.25 UTC, ETO BAMRA = 12.15 UTC. 5 nm before VADNO (N57\u00b0 27\u2019 W003\u00b0 38\u2019), ATC instructs a speed change: \u201cReduce speed, cross BAMRA not before 12.17 UTC\u201d. What is the required reduction in groundspeed?",
      "choices": [
        "15 kt",
        "25 kt",
        "10 kt",
        "20 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "20 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following NOTAM, are you able to fly passengers into EUAD on a charter flight? Q) EGTT/QAZCA/IV/NBO/AE/000/022/5334N00021W003 A) EUAD B) FROM 15/12/08 0942 C) TO PERM E) AERODROME ATZ ACTIVE 0620-2115 DAILYAD OPEN, ATS AVBL, USE OF THE AD IS PRIOR PERMISSION REQUIRED 0620-0630 UTC FOR NON SKED MOVEMENTSEUAD AD 2.3 AND AD 2.17 REFER",
      "choices": [
        "Yes, but you must file a flight plan before departing, at least two hours before the scheduled arrival time.",
        "Yes, but you need prior permission between 06:20-21:15.",
        "Yes, you can fly in at any time after 06:30 UTC, even though the airfield is open from 06:20.",
        "Yes, you can fly in at any time between 06:20-21:15 UTC daily."
      ],
      "answer": "Yes, you can fly in at any time after 06:30 UTC, even though the airfield is open from 06:20."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to the LRJT 1 Integrated Cruise table. A turbojet aeroplane is flying using the following data: Flight level FL 330, Long Range (LR) cruise, Mass of 160 000 kg, Temperature: ISA, Head wind component: 120 kt, Remaining flight time: 4h 30 min Referring to the image above. Which of the following correctly indicates the ground distance remaining?",
      "choices": [
        "1447 NGM",
        "1328 NGM",
        "2408 NGM",
        "1868 NGM"
      ],
      "answer": "1328 NGM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figures 4.7.1a & 4.7.1b Given a distance of 800 nm to the diversion from the critical point, a 50 kt headwind, a weight of 50 000 kg at the critical point, ISA conditions and no icing; calculate the critical fuel reserve required.",
      "choices": [
        "7800 kg",
        "6300 kg",
        "8100 kg",
        "6000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "8100 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft was over A at 1435 hours flying direct to B. Given: Distance A to B 2900 NM, True airspeed 470 kt, Mean wind component OUT +55 kt, Mean wind component BACK -75 kt. The ETA for reaching the point of equal time (PET) between A and B is:",
      "choices": [
        "17:21:00",
        "17:44:00",
        "18:46:00",
        "16:57:00"
      ],
      "answer": "16:57:00"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the following NOTAM, what time does the Tower close on Saturdays in winter? AMEND AD HR WINTER MON-FRI 0815-1215, 1315-1730 SAT 0815-1230 SUMMER MON-SAT 0700-1730APP/TWR WINTER MON-FRI 0815-1215, 1315-1730 SAT 0815-1215 SUMMER MON-SAT 0700-1800.",
      "choices": [
        "12:15:00",
        "12:30:00",
        "18:00:00",
        "17:30:00"
      ],
      "answer": "12:15:00"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to the LRJT 1 Integrated Cruise table. For a long distance flight at FL 370, \"Long Range\" regime, divided into 4 flight legs with the following specifications: Segment AB - Ground distance: 1000 NM. headwind component: 100 kt Segment BC - Ground distance: 2000 NM. headwind component: 50 kt Segment CD - Ground distance: 500 NM. tailwind component:50 kt Segment DE - Ground distance: 1500 NM. tailwind component: 100 kt The total air distance is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "5000 NAM",
        "4800 NAM",
        "4517 NAM",
        "5200 NAM"
      ],
      "answer": "5200 NAM"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a flight the fuel indicators show that the remaining amount of fuel is 100 lb after 38 minutes. The total amount of fuel at take off was 160 lb. For the alternate fuel, 30 lb is necessary. The planned fuel for taxi is 13 lb. Final reserve fuel is estimated at 50 lb. If the fuel flow remains the same, how many minutes can be flown to the destination with the remaining fuel?",
      "choices": [
        "12 minutes.",
        "44 minutes.",
        "63 minutes.",
        "4 minutes."
      ],
      "answer": "12 minutes."
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2 and any other relevant data, answer the following questions for an approach to land at Stuttgart Airport, Germany (EDDS): Using BADSO 2A arrival, what is the frequency of the navaid to which you should proceed in case of communications failure?",
      "choices": [
        "109.2 MHz",
        "109.2 KHz",
        "109.2 Hz",
        "109.2 GHz"
      ],
      "answer": "109.2 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Referring to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2 and any other relevant data, answer the following questions for an approach to land at Stuttgart Airport, Germany (EDDS): What is the appropriate frequency for obtaining local weather information for the BADSO 2A arrival?",
      "choices": [
        "126.125 MHz",
        "126.125 KHz",
        "126.125 Hz",
        "126.125 GHz"
      ],
      "answer": "126.125 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "An MRJT aircraft is flying with its landing gear down. Complete the following: The aircraft's speed is limited to a ______ of 220 KIAS.",
      "choices": [
        "maximum",
        "minimum",
        "threshold",
        "cruising speed"
      ],
      "answer": "maximum"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2 and CAP 697, Fig. 4.3.1 (select the correct version). Your planned route is from Shannon Airport, Republic of Ireland (EINN) via SHA VOR/DME - V14 - DUB VOR/DME - L975 - WAL VOR/DME - Y53 - PEDIG - DCT East Midlands Airport, England (EGNX). Forecast conditions are a 25 kt headwind component, a cruising altitude of FL330, a landing weight of 50 000 kg and a temperature of ISA +10\u00b0C. What is the trip fuel and time? (Note: Ignore the altitude limitations of the E(LO) chart)",
      "choices": [
        "2640 kg and 54 min.",
        "2140 kg and 69 min.",
        "2020 kg and 57 min.",
        "2280 kg and 54 min."
      ],
      "answer": "2280 kg and 54 min."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your CAP 696 Figure 4.5.4 Given: Economy descent profile, TOD at FL 310 descending to an airport 600 ft amsl. QNH = 1033 hPa. Estimated landing weight = 40 000 kg, and a 20kt tailwind component. What is the time, fuel and distance for the descent?",
      "choices": [
        "20 min, 280 kg, 103 NGM.",
        "20 min, 280 kg, 95 NGM.",
        "20 min, 280 kg, 88 NGM.",
        "20 min, 280 kg, 81 NGM."
      ],
      "answer": "20 min, 280 kg, 95 NGM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following NOTAM information, what operating hours can be expected for BRISTOL RADAR during the summer? ATS SURVEILLANCE SERVICES AND PROCEDURES BRISTOL LOWER AIRSPACE RADAR SERHR CHANGED TO 1000- 1800 WINTER (SUMMER 1HR EARLIER) ENR 1.6 PARAGRAPH 4.1.6 REFERS NOTAM EG/B0056/16 >>> END-OF-BULLETIN <<<",
      "choices": [
        "1000-1800",
        "0900-1700",
        "0900-1900",
        "1100-1900"
      ],
      "answer": "0900-1700"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: Track 355\u00b0 (T), Wind velocity 340/30 kt, TAS 140 kt, Total distance A to B 350 NM. What is the time and the distance to the point of equal time between A and B?",
      "choices": [
        "114 mins; 211 NM.",
        "75 mins; 140 NM.",
        "50 mins; 140 NM.",
        "75 mins; 211 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "114 mins; 211 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697, Fig. 4.4. Given a landing weight at destination of 50 000 kg; a destination airport elevation of 2200 ft, a QNH of 1015 hPa, a required landing weight at the alternate airport of 46 000 kg an alternate airport elevation of 3100 ft amsl and a QNH of 998 hPa, calculate the final reserve fuel.",
      "choices": [
        "1070 kg.",
        "2140 kg.",
        "2220 kg.",
        "1110 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "1070 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 4.7.2 Given an ETOPS approval time of 120 minutes, long range cruise (LRC) technique and a weight of 55 000 kg at time of diversion; what is your permissible radius of operation on one engine?",
      "choices": [
        "803 NM.",
        "380 NM.",
        "752 NM.",
        "743 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "743 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given: True Air Speed: 135 kt, True course: 270\u00b0, Wind: 340\u00b0 /20 kt, Distance: 53 NM. Determine ground speed (GS) and flight time for covering the given distance:",
      "choices": [
        "127 kt, 25 minutes",
        "115 kt, 28 minutes",
        "127 kt, 17 minutes",
        "107 kt, 30 minutes"
      ],
      "answer": "127 kt, 25 minutes"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the following NOTAM, what is the maximum height of the balloon involved? Q) EUAD/QWCLW/IV/M/W/000/004/5339N00135W001 A) EUAD B) FROM 15/12/14 1348C) TO 16/03/06 1830 E) UNMANNED CAPTIVE BALLOON IN LOW FLYING AREA AVOIDANCE AREA WI 1NM RADIUSMAX HEIGHT 200FT AGL/324FT AMSL15/12/06/OPSLFLOWER Surface, UPPER 324 Feet AMSL SCHEDULE DEC 14 1348-1600, DEC 15-31 0700-1600, JAN 01-31 0700-1630, FEB 01-29 0700-1730, MAR 01-06 0600-1830",
      "choices": [
        "324 feet AMSL.",
        "324 feet AGL.",
        "200 feet AMSL.",
        "The height is variable."
      ],
      "answer": "324 feet AMSL."
    },
    {
      "question": "For pre-flight planning purposes, what is the minimum Fuel required for the Commercial Air Transport flight in a Jet aircraft aeroplane, given the following information? Assume the Basic Fuel Scheme WITHOUT variations applies. Trip Fuel: 3740 kg, Fuel to alternate: 936 kg, Taxi Fuel: 140 kg, Fuel flow at 1500 ft above destination aerodrome: 2132 kg/h, Extra Fuel: 0 kg, Discretionary Fuel: 0 kg",
      "choices": [
        "5882 kg",
        "6069 kg",
        "4816 kg",
        "6948 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "6069 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following data, what is the maximum extra fuel that may be uplifted? Maximum Zero Fuel Mass: 155 000 kg, Maximum Take-off Mass: 210 000 kg, Maximum Landing Mass: 175 000 kg, Planned ZFM: 155 000 kg, Take-off Fuel: 48 600 kg, Trip Fuel: 42 500 kg, Fuel tank capacity = 65 000 litres. Jet Fuel A-1 Specific Gravity = 0.82. Each 1000 kg extra in mass incurs fuel penalty values of: TOM: +260 kg, LDM: +370 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "5720 kg.",
        "6400 kg.",
        "13 900 kg.",
        "4700 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "4700 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information for a Commercial Air Transport operation, calculate the maximum possible Extra Fuel, including any fuel penalty, that can be uplifted. Maximum Ramp Mass 63 060 kg, MTOM 62 800 kg, MLM 54 900 kg, MZFM 51 300 kg, DOM 33 200 kg, Traffic Load 12 375 kg, T/O Fuel 3575 kg, Trip Fuel 2100 kg, Taxi Fuel 195 kg, Fuel burn correction per 1000 kg of Extra Fuel based upon: TOM: + 40 kg and LDM: + 42kg, Fuel tank capacity 16 145 kg",
      "choices": [
        "13 650 kg",
        "8180 kg",
        "5725 kg",
        "7850 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "8180 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)11 and CAP 697, Figure 4.5.3.2. An aircraft crosses TORINO VOR/DME (TOP) at FL 350 at M0.74, with an aircraft mass of 52 500 kg, en-route along M730 via GENOA VOR/DME (GEN) (N44\u00b025' E009\u00b005'), FRZ and ANC to SPLIT VOR/DME (SPL). Given a 60 kt headwind and ISA -20\u00b0C, what is the fuel required between GEN and SPL?",
      "choices": [
        "2000 kg.",
        "1976 kg.",
        "2322 kg.",
        "2350 kg."
      ],
      "answer": "2322 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "A ground distance of 135 NM shall be covered with a planned TAS of 450 kt; the fuel consumption is 5 kg/NM. The original fuel planning was made considering the forecast wind component of -25 kt. Before departure, the forecast is revised to a wind component of +25 kt. How much fuel is required in addition to the original calculation?",
      "choices": [
        "0 kg",
        "75 kg",
        "250 kg.",
        "50 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "0 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart E (LO)2. You want to fly from POLE HILL POL 112.1 (N53 45W002 06) to OTBED (N53 18 E000 02). Which route would you select?",
      "choices": [
        "POL Y70 GOLES Y70 OTBED",
        "POL N601 DESIG L60 OTBED",
        "POL N57 DENBY L975 DESIG L70 MAMUL L60 OTBED",
        "POL N57 DENBY L70 L60 OTBED"
      ],
      "answer": "POL N57 DENBY L975 DESIG L70 MAMUL L60 OTBED"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Alicante LEAL (19-1): An aircraft has suffered a radio failure, which method of entry should we use:",
      "choices": [
        "East of south route.",
        "Proceed direct to airfield and fly right hand triangles.",
        "Can not land , must divert.",
        "North Route."
      ],
      "answer": "East of south route."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart Amsterdam Chart 11-1. You are cleared for an ILS approach 06 for runway via SUGOL. The last clearance you receive is to descend to FL70. You may leave this level:",
      "choices": [
        "After passing SPL.",
        "After passing CH locator.",
        "After passing 9.2 KAG DME inbound.",
        "When established on the final track (localizer captured) for ILS 06."
      ],
      "answer": "After passing SPL."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Amsterdam (EHAM) chart 11-1. An aircraft in approaching category A is cleared for the procedural ILS approach to runway 06 via CH Locator. At what point should the base turn into localiser track of 058\u00b0 (M) be started?",
      "choices": [
        "1 min after passing overhead the CH Locator.",
        "9.2 NM DME range from ICAG DME.",
        "11.1 NM DME range from SPL DME.",
        "2 mins after passing overhead the CH Locator."
      ],
      "answer": "1 min after passing overhead the CH Locator."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft after passing the Initial Approach Fix and before turning onto the final approach course to establish the Localizer of an ILS approach procedure, is authorised to descend to 4000 ft. The aircraft gets into clouds and suddenly loses all his navigation systems continuing flying only with its stand-by compass. To what altitude must the aircraft descend or climb?",
      "choices": [
        "Descent until the FAP altitude.",
        "Climb to the highest MSA 4600 ft.",
        "Descent until the DA.",
        "Descent to the MSA of the sector and maintain ."
      ],
      "answer": "Climb to the highest MSA 4600 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Amsterdam (EHAM) chart 10-2. You are approaching to Amsterdam EHAM after ARTIP and you need to get ATIS information. Which Navaids facility will provide ATIS information?",
      "choices": [
        "SPL",
        "EEL",
        "RKN",
        "SPY"
      ],
      "answer": "SPL"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Amsterdam Chart 10-2 and 10-1P. You are approaching AMSTERDAM via REKKEN 2A. Which of the following procedures should be followed in case of a radio communication failure?",
      "choices": [
        "Fly a holding pattern for at least 7 minutes.",
        "Descend below the ceiling and continue VFR to the airport.",
        "Continue on a direct course towards the airport.",
        "Follow the procedures provided on the 10-1P pages of your route manual."
      ],
      "answer": "Follow the procedures provided on the 10-1P pages of your route manual."
    },
    {
      "question": "Reference GSPRM Jeppesen Charts Amsterdam 10-3C, 10-3D. Which SID do you use for runway 04?",
      "choices": [
        "ANDIK 1N",
        "ANDIK 2G",
        "ANDIK 2E",
        "ANDIK 2F"
      ],
      "answer": "ANDIK 2F"
    },
    {
      "question": "When reviewing the wind charts in the briefing room, you notice that the average wind in cruise will be 25 kt tailwind. Given the following data, what will be the flight time to destination? Time to top of climb: 28 minutes, Cruise leg: 760 NM, FL330 TAS 470 kt ISA -10\u00b0C, Time from top of descent to landing: 20 minutes",
      "choices": [
        "2 hours 25 minutes",
        "2 hours 20 minutes",
        "1 hour 37 minutes",
        "1 hour 32 minutes"
      ],
      "answer": "2 hours 20 minutes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart Amsterdam Chart 10-2. What is the clearance limit of the given STAR chart?",
      "choices": [
        "EELDE (EEL)",
        "SCHIPHOL (SPL)",
        "NORKU",
        "ARTIP"
      ],
      "answer": "ARTIP"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Alicante charts 10-3C & 10-3E. Aircraft fully RNAV equipped are suitable for what SID for Runway 10?",
      "choices": [
        "MITOS 1C",
        "SOPET 1G",
        "SOPET 1F",
        "MITOS 2A"
      ],
      "answer": "MITOS 2A"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart E(LO)2. A flight is planned along route T420, course 330\u00b0 , FL380, inbound TRENT VOR/DME (TNT). A descent should be initiated to pass waypoint ELVOS at FL200. Calculate the Top of Descent (ToD) relating to TRENT for a ground speed of 200 Kt and a rate of descent of 1500 FT/min:",
      "choices": [
        "65 NM",
        "109 NM",
        "55 NM",
        "40 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "65 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Charts Alicante 10-2, 10-2A, 10-2B, 10-2C. A flight from UK to Spain, destination Alicante, is going to pass Valencia VOR/DME. Which of the following STAR charts would be suitable?",
      "choices": [
        "Chart 10-2A",
        "Chart 10-2C",
        "Chart 10-2",
        "Chart 10-2B"
      ],
      "answer": "Chart 10-2B"
    },
    {
      "question": "A __________ route is an ATS route that you can only plan to use, and is only available to use, under specified conditions.",
      "choices": [
        "repetitive",
        "conditional",
        "cleared",
        "TANGO"
      ],
      "answer": "conditional"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen SCHIPHOL 10-2. You experience a total RNAV system failure en-route to your destination, Amsterdam Schiphol aerodrome. During descent, Schiphol Arrival assigns you the NORKU 2A arrival. Can you accept this STAR?",
      "choices": [
        "Yes, if you given vectors to OSKUR.",
        "No, because it is an RNAV STAR.",
        "No, because it is an RNAV STAR. However, you can request REKKEN 2A.",
        "You can follow NORKU 2A because it is a conventional STAR."
      ],
      "answer": "No, because it is an RNAV STAR."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart E(LO)2. You are flying at FL360, heading NW and ATC tell you have to be at FL200 over ELVOS. How far from TRENT (N53 03 W001 40) should you start your descent? TAS 420, ROD 2000 ft / min. Answer in NM.",
      "choices": [
        "126 NM",
        "56 NM",
        "81 NM",
        "70 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "81 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart Alicante 10-3A. Which of the following statements contains all corresponding altitude and flight level instructions when departing via CATON 2C?",
      "choices": [
        "At D9.5 ALT not below 3100 ft, overhead VILNA not above FL 110, overhead NARGO at or above FL 110, at CATON below FL 230.",
        "At D9.5 ALT above 3100 ft, overhead VILNA below FL 110, overhead NARGO above FL 110, at CATON above FL 230.",
        "At D9.5 ALT at or above 3100 ft, overhead VILNA at or above FL80, overhead NARGO at or above FL110, at CATON at or below FL230.",
        "At D9.5 ALT not below 3100 ft, overhead VILNA at or above FL80, overhead NARGO at or above FL110, at CATON below FL230."
      ],
      "answer": "At D9.5 ALT at or above 3100 ft, overhead VILNA at or above FL80, overhead NARGO at or above FL110, at CATON at or below FL230."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Charts Alicante 19-1, 19-2, 19-3. What is the magnetic bearing from reporting point N to NE?",
      "choices": [
        "221",
        "44",
        "66",
        "246"
      ],
      "answer": "66"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Charts Alicante 19-1, 19-2, 19-3. When approaching Alicante, what is the procedure if you experience a communication failure?",
      "choices": [
        "Proceed in the direction of SW reporting point, assume a track east of South Route to S reporting point and maintain a maximum of 800 ft AMSL.",
        "Turn to the closest aerodrome without control zone, land there and inform ATC via phone call.",
        "Maintain heading and altitude for 7 minutes, then descend to 2000 ft and proceed to closest VFR reporting point and hold, waiting for light signals.",
        "Set transponder 7600, proceed according to your filed flight plan if no instructions have been received previously, otherwise follow latest ATC instructions."
      ],
      "answer": "Proceed in the direction of SW reporting point, assume a track east of South Route to S reporting point and maintain a maximum of 800 ft AMSL."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Chart E (LO)2. What is the Frequency of aeronautical service when overflying TULIP:",
      "choices": [
        "123.9",
        "131.85",
        "124.05",
        "125.75"
      ],
      "answer": "125.75"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM AMSTERDAM - Charts 10-2, 10-2A, 10-2B, 10-2C. You are flying from PARIS to AMSTERDAM, which set of STAR is available for you?",
      "choices": [
        "10-2A",
        "10-2B",
        "2025-10-02 00:00:00",
        "10-2C"
      ],
      "answer": "10-2A"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2. Routing north from BCN VOR/DME (N51\u00b0 44' W003\u00b0 16') along N864 to WAL VOR/DME (N53\u00b0 24' W003\u00b0 08'), what is the lowest available cruising altitude from the options given?",
      "choices": [
        "FL 180",
        "FL 220",
        "FL 210",
        "FL 240"
      ],
      "answer": "FL 220"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following Instrument Approach Operations are classified as 3D Approach Operations: 1. RNP APCH (GNSS and baro VNAV) 2. GLS 3. PAR 4. RNP 1 5. ILS 6. RNP APCH (SBAS)",
      "choices": [
        "Only 1, 5 and 6.",
        "2, 3, 4, 5 and 6.",
        "1, 3, 4 and 6.",
        "1, 2, 3, 5 and 6."
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2, 3, 5 and 6."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Chart E (LO)2. On an IFR flight close to airfield LELYSTAD (EHLE, N52\u00b028' E005\u00b0 32') you need to determine the distance to the corresponding DME station. Which of the following is the correct frequency and identifier?",
      "choices": [
        "Channel 51, FRO",
        "326 kHz, LLS",
        "123.67 MHz, AFIS",
        "111.4 MHz, FRO"
      ],
      "answer": "111.4 MHz, FRO"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen ALICANTE (LEAL) 10-3A. An aircraft receives the following ATC clearance from the Alicante (LEAL) DELIVERY: \"Cleared to destination via the CATON 2C standard departure from runway 28,squawk 4017\". What are the altitude restrictions for this SID?",
      "choices": [
        "At or above 3100 ft at 9.5 NM from ALT, At or above 11 000 ft at VILNA, At or above 11 000 ft at NARGO",
        "At or above 3100 ft at 9.5 NM from ALT, At or above FL80 at VILNA, At or above FL110 at NARGO, At or below FL230 at CATON",
        "At or above 3100 ft at 9.5 NM from ALT, At or above FL110 at VILNA, At or above FL110 at NARGO",
        "At or above FL70 overhead ALT, At or above FL110 at VILNA, At or above FL110 at NARGO, At or below FL230 at CATON"
      ],
      "answer": "At or above 3100 ft at 9.5 NM from ALT, At or above FL80 at VILNA, At or above FL110 at NARGO, At or below FL230 at CATON"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen E(L0)2. Find the magnetic bearing and distance from Trent (TNT) VOR/DME (53\u00b003'N, 001\u00b040'W) to waypoint AMVEL (53\u00b011'N, 000\u00b0 02'W).",
      "choices": [
        "084\u00b0M / 59 NM",
        "260\u00b0M / 52 NM",
        "264\u00b0M / 58 NM",
        "080\u00b0M / 51 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "084\u00b0M / 59 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM Terminal Section IFR RNAV Initial Approach Chart for Nantes, France (10-2B) What is the minimum sector altitude at DOGOV and what is the direct track distance from DOGOV to Nantes airport?",
      "choices": [
        "3000 ft - not specified",
        "3000 ft - 15 NM.",
        "FL 70 - 13 NM.",
        "2100 ft - 15 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "2100 ft - 15 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "In ATC Flight plan item 15, speed of 120 kt will be entered as:",
      "choices": [
        "120KT",
        "N120",
        "N0120",
        "K0120"
      ],
      "answer": "N0120"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)14. You are flying from Izmir, Turkey and are approaching Santorini, Greece along ATS route J62. The wind is from the south. Find the appropriate plates and identify the bearing and range from KORAX to SNI .",
      "choices": [
        "155\u00b0M - 9 nm",
        "335\u00b0M - 9 nm",
        "335\u00b0T - 9 nm",
        "155\u00b0M - 9 km"
      ],
      "answer": "155\u00b0M - 9 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM chart for Santorini, Greece with the code 13-3. What is the DME Arc range for the VOR B procedure for RWY 34?",
      "choices": [
        "8 NM.",
        "12 NM.",
        "14 NM.",
        "10 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "10 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Excluding RVSM an appropriate flight level for IFR flight in accordance with semi-circular height rules on a magnetic course of 200\u00b0 is:",
      "choices": [
        "FL310",
        "FL320",
        "FL290",
        "FL300"
      ],
      "answer": "FL310"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying over terrain of up to 2000 ft elevation. The Minimum Holding Altitude (MHA) over this terrain provides, in the holding area, a minimum obstacle clearance of how many metres?",
      "choices": [
        "450 m",
        "300 m",
        "600 m",
        "900 m"
      ],
      "answer": "300 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Alicante (LEAL) S10 10-3C. A flight is filed to depart from Alicante aerodrome (LEAL) via waypoint MITOS during FMS setup, what constraints should be verified as correct for a MITOS S10 from Runway 28?",
      "choices": [
        "Min 3100 ft at 9.5 NM from ALT, Min 5000 ft SUMMO",
        "Max 3100 ft at 9.5 NM from ALT, Max 220 kt during the turn until ALT Radial 246, 6.3 NM Min 5000 ft at SUMMO",
        "Min 3100 ft at 9.5 NM from ALT Max 220 kt until MITOS, Min 5000 ft at SUMMO",
        "Min 3100 ft at 9.5 NM from ALT, Max 220 kt during the turn until ALT Radial 246, 6.3 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "Min 3100 ft at 9.5 NM from ALT, Max 220 kt during the turn until ALT Radial 246, 6.3 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM Terminal Section IFR Charts for Alicante, Spain 10-3A - 10-3G. You are departing to the west. Your aircraft is not RNAV certified. W/V = 275/20. TAS after take-off = 120 kt. What departure procedure should you use and what is the minimum climb gradient and rate of climb required?",
      "choices": [
        "YES 3A - 5.0% @ 506 fpm",
        "YES 1D - 5.0% @ 557 fpm",
        "YES 1D - 5.5% @ 557 fpm",
        "YES 1D - 7.0% @ 709 fpm"
      ],
      "answer": "YES 1D - 5.5% @ 557 fpm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 3.1 Given a departure airport at a pressure altitude of 4000 ft (OAT +37\u00b0C), an MEP aircraft climbs to FL140 (OAT +10\u00b0C), what is the time, fuel and distance used in the climb?",
      "choices": [
        "4 USG, 7 min, 12 NM.",
        "14 USG, 25 min, 46 NM.",
        "10 USG, 18 min, 33 NM.",
        "18 USG, 32 min, 58 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "10 USG, 18 min, 33 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2. What is the flight time from DUB VOR/DME (N53\u00b0 34' W006\u00b0 20') via LIFFY along UL975 to WAL VOR/DME (N53\u00b0 24' W003\u00b0 08') at FL 210 (OAT = ISA), CAS = 210 kt, W/V = 240/30.",
      "choices": [
        "25 min",
        "21 min",
        "19 min",
        "23 min"
      ],
      "answer": "21 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)14. You are flying from Izmir, Turkey and are approaching Santorini, Greece along ATS route J62. The wind is from the south. Find the appropriate plates and identify the minimum holding altitude at KORAX.",
      "choices": [
        "5300",
        "7000",
        "3500",
        "6000"
      ],
      "answer": "3500"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 3.2 Given a cruise pressure altitude of FL100 (OAT ISA +10\u00b0C), using economy power, and a 40 kt tailwind component, what is the aircraft\u2019s still air range with a 45 minute reserve?",
      "choices": [
        "750 NM.",
        "760 NM.",
        "770 NM.",
        "670 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "770 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2. What is the lowest Grid MORA for a direct track between Shannon, Ireland (N52\u00b0 43' W008\u00b0 52') and Manchester, England (N53\u00b0 21' W002\u00b0 16')?",
      "choices": [
        "4400",
        "4800",
        "4900",
        "3500"
      ],
      "answer": "4900"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)14. You are flying from Izmir, Turkey and are approaching Santorini, Greece along ATS route J62. The wind is from the south. Find the appropriate plates and identify the radio navigation aid and its frequency on which the arrival to Santorini is based.",
      "choices": [
        "MIL 113.5 KHz",
        "SNI 110.4 MHz",
        "SNI 110.4 KHz",
        "MKN 110.0 KHz"
      ],
      "answer": "SNI 110.4 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using Flight Planning Manual MRJT 1 Figure 4.5.4. Planning an IFR flight from Paris to London for the twin jet aeroplane. Given: Estimated Landing Mass 49 700 kg, Cruise level FL280, Average wind 280\u00b0 / 40 kts, Average True Course 320\u00b0, Descent profile M 074 / 250 KIAS. Determine the fuel consumption from the top of descent to London (elevation 80 ft).",
      "choices": [
        "320 kg",
        "210 kg",
        "273 kg",
        "263 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "273 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Alicante Charts 10-2A, 10-2B, 10-2C, 10-2D. You are planning a flight from ATHENS to ALICANTE. Which of the STAR charts will you most likely consider when choosing an arrival route for your operational flight plan to determine the flight distance and fuel requirements?",
      "choices": [
        "10-2B",
        "10-2A",
        "10-2C",
        "10-2D"
      ],
      "answer": "10-2C"
    },
    {
      "question": "You must fly IFR on an airway orientated 135\u00b0 magnetic with a MSA at 7800 ft. Knowing the QNH is 1025 hPa and the temperature is ISA +10\u00b0, the minimum flight level you must fly at is:",
      "choices": [
        "90",
        "80",
        "75",
        "70"
      ],
      "answer": "90"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2. What is the total track distance between HON VOR/DME (N52\u00b0 21' W001\u00b0 40') and SOMVA (N52\u00b0 18' E002\u00b0 39')?",
      "choices": [
        "161 000 m.",
        "161 NM.",
        "161 km.",
        "161 000 yd."
      ],
      "answer": "161 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM chart for Santorini, Greece with the code 13-3. What is the MDA and RVR for the straight in approach for the VOR B procedure for RWY 34?",
      "choices": [
        "1700'",
        "1577'",
        "nan",
        "3000'"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart E(LO)1. A section of a flight is carried out from SUMBURGH (SUM) to ABERDEEN (ADN) along airway Y905. Choose the lowest flight level which can be used for the whole section:",
      "choices": [
        "FL80",
        "FL110",
        "FL100",
        "FL190"
      ],
      "answer": "FL110"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart E (LO)2. The section of a routing is via airway Y96 from NORBO to TALLA (TLA, N55\u00b030' W003\u00b021'). What is the true course to TLA?",
      "choices": [
        "079\u00b0",
        "176\u00b0",
        "096\u00b0",
        "279\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "096\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the GSPRM chart for London, UK, with the code 10-2F?",
      "choices": [
        "London Heathrow STAR LAM 3A Arrival.",
        "Tromso, Norway RNAV STAR RNAV GILGU 3L RNAV Arrival.",
        "London Heathrow SID LAM 3A Arrival.",
        "Stuttgart, Germany RNAV Transition BABEG 1E."
      ],
      "answer": "London Heathrow STAR LAM 3A Arrival."
    },
    {
      "question": "ELO-2 Flying from Norbo to Deans Cross by route T256, how would this be written in a Navigation flight plan?",
      "choices": [
        "NORBO 144\u00b0 T256,RINPO DCS",
        "DCT NORBO 144\u00b0 DCS",
        "NORBO 144\u00b0 T256,OSMEG 136\u00b0 DCS",
        "NORBO 144\u00b0 T256,NYG 136\u00b0 DCS"
      ],
      "answer": "NORBO 144\u00b0 T256,NYG 136\u00b0 DCS"
    },
    {
      "question": "The MSA ls 2500 ft and the ATC instructs the pilot to turn to heading 180\u00b0 and descend to 2300 ft to be vectored for the ILS. What does the pilot have to do?",
      "choices": [
        "Turn to heading 180\u00b0, maintain current altitude, and call ATC because 2300 ft is below MSA.",
        "Turn to heading 180\u00b0 and descend to 2300 ft.",
        "Maintain current heading and call ATC because 2300 ft is below MSA.",
        "Turn to heading 180\u00b0, descend to 2500 ft and call ATC because 2300 ft is below MSA."
      ],
      "answer": "Turn to heading 180\u00b0 and descend to 2300 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 3.6 Given top of descent at FL160 (OAT -20\u00b0C), destination airport at a pressure altitude of 6000 ft (OAT 0\u00b0C), what is the time, fuel and distance used during the descent?",
      "choices": [
        "6 min, 2 USG, 16 NM.",
        "10 min, 4 USG, 26 NM.",
        "16 min, 6 USG, 42 NM.",
        "4 min, 11 USG, 26 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "10 min, 4 USG, 26 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "How many feet do you have to climb to reach FL75? Given: Departure aerodrome elevation 1500 ft, QNH 1023 hPa, Temperature ISA, (1hPa=30 ft)",
      "choices": [
        "6000 ft",
        "6600 ft",
        "6300 ft",
        "7800 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "6300 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The airways which run north-south to the west of Portugal, which allow European continental traffic to transit through North Atlantic oceanic airspace without having to adhere to all the procedures and equipment requirements normally associated with oceanic areas, are known as the __________ routes.",
      "choices": [
        "UPPER",
        "VICTOR",
        "TANGO",
        "SUPERSONIC"
      ],
      "answer": "TANGO"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(HI)2. What is the difference in flight time between (a) the direct route from DCS VOR/DME (N54\u00b0 43' W003\u00b0 20') along UL612 to HON VOR/DME (N52\u00b0 21' W001\u00b0 40') and (b) the route via WAL VOR/DME (N53\u00b0 24' W003\u00b0 08'), both flown at the same groundspeed of 171 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "2 min",
        "4 min",
        "5 min",
        "3 min"
      ],
      "answer": "3 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 3.2 Given a cruise pressure altitude of FL130 (OAT ISA +20\u00b0C), using 75% power, and a 40 kt tailwind component, what is the aircraft\u2019s maximum still air range with no reserve?",
      "choices": [
        "730 NM.",
        "740 NM.",
        "710 NM.",
        "750 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "750 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 3.1 Given a departure airport at a pressure altitude of 2000 ft (OAT +20\u00b0C), an MEP aircraft climbs to FL100, no ISA deviation, what is the fuel, time and distance used in the climb?",
      "choices": [
        "9 USG, 16 min, 29 NM.",
        "11 USG, 20 min, 34 NM.",
        "2 USG, 4 min, 6 NM.",
        "7 USG, 13 min, 22 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "7 USG, 13 min, 22 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Amsterdam- chart 11-1. Which of the following are approach lights provided for Amsterdam ILS 06 approach?",
      "choices": [
        "A runway lead in lightning system (RLLS).",
        "A high intensity approach light system.",
        "GA lights in 2000 ft.",
        "PAPI lights."
      ],
      "answer": "A high intensity approach light system."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2. An aircraft is routing from SHA VOR/DME to CRK VOR/DME along N160. Shannon QNH = 993 hPa. OAT = ISA -10\u00b0C. What is the lowest pressure altitude that the aircraft can fly at to comply with obstacle clearance and cruising level rules?",
      "choices": [
        "FL 60",
        "FL 80",
        "FL 70",
        "FL 50"
      ],
      "answer": "FL 70"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2. Assuming nil wind conditions, at which point is the first change of magnetic heading between DUB VOR/DME and WAL VOR/DME along ATS route L975?",
      "choices": [
        "LIFFY",
        "No heading change",
        "IDEXA",
        "MALUD"
      ],
      "answer": "LIFFY"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)14. You are flying from Izmir, Turkey and are approaching Santorini, Greece along ATS route J62. The wind is from the south. Find the appropriate plates and identify the approach procedure to be used.",
      "choices": [
        "STAR PEXAN 1C",
        "STAR BINKI 1A",
        "STAR UVRIT 1C",
        "STAR IRBEG 1C"
      ],
      "answer": "STAR IRBEG 1C"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prior to an IFR flight, when filling in the ICAO flight plan, the time information which should be entered in box 13 (time) is:",
      "choices": [
        "The time of flight plan filing.",
        "Planned take-off time.",
        "Planned engine start time.",
        "Estimated off-block time."
      ],
      "answer": "Estimated off-block time."
    },
    {
      "question": "ln the ITEM 9 of an ICAO ATS Flight Plan, what does the letter M denote?",
      "choices": [
        "Medium wake turbulence.",
        "Military traffic.",
        "More than one aircraft.",
        "MLS equipped."
      ],
      "answer": "Medium wake turbulence."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - Greece Aerodrome Directory (7-3). What is the local time (LT) in Greece in Winter and Summer?",
      "choices": [
        "LT - 3 Hours = UTC; LT - 2 Hours = UTC",
        "LT + 2 Hours = UTC; LT + 3 Hours = UTC",
        "LT = UTC + 2 Hours; LT = UTC + 3 Hours",
        "LT = UTC - 2 Hours; LT = UTC - 3 Hours"
      ],
      "answer": "LT = UTC + 2 Hours; LT = UTC + 3 Hours"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to your Jeppesen GSPRM IFR Chart E(LO)2. What is the total track distance between GOW VOR/DME and HON VOR/DME and what is the ETE at an average groundspeed of 380 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "154 nm - 24 min.",
        "432 km - 37 min.",
        "233 nm - 40 min.",
        "285 km - 45 min."
      ],
      "answer": "432 km - 37 min."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 3.6 Given top of descent at FL180 (OAT -20\u00b0C), destination airport at a pressure altitude of 3000 ft (OAT +22\u00b0C), what is the fuel, time and distance used during the descent?",
      "choices": [
        "7 USG, 22 min, 57 NM.",
        "1 USG, 3 min, 8 NM.",
        "5 USG, 15 min, 41 NM.",
        "6 USG, 19 min, 49 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "5 USG, 15 min, 41 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the standard ICAO classification, which is the equivalent of the European classification of B-RNAV?",
      "choices": [
        "RNAV 5",
        "RNAV 1",
        "RNAV 10",
        "RNP 5"
      ],
      "answer": "RNAV 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft with reciprocating engines plans to fly to an aerodrome, with a trip range in cruise flight of 275 nm at an average GS of 165 kt. Fuel flow is 480 kg/hr. The total alternate and final reserve fuel required to fly to the nearest adequate destination alternate aerodrome is 580 kg. What category of aerodrome is the destination?",
      "choices": [
        "Remote aerodrome.",
        "Destination alternate.",
        "Isolated aerodrome.",
        "Adequate aerodrome."
      ],
      "answer": "Isolated aerodrome."
    },
    {
      "question": "VFR flights shall not be flown over the congested areas of cities at a height less than:",
      "choices": [
        "The highest obstacle.",
        "2000 ft above the highest obstacle within a radius of 600 ft from the aircraft.",
        "1000 ft above the highest obstacle within a radius of 600 m from the aircraft.",
        "500 ft above the highest obstacle."
      ],
      "answer": "1000 ft above the highest obstacle within a radius of 600 m from the aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "On a VFR flight, the traffic circuit altitude has to be established 5 NM before reaching the destination aerodrome. The descent must begin no later than how many nautical miles' ground distance from the airfield? Rate of descent: 500 ft/min, Ground speed during descent: 130 kt, Initial altitude: 4500 ft AMSL, Traffic circuit altitude: 2500 ft AMSL",
      "choices": [
        "20 NM",
        "9 NM",
        "14 NM",
        "25 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "14 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many feet you have to climb to reach FL75? Given: Departure aerodrome elevation 1500 ft, QNH = 1023 hPa, Temperature = ISA, 1 hPa = 30 ft",
      "choices": [
        "6000 ft.",
        "7800 ft.",
        "6600 ft.",
        "6300 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "6300 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the TAS in the cruise at the highest VFR cruising altitude between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden ((EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006?' Visibility: 20 km Cloud: OVC 7000 Temperature: ISA QNH: 1033 hPa W/V: 100\u00b0(T)/30 kt CAS: 145 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "127 kt",
        "156 kt",
        "160 kt",
        "162 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "156 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. Flying from REGENSBURG EDNR (N49\u00b008' E012\u00b005') to STRUNKOVICE LKSR (N49\u00b005' E014\u00b004.5') What is your Magnetic Track?",
      "choices": [
        "93",
        "95",
        "89",
        "80"
      ],
      "answer": "89"
    },
    {
      "question": "When reviewing the wind charts in the briefing room, you notice that the average wind in cruise will be 25 kt headwind. Given following data, what will be the flight time to destination? Time to top of climb : 30 min, Cruise leg: 740 NM, FL380, TAS: 460 kt, ISA -10\u00b0C, Time from top of descent to landing : 22 minutes",
      "choices": [
        "2 h 28 mins",
        "1 h 36 mins",
        "1 h 42 mins",
        "2 h 34 mins"
      ],
      "answer": "2 h 34 mins"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. Refer to MUNCHEN airport (EDDM, N048\u00b0 21.23' E11\u00b0 47.17'). What is the lowest altitude of class C airspace?",
      "choices": [
        "3500 ft",
        "4500 ft",
        "FL105",
        "FL65"
      ],
      "answer": "3500 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - AMSTERDAM Terminal Chart 16-2. What is the MDA for the NDB approach on runway 18C?",
      "choices": [
        "1312 ft",
        "702 ft",
        "880 ft",
        "690 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "690 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the time it will take to fly from A to B on a cross country flight given the data below. Distance A to B: 83 NM, TAS:120 kt, TT: 130\u00b0, W/V: 022\u00b0/23 kt",
      "choices": [
        "38.3 minutes",
        "37.7 minutes",
        "36.9 minutes",
        "39.8 minutes"
      ],
      "answer": "39.8 minutes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the wind correction angle to be applied? Wind = 060\u00b0/60 kts (T), TAS= 380 kts, Variation = 5\u00b0E, Heading = 85\u00b0 (M)",
      "choices": [
        "5\u00b0R",
        "10\u00b0R",
        "10\u00b0L",
        "5\u00b0L"
      ],
      "answer": "5\u00b0L"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen ALICANTE VFR Approach Plate 19-1. On recovery to Alicante from the East; what is the maximum altitude approaching the NE Reporting Point?",
      "choices": [
        "1500 ft",
        "FL75",
        "2000 ft",
        "1000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "2000 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is best described by the following definition? \"In the context of the fuel/energy policy or fuel/energy schemes, a landing at an adequate aerodrome or operating site with no less than the final reserve fuel/energy remaining and in compliance with the applicable operational procedures and aerodrome operating minima.\"",
      "choices": [
        "Diversion.",
        "Safe landing.",
        "Arrival.",
        "Adequate landing."
      ],
      "answer": "Safe landing."
    },
    {
      "question": "A mountain 6011 ft AMSL will be crossed. What is the lowest VFR ICAO level the aircraft must fly to obtain a clearance of 2000 ft? Given: Variation: 10\u00b0W, Aircraft's Track: 356\u00b0T, Aircraft's HDG: 355\u00b0M, QNH: 990 hPa Assume 7 hPa = 30 M",
      "choices": [
        "FL090",
        "FL115",
        "FL085",
        "FL095"
      ],
      "answer": "FL095"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given a TAS of 525 kt and a GS of 400 kt, what is the nautical ground mile equivalent of 350 NAM?",
      "choices": [
        "300 NGM",
        "450 NGM",
        "267 NGM",
        "200 NGM"
      ],
      "answer": "267 NGM"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the ATS flight plan Item 15, for a flight along a designated route, where the departure aerodrome is not on or connected to that route:",
      "choices": [
        "It is not necessary to indicate the point of joining that route as it will be obvious to the ATS unit.",
        "The words \u201cas cleared\u201d should be entered.",
        "It is necessary only to give the first reporting point on that route.",
        "The letters DCT should be entered, followed by the point of joining the ATS route."
      ],
      "answer": "The letters DCT should be entered, followed by the point of joining the ATS route."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Alicante 10-3 chart. Departure procedure Astro4A, QNH 1040, ROC 800 FT/min, GS 133 KT, at ALT VOR climb from 4000 FT to FL 080. When will you reach TOC?",
      "choices": [
        "At Vilna",
        "2 NM after Vilna",
        "7 NM before Vilna",
        "5 NM before Vilna"
      ],
      "answer": "7 NM before Vilna"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. Find the the frequency of the LINZ ATIS.",
      "choices": [
        "129.62 MHz",
        "118.40 MHz",
        "128.12 MHz",
        "116.60 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "128.12 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, calculate the drift angle: TAS: 179 kt, Wind: 330\u00b0(M)/25 kt, VAR: 20\u00b0W, Course: 210\u00b0(M)",
      "choices": [
        "12\u00b0 Left",
        "8\u00b0 Left",
        "10\u00b0 Left",
        "18\u00b0 Left"
      ],
      "answer": "8\u00b0 Left"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen ALICANTE - charts 19-1, 19-2 and 19-3. What is the maximum permissible altitude for reaching the compulsory reporting point NE?",
      "choices": [
        "1500 m AMSL",
        "1500 ft AMSL",
        "2000 ft AMSL",
        "2000 m AMSL"
      ],
      "answer": "2000 ft AMSL"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart Amsterdam 10-2B. The ATIS can be found on which VOR?",
      "choices": [
        "SCHIPHOL VOR",
        "REKKEN VOR",
        "SPJKEROOR",
        "EELDE VOR"
      ],
      "answer": "SCHIPHOL VOR"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart Aberdeen 10-1R. What is the frequency of Aberdeen Radar?",
      "choices": [
        "119.5",
        "119.05",
        "114.5",
        "114.3"
      ],
      "answer": "119.05"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen VFR Chart ED-4 chart. Flying from EDPJ LAICHINGEN airport (48\u00b030'N 009\u00b038'E) to EDTM MENGEN airport (48\u00b003'N 009\u00b022'E). What is the magnetic course and the distance?",
      "choices": [
        "Magnetic course: 020\u00b0; Distance: 58 NM.",
        "Magnetic course: 200\u00b0; Distance: 29 NM.",
        "Magnetic course: 200\u00b0; Distance: 58 NM.",
        "Magnetic course: 020\u00b0; Distance: 29 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "Magnetic course: 200\u00b0; Distance: 29 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the correct VFR cruising altitude when crossing a mountain range (elevation = 7749' amsl) on a true track of 187\u00b0 (magnetic variation = 14\u00b0E). QNH = 1013 hPa?",
      "choices": [
        "FL 100",
        "FL 110",
        "FL 115",
        "FL 95"
      ],
      "answer": "FL 115"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the approximate mass of 2600 ltr of JET-A1, having a specific gravity of 0.81?",
      "choices": [
        "4650 lb",
        "575 Imp Gal",
        "21 000 lb",
        "4650 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "4650 lb"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP workbook SEP Figure 2.4. Given: Aeroplane mass at start-up 3663 lbs, Aviation gasoline (density 6 lbs/gal), Take-off altitude sea level, Headwind 40 kt, Cruising altitude 8000 ft, Power setting full throttle 2300 RPM, 20 degrees celsius lean of peak EGT. Calculate the range.",
      "choices": [
        "844 NM",
        "730 NM",
        "633 NM",
        "547.5 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "633 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen VFR Alicante Charts 19-1, 19-2, 19-3. What is the distance (NM) between reporting points N and NE?",
      "choices": [
        "5 NM",
        "7.5 NM",
        "5.5 NM",
        "14 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "7.5 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the ATS flight plan Item 19, emergency and survival equipment carried on the flight should be indicated by:",
      "choices": [
        "Placing a tick in the relevant box.",
        "Circling the relevant box.",
        "Crossing out the box relevant to any equipment not carried.",
        "Listing the items carried on the \u201cREMARKS\u201d line."
      ],
      "answer": "Crossing out the box relevant to any equipment not carried."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which type of report is described by the following description: \"The XXXXX, also known as the surface actual (SA), reports the actual weather existing at the aerodrome at the time of the report.\"",
      "choices": [
        "TAF",
        "NOTAM",
        "METAR",
        "SIGWX"
      ],
      "answer": "METAR"
    },
    {
      "question": "\"The mass of an aeroplane plus standard items such as: unusable fuel and other unusable fluids; lubricating oil in engine and auxiliary units; fire extinguishers; pyrotechnics; emergency oxygen equipment; supplementary electronic equipment.\" This definition best describes which of the following?",
      "choices": [
        "BEM",
        "DOM",
        "MBE",
        "ZFM"
      ],
      "answer": "BEM"
    },
    {
      "question": "When completing an ATS flight plan before departure, the time information which should be entered in item 13 'Time' is:",
      "choices": [
        "Estimated off-block time.",
        "Planned engine start time.",
        "The time of flight plan filing.",
        "Planned take-off time."
      ],
      "answer": "Estimated off-block time."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given a GS of 120 kt, a nautical ground mile distance of 400 NGM and a nautical air mile distance of 420 NAM, what is the equivalent TAS?",
      "choices": [
        "126 kt",
        "105 kt",
        "141 kt",
        "162 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "126 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following Information, calculate the drift angle: TAS:179 kt Wind: 330\u00b0(M)/25 kt VAR: 20\u00b0W Course: 210\u00b0(M)",
      "choices": [
        "10\u00b0 Left",
        "8\u00b0 Left",
        "18\u00b0 Left",
        "12\u00b0 Left"
      ],
      "answer": "8\u00b0 Left"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following, calculate the ATOM of PadAir flight 666 from London Heathrow to Edinburgh. MZFM 51 300 kg, MSTOM 62 800 kg, MSLM 54 900kg, PLTOM 59 750 kg, PLLM 58 900 kg, Block fuel 8000 kg, Taxi fuel 260 kg, Trip fuel 2300 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "59 040 kg",
        "57 200 kg",
        "62 800 kg",
        "59 750 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "57 200 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What information is broadcast on ATIS?",
      "choices": [
        "Runways and approaches available at aerodrome, actual weather, arriving and departing traffic",
        "Runway in use, approach type and DH/MDH, actual weather",
        "Runway in use, approach type, forecast weather",
        "Runway in use, approach type, actual weather"
      ],
      "answer": "Runway in use, approach type, actual weather"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is meant by the acronym UNUSUFN in a non-scheduled GPS satellite outage?",
      "choices": [
        "Unreadable until further notice.",
        "Unserviceable until further notification.",
        "Unserviceable in flight.",
        "Unusable until further notice."
      ],
      "answer": "Unusable until further notice."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the height of the highest obstacle within 5 nm of track between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden ((EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006?' Visibility: 20 km Cloud: OVC 7000 Temperature: ISA QNH: 1033 hPa W/V: 100\u00b0(T)/30 kt CAS: 145 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "5500 ft",
        "2359 ft",
        "1895 ft",
        "2803 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "2803 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the chart the minimum obstruction clearance altitude (MOCA) is 8500 ft. The meteorological data gives an outside air temperature of -20\u00b0C at FL 85. The QNH, given by a met. station at an elevation of 4000 ft, is 1003 hPa. What is the minimum pressure altitude which should be flown according to the given MOCA?",
      "choices": [
        "8500 ft.",
        "8800 ft.",
        "8200 ft.",
        "12800 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "8800 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, when flying between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden ((EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006', what radio navigation aid could you use for distance and (nearly) accurate groundspeed to the first line feature, the A81 autobahn (motorway)? Visibility: 20 km Cloud: OVC 7000 Temperature: ISA QNH: 1033 hPa W/V: 100\u00b0(T)/30 kt CAS: 145 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "KBD DME 115.80 MHz",
        "KRH VOR/DME 115.95 MHz",
        "LBU VOR/DME 109.20 MHz",
        "SHD DME 108.05 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "SHD DME 108.05 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the formula for calculating the Point of Safe Return?",
      "choices": [
        "PSR = (E x H) \u00f7 (O + H)",
        "PSR = (E x O) \u00f7 (O + H)",
        "PSR = (E + H) \u00f7 (O x H)",
        "PSR = (D x H) \u00f7 (O + H)"
      ],
      "answer": "PSR = (E x H) \u00f7 (O + H)"
    },
    {
      "question": "When would you expect to use an 'abbreviated flight plan'?",
      "choices": [
        "In flight.",
        "On clearance for taxi.",
        "On clearance for take-off.",
        "The day before flight, to give advance notification of intention."
      ],
      "answer": "In flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "Who is ultimately responsible for ensuring that, even in case of diversion, the remaining fuel is not less than the fuel required to proceed to an aerodrome where a safe landing can be made, with final reserve fuel remaining.",
      "choices": [
        "Handling Operator",
        "Fuel Loading Agent",
        "Fuel Bowser Operator",
        "Commander"
      ],
      "answer": "Commander"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to the Jeppesen GSPRM, VFR+GPS Chart ED-4. What is the minimum grid area altitude in the chart grid box bounded by the coordinates N48\u00b030\u2019 E012\u00b000\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "3300' amsl",
        "3800' amsl",
        "3700' amsl",
        "3200' amsl"
      ],
      "answer": "3200' amsl"
    },
    {
      "question": "A VFR flight is planned from aerodrome A to aerodrome B on a 085\u00b0 track. What would be an appropriate Flight Level for this route?",
      "choices": [
        "FL50",
        "FL55",
        "FL60",
        "FL65"
      ],
      "answer": "FL55"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, in accordance with the Basic Fuel/Energy Scheme, what trip fuel is required? Taxi fuel 280 kg, APU burn 120 kg, Take-off fuel 750 kg. Climb to cruise altitude 1500 kg, Cruise 2 hr 30 min at a fuel flow of 2800 kg/hr, descent and landing 300 kg, Contingency fuel not stated, Alternate fuel 2200 kg and Final reserve 1200 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "9850 kg",
        "9970 kg",
        "9550 kg",
        "13150 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "9550 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the principal means of improving and maintaining the integrity of the GPS navigation signals.",
      "choices": [
        "INTEG and WARN",
        "GBAS, SBAS and RAIM",
        "PRN, ALMANAC and EPHEMERIS",
        "ILS, MLS and GLS"
      ],
      "answer": "GBAS, SBAS and RAIM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 2.4. Find the maximum range of an aircraft, given a cruise pressure altitude of 8000 ft, a full throttle power setting of 2300 RPM, and nil wind?",
      "choices": [
        "894 nm",
        "800 nm",
        "912 nm",
        "845 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "845 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given a TAS of 150 kt, a nautical ground mile distance of 800 NGM and a nautical air mile distance of 600 NAM, what is the equivalent GS?",
      "choices": [
        "300 kt",
        "400 kt",
        "150 kt",
        "200 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "200 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the 3 main sections of the Aeronautical Information Publication (AIP)?",
      "choices": [
        "GEN, ENR, AD",
        "NOTAM, AIS, ENR",
        "ENG, AD, ENR",
        "AIP, ENR, AD"
      ],
      "answer": "GEN, ENR, AD"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the sentence: A single repetitive flight plan (RPL) may be filed for IFR flights, operated regularly on the same day of consecutive weeks, on at least __________ occasions, or for flights operated every day, on at least __________ consecutive days.",
      "choices": [
        "10; 15",
        "15; 10",
        "10; 5",
        "10; 10"
      ],
      "answer": "10; 10"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to the Jeppesen GSPRM, VFR+GPS Chart ED-4. What is the projection type and scale of the chart?",
      "choices": [
        "Mercator's Conformal Conical Projection - 1:500 000",
        "Lambert's Conformal Conical Projection - 1:500 000",
        "Lambert's Conformal Conical Projection - 1:5 000 000",
        "Lambert's Conformal Cylindrical Projection - 1:500 000"
      ],
      "answer": "Lambert's Conformal Conical Projection - 1:500 000"
    },
    {
      "question": "For which of the following is the filing of a flight plan NOT compulsory?",
      "choices": [
        "Any flight, longer than 50 km, from a UK aerodrome with aircraft Maximum Total Weight Authorised (MTWA) greater than 7500 kg.",
        "All flights in classes A, B, C or D airspace.",
        "Flights to or from the UK, crossing a UK FIR boundary.",
        "Any flight in Class F airspace wishing to participate in an Air Traffic Advisory Service."
      ],
      "answer": "Any flight, longer than 50 km, from a UK aerodrome with aircraft Maximum Total Weight Authorised (MTWA) greater than 7500 kg."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 2.2. Given a power setting of 23 in.Hg. and 2300 RPM, ISA +20\u00b0C, find the manifold air pressure, fuel flow, indicated speed and true air speed for the optimum cruise at a pressure altitude of 12 000 ft.",
      "choices": [
        "19.2 in.Hg, 10.6 GPH, 135 KIAS and 153 KTAS",
        "19.2 in.Hg, 10 GPH, 123 KIAS and 151 KTAS",
        "19.2 in.Hg, 10.3 GPH, 129 KIAS and 152 KTAS",
        "19.1 in.Hg, 10.9 GPH, 132 KIAS and 161 KTAS"
      ],
      "answer": "19.2 in.Hg, 10 GPH, 123 KIAS and 151 KTAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. A VFR flight from LOLK to LOLF. Which of the following nav aids would be a suitable radio navigation aid for the flight?",
      "choices": [
        "N46\u00b026\u2019; E015\u00b008\u2019",
        "N48\u00b026\u2019; E014\u00b008\u2019",
        "N48\u00b026\u2019; E011\u00b008\u2019",
        "N45\u00b026\u2019; E014\u00b008\u2019"
      ],
      "answer": "N48\u00b026\u2019; E014\u00b008\u2019"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen VFR chart ED-4. What is the True Course and distance for a direct flight from Scharnstein aerodrome (LOLC) (N47\u00b054' E013\u00b056') to Trieben aerodrome (LOGI) (N47\u00b030' E014\u00b030')?",
      "choices": [
        "141\u00b0 and 32 NM",
        "137\u00b0 and 33 NM",
        "317\u00b0 and 33 NM",
        "136\u00b0 and 63 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "137\u00b0 and 33 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are flying a constant compass heading of 252\u00b0. Variation is 22\u00b0E, deviation is 3\u00b0W and your INS is showing a drift of 9\u00b0 right. True track is ?",
      "choices": [
        "242\u00b0",
        "280\u00b0",
        "262\u00b0",
        "224\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "280\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL180, OAT -11\u00b0C, QNH 1003. What is the true altitude?",
      "choices": [
        "18 000 ft",
        "18 408 ft",
        "16 992 ft",
        "17 500 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "18 408 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "When completing Item 9 of the ATS flight plan, if there is no appropriate aircraft designator, the following should be entered:",
      "choices": [
        "The most descriptive abbreviation.",
        "\u201cXXXX\u201d followed by an entry in Item 18.",
        "\u201cNONE\u201d",
        "\u201cZZZZ\u201d followed by an entry in Item 18."
      ],
      "answer": "\u201cZZZZ\u201d followed by an entry in Item 18."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen VFR Chart ED-4. Choose the correct statement on a standard day regarding the airspace above Stuttgart Airport (EDDS, N48\u00b041.4', E009\u00b013.3').",
      "choices": [
        "At 4000 ft AMSL you would be in class C airspace.",
        "At 4000 ft AMSL you would be in class E airspace.",
        "At 4000 ft AMSL you would be in class D airspace.",
        "At 4000 ft AMSL you would be in class G airspace."
      ],
      "answer": "At 4000 ft AMSL you would be in class C airspace."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the highest Minimum Grid Area Altitude between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden ((EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006?' Visibility: 20 km Cloud: OVC 7000 Temperature: ISA QNH: 1033 hPa W/V: 100\u00b0(T)/30 kt CAS: 145 kt",
      "choices": [
        "5500 ft",
        "3500 ft",
        "4200 ft",
        "4100 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "5500 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, when flying between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden ((EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006', what station and frequency should you contact for a flight information service on leaving Schw\u00e4bish Hall Information? Visibility: 20 km Cloud: OVC 7000 Temperature: ISA QNH: 1033 hPa W/V: 100\u00b0(T)/30 kt CAS: 145 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "Stuttgart Tower 119.05 MHz",
        "V\u00f6lkleshofen Lichtenberg 130.12 MHz",
        "Schw\u00e4bish Hall 108.05 MHz",
        "Langen Information 128.95 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "Langen Information 128.95 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "What happens to the Point of Equal Time when flying with a wind component present?",
      "choices": [
        "The PET moves into a headwind, closer to the destination.",
        "The PET moves into a tailwind, further from the departure point.",
        "The PET moves into a tailwind, closer to the destination.",
        "The PET moves into a headwind, closer to the departure point."
      ],
      "answer": "The PET moves into a headwind, closer to the destination."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Alicante VFR chart 19-1. How many VFR approaches are available?",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "3",
        "5",
        "2"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the sentence: All flight plans should be filed at least __________ minutes before the EOBT. EOBT = Estimated Off Blocks Time.",
      "choices": [
        "45",
        "60",
        "30",
        "15"
      ],
      "answer": "60"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to the Jeppesen GSPRM, VFR+GPS Chart ED-4. What feature can be found at N47\u00b010\u2019 E011\u00b040\u2019?",
      "choices": [
        "PAT DME 112.00 MHz.",
        "Obstacle 2014' amsl.",
        "Danger Area, LO D-21.",
        "Lit obstacle 2129' amsl."
      ],
      "answer": "Danger Area, LO D-21."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. Find the frequency of the navaid which is located approximately 11 NM south of Munich aerodrome?",
      "choices": [
        "115.00 MHz",
        "112.30 MHz",
        "113.20 MHz",
        "114.40 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "112.30 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the 3 main classifications of space weather warnings?",
      "choices": [
        "R (Regional blackouts), G (Global blackouts), S (Specific blackouts).",
        "R (Radio blackouts), G (Geomagnetic blackouts), S (Solar radiation blackouts).",
        "R (Radio blackouts), G (Geomagnetic storms), S (Solar radiation storms).",
        "R (Radio interruptions), G (Geomagnetic static), S (Solar radiation static)."
      ],
      "answer": "R (Radio blackouts), G (Geomagnetic storms), S (Solar radiation storms)."
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of GPS message can be separated into Scheduled Outages and Non-Scheduled Outages?",
      "choices": [
        "NOTAM",
        "ASHTAM",
        "NANU",
        "RAIM"
      ],
      "answer": "NANU"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft overflies OSMAN at 11.15 UTC and flies a direct track of 80 nm to PEDLO, passing overhead at 11.35 UTC. The TWC is 40 kt. What is the approximate distance covered, measured in nautical air miles?",
      "choices": [
        "96 NAM",
        "201 NAM",
        "67 NAM",
        "141 NAM"
      ],
      "answer": "67 NAM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, calculate the maximum attainable flight time and range. Average fuel flow: 9.6 US gal/h Available fuel: 50 US gal TAS:100 kt Wind component: 15 kt tailwind The flight time is (1) \u2026. and the range is (2) \u2026..",
      "choices": [
        "(1) 5 hours 20 minutes: (2) 599 NM",
        "(1) 5 hours 13 minutes; (2) 599 NM",
        "(1) 5 hours 20 minutes; (2) 521 NM",
        "(1) 5 hours 13 minutes; (2) 521 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) 5 hours 13 minutes; (2) 599 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight planning chart for an aeroplane, states that the time to reach FL 190 at a given gross mass is 22 minutes and the distance travelled is 66 NM (no wind). What will be the distance travelled with a average head wind component of 35 kt?",
      "choices": [
        "53 NM",
        "61 NM",
        "85 NM",
        "79 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "53 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the minimum percentage of planned fuel that can be loaded as contingency fuel under the Basic Fuel/Energy Scheme?",
      "choices": [
        "0.06",
        "0.05",
        "0.02",
        "0.03"
      ],
      "answer": "0.05"
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of flight plan is used by operators who fly regular and/or scheduled flights using the same aircraft type and routing?",
      "choices": [
        "Randomised flight plan",
        "Repetitive flight plan",
        "Authoritive flight plan",
        "Repeat flight plan"
      ],
      "answer": "Repetitive flight plan"
    },
    {
      "question": "A helicopter is on a 130 nm leg to an off-shore oil rig. Its TAS is 150 kt with a 20 kt headwind, its endurance is 3 hr without reserve. Upon reaching destination, it is asked to proceed outbound to locate a ship in distress, on a track which gives a 15 kt tailwind. Maintaining zero reserve on return to the oil rig, the helicopter can fly outbound for a distance of:",
      "choices": [
        "91 nm",
        "223 nm",
        "181 nm",
        "148 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "148 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the meaning of the following NOTAM? Q) EGTT/QSFAU/IV/B/A/000/999/5215N00253W005 B) FROM: 19/01/31 09:00 C) TO: 19/01/31 16:30 E) AFIS NOT AVBL DUE SHORTAGE OF STAFF DUE WX",
      "choices": [
        "Airport Fire Service is not available between 09.00 and 16.30 local time on 19th January due to staff shortage due to weather.",
        "Airport Flight Information Service is not available between 09.00 and 16.30 UTC on 31st January 2019 due to staff shortage due to weather.",
        "Aerodrome Flight Information Service is not available between 09.00 and 16.30 local time on 31st January 2019 due to staff shortage due to weather.",
        "Aerodrome Flight Information Service is not available between 09.00 and 16.30 UTC on 31st January 2019 due to staff shortage due to weather."
      ],
      "answer": "Aerodrome Flight Information Service is not available between 09.00 and 16.30 UTC on 31st January 2019 due to staff shortage due to weather."
    },
    {
      "question": "Given a TAS of 200 kt and a GS of 160 kt, what is the nautical air mile equivalent of 240 NGM?",
      "choices": [
        "100 NAM",
        "450 NAM",
        "300 NAM",
        "200 NAM"
      ],
      "answer": "300 NAM"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum permissible structural mass at the start of the take-off run.\" This definition best describes which of the following?",
      "choices": [
        "PLTOM",
        "ATOM",
        "MSTOM",
        "RTOM"
      ],
      "answer": "MSTOM"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Amsterdam (16-2) You are in a class B aircraft flying at 185 kt. What is the visibility limit for a circle to land approach?",
      "choices": [
        "1500 m",
        "1600 m",
        "2400 m",
        "3600 m"
      ],
      "answer": "3600 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft takes off from an aerodrome at an elevation of 1000 ft amsl and climbs to 7000 ft amsl at a rate of climb of 500 fpm, and an average TAS of 100 kt, with a tailwind of 20 kt. What is the approximate distance covered to the top of climb?",
      "choices": [
        "39 nm",
        "44 km",
        "24 km",
        "44 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "44 km"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 2.5. Given a cruising pressure altitude of 9000 ft and a FULL THROTTLE power setting at 2300 RPM, what are the safe and ATC endurances in hours and minutes?",
      "choices": [
        "4 hr 55 min & 5 hr 40 min",
        "5 hr 30 min & 6 hr 15 min",
        "6 hr 15 min & 5 hr 30 min",
        "5 hr 30 min & 6 hr 00 min"
      ],
      "answer": "5 hr 30 min & 6 hr 15 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following data, calculate the maximum take-off fuel for the aircraft. MSTOM 59 800 kg, RLM 54 200 kg, DOM 38 000 kg, MZFM 50 800 kg, PLTOM 54 600 kg, Trip fuel 3000 kg, Take-off fuel 6000 kg, Traffic Load 9500 kg.",
      "choices": [
        "9000 kg",
        "8200 kg",
        "7100 kg",
        "6000 kg"
      ],
      "answer": "7100 kg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Considering final reserve fuel, what is the minimum that must be on board the aircraft at landing, in accordance with the Basic Fuel/Energy Scheme?",
      "choices": [
        "45 mins holding at 1000 ft AAL for a turbine aircraft",
        "30 mins holding at 1500 ft AAL for a piston aircraft",
        "45 mins holding at 1500 ft AAL for a piston aircraft",
        "45 mins holding at 1500 ft AAL for a turbine aircraft"
      ],
      "answer": "45 mins holding at 1500 ft AAL for a piston aircraft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM Jeppesen Chart Alicante 11-1. What is the height of the highest obstacle within the approach plan view?",
      "choices": [
        "4200 ft",
        "4252 ft",
        "3718 ft",
        "625 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "4252 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the volume of 460 US Gal of AVGAS, having a specific gravity of 0.72?",
      "choices": [
        "1250 kg",
        "384 Imp Gal",
        "2760 lb",
        "17 300 ltr"
      ],
      "answer": "384 Imp Gal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pre-flight Predictive RAIM - AUGUR - allows users to predict operations in which areas of operation?",
      "choices": [
        "Terminal Areas and Radar Vectoring Areas",
        "Terminal Areas (RNAV/RNP 1) and Final Approach (LNAV only)",
        "Terminal Areas (RNAV/RNP 1) and Final Approach (LNAV and LNAV/VNAV)",
        "Terminal Areas (RNAV/RNP 0.3) and Final Approach (LPV)"
      ],
      "answer": "Terminal Areas (RNAV/RNP 1) and Final Approach (LNAV and LNAV/VNAV)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 2.3. Given a power setting of 21 in.Hg. and 2100 RPM, OAT = -3\u00b0C in ISA conditions, find the manifold air pressure, fuel flow, indicated speed and true air speed for the economy cruise at full throttle and pressure altitude of 10 000 ft.",
      "choices": [
        "20.8 in.Hg, 10.0 GPH, 132 KIAS and 144 KTAS",
        "21.0 in.Hg, 9.6 GPH, 126 KIAS and 140 KTAS",
        "20.8 in.Hg, 9.6 GPH, 126 KIAS and 143 KTAS",
        "20.8 in.Hg, 9.5 GPH, 119 KIAS and 141 KTAS"
      ],
      "answer": "20.8 in.Hg, 9.6 GPH, 126 KIAS and 143 KTAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Item 9 of the ATS flight plan includes 'NUMBER AND TYPE OF AIRCRAFT'In this case 'NUMBER' means:",
      "choices": [
        "The registration number of the aircraft.",
        "The number of aircraft which will separately be using a repetitive flight plan (RPL).",
        "The ICAO type designator number as set out in ICAO Doc 8643.",
        "The number of aircraft flying in a group."
      ],
      "answer": "The number of aircraft flying in a group."
    },
    {
      "question": "\"The maximum permissible aircraft mass on landing, subject to meeting aircraft performance requirements at the destination airfield at the time of flight. Often determined by Landing Distance Available and go-around climb performance requirements.\" This definition best describes which of the following?",
      "choices": [
        "RLM",
        "ALM",
        "MSLM",
        "PLLM"
      ],
      "answer": "PLLM"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the event that SELCAL is prescribed by an appropriate authority, in which section of the ATS flight plan will the SELCAL code be entered?",
      "choices": [
        "EQUIPMENT",
        "ROUTE",
        "AIRCRAFT IDENTIFICATION",
        "OTHER INFORMATION"
      ],
      "answer": "OTHER INFORMATION"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the formula for calculating the Point of Equal Time?",
      "choices": [
        "PET = (D x H) \u00f7 (O + H)",
        "PET = (O \u00f7 H) \u00f7 (O + H)",
        "PET = (O x H) x (D \u00f7 H)",
        "PET = (D + H) \u00f7 (O + H)"
      ],
      "answer": "PET = (D x H) \u00f7 (O + H)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. You depart from BEILNGRIES / EDNC aerodrome (N49 01.3 E011 29.1) and then continue eastbound at the minimum grid altitude. Your altimeter scale is incorrectly set to 1010 hPa while the QNH given by the aerodrome is 1001 hPa. What is your approximate true altitude, shortly after departure, if the temperature at 3500 ft is 18\u00b0C?",
      "choices": [
        "3690 ft",
        "3230 ft",
        "3310 ft",
        "3580 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "3310 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of service provides aerodrome information in data rather than aural form.",
      "choices": [
        "ACARS",
        "D-ATIS",
        "ATIS",
        "VOLMET"
      ],
      "answer": "D-ATIS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to CAP 697 Figure 2.1. Given OAT = ISA and a departure airport at sea level, an aircraft with a take-off mass of 3650 lb climbs to FL120 for its cruise. Calculate the time, the fuel and distance in the climb?",
      "choices": [
        "12 min, 4.2 USG, 24 nm",
        "23 min, 7.4 USG, 47 nm",
        "19 min, 6.4 USG, 38 nm",
        "9 min, 3.5 USG, 19 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "19 min, 6.4 USG, 38 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "A descent is planned from 7500 ft AMSL so as to arrive at 1000 ft AMSL 6 NM from a VORTAC. With a GS of 156 kts and a rate of descent of 800 ft/min. The distance from the VORTAC when descent is started is:",
      "choices": [
        "30.2 NM",
        "27.1 NM",
        "15.0 NM",
        "11.7 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "27.1 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the acronym ATFM, commonly used in modern commercial aviation, stand for?",
      "choices": [
        "Air Traffic Flow Management.",
        "Aviation Traffic Fuel Management.",
        "Air Traffic Flight Plan Management.",
        "Air Traffic Flow Movements."
      ],
      "answer": "Air Traffic Flow Management."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the ATS flight plan item 7, for a radio equipped aircraft, the identifier must always:",
      "choices": [
        "Include an indication of the aircraft type.",
        "Include the operating agency designator.",
        "Include the aircraft registration marking.",
        "Be the RTF callsign to be used."
      ],
      "answer": "Be the RTF callsign to be used."
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to GSPRM - VFR chart ED-4. An aircraft is on a VFR flight in Austria. The departure airfield is RIED KIRCHHEIM (LOLK, N48 12.8 E13 20.8) and the destination is FREISTADT (LOLF, N48 30.9 E14 24.5). Which of the following radio frequencies should be used as a radio navigation aid if the pilot intends to fly directly to the destination?",
      "choices": [
        "122.32 (Freistadt airfield)",
        "116.60 MHz (Linz VOR)",
        "113.50 MHz (Freistadt VOR)",
        "327 kHz (Linz NDB)"
      ],
      "answer": "113.50 MHz (Freistadt VOR)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the correct VFR cruising altitude, on a heading of 176\u00b0T in nil wind, in a region where magnetic variation is 6\u00b0W?",
      "choices": [
        "FL 180",
        "FL 175",
        "FL 125",
        "FL 210"
      ],
      "answer": "FL 125"
    },
    {
      "question": "Refer to Jeppesen GSPRM VFR+GPS Chart ED-4 What frequency is used for VDF at Stuttgart airport (EDDS) (N48\u00b041.4\u2019 E009\u00b013.3\u2019)?",
      "choices": [
        "134.50 MHz",
        "118.80 MHz",
        "129.60 MHz",
        "122.80 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "118.80 MHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Complete the sentence: For North Atlantic flights and those subject to Air Traffic Flow Management (ATFM) measures, the flight plan must be filed not less than __________ hours before EOBT. EOBT = Estimated Off Blocks Time.",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "6",
        "2",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, what is the TAS in the cruise at the highest VFR cruising altitude between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden (EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006?' Visibility: 20 km Cloud: OVC 7000 Temperature: ISA QNH: 1033 hPa W/V: 100\u00b0(T)/30 kt CAS: 145 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "160 kt",
        "127 kt",
        "162 kt",
        "156 kt"
      ],
      "answer": "156 kt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given the following information, when flying between Schw\u00e4bish Hall (EDTY) N49\u00b008' E009\u00b047' and Karlsruhe/Baden-Baden (EDSB) N48\u00b046' E008\u00b006', what is the flight time between the line features formed by the A81 and A8 autobahns (motorways)? Visibility: 20 km Cloud: OVC 7000 Temperature: ISA QNH: 1033 hPa W/V: 100\u00b0(T)/30 kt CAS: 145 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "38 min",
        "9 min",
        "19 min",
        "7.5 min"
      ],
      "answer": "9 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given that distance from REKLO to SAMDU is 240 nm into a 40 kt headwind, TAS = 160 kt, what is the distance to the PET from REKLO (in nm)?",
      "choices": [
        "120",
        "110",
        "150",
        "100"
      ],
      "answer": "150"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does an entry of G mean in ITEM 10 EQUIPMENT of the ICAO Flight Plan form?",
      "choices": [
        "A GPS receiver that can be augmented by Galileo is fitted.",
        "The aircraft is suitably equipped for any published GNSS procedure.",
        "A GPS receiver that complies with the requirements of ICAO Annex 10 is fitted.",
        "A GNSS receiver that complies with the requirements of ICAO Annex 10 is fitted."
      ],
      "answer": "A GNSS receiver that complies with the requirements of ICAO Annex 10 is fitted."
    }
  ],
  "COM": [
    {
      "question": "What is the minimum rest at the home base?",
      "choices": [
        "12",
        "10",
        "14",
        "8"
      ],
      "answer": "12"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the time interval between Recurrent training",
      "choices": [
        "6 Months",
        "8 Months",
        "12 Months",
        "24 Months"
      ],
      "answer": "12 Months"
    },
    {
      "question": "Can you Take-off when no RVR is availiable",
      "choices": [
        "No",
        "Yes, if you can determin it yourself",
        "Yes, if your operator says so",
        "Never"
      ],
      "answer": "Yes, if you can determin it yourself"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the time interval between operator proffeciency check",
      "choices": [
        "6 Months",
        "8 Months",
        "12 Months",
        "24 Months"
      ],
      "answer": "6 Months"
    },
    {
      "question": "When do we speak of LVR",
      "choices": [
        "RVR below 1200",
        "RVR below 600",
        "RVR below 400",
        "RVR below 300"
      ],
      "answer": "RVR below 400"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the lowest approved MDH for a VOR",
      "choices": [
        "300 ft",
        "600 ft",
        "250 ft",
        "200 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "300 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Can you take-off after your holdover-time has elapsed",
      "choices": [
        "Yes",
        "Yes, if approved so by the opperator",
        "No, you need to redo your anti-icing",
        "Yes, if you have to take-off"
      ],
      "answer": "No, you need to redo your anti-icing"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a consequence of a tailwind windshear",
      "choices": [
        "Above the glidslope",
        "Below the glideslope",
        "Increased TAS",
        "Decreased GS"
      ],
      "answer": "Below the glideslope"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where are the flighthours and aircraft-info stored?",
      "choices": [
        "Tech-Log",
        "Journey Log",
        "Certificate of Airworthiness",
        "Flightplan"
      ],
      "answer": "Tech-Log"
    },
    {
      "question": "What concept is in focus when icing conditions exist?",
      "choices": [
        "Clean wing concept",
        "Clean aircraft concept",
        "Anti-Icing measures",
        "Clean Engines Concept"
      ],
      "answer": "Clean aircraft concept"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is an accurate description of wet snow?",
      "choices": [
        "Snow which, if compacted by hand, will stick together and tend to or form a snowball",
        "Snow which can be blown if loose or, if compacted by hand, will fall apart again upon release",
        "Water-saturated snow which, with a heel-and-toe slap-down motion against the ground, will be displaced with a splatter",
        "Snow with a layer of water above it"
      ],
      "answer": "Snow which, if compacted by hand, will stick together and tend to or form a snowball"
    },
    {
      "question": "When more than one cabin crew member is required, the composition of the cabin crew shall include a senior cabin crew member nominated by:",
      "choices": [
        "The commander",
        "The Operator",
        "The flight dispatcher",
        "The commitee of senior cabin crew members"
      ],
      "answer": "The Operator"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    },
    {
      "question": "nan",
      "choices": [
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan",
        "nan"
      ],
      "answer": "nan"
    }
  ],
  "MET": [
    {
      "question": "What is the interval over which the wind speed is reported for METARs and SPECIs?",
      "choices": [
        "10 min",
        "7 min",
        "2 min",
        "4 min"
      ],
      "answer": "10 min"
    },
    {
      "question": "A plain in western Europe with an average elevation of 500 m (1600 ft) above sea level is covered with a uniform AC layer of cloud during the summer months. At what height above the ground is the base of this cloud to be expected?",
      "choices": [
        "15 000 - 25 000 ft",
        "7000 - 15 000 ft",
        "100 - 1500 ft",
        "1500 - 7000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "7000 - 15 000 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is encountered during the summer, over land, in the centre of a cold air drop?",
      "choices": [
        "Showers and thunderstorms.",
        "Fine weather CU.",
        "Clear sky.",
        "Strong westerly winds."
      ],
      "answer": "Showers and thunderstorms."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Bora?",
      "choices": [
        "An anabatic wind in the Rockies.",
        "Cold katabatic wind over the Adriatic.",
        "Northerly wind blowing from the Mediterranean.",
        "Warm anabatic wind blowing to the Mediterranean."
      ],
      "answer": "Cold katabatic wind over the Adriatic."
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the facility with the service it provides: Forecasts of volcanic ash clouds.",
      "choices": [
        "WMO",
        "VAACs",
        "MWO",
        "WAFC"
      ],
      "answer": "VAACs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mountains can affect ice accretion, due to orographic intensification, because:",
      "choices": [
        "They form a topographical barrier where high pressure systems with moderate to severe icing conditions may form.",
        "This is often referred to as the F\u00f6hn effect.",
        "The air may become polluted by dust from the mountain slopes, creating hygroscopic freezing nuclei.",
        "On the leeward side supercooled water droplets form due to the associated temperature drop."
      ],
      "answer": "The air may become polluted by dust from the mountain slopes, creating hygroscopic freezing nuclei."
    },
    {
      "question": "The stages and life cycle of a mid-latitude depression are:",
      "choices": [
        "Cyclogenesis, occluded, frontolysis, and mature.",
        "Cyclogenesis, mature, occluded and frontolysis.",
        "Frontolysis, occluded, cyclogenesis, and mature.",
        "Occluded, cyclogenesis, frontolysis, and mature."
      ],
      "answer": "Cyclogenesis, mature, occluded and frontolysis."
    },
    {
      "question": "When are the rainy seasons in equatorial Africa?",
      "choices": [
        "March to May and August to October",
        "December to February and July to October.",
        "March to May and October to November",
        "April to July and December to February."
      ],
      "answer": "March to May and October to November"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are flying in the northern hemisphere at 2000 ft over a flat country area. An anticyclone is ahead of you and a depression is behind you. The wind affecting you, will be:",
      "choices": [
        "From ahead.",
        "From behind.",
        "From your right.",
        "From your left."
      ],
      "answer": "From your right."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the average diameter of a tropical revolving storm in the mature stage?",
      "choices": [
        "1200 km",
        "500 km",
        "10 km",
        "50 km"
      ],
      "answer": "500 km"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does RVR stand for?",
      "choices": [
        "Reduced vertical range.",
        "Radio VHF range.",
        "Reduced visibility range.",
        "Runway visual range."
      ],
      "answer": "Runway visual range."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ images can reveal wind patterns and jet streams. Darker colours indicate drier air; brighter colours indicate high moisture content, or vice versa.",
      "choices": [
        "Infrared",
        "Visible",
        "Water vapour",
        "Doppler"
      ],
      "answer": "Water vapour"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many hurricanes form on average per year in the Atlantic?",
      "choices": [
        "1",
        "6",
        "15",
        "25"
      ],
      "answer": "6"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following situations favours the formation of heavy thunderstorms?",
      "choices": [
        "The passage of a warm front in the morning.",
        "A cold front on the leeward side of a mountain range.",
        "A cold front approaching a mountain range in the evening.",
        "A warm sector moving over a snow-covered ground."
      ],
      "answer": "A cold front approaching a mountain range in the evening."
    },
    {
      "question": "The wind speed in a system with curved isobars compared to a system with straight isobars is (other conditions being the same):",
      "choices": [
        "always lower.",
        "higher if curvature is cyclonic.",
        "higher if curvature is anticyclonic.",
        "always higher."
      ],
      "answer": "higher if curvature is anticyclonic."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the code R24R/P1500 mean?",
      "choices": [
        "RVR RWY 24 right 1500 metres.",
        "Snow clearance in progress on RWY 24 right, useable runway length 1500 metres.",
        "RVR RWY 24 right below 1500 metres.",
        "RVR RWY 24 right above 1500 metres."
      ],
      "answer": "RVR RWY 24 right above 1500 metres."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which 2 of the following statements about airborne weather radar (AWR) is/are correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Most modern AWR can detect areas of ice crystal icing.",
        "Anomalous propagation is a phenomenon which causes CBs to be hidden.",
        "Antenna pan (sweep) is controlled automatically by the system. Tilt always has to be manually adjusted by the crew.",
        "Most modern AWR have doppler capability."
      ],
      "answer": "Most modern AWR have doppler capability., AWR can only detect returns from liquid water."
    },
    {
      "question": "Atmospheric __________ is mostly caused by rising or sinking air drawing in air from either side.",
      "choices": [
        "convergence",
        "divergence",
        "subsidence",
        "advection"
      ],
      "answer": "convergence"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which is true of a secondary depression in the northern hemisphere?",
      "choices": [
        "It tends to maintain its position relative to the primary.",
        "It rapidly closes on, and merges with the primary.",
        "It tends to move round the primary in an anticyclonic sense.",
        "It tends to move round the primary in a cyclonic sense."
      ],
      "answer": "It tends to move round the primary in a cyclonic sense."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct? A cold front:",
      "choices": [
        "usually moves across the surface faster than a warm front.",
        "is the part of the depression where the wind flows from low to high pressure.",
        "is characterised by the exchange of cold air by warm air.",
        "will circle the centre of the depression in an anticlockwise direction in the southern hemisphere."
      ],
      "answer": "usually moves across the surface faster than a warm front."
    },
    {
      "question": "What does the term SIGMET signify?",
      "choices": [
        "A SIGMET is an actual weather report at an aerodrome and is generally issued at half-hourly intervals.",
        "A SIGMET is a flight forecast, issued by the meteorological station several times daily.",
        "A SIGMET is a warning of dangerous meteorological conditions.",
        "A SIGMET is a brief landing forecast added to the actual weather report."
      ],
      "answer": "A SIGMET is a warning of dangerous meteorological conditions."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which part of the world are tropical revolving storms (TRS) most frequent?",
      "choices": [
        "Caribbean.",
        "Northern Indian Oceans around India, Sri Lanka.",
        "North-West Pacific (for example Japan, Korea, SE Asia).",
        "Madagascar, Eastern Indian Ocean."
      ],
      "answer": "North-West Pacific (for example Japan, Korea, SE Asia)."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the northern hemisphere advection of warm air aloft indicates:",
      "choices": [
        "the approach of a warm occlusion.",
        "backing winds with increasing heights.",
        "the formation of advection fog.",
        "increasing probability for showers."
      ],
      "answer": "the approach of a warm occlusion."
    },
    {
      "question": "The pressure steadily __________ as a warm front approaches.",
      "choices": [
        "rises",
        "falls",
        "remains constant",
        "fluctuates"
      ],
      "answer": "falls"
    },
    {
      "question": "Subsidence is a feature of __________ pressure systems.",
      "choices": [
        "low",
        "high",
        "mid",
        "stationary"
      ],
      "answer": "high"
    },
    {
      "question": "Generally, cold fronts move __________ than warm fronts.",
      "choices": [
        "slower",
        "faster",
        "same speed",
        "None of these"
      ],
      "answer": "faster"
    },
    {
      "question": "The location of which jet stream is largely dependent on the position of weather fronts?",
      "choices": [
        "Equatorial Easterly jet.",
        "The subtropical front jet.",
        "Arctic jet stream.",
        "The polar front jet ."
      ],
      "answer": "The polar front jet ."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ lows result from small-scale lows forming downwind of mountain barriers.",
      "choices": [
        "Thermal",
        "Divergence",
        "Orographic",
        "Convergence"
      ],
      "answer": "Orographic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Air rising or sinking in the atmosphere encounters barriers which prevent further vertical motion so, vertical motion is translated into horizontal motion. This is common at the bottom of high pressures near the surface and the top of low pressures near the tropopause. This description describe the mechanism which causes __________.",
      "choices": [
        "divergence",
        "convergence",
        "cyclogenesis",
        "None of these"
      ],
      "answer": "divergence"
    },
    {
      "question": "VTSP CNL AD WRNG 2 300100/300300 This message means:",
      "choices": [
        "There is an aerodrome warning between 01:00Z and 03:00Z on the 30th of the month.",
        "There are two occasional warnings for a certain weather phenomena.",
        "The aerodrome warning number 2 issued at VTSP is canceled.",
        "The aerodrome VTSP is closed during the mentioned timeframe."
      ],
      "answer": "The aerodrome warning number 2 issued at VTSP is canceled."
    },
    {
      "question": "A blocking anticyclone in the northern hemisphere is:",
      "choices": [
        "a cold anticyclone, situated over Scandinavia and steering depressions.",
        "a cold anticyclone, situated between 50\u00b0N and 70\u00b0N and steering depressions.",
        "a quasi-stationary, cold anticyclone, situated between 50\u00b0N and 70\u00b0N.",
        "a quasi-stationary, warm anticyclone, situated between 50\u00b0N and 70\u00b0N."
      ],
      "answer": "a quasi-stationary, warm anticyclone, situated between 50\u00b0N and 70\u00b0N."
    },
    {
      "question": "They prepare global sets of gridded forecasts for flight planning (upper wind, temperature, humidity) and also produce gridded datasets for specific FLs showing the temperature of the tropopause, the direction and speed of the maximum wind, cumulonimbus clouds, icing and turbulence. This is a function of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "meteorological optical rangers",
        "world area forecast centres",
        "meteorological watch offices",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "answer": "world area forecast centres"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which general direction does a polar front depression move?",
      "choices": [
        "Across the front towards the south.",
        "Along the front towards the west.",
        "Across the front towards the north.",
        "Along the front towards the east."
      ],
      "answer": "Along the front towards the east."
    },
    {
      "question": "You are on an approach to an airfield, descending through the friction layer. The wind changes from a headwind to a slight right crosswind.",
      "choices": [
        "The airfield is most probably situated near water (on the coast).",
        "This is due to changing wind directions on approach.",
        "This is typical for northern hemisphere.",
        "This is typical for southern hemisphere."
      ],
      "answer": "This is typical for southern hemisphere."
    },
    {
      "question": "Continental tracks __________ the relative and absolute humidity of an air mass.",
      "choices": [
        "have no effect on",
        "decrease",
        "increase",
        "change"
      ],
      "answer": "decrease"
    },
    {
      "question": "What types of cloud will you see flying at FL 50 towards a warm front?",
      "choices": [
        "At some 500 km from the front, groups of CB, later at some 250 km thickening AS.",
        "At some 500 km AS, later CS and at some 80 km before the front CB.",
        "At some 800 km CS, later AS, and at some 300 km NS until the front.",
        "Mainly clear skies. At some 100 km from the front NS begins."
      ],
      "answer": "At some 800 km CS, later AS, and at some 300 km NS until the front."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the meanings of the meteorological abbreviations SQ, BR, MIFG and SG respectively?",
      "choices": [
        "Sudden increase in wind speed lasting for at least one minute / mist / shallow fog / snowgrains.",
        "Short wind gust / fog / shallow fog / snowgrains.",
        "Short wind gust / mist / shallow fog / polar snow.",
        "Sudden strong increase in wind speed lasting for at least one minute / haze / patches of fog / snowgrains."
      ],
      "answer": "Sudden increase in wind speed lasting for at least one minute / mist / shallow fog / snowgrains."
    },
    {
      "question": "The worst weather in an occluded front occurs __________.",
      "choices": [
        "near the apex of the occlusion",
        "in the warm sector air",
        "behind the cold front",
        "along the warm front"
      ],
      "answer": "near the apex of the occlusion"
    },
    {
      "question": "A SIGMET message concerning a tropical cyclone begins with a 2-letter identifier code group:",
      "choices": [
        "WV",
        "TC",
        "AT",
        "WC"
      ],
      "answer": "TC"
    },
    {
      "question": "On which coast of North America, is the danger of tropical revolving storms the greatest?",
      "choices": [
        "W coast.",
        "SE coast.",
        "N coast.",
        "NE coast."
      ],
      "answer": "SE coast."
    },
    {
      "question": "Tropical revolving storms require energy from a large body of water which must be greater than __________\u00b0C.",
      "choices": [
        "26",
        "0",
        "5",
        "10"
      ],
      "answer": "26"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Europe, warm occlusions are more common in __________; cold occlusions are more common in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "summer; winter",
        "winter; summer",
        "summer; summer",
        "winter; winter"
      ],
      "answer": "winter; summer"
    },
    {
      "question": "A continuous broadcast of arrival or departure information for busy airports, preceded by an identification letter. Includes such information as runway in use, surface wind, RVR, present weather, significant cloud and type of approach expected. This is a description of a service called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "aerodrome traffic information service (ATIS)",
        "VOLMET",
        "automatic terminal information service (ATIS)",
        "aerodrome terminal information service (ATIS)"
      ],
      "answer": "automatic terminal information service (ATIS)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Surface wind measurements contained in METAR and SPECI reports are referenced to __________ North and are averaged over the previous __________ minutes.",
      "choices": [
        "True; 10",
        "True; 30",
        "Magnetic; 30",
        "Magnetic; 10"
      ],
      "answer": "True; 10"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mountain waves should be expected:",
      "choices": [
        "on the downwind side of the mountain range.",
        "on the upwind side of the mountain range.",
        "directly over the mountain range.",
        "when instability is high."
      ],
      "answer": "on the downwind side of the mountain range."
    },
    {
      "question": "The whole polar front moves in the same direction as, and parallel to, the isobars in the __________ at a speed determined by the geostrophic interval of the __________ isobars.",
      "choices": [
        "warm sector; warm sector",
        "cold sector; warm sector",
        "cold sector; cold sector",
        "warm sector; cold sector"
      ],
      "answer": "warm sector; warm sector"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the facility with the service it provides: Provides SIGMETs and AIRMETs.",
      "choices": [
        "VAACs",
        "MWO",
        "WAFC",
        "WMO"
      ],
      "answer": "MWO"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the facility with the service it provides: Provides operational information and also implements a global framework for the national met services.",
      "choices": [
        "MWO",
        "WAFC",
        "WMO",
        "TCACs"
      ],
      "answer": "WMO"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the met product and its description: A weather advisory issued by MWO's that contains meteorological information concerning the safety of all aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "AIRMET",
        "SPECI",
        "SIGMET",
        "TAF"
      ],
      "answer": "SIGMET"
    },
    {
      "question": "Subsidence tends to produce __________ pressure gradients with little weather.",
      "choices": [
        "strong",
        "slack",
        "no",
        "changing"
      ],
      "answer": "slack"
    },
    {
      "question": "Non-frontal low-pressure areas with weak circulation that occur due to intense heating over the continents in the subtropics during the warm season. This is a description of a __________ low.",
      "choices": [
        "thermal",
        "orographic",
        "divergence",
        "Convergence"
      ],
      "answer": "thermal"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the typical position of ITCZ in July?",
      "choices": [
        "Passing through Freetown, Bahamas.",
        "20\u00b0N over West Africa.",
        "Over West Africa at 25\u00b0 N and stretches up to the north of the Arabian sea.",
        "Near the Canaries."
      ],
      "answer": "20\u00b0N over West Africa."
    },
    {
      "question": "Although the large-scale structure of atmospheric circulation varies from year to year (e.g. El Nino/La Nina events), the basic structure remains fairly constant because it is determined by:",
      "choices": [
        "the Earth's rotation rate, the passage of air from high to low pressure, and the unequal heating of land and sea.",
        "the permanent transport of heat from the equator to higher latitudes by ocean currents such as the Gulf Stream.",
        "varying solar influx, which is compensated by the specific heat capacity of the continents and seas.",
        "the Coriolis force acting on the atmosphere and the constant temperature profiles over the oceans."
      ],
      "answer": "the Earth's rotation rate, the passage of air from high to low pressure, and the unequal heating of land and sea."
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the met product and its description: Weather report which supplements routine reports when significant improvements or deteriorations occur.",
      "choices": [
        "METAR",
        "SPECI",
        "TAF",
        "SIGMET"
      ],
      "answer": "SPECI"
    },
    {
      "question": "Air masses that travel from warmer to colder locations are cooled from below, this __________ the ELR and __________ stability.",
      "choices": [
        "decreases; increases",
        "increases; increases",
        "increases; decreases",
        "decreases; decreases"
      ],
      "answer": "decreases; increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "Convergence tends to __________ the creation of active weather.",
      "choices": [
        "weaken",
        "promote",
        "diminish",
        "have no effect on"
      ],
      "answer": "promote"
    },
    {
      "question": "At the passing of a warm front, the wind __________.",
      "choices": [
        "remains constant",
        "veers then backs",
        "backs then veers",
        "veers"
      ],
      "answer": "backs then veers"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where is a squall line most likely to be expected?",
      "choices": [
        "In front of a cold occlusion at higher levels.",
        "At the surface position of a warm front.",
        "In front of an active cold front.",
        "Behind a cold front."
      ],
      "answer": "In front of an active cold front."
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the met product and its description: Met actuals report giving routine weather reports.",
      "choices": [
        "SIGMET",
        "METAR",
        "GAMET",
        "SPECI"
      ],
      "answer": "METAR"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a significant weather chart you notice a surface weather front with an arrow labelled with the number 5 pointing outward perpendicular from the front. This would indicate:",
      "choices": [
        "A front speed is 5 kt.",
        "A front is 5000 ft AMSL.",
        "A front thickness is 5 km.",
        "A front movement is 5 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "A front speed is 5 kt."
    },
    {
      "question": "An _____ is a report from an aircraft in flight given in either of 2 standard formats: Routine aircraft observations given during en-route and climb-out phases of the flight; generally only requested from aircraft with a data link capability. Special and other non-routine aircraft observations during any phase of the flight.",
      "choices": [
        "special report (SPECI)",
        "pilot report (PIREP)",
        "air report (AIREP)",
        "meteorological report (METAR)"
      ],
      "answer": "air report (AIREP)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Most mid-latitude depressions move from __________ to __________ in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "east; west; the northern hemisphere",
        "west; east; the northern hemisphere",
        "west; east; the southern hemisphere",
        "west; east; both hemispheres"
      ],
      "answer": "west; east; both hemispheres"
    },
    {
      "question": "Both types of AIREP can be transmitted by datalink or voicecom __________.",
      "choices": [
        "to an appropriate ATC controller",
        "to meteorological watch offices",
        "to WAFCs",
        "at any time"
      ],
      "answer": "to an appropriate ATC controller"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 3 main air masses that affect Europe are:",
      "choices": [
        "Polar Maritime, Arctic Maritime and Tropical Maritime.",
        "Polar Maritime, Tropical Maritime and Tropical Continental.",
        "Polar Maritime, Tropical Maritime and Tropical Maritime.",
        "Polar Maritime, Polar Continental and Arctic Maritime."
      ],
      "answer": "Polar Maritime, Tropical Maritime and Tropical Continental."
    },
    {
      "question": "Polar lows are caused by very cold air from ice shelves or very cold land masses blowing over the relatively warmer sea. This produces __________ atmospheric conditions.",
      "choices": [
        "relatively stable",
        "stable",
        "moderately unstable",
        "very unstable"
      ],
      "answer": "very unstable"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pre-recorded, plain language, ground-to-air radio broadcasts of aerodrome reports and forecasts are known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "VOLMET",
        "SPECI",
        "TAF",
        "ATIS"
      ],
      "answer": "VOLMET"
    },
    {
      "question": "Maritime tracks __________ the relative and absolute humidity of an air mass.",
      "choices": [
        "decrease",
        "increase",
        "have no effect on",
        "change"
      ],
      "answer": "increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "If during the last 10 minutes preceding the issuance of a METAR the wind velocity deviates more than 10 kt from mean value obtained during the same period of time, this will be indicated as:",
      "choices": [
        "A squall.",
        "Geostrophic wind.",
        "TEMPO 10 kts.",
        "A gust."
      ],
      "answer": "A gust."
    },
    {
      "question": "In an occluded front, the warm sector air is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "squeezed between the warm and cold fronts",
        "lifted off the surface",
        "located in the warm sector",
        "located behind the cold front"
      ],
      "answer": "lifted off the surface"
    },
    {
      "question": "At the approach of a warm front (northern hemisphere) the wind direction changes from the surface up to the tropopause. The effect of this change is that the wind",
      "choices": [
        "backs in the friction layer and veers above the friction layer.",
        "veers in the friction layer and veers above the friction layer.",
        "veers in the friction layer and backs above the friction layer.",
        "backs in the friction layer and backs above the friction layer."
      ],
      "answer": "veers in the friction layer and veers above the friction layer."
    },
    {
      "question": "What average geographical latitude is assumed for the zone of the travelling frontal depressions?",
      "choices": [
        "10\u00b0N",
        "60\u00b0N",
        "80\u00b0N",
        "30\u00b0N"
      ],
      "answer": "60\u00b0N"
    },
    {
      "question": "The approximate inclined plane of a warm front is:",
      "choices": [
        "1/150",
        "1/500",
        "1/300",
        "1/50"
      ],
      "answer": "1/150"
    },
    {
      "question": "Air masses that travel over colder to warmer locations are heated from below, this __________ the ELR and __________ stability.",
      "choices": [
        "increases; increases",
        "decreases; increases",
        "decreases; reduces",
        "increases; reduces"
      ],
      "answer": "increases; reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tracking clouds, or areas of water vapour across consecutive satellite images, can reveal __________.",
      "choices": [
        "atmospheric motion vectors",
        "vertical development of CBs",
        "areas of CAT",
        "fronts"
      ],
      "answer": "atmospheric motion vectors"
    },
    {
      "question": "Winds reported by the control tower and in local routine reports (ATIS) are averaged over the previous __________ minutes and are referenced to __________ North.",
      "choices": [
        "10; True",
        "10; Magnetic",
        "2; True",
        "2; Magnetic"
      ],
      "answer": "2; Magnetic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which option correctly places, in a chronological order, the four stages of a mid-latitude depression life cycle? The stages are named and described as follows: Occlusion: the cold front has caught up with the warm front, the warm air has been partially lifted up. Developed: fronts are well defined, there is a pronounced warm sector. Cyclogenesis: a disturbance and fall in pressure causes cyclonic circulation. Frontolysis: all the warm air has been lifted up.",
      "choices": [
        "Occlusion, Frontolysis, Developed, Cyclogenesis.",
        "Frontolysis, Cyclogenesis, Developed, Occlusion.",
        "Cyclogenesis, Frontolysis, Developed, Occlusion.",
        "Cyclogenesis, Developed, Occlusion, Frontolysis."
      ],
      "answer": "Cyclogenesis, Developed, Occlusion, Frontolysis."
    },
    {
      "question": "How often shall the information produced by an airfield windshear alert system be updated?",
      "choices": [
        "Every 30 minutes.",
        "Every hour.",
        "Every 15 minutes.",
        "Every minute."
      ],
      "answer": "Every minute."
    },
    {
      "question": "The 500 hPa contour chart is equivalent to:",
      "choices": [
        "FL90",
        "FL300",
        "FL180",
        "FL50"
      ],
      "answer": "FL180"
    },
    {
      "question": "An occluded front is formed by __________.",
      "choices": [
        "cyclogenesis",
        "cyclonism",
        "cyclic uplift",
        "frontolysis"
      ],
      "answer": "cyclogenesis"
    },
    {
      "question": "The mass of air in the column reduces because air leaves more quickly at high level than it can enter at the surface. Net loss of mass means lower pressure. This is a description of high level __________.",
      "choices": [
        "divergence",
        "depression",
        "convergence",
        "convection"
      ],
      "answer": "divergence"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the facility with the service it provides: Forecasts of tropical cyclones.",
      "choices": [
        "VAACs",
        "TCACs",
        "WAFC",
        "WMO"
      ],
      "answer": "TCACs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tropical revolving storms require an unstable, moist atmosphere with little vertical shear and can only begin to generate beyond the latitudes of __________\u00b0N/S.",
      "choices": [
        "25",
        "50",
        "30",
        "5"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the met product and its description: An area forecast for low altitude intended for GA aircraft.",
      "choices": [
        "TAF",
        "METAR",
        "AIRMET",
        "GAMET"
      ],
      "answer": "GAMET"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where are easterly waves found?",
      "choices": [
        "On the poleward side of the subtropical high pressure belt.",
        "Between subtropical high pressure cells and ITCZ.",
        "In the region of the subtropical jet stream.",
        "In the temperate latitudes."
      ],
      "answer": "Between subtropical high pressure cells and ITCZ."
    },
    {
      "question": "Between which latitudes are you most likely to find the region of travelling polar front depressions during summer?",
      "choices": [
        "15\u00b0 - 25\u00b0.",
        "25\u00b0 - 45\u00b0.",
        "10\u00b0 - 15\u00b0.",
        "45\u00b0 - 70\u00b0."
      ],
      "answer": "45\u00b0 - 70\u00b0."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which 1 of the following cloud sequences describes the onset and arrival of a warm front? In order of appearance over an observer on the ground:",
      "choices": [
        "Ci, Cs AS, NS, St.",
        "Cb Ac",
        "St, Ci, Cs, NS.",
        "AS, NS, Cb. St"
      ],
      "answer": "Ci, Cs AS, NS, St."
    },
    {
      "question": "When flying in mountainous terrain and assuming ISA temperatures and strong winds, which of the following is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "In cases of the venturi effect, the indicated altitude of the aircraft is lower than the actual altitude.",
        "In cases of the combined effect of surface friction and adiabatic compression of the air, the dynamic pressure is lower than indicated by the altimeter.",
        "In cases of adiabatic compression of the air, the temperature is lower than indicated.",
        "In cases of the venturi effect, the actual altitude of the aircraft is lower than the indicated altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "In cases of the venturi effect, the actual altitude of the aircraft is lower than the indicated altitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the typical bases of 'ALTO' type clouds in mid-latitudes?",
      "choices": [
        "6500 ft",
        "Surface",
        "1000 ft",
        "16 500 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "6500 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "A layer of stratus is most likely to be dispersed by:",
      "choices": [
        "Adiabatic cooling due to subsidence.",
        "The release of latent heat due to precipitation.",
        "Insolation resulting in the lifting of the condensation level.",
        "Absorption of long waved solar radiation in the stratus layer."
      ],
      "answer": "Insolation resulting in the lifting of the condensation level."
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the type of precipitation with the most appropriate description. Transparent or partly or completely opaque pieces of ice with a diameter 5 mm to 50 mm.",
      "choices": [
        "Snow pellets",
        "Hail",
        "Snow grains",
        "Ice pellets"
      ],
      "answer": "Hail"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Bora is a type of __________ wind.",
      "choices": [
        "anabatic",
        "katabatic",
        "thermal",
        "Foehn"
      ],
      "answer": "katabatic"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is a suspension of very small, usually microscopic water drops (liquid or solid) in the air, reducing visibility at the surface to between 1000 m and 5000 m.",
      "choices": [
        "Haze",
        "Sea smoke",
        "Mist",
        "Fog"
      ],
      "answer": "Mist"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jet streams have a core speed of at least __________ kt, are typically about 2000 NM long and about __________ NM wide.",
      "choices": [
        "60; 200",
        "20; 50",
        "5; 200",
        "10; 100"
      ],
      "answer": "60; 200"
    },
    {
      "question": "This (non-precipitating) cloud type is called __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "cumulus",
        "cirrostratus",
        "cirrocumulus",
        "altocumulus"
      ],
      "answer": "cumulus"
    },
    {
      "question": "The reporting code 'FG' indicates that the visibility is less than __________.",
      "choices": [
        "500 m",
        "1500 m",
        "5000 m",
        "1000 m"
      ],
      "answer": "1000 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following choices lists only main cloud genera that are mostly the clue for an unstable thermal stratification in the atmosphere?",
      "choices": [
        "Cirrocumulus, altostratus, stratocumulus.",
        "Cirrocumulus, altocumulus, cumulus.",
        "Stratocumulus, altostratus, cirrus.",
        "Cirrostratus, altostratus, stratus."
      ],
      "answer": "Cirrocumulus, altocumulus, cumulus."
    },
    {
      "question": "The main factor which contributes to the formation of very low clouds ahead of a warm front is the:",
      "choices": [
        "reduction of outgoing radiation due to clouds.",
        "warm air moving over a cold surface.",
        "saturation of the warm air by rain falling into it and evaporating.",
        "saturation of the cold air by rain falling into it and evaporating."
      ],
      "answer": "saturation of the cold air by rain falling into it and evaporating."
    },
    {
      "question": "Assign the description to an icing intensity category: The rate of accumulation is such that even short encounters become potentially hazardous.",
      "choices": [
        "Trace",
        "Moderate",
        "Severe",
        "Light"
      ],
      "answer": "Moderate"
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of clouds can one expect after a cold front has passed?",
      "choices": [
        "Cumulus clouds.",
        "Cirrostratus clouds.",
        "Cumulonimbus clouds.",
        "Cirrus clouds."
      ],
      "answer": "Cumulus clouds."
    },
    {
      "question": "Changes in altitude and/or attitude occur, the aircraft remains in positive control at all times and the IAS fluctuates 15-25 kt. (0.5-1.0 g). This is a description of:",
      "choices": [
        "Light turbulence.",
        "Moderate turbulence",
        "Intermittent turbulence.",
        "Severe turbulence"
      ],
      "answer": "Moderate turbulence"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associated the type of wind with the appropriate description: During the night, cooling surface air flows downslope.",
      "choices": [
        "Anabatic",
        "Katabatic",
        "Mountain",
        "Valley"
      ],
      "answer": "Katabatic"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which of these temperature bands is ice most likely to form on the aircraft structure?",
      "choices": [
        "0\u00b0C to -10\u00b0C.",
        "-35\u00b0C to -50\u00b0C.",
        "+10\u00b0C to 0\u00b0C.",
        "-20\u00b0C to -35\u00b0C."
      ],
      "answer": "0\u00b0C to -10\u00b0C."
    },
    {
      "question": "A strong difference in wind speed or direction over a relatively short distance is known as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "gust",
        "windshear",
        "downdraught",
        "microburst"
      ],
      "answer": "windshear"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following factors have the greatest effect on the formation of the various types of ice on an aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "Cloud temperature and droplet size.",
        "Aircraft speed and size of cloud droplets.",
        "Aircraft speed and curvature of the aerofoil.",
        "Relative humidity inside the cloud."
      ],
      "answer": "Cloud temperature and droplet size."
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the type of precipitation with the most appropriate description. White, opaque, approximately round ice particles. Often falling with snow, near 0 \u00b0C. Normal diameter is 2 mm to 5 mm.",
      "choices": [
        "Ice pellets",
        "Snow grains",
        "Snow pellets",
        "Hail"
      ],
      "answer": "Snow pellets"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most common hazards that thunderstorms pose to aviation include:",
      "choices": [
        "heavy precipitation, lightning.",
        "severe icing.",
        "windshear, severe turbulence, hail.",
        "all of the answers described are correct."
      ],
      "answer": "all of the answers described are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following cloud types is found at high levels?",
      "choices": [
        "SC",
        "CC",
        "ST",
        "AC"
      ],
      "answer": "CC"
    },
    {
      "question": "If a SCWD slowly freezes after contact with an airframe it usually creates __________ ice.",
      "choices": [
        "clear",
        "rime",
        "hoar frost",
        "mixed"
      ],
      "answer": "clear"
    },
    {
      "question": "Occasional turbulence is defined as turbulence which is experienced for __________ of the time.",
      "choices": [
        "less than 1/3rd",
        "less than 2/3rds",
        "less than 1/2",
        "more than 2/3rds"
      ],
      "answer": "less than 1/3rd"
    },
    {
      "question": "Potentially the most dangerous form of windshear is:",
      "choices": [
        "Windshear on the final approach.",
        "High level windshear.",
        "Vertical windshear.",
        "Horizontal windshear."
      ],
      "answer": "Windshear on the final approach."
    },
    {
      "question": "Assign the correct description to the type of wind: Occurs along the valleys of coastlines east of the Adriatic sea.",
      "choices": [
        "Mistral",
        "Bora",
        "Foehn",
        "Sirocco"
      ],
      "answer": "Bora"
    },
    {
      "question": "A permanent, persistent jet stream created by the temperature difference between the Hadley and Ferrel cells and found between 25\u00b0 (winter) to 40\u00b0 (summer) Is a description of the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "arctic front jet stream",
        "polar front jet stream",
        "subtropical jet stream",
        "the easterly jet stream"
      ],
      "answer": "subtropical jet stream"
    },
    {
      "question": "Snowflakes __________ in size as the temperature rises towards 0\u00b0C.",
      "choices": [
        "decrease",
        "remain same",
        "increase",
        "are not affected"
      ],
      "answer": "increase"
    },
    {
      "question": "The fastest jet stream is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "easterly equatorial jet stream",
        "polar front jet stream",
        "subtropical jet stream",
        "arctic front jet stream"
      ],
      "answer": "subtropical jet stream"
    },
    {
      "question": "Coalescence describes the process in which:",
      "choices": [
        "Small particles of ice come together to form large clumps of hail.",
        "Falling water droplets in relatively warm clouds (above 0\u00b0C) come together and grow until they are massive enough to fall as rain.",
        "Falling water droplets in very cold clouds (colder than -15\u00b0C) form large droplets of supercooled rain.",
        "Falling ice particles in relatively warm clouds (above 0\u00b0C) descend and melt into large water droplets, eventually falling as rain."
      ],
      "answer": "Falling water droplets in relatively warm clouds (above 0\u00b0C) come together and grow until they are massive enough to fall as rain."
    },
    {
      "question": "When reporting vertical visibility at a German aerodrome, the code group VV004 means:",
      "choices": [
        "The vertical visibility is 400 m.",
        "The vertical visibility is 4 ft.",
        "The vertical visibility is 4000 ft.",
        "The vertical visibility is 400 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "The vertical visibility is 400 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "Orographic storms form __________.",
      "choices": [
        "at warm fronts",
        "as a result of sea breezes",
        "at cold fronts",
        "in mountainous areas"
      ],
      "answer": "in mountainous areas"
    },
    {
      "question": "The seasonal jet stream found only in the northern hemisphere at about 60\u00b0N in the arctic ocean is called the __________ jet stream.",
      "choices": [
        "easterly equatorial",
        "arctic front",
        "subtropical jet",
        "polar front"
      ],
      "answer": "arctic front"
    },
    {
      "question": "The saturated air lying immediately above the warm moist surface almost instantly condenses when it comes into contact with the colder air. A marked inversion is required and temperatures are often close to zero. This describes the formation of __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "radiation fog",
        "sea smoke",
        "advection fog",
        "arctic fog"
      ],
      "answer": "sea smoke"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the US, in __________ very large tornadoes can develop, with much stronger winds and a diameter of about 150 metres or more.",
      "choices": [
        "late summer",
        "winter",
        "spring and early summer",
        "early autumn"
      ],
      "answer": "spring and early summer"
    },
    {
      "question": "The threat of negative windshear is a sudden __________ in airspeed.",
      "choices": [
        "increase",
        "reduction",
        "fluctuation",
        "shift"
      ],
      "answer": "reduction"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the type of precipitation with the most appropriate description. Transparent or translucent ice particles that cannot be crushed easily and have a diameter < 5 mm. May indicate that, at higher levels, freezing rain is present.",
      "choices": [
        "Ice pellets",
        "Snow grains",
        "Snow pellets",
        "Hail"
      ],
      "answer": "Ice pellets"
    },
    {
      "question": "Below about __________\u00b0C SCWD are rarely, if ever, encountered.",
      "choices": [
        "-55",
        "-45",
        "-25",
        "-20"
      ],
      "answer": "-45"
    },
    {
      "question": "A large, severe storm characterised with a mesocyclone/rotating updraft. The powerful rotating updraft allows the storm to live longer and become more \u2018organised\u2019 than normal single cell or multi-cell thunderstorms. They commonly produce tornadoes, large hail and destructive winds. This is a description of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "squall",
        "a supercell storm",
        "an air-mass thunderstorm",
        "typical thunderstorm"
      ],
      "answer": "a supercell storm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assign the correct description to the type of wind: Forms when an area of high-pressure sits over the cold central European land mass while low-pressure develops over the warmer sea.",
      "choices": [
        "Mistral",
        "Bora",
        "Sirocco",
        "Foehn"
      ],
      "answer": "Bora"
    },
    {
      "question": "Overland, in the friction layer, the surface wind speed is about __________% of the geostrophic wind speed.",
      "choices": [
        "70",
        "50",
        "25",
        "10"
      ],
      "answer": "50"
    },
    {
      "question": "It forms when high pressure systems stop the vertical motion of air, trapping pollutants in the lower layers. It requires a good supply of particles from dust, sand and pollution and relatively stable atmospheric conditions. This is a description of the formation of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "Haze",
        "Mist",
        "Fog",
        "Sea smoke"
      ],
      "answer": "Haze"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the definition and defined term: The greatest horizontal distance at which a black object near the ground can be seen against a bright background. Or, the greatest distance at which a light of 1000 candelas can be seen against an unlit background.",
      "choices": [
        "Prevailing visibility",
        "SVR",
        "RVR",
        "Met visibility"
      ],
      "answer": "Met visibility"
    },
    {
      "question": "Turbulent mixing promotes cloud formation, usually __________ the turbulent inversion.",
      "choices": [
        "just below",
        "just above",
        "at exactly",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "answer": "just above"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fog comprising SCWD is known as __________ fog.",
      "choices": [
        "sea smoke",
        "ice",
        "freezing",
        "haze"
      ],
      "answer": "freezing"
    },
    {
      "question": "Centrifugal force reduces the wind speed around a low and increases the speed around a high, for the same isobar spacing when compared to the geostrophic wind. This is a description of the creation of the __________ wind.",
      "choices": [
        "isobaric",
        "gradient",
        "PGF",
        "geostrophic"
      ],
      "answer": "gradient"
    },
    {
      "question": "The impact of __________ droplets falling on a water surface is imperceptible. Visibility is inversely related to both the intensity of precipitation and the number of droplets.",
      "choices": [
        "drizzle",
        "rain",
        "sleet",
        "hail"
      ],
      "answer": "drizzle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mixed clouds comprise __________ and water droplets and are often the middle level clouds.",
      "choices": [
        "ice crystals",
        "snow",
        "rain",
        "supercooled water"
      ],
      "answer": "ice crystals"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the wings of an aircraft are contaminated with ice, one can expect the aircraft to have:",
      "choices": [
        "Degraded stall characteristics but a better gust response due to an improved roll behaviour.",
        "Nearly unchanged stall characteristics as the ice will mostly form on the thickest and thus the innermost part of the wing.",
        "Degraded stall characteristics and problems with roll manoeuvres.",
        "A degraded response in the roll, pitch and yaw axes but improved stall characteristics (due to the increased wing area)."
      ],
      "answer": "Degraded stall characteristics and problems with roll manoeuvres."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following scenarios will most likely produce advection fog?",
      "choices": [
        "A mild moist airstream flowing over colder surfaces with a wind in excess of 30 kt.",
        "A light breeze blowing colder air out to sea.",
        "Morning in autumn with freezing temperature over land but still a couple degrees above freezing over sea, with a slight wind from sea to land.",
        "Warm moist air settling over a warmer surface under no-wind conditions."
      ],
      "answer": "Morning in autumn with freezing temperature over land but still a couple degrees above freezing over sea, with a slight wind from sea to land."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is mixed ice/opaque Ice and where can it be found?",
      "choices": [
        "Mixed ice consists of rime ice and hoar frost can be found in CI and AS clouds.",
        "Mixed ice consists of freezing fog and rime ice and can be found in NS and CB clouds.",
        "Mixed ice consists of clear ice and  freezing rain and can be found in CB clouds.",
        "Mixed ice consists of clear ice and rime ice and can be found ln NS clouds."
      ],
      "answer": "Mixed ice consists of clear ice and rime ice and can be found ln NS clouds."
    },
    {
      "question": "Assign the description to an icing intensity category: The rate of accumulation can overwhelm de-icing/anti-icing systems. Immediate exit from the condition is necessary or divert and land asap.",
      "choices": [
        "Light",
        "Severe",
        "Moderate",
        "Trace"
      ],
      "answer": "Severe"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associated the type of wind with the appropriate description: During the day, warm, less dense air at the surface flows upslope.",
      "choices": [
        "Katabatic",
        "Mountain",
        "Valley",
        "Anabatic"
      ],
      "answer": "Anabatic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these are examples of a stable cloud?",
      "choices": [
        "CB",
        "AC",
        "CS",
        "CU"
      ],
      "answer": "CS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which precipitation type generally has the greatest impact on visibility?",
      "choices": [
        "Snow",
        "Hail.",
        "Drizzle.",
        "Heavy rain."
      ],
      "answer": "Snow"
    },
    {
      "question": "A build-up of static electricity due to collisions with particles can cause a blueish coloured light which is often seen flickering around the edges and over the surfaces of the windscreen. This is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Air to air lightning.",
        "Bioluminescence.",
        "Static electricity.",
        "St Elmo's fire."
      ],
      "answer": "St Elmo's fire."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ thunderstorms are associated with unstable warm fronts and most cold fronts.",
      "choices": [
        "Frontal",
        "Multi-cell",
        "Air mass",
        "Single-cell"
      ],
      "answer": "Frontal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the cloud type with the severity of icing most likely to be encountered: Cu.",
      "choices": [
        "Moderate",
        "Nil",
        "Occasionally Severe",
        "Light"
      ],
      "answer": "Light to moderate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the cloud type with the severity of icing likely to be encountered: St.",
      "choices": [
        "Light",
        "Nil",
        "Moderate",
        "Light to Moderate"
      ],
      "answer": "Light to Moderate"
    },
    {
      "question": "This cloud species is called __________ because it is markedly sprouting and has a bulging upper part.",
      "choices": [
        "virga",
        "cumulonimbus",
        "congestus",
        "calvus"
      ],
      "answer": "congestus"
    },
    {
      "question": "An __________ is a line of equal windspeed.",
      "choices": [
        "isobar",
        "isotach",
        "isotherm",
        "isohypse"
      ],
      "answer": "isotach"
    },
    {
      "question": "A strong low level wind that emanates from beneath convective storms and blows radially in all directions is a generic description of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "gust",
        "a downburst",
        "thunderstorm",
        "windshear"
      ],
      "answer": "a downburst"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most severe airframe icing is associated with __________ SCWD because, on impact with an airframe, the rate of freezing of the SCWD is __________ by the release of latent heat.",
      "choices": [
        "small; slowed",
        "large; accelerated",
        "large; slowed",
        "small; accelerated"
      ],
      "answer": "large; slowed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is true about the relationship between the water content of different types of winter precipitation and the associated visibility?",
      "choices": [
        "light snow compared to heavy snow causes a lower visibility due to the compact nature of the small snowflakes associated with light snow.",
        "ice pellets and freezing rain, because they have a bigger structure, obscure more than snowflakes.",
        "hail from thunderstorms obscures more than snowflakes due to the greater whiteness (the property of being white in colour) of hail.",
        "snowflakes, due to their open structure, obscure more than water droplets."
      ],
      "answer": "snowflakes, due to their open structure, obscure more than water droplets."
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ are large scale downbursts of 5-20 minutes, more than 4 km in area. Wind speed can exceed 130 kt. They can cause widespread damage similar to tornadoes.",
      "choices": [
        "Windshear",
        "Microbursts",
        "Macrobursts",
        "Gust"
      ],
      "answer": "Macrobursts"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the type of wind with the appropriate description: Well developed winds create flow from the tops of mountains, down the valleys and onto the plains. They peak at dawn.",
      "choices": [
        "Warm Air",
        "Katabatic",
        "Anabatic",
        "Valley"
      ],
      "answer": "Katabatic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which type of cloud is most typical evidence of stable air conditions?",
      "choices": [
        "Cumulus",
        "Cirrostratus",
        "Altocumulus castellanus",
        "Cumulonimbus"
      ],
      "answer": "Cirrostratus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about lightning and lightning strikes is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "Spherical lightning often penetrate into aircraft.",
        "Lightning strikes always cause heavy damage.",
        "The aircraft is temporarily part of the lightning trajectory.",
        "Compasses and electronics are always affected."
      ],
      "answer": "The aircraft is temporarily part of the lightning trajectory."
    },
    {
      "question": "The arctic front jet stream occurs from about 20 000 to __________ 000 ft.",
      "choices": [
        "25",
        "50",
        "30",
        "75"
      ],
      "answer": "30"
    },
    {
      "question": "Small SCWD are commonly associated with ambient temperatures between -15\u00b0C and __________\u00b0C.",
      "choices": [
        "-20",
        "-25",
        "-45",
        "-55"
      ],
      "answer": "-45"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the type of wind with the appropriate description: Well developed winds in the mid-afternoon cause a general flow of air from the plains and valleys up towards the mountain tops.",
      "choices": [
        "Katabatic",
        "Cold Air",
        "Anabatic",
        "Mountain"
      ],
      "answer": "Anabatic"
    },
    {
      "question": "When air directly in contact with a cold surface cools and condenses into cloud, this mechanism is known as __________ cooling.",
      "choices": [
        "radiative",
        "adiabatic",
        "advective",
        "mechanical"
      ],
      "answer": "radiative"
    },
    {
      "question": "Clouds dissipate by the process of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "condensation",
        "radiation",
        "advection",
        "evaporation"
      ],
      "answer": "evaporation"
    },
    {
      "question": "When established on the final approach path, and after passing below a cloud associated with a microburst, an aircraft can experience:",
      "choices": [
        "Pitch changes without pilot input.",
        "Increasing headwind.",
        "Alternating yawing movements.",
        "Reduced visibility."
      ],
      "answer": "Pitch changes without pilot input."
    },
    {
      "question": "How high can a Cumulonimbus (CB) cloud be?",
      "choices": [
        "6000 ft",
        "15 000 ft",
        "20 000 ft",
        "40 000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "40 000 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "An __________ is a line on a chart connecting points of equal height and equal barometric pressure.",
      "choices": [
        "isotherm",
        "isohypse",
        "isotach",
        "isobar"
      ],
      "answer": "isohypse"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is drizzle?",
      "choices": [
        "Water droplets of more than 0.5 mm in diameter.",
        "Precipitation which forms mostly in CB and CU clouds.",
        "Typical precipitation, when NS clouds are present.",
        "Small water droplets of 0.2 to 0.5 mm in diameter."
      ],
      "answer": "Small water droplets of 0.2 to 0.5 mm in diameter."
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the reported cloud amount with the coverage in oktas: 3-4 oktas.",
      "choices": [
        "SKC",
        "SCT",
        "FEW",
        "OVC"
      ],
      "answer": "SCT"
    },
    {
      "question": "It is formed in __________ atmospheric conditions.",
      "choices": [
        "unstable",
        "stable",
        "conditionally unstable",
        "absolutely stable"
      ],
      "answer": "unstable"
    },
    {
      "question": "The approximate ratio of jet stream length to their width is __________:1.",
      "choices": [
        "10",
        "1",
        "100",
        "1000"
      ],
      "answer": "10"
    },
    {
      "question": "A complex of thunderstorms that becomes organised on a scale larger than individual thunderstorms, but smaller than extratropical cyclones, is called a _____.",
      "choices": [
        "mesostrophic convective cyclone.",
        "mesoscale convective system.",
        "massive convective storm.",
        "mesoscale convective cyclone."
      ],
      "answer": "mesoscale convective system."
    },
    {
      "question": "Atmospheric air is normally __________ charged.",
      "choices": [
        "negatively",
        "neutrally",
        "positively",
        "statically"
      ],
      "answer": "positively"
    },
    {
      "question": "The reporting group \u2018BR\u2019 indicates that the visibility is less than 5000 m but more than ____.",
      "choices": [
        "1500 m",
        "3000 m",
        "2500 m",
        "1000 m"
      ],
      "answer": "1000 m"
    },
    {
      "question": "Why are there no or very few clouds, when a high pressure area is present?",
      "choices": [
        "Warm air moves over a cold surface, thus, generating stability.",
        "The air is warmed from below.",
        "Because of rising air, cooling adiabatically at the saturated adiabatic lapse rate.",
        "Because of subsiding air, subject to adiabatic heating."
      ],
      "answer": "Because of subsiding air, subject to adiabatic heating."
    },
    {
      "question": "Hill fog is formed by __________ lifting of air.",
      "choices": [
        "orographic",
        "frontal",
        "thermal",
        "mechanical"
      ],
      "answer": "orographic"
    },
    {
      "question": "A thin layer of hard frost on the upper surfaces of the wings before flight:",
      "choices": [
        "Isn't dangerous because the ice layer is very thin.",
        "Isn't dangerous because its likely to blow off during the take-off roll.",
        "Is often found on aircraft left out overnight, but is usually confined to surfaces in contact with wing fuel.",
        "Is potentially very dangerous and must be removed before flight."
      ],
      "answer": "Is potentially very dangerous and must be removed before flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "The RVR is usually __________ the reported ground or met visibility.",
      "choices": [
        "less than",
        "greater than",
        "the same as",
        "greater, equal, or less than"
      ],
      "answer": "greater than"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the reported cloud amount with the coverage in oktas: 0 oktas.",
      "choices": [
        "FEW",
        "SKC",
        "OVC",
        "SCT"
      ],
      "answer": "SKC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement corresponds to the definition of severe turbulence?",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft may be out of control for short periods, occupants are forced violently against seat belts, loose objects are tossed about.",
        "Aircraft gets out of control and crashes.",
        "Aircraft will be damaged and an emergency landing will be absolutely necessary.",
        "Difficulty in walking, occupants feel strain against seat belts, loose objects move about."
      ],
      "answer": "Aircraft may be out of control for short periods, occupants are forced violently against seat belts, loose objects are tossed about."
    },
    {
      "question": "Fog or mist forms when the surface air becomes __________. Further cooling causes condensation/sublimation.",
      "choices": [
        "saturated",
        "super-saturated",
        "inverted",
        "mixed"
      ],
      "answer": "saturated"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mountain waves form when winds blow at approximately __________ relative to the mountain axis.",
      "choices": [
        "180\u00b0",
        "45\u00b0",
        "90\u00b0",
        "parallel"
      ],
      "answer": "90\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which 1 of these is NOT a recognised process for cloud formation?",
      "choices": [
        "Adiabatic cooling (rising air expands and cools).",
        "Mechanical processes (air is forced up by turbulence, mountains or fronts and cools).",
        "Advection (warm, moist air moves over a cooler surface and cools).",
        "Radiative cooling (surface layers cool at night through net loss of energy)"
      ],
      "answer": "Sublimation (air sublimates moisture from melting ice crystals and cools)."
    },
    {
      "question": "A westerly wind is one which flows __________ the west.",
      "choices": [
        "from",
        "to",
        "towards",
        "away from"
      ],
      "answer": "from"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the meaning of the abbreviation 'LLWAS'?",
      "choices": [
        "A low level warning system for the detection of thunderstorms.",
        "A North American system for detection and warning provision of marked temperature inversions.",
        "A North American system for detection and warning provision of low level windshear.",
        "A North American radar network for the detection of tornadoes."
      ],
      "answer": "A North American system for detection and warning provision of low level windshear."
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the cloud type with the severity of icing likely to be encountered: As.",
      "choices": [
        "Light to Moderate",
        "Light",
        "Occasionally Severe",
        "Nil"
      ],
      "answer": "Light to Moderate"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary cause of jet streams is large __________ differences between adjacent air masses.",
      "choices": [
        "speed",
        "pressure",
        "temperature",
        "density"
      ],
      "answer": "temperature"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following layers of fog above land is coded as MIFG?",
      "choices": [
        "A layer 7 m deep.",
        "A layer less than 2 m above ground level.",
        "A layer 5 m deep.",
        "A layer up to 3 m above ground level."
      ],
      "answer": "A layer less than 2 m above ground level."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following conditions are most favourable to the formation of mountain waves?",
      "choices": [
        "Moist unstable air at mountain top and wind of less than 5 knots blowing across the mountain ridge.",
        "Unstable air at mountain top altitude and a wind at least 20 knots blowing across the mountain ridge.",
        "Either stable or unstable air at mountain top and a wind of at least 30 knots blowing parallel to the mountain ridge.",
        "Stable air at mountain top altitude and a wind at least 20 knots blowing across the mountain ridge"
      ],
      "answer": "Stable air at mountain top altitude and a wind at least 20 knots blowing across the mountain ridge"
    },
    {
      "question": "The largest SCWD are most likely to be found in the lower levels of __________ clouds. SCWD __________ encountered outside of cloud.",
      "choices": [
        "stratiform; are never",
        "cumuliform; are sometimes",
        "stratiform; are sometimes",
        "cumuliform; are never"
      ],
      "answer": "cumuliform; are sometimes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statements most accurately describes the mechanism for hail formation?",
      "choices": [
        "Hail forms in the coldest types of stratus, being kept aloft by mechanical turbulence and thus growing until they are heavy enough to fall to the surface.",
        "Water droplets ascend in updrafts, growing by collision and coalescence, they freeze and grow further as they ascend until they are heavy enough to fall out of the cloud.",
        "Hail is produced by snow flakes which partially melt and coalesce after they fall out of the cloud.",
        "Water droplets fall through a cumulus, gathering ice crystals as they fall. Warmer air in the lower regions of the cloud partially melts them to form a type of clear ice."
      ],
      "answer": "Water droplets ascend in updrafts, growing by collision and coalescence, they freeze and grow further as they ascend until they are heavy enough to fall out of the cloud."
    },
    {
      "question": "Overland, in the friction layer, the difference in direction between the surface wind and the geostrophic wind is about__________\u00b0.",
      "choices": [
        "45",
        "90",
        "180",
        "30"
      ],
      "answer": "30"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assign the correct description to the type of wind: Is channelled along the Rhone valley- a natural venturi amplifying the wind speed.",
      "choices": [
        "Mistral",
        "Bora",
        "Foehn",
        "Sirocco"
      ],
      "answer": "Mistral"
    },
    {
      "question": "Altostratus clouds are classified as:",
      "choices": [
        "Low level clouds.",
        "Convective clouds",
        "Medium level clouds.",
        "High level clouds."
      ],
      "answer": "Medium level clouds."
    },
    {
      "question": "Compared to a microburst, a macroburst:",
      "choices": [
        "Affects a larger area.",
        "Occurs over a shorter time period.",
        "Is free of rain",
        "Has an updraft."
      ],
      "answer": "Affects a larger area."
    },
    {
      "question": "Nocturnal jets, also known as boundary layer jets, are a type of __________ jet stream.",
      "choices": [
        "low level",
        "high level",
        "mid-level",
        "polar"
      ],
      "answer": "low level"
    },
    {
      "question": "Drizzle is most commonly associated with clouds that have __________ updrafts.",
      "choices": [
        "very strong",
        "very weak",
        "strong",
        "medium"
      ],
      "answer": "very weak"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct? 1. In a mixed cloud the ice crystals grow at the expense of supercooled water droplets. 2. In the mid-latitudes heavy rain showers are only formed by the coalescence process.",
      "choices": [
        "1 and 2.",
        "None of the above.",
        "2 only.",
        "1 only."
      ],
      "answer": "1 only."
    },
    {
      "question": "Thin wings are __________ prone to icing than thick wings.",
      "choices": [
        "more",
        "less",
        "equally",
        "not"
      ],
      "answer": "more"
    },
    {
      "question": "An air mass containing St and Sc clouds is cooling as it is lifted over high ground. Which of the following will happen to the concentration of water droplets or ice particles?",
      "choices": [
        "The concentration will decrease.",
        "The concentration will remain the same, and their sizes will increase.",
        "The concentration will increase.",
        "The concentration will remain the same."
      ],
      "answer": "The concentration will increase."
    },
    {
      "question": "For mountain waves to form the atmosphere must be __________.",
      "choices": [
        "stable",
        "unstable",
        "neutrally stable",
        "extremely unstable"
      ],
      "answer": "stable"
    },
    {
      "question": "Wind direction is given in degrees relative to __________ North in most meteorological reports and __________ North in reports broadcast by ATC.",
      "choices": [
        "True; Magnetic",
        "Magnetic; True",
        "True; True",
        "Magnetic; Magnetic"
      ],
      "answer": "True; Magnetic"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rapid, temporary, localised increase in wind speed is called a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "shear",
        "gust",
        "downdraught",
        "squal"
      ],
      "answer": "gust"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the cloud type with the severity of icing likely to be encountered: Sc.",
      "choices": [
        "Nil",
        "Occasionally Severe",
        "Light to Moderate",
        "Moderate"
      ],
      "answer": "Light to Moderate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assign the correct description to the type of wind: Is driven by high-pressure over north-western Europe and low pressure in the Mediterranean.",
      "choices": [
        "Mistral",
        "Bora",
        "Sirocco",
        "Foehn"
      ],
      "answer": "Mistral"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statements concerning the formation of aircraft icing is most correct?",
      "choices": [
        "A cloud consisting of both supercooled water droplets and ice crystals produces aircraft icing.",
        "Greatest risk of icing conditions is experienced in cirrus clouds.",
        "Probability of icing increases when dry snow starts to fall from a cloud.",
        "Greatest risk of icing when cloud temperature decreases well below minus 12\u00b0C."
      ],
      "answer": "A cloud consisting of both supercooled water droplets and ice crystals produces aircraft icing."
    },
    {
      "question": "The RVR stop-end measurement is normally taken about __________m from the end of the runway.",
      "choices": [
        "1000",
        "300",
        "50",
        "1500"
      ],
      "answer": "300"
    },
    {
      "question": "This cloud type is called __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "stratus",
        "nimbostratus",
        "cirrocumulus",
        "cirrostratus"
      ],
      "answer": "cirrocumulus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the cloud type with the severity of icing likely to be encountered: Ns (near its base).",
      "choices": [
        "Moderate",
        "Light to Moderate",
        "Light",
        "Occasionally Severe"
      ],
      "answer": "Occasionally Severe"
    },
    {
      "question": "Visible ice crystals at your flight level indicate a __________ risk of clear ice.",
      "choices": [
        "increased",
        "lesser",
        "greater",
        "nil"
      ],
      "answer": "lesser"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the night the land cools much more rapidly than the sea. The warmer air over the sea rises, drawing air off the land. This describes:",
      "choices": [
        "An anabatic wind.",
        "A katabatic wind.",
        "A land breeze.",
        "A sea breeze."
      ],
      "answer": "A land breeze."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following cloud types is a medium level cloud?",
      "choices": [
        "ST",
        "CS",
        "SC",
        "AS"
      ],
      "answer": "AS"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which of the following situations can freezing rain be encountered?",
      "choices": [
        "Behind a warm front in the summer.",
        "Ahead of a warm front in the winter.",
        "Ahead of a cold front in the summer.",
        "Ahead of a warm front in any conditions."
      ],
      "answer": "Ahead of a warm front in the winter."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is signified if an occlusion is described as 'cold'?",
      "choices": [
        "It derives from a polar depression.",
        "The air ahead of the associated warm front is colder than the air behind the associated cold front.",
        "The air ahead of the associated warm front is less cold than the air behind the associated cold front.",
        "The air mass is less cold than ISA."
      ],
      "answer": "The air ahead of the associated warm front is less cold than the air behind the associated cold front."
    },
    {
      "question": "An average tornado typically has a rotational windspeed of about __________ kt.",
      "choices": [
        "150",
        "300",
        "200",
        "100"
      ],
      "answer": "100"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what type of cloud would you likely encounter the most severe icing and turbulence?",
      "choices": [
        "CB",
        "SC",
        "NS",
        "CI"
      ],
      "answer": "CB"
    },
    {
      "question": "A semi-permanent, disjointed sinuous jet stream found between 40\u00b0N and 65\u00b0N which is stronger and higher in winter is a description of the __________ __________ jet stream.",
      "choices": [
        "easterly equatorial",
        "polar front",
        "subtropical jet",
        "arctic front"
      ],
      "answer": "polar front"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about airframe icing is/are correct?",
      "choices": [
        "The worst airframe icing results from small supercooled water droplets freezing instantly on contact with the airframe.",
        "Rime ice is formed by slow-freezing supercooled water droplets.",
        "Airframe icing occurs when supercooled water droplets come into contact with a sub-zero airframe.",
        "The severest airframe icing occurs when an airframe comes into contact with ice crystals at high altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Airframe icing occurs when supercooled water droplets come into contact with a sub-zero airframe."
    },
    {
      "question": "Associate the type of precipitation with the most appropriate description. Very small, opaque, white particles of ice which fall from stratiform clouds. Flat or elongated. Diameter < 1 mm.",
      "choices": [
        "Hail",
        "Snow pellets",
        "Snow grains",
        "Ice pellets"
      ],
      "answer": "Snow grains"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mountain waves may be visible due to the presence of __________ cloud and/or rotor cloud.",
      "choices": [
        "cumuliform",
        "lenticular",
        "stratiform",
        "cirrocumulus"
      ],
      "answer": "lenticular"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ are small scale downbursts of 2-5 minutes and less than 4 km. The windspeed can be up to 130 kt.",
      "choices": [
        "Windshear",
        "Macrobursts",
        "Microbursts",
        "Gust"
      ],
      "answer": "Microbursts"
    },
    {
      "question": "Warm moist air passes over a cooler surface cooling its low layers below its dew point. The surface temperature must be below the dew point of the warmer air. This describes the creation of __________ fog.",
      "choices": [
        "advection",
        "steam",
        "radiation",
        "frontal"
      ],
      "answer": "advection"
    },
    {
      "question": "During which stage of thunderstorm development are rotor winds characterised by roll clouds most likely to occur?",
      "choices": [
        "Cumulus stage.",
        "Cumulus stage and mature stage.",
        "Mature stage.",
        "Dissipating stage."
      ],
      "answer": "Mature stage."
    },
    {
      "question": "Over the sea, the values for direction and speed are__________\u00b0 and __________% respectively.",
      "choices": [
        "30; 70",
        "30; 50",
        "10; 50",
        "10; 30"
      ],
      "answer": "10; 70"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cloud to ground lightning delivers __________ charges from the air to the ground.",
      "choices": [
        "positive",
        "negative",
        "neutral",
        "alternating"
      ],
      "answer": "negative"
    },
    {
      "question": "How far and how high up can mountain waves reach originating from the Rocky Mountains (USA)?",
      "choices": [
        "By the dimensions of the affecting mountain.",
        "Up to the tropopause and 600 NM downwind.",
        "Up to the tropopause and horizontally as long as there are mountains.",
        "Up to 36 000 ft and approximately 300 NM downwind."
      ],
      "answer": "Up to the tropopause and 600 NM downwind."
    },
    {
      "question": "Define a 'LOW'",
      "choices": [
        "None of the above.",
        "An area with lower pressure than that of the horizontal environments.",
        "An area of divergence.",
        "A trough."
      ],
      "answer": "An area with lower pressure than that of the horizontal environments."
    },
    {
      "question": "Assign the appropriate type of stability to the description of event: A strong atmospheric inversion.",
      "choices": [
        "Lapse rate",
        "Increased instability.",
        "Absolute stability",
        "Increased stability."
      ],
      "answer": "Absolute stability"
    },
    {
      "question": "The pressure measuring device which uses a flexible, partially evacuated metal capsule, is called an __________ barometer.",
      "choices": [
        "mercury",
        "anaeroid",
        "barograph",
        "aneroid"
      ],
      "answer": "anaeroid"
    },
    {
      "question": "When flying in warm air (warmer than standard atmosphere), indicated altitude is:",
      "choices": [
        "Equal to the standard altitude.",
        "The same as the true altitude.",
        "Lower than the true altitude.",
        "Higher than the standard altitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Lower than the true altitude."
    },
    {
      "question": "Considering the North Atlantic area north of 60\u00b0N during the winter, the mean height of the Tropopause is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "37 000 ft",
        "29 000 ft",
        "56 000 ft",
        "20 000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "29 000 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary means of transferring energy vertically through the atmosphere is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "advection",
        "convection",
        "radiation",
        "conduction"
      ],
      "answer": "convection"
    },
    {
      "question": "3 principal types of high pressure zones occur at mid-latitudes:",
      "choices": [
        "The cold temporary anticyclone, the warm high and the cold high.",
        "The cold temporary cyclone, the warm high and the cold high.",
        "Subsidence, convergence and cold highs over the seas.",
        "Depressions, highs and cyclones."
      ],
      "answer": "The cold temporary anticyclone, the warm high and the cold high."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a mountain-valley wind circulation, the mountain wind blows:",
      "choices": [
        "During the day down from the mountains.",
        "At night down from the mountains.",
        "During the day up from the valley.",
        "At night up from the valley."
      ],
      "answer": "At night down from the mountains."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Earth's surface cools at night because:",
      "choices": [
        "It is windier at night.",
        "The earth continues to radiate heat so there is a net loss of energy.",
        "The atmospheric air is colder at night because there is no solar radiation.",
        "It radiates heat to space."
      ],
      "answer": "The earth continues to radiate heat so there is a net loss of energy."
    },
    {
      "question": "Air temperature is a measure of __________ energy.",
      "choices": [
        "static",
        "potential",
        "kinetic",
        "dynamic"
      ],
      "answer": "kinetic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding the temperature at the tropopause?",
      "choices": [
        "It is higher in equatorial regions than in polar regions.",
        "Tropopause temperature is independent of latitude.",
        "It is highest in middle latitudes.",
        "It is constant"
      ],
      "answer": "It is higher in polar regions than in equatorial regions."
    },
    {
      "question": "The US still uses the imperial unit __________ .",
      "choices": [
        "millibar (mb)",
        "pounds per square inch (psi)",
        "inches of mercury (inHg)",
        "hectopascal (hPa)"
      ],
      "answer": "inches of mercury (inHg)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Although the large-scale structure of atmospheric circulation varies from year to year (e.g. El Nio/La Nia events), the basic structure remains fairly constant because it is determined by:",
      "choices": [
        "The permanent transport of heat from the equator to higher latitudes by ocean currents such as the Gulf Stream.",
        "Varying solar influx, which is compensated by the specific heat capacity of the continents and seas.",
        "The Coriolis force acting on the atmosphere and the constant temperature profiles over the oceans.",
        "Solar influx only"
      ],
      "answer": "The Earth's rotation rate, the passage of air from high to low pressure, and the unequal heating of land and sea."
    },
    {
      "question": "In a land and sea breeze circulation the land breeze blows:",
      "choices": [
        "During the night and is weaker than the sea breeze.",
        "During the day and is weaker than the sea breeze.",
        "During the night and is stronger than the sea breeze.",
        "During the day and is stronger than the sea breeze."
      ],
      "answer": "During the night and is weaker than the sea breeze."
    },
    {
      "question": "With regard to temperature, which of the following is correct for the polar climates?",
      "choices": [
        "The mean temperature of all months is below plus 10\u00b0C.",
        "The mean temperature of all months is below minus 10\u00b0C.",
        "The mean temperature of all months is above 0\u00b0C, but temperatures as high as plus 10\u00b0C will never be reached.",
        "The mean temperature of the warmest month is 10\u00b0C or above, and of the coldest month below minus 3\u00b0C."
      ],
      "answer": "The mean temperature of all months is below plus 10\u00b0C."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the term from its definition: The vertical distance above the ground.",
      "choices": [
        "Altitude",
        "QFE",
        "QNH",
        "Height"
      ],
      "answer": "Height"
    },
    {
      "question": "The wind which results from warming on the side of a mountain valley is known as:",
      "choices": [
        "Anabatic Wind",
        "Land breeze.",
        "Katabatic wind",
        "Foehn breeze."
      ],
      "answer": "Anabatic Wind"
    },
    {
      "question": "An outside air temperature of -35 \u00b0C is measured while cruising at FL200. What is the temperature deviation from the ISA at this level?",
      "choices": [
        "10\u00b0C warmer than ISA.",
        "10\u00b0C colder than ISA.",
        "5\u00b0C colder than ISA.",
        "5\u00b0C warmer than ISA."
      ],
      "answer": "10\u00b0C colder than ISA."
    },
    {
      "question": "Cold air compacts isobaric pressure levels. The true distance between any given flight level and the surface __________.",
      "choices": [
        "increases",
        "reduces",
        "stays the same",
        "fluctuates"
      ],
      "answer": "reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "A parcel of air has been cooled to the point where its relative humidity is 100%, further cooling will result in __________.",
      "choices": [
        "freezing",
        "evaporation",
        "condensation",
        "sublimation"
      ],
      "answer": "condensation"
    },
    {
      "question": "A battery-powered telemetry instrument carried into the atmosphere by a weather balloon which measures various atmospheric parameters and transmits them by radio to a ground receiver is called a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "transponder",
        "radiosonde",
        "meteosat",
        "radio satellite"
      ],
      "answer": "radiosonde"
    },
    {
      "question": "Subsiding air warms at the DALR of 3\u00b0C per 1000 ft which is __________ than the average ELR.",
      "choices": [
        "the same as",
        "faster",
        "slower",
        "equal to"
      ],
      "answer": "faster"
    },
    {
      "question": "A flight level is a __________ altitude expressed in hundreds of feet.",
      "choices": [
        "density",
        "pressure",
        "temperature",
        "standard"
      ],
      "answer": "pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "The geostrophic wind scale quantifies the relationship between isobar spacing and the __________ __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "geostrophic gradient force.",
        "isobaric gradient force.",
        "pressure gradient force.",
        "geostrophic coriolis force."
      ],
      "answer": "pressure gradient force."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the proximity of the polar jet stream, where do wind shear and clear air turbulence (CAT) occur?",
      "choices": [
        "The largest vertical wind shears are found at the jet stream core.",
        "CAT is generated by horizontal wind shear only.",
        "In units of kt/1000 ft, horizontal wind shears near the jet stream are larger than vertical wind shears.",
        "Most CAT areas are found on the cyclonic side of the jet stream."
      ],
      "answer": "Most CAT areas are found on the cyclonic side of the jet stream."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which type wind flows down slope becoming warmer and drier?",
      "choices": [
        "Mountain breeze.",
        "Land breeze.",
        "Katabatic wind.",
        "Valley wind."
      ],
      "answer": "Katabatic wind."
    },
    {
      "question": "A percentage figure comparing the amount of water vapour actually present in the air and the maximum amount it can possibly hold is known as the __________; __________.",
      "choices": [
        "dew; point",
        "dew; humidity",
        "relative; point",
        "relative; humidity"
      ],
      "answer": "relative; humidity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the type of inversion with the appropriate descriptor: Formed at night when colder, denser air sinks, displacing warmer air aloft.",
      "choices": [
        "Valley",
        "Frontal",
        "Friction Layer",
        "Subsidence"
      ],
      "answer": "Valley"
    },
    {
      "question": "The wind indicator for a weather observation receives the measured value from an anemometer. Where is this instrument placed?",
      "choices": [
        "Close to the station about 2 m above the ground.",
        "1 m above the runway.",
        "On a mast 10 m above the runway.",
        "On a mast 20 m above the runway."
      ],
      "answer": "On a mast 10 m above the runway."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statements applies to the tropopause?",
      "choices": [
        "It is, by definition, a temperature inversion.",
        "It separates the troposphere from the stratosphere.",
        "It indicates a strong temperature lapse rate.",
        "It is constant"
      ],
      "answer": "It separates the troposphere from the stratosphere."
    },
    {
      "question": "Between mean sea level and a height of 20 km, the lowest temperature in the ICAO Standard Atmosphere (ISA) is:",
      "choices": [
        "-100 \u00b0C",
        "-44.7 \u00b0C",
        "-273 \u00b0C",
        "-56.5 \u00b0C"
      ],
      "answer": "-56.5 \u00b0C"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assign the appropriate type of stability to the description of event: Cold air advection over a warmer surface.",
      "choices": [
        "Absolute stability",
        "Increased instability.",
        "Lapse rate",
        "Increased stability."
      ],
      "answer": "Increased instability."
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary mechanism for heat transfer within the atmosphere is __________ caused by the horizontal variation in air __________.",
      "choices": [
        "diurnal variation; volume",
        "diurnal variation; density",
        "air movement; density",
        "air movement; volume"
      ],
      "answer": "air movement; density"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these statements about the tropopause are correct or incorrect? 1- In the real atmosphere the tropopause is a continuous surface. 2- The height of the tropopause in the ISA is 11 km.",
      "choices": [
        "1 and 2 are correct.",
        "1 is correct, 2 is not correct.",
        "1 is not correct, 2 is correct.",
        "1 and 2 are incorrect."
      ],
      "answer": "1 is not correct, 2 is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "The horizontal transfer of energy in the atmosphere is called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "convection",
        "radiation",
        "conduction",
        "advection"
      ],
      "answer": "advection"
    },
    {
      "question": "In warm air the true distance between flight levels __________.",
      "choices": [
        "reduces",
        "stays the same",
        "increases",
        "varies"
      ],
      "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is correct regarding an anabatic wind? It can be described as a wind that blows:",
      "choices": [
        "Upslope caused by instability due the adiabatic heating in a valley.",
        "Downslope due to cold air that slides down a valley.",
        "Upslope due to warming of air in a valley.",
        "Downslope"
      ],
      "answer": "Upslope due to warming of air in a valley."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the terms from the definition: The phase change from solid ice to water vapour.",
      "choices": [
        "Evaporation",
        "Freezing",
        "Condensation",
        "Sublimation"
      ],
      "answer": "Sublimation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the type of inversion with the appropriate descriptor: Common in high pressure areas, where the descending dry air warms faster than the static environmental air.",
      "choices": [
        "Frontal",
        "Friction Layer",
        "Valley",
        "Subsidence"
      ],
      "answer": "Subsidence"
    },
    {
      "question": "High level __________ promotes subsidence (sinking air) air which then __________ near the surface.",
      "choices": [
        "convergence; diverges",
        "divergence; converges",
        "divergence; diverges",
        "convergence; converges"
      ],
      "answer": "convergence; diverges"
    },
    {
      "question": "A line of equal temperature, or a region of constant temperature with height, is called an __________.",
      "choices": [
        "isotherm",
        "isobar",
        "inversion",
        "isobaric"
      ],
      "answer": "isotherm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify this pressure feature by its description: A region where the atmospheric pressure at the surface is greater than its surrounding environment.",
      "choices": [
        "Low Pressure",
        "Ridge",
        "Anticyclone",
        "Trough"
      ],
      "answer": "Anticyclone"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the terms from the definition: The phase change of water from liquid to solid.",
      "choices": [
        "Freezing",
        "Evaporation",
        "Condensation",
        "Sublimation"
      ],
      "answer": "Freezing"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following combinations of pressure and temperature is correct in the ICAO standard atmosphere?",
      "choices": [
        "300 hPa -50.5\u00b0C",
        "700 hPa -8.4\u00b0C",
        "500 hPa -21.1\u00b0C",
        "200 hPa -62.3\u00b0C"
      ],
      "answer": "500 hPa -21.1\u00b0C"
    },
    {
      "question": "An isobaric trough results in __________ weather because there is pronounced surface __________.",
      "choices": [
        "significant; divergence",
        "little; divergence",
        "significant; convergence",
        "little; convergence"
      ],
      "answer": "significant; convergence"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the __________ over SE Asia, the tropopause can be as high as FL 600.",
      "choices": [
        "summer",
        "winter",
        "spring",
        "Autumn"
      ],
      "answer": "summer"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify this pressure feature by its description: An extension of a high, characterised by a protrusion of isobars away from the centre of the high.",
      "choices": [
        "Trough",
        "Low Pressure",
        "Ridge",
        "Anticyclone"
      ],
      "answer": "Ridge"
    },
    {
      "question": "When a parcel of displaced air has the same lapse rate as the ELR, the atmospheric conditions are __________.",
      "choices": [
        "conditionally stable",
        "neutrally stable",
        "unconditionally stable",
        "absolutely stable"
      ],
      "answer": "neutrally stable"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the ISA, between 11 km and 20 km altitude, the temperature lapse rate is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "isothermal",
        "isometric",
        "endothermal",
        "exothermal"
      ],
      "answer": "isothermal"
    },
    {
      "question": "3\u00b0/1000 ft is the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "DALR",
        "SALR",
        "lapse rate",
        "ELR"
      ],
      "answer": "DALR"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cold air compacts isobaric pressure levels. The true vertical distance between each flight level __________.",
      "choices": [
        "stays the same",
        "reduces",
        "increases",
        "is constant"
      ],
      "answer": "reduces"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the terms from the definition: The phase change from water vapour to liquid water.",
      "choices": [
        "Freezing",
        "Condensation",
        "Sublimation",
        "Evaporation"
      ],
      "answer": "Condensation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Convergence over a uniform surface is caused by:",
      "choices": [
        "Frictional force together with anti - cyclonic curvature of the isobars.",
        "Frictional force together with straight isobars.",
        "Frictional force together with cyclonic curvature of the isobars.",
        "Frictional force only."
      ],
      "answer": "Frictional force together with cyclonic curvature of the isobars."
    },
    {
      "question": "A stark temperature change between the major air masses causes the tropopause to change height rapidly. This mainly happens between the Hadley, Ferrel and Polar __________ and is known as a __________.",
      "choices": [
        "cells; break or 'fold'",
        "cells; inversion",
        "surfaces; front",
        "jet streams; break or 'fold'"
      ],
      "answer": "cells; break or 'fold'"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the temperature at 20 000 ft in the ICAO Standard Atmosphere?",
      "choices": [
        "-25\u00b0C",
        "-30\u00b0C",
        "-20\u00b0C",
        "-15\u00b0C"
      ],
      "answer": "-25\u00b0C"
    },
    {
      "question": "Conditions most favourable for the formation of a low-level frictional turbulence are:",
      "choices": [
        "Strong wind, smooth terrain, stable lapse rate.",
        "Light wind, rough terrain, stable lapse rate.",
        "Strong wind, rough terrain, steep lapse rate.",
        "light wind, smooth terrain and a stable lapse rate"
      ],
      "answer": "Strong wind, rough terrain, steep lapse rate."
    },
    {
      "question": "The atmosphere is divided into layers according to how the __________ varies with height.",
      "choices": [
        "pressure",
        "temperature",
        "density",
        "humidity"
      ],
      "answer": "temperature"
    },
    {
      "question": "The primary heat source for the atmosphere is:",
      "choices": [
        "Incoming solar radiation.",
        "Terrestrial radiation from the Earth to the air.",
        "Terrestrial radiation from the air to the Earth.",
        "Cosmic radiation"
      ],
      "answer": "Terrestrial radiation from the Earth to the air."
    },
    {
      "question": "At high altitudes a powerful oxidant called __________ must be removed from the cabin air.",
      "choices": [
        "solar radiation",
        "ozone",
        "cosmic radiation",
        "nitrogen"
      ],
      "answer": "ozone"
    },
    {
      "question": "The vertical position of an aircraft at, or below, the transition altitude is normally expressed as as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "height",
        "flight level",
        "altitude",
        "pressure altitude"
      ],
      "answer": "altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the term from its definition: The calculated barometric pressure at MSL, derived by observing the current pressure at an aerodrome and correcting for elevation using ISA.",
      "choices": [
        "Altitude",
        "Height",
        "QFE",
        "QNH"
      ],
      "answer": "QNH"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the type of inversion with the appropriate descriptor: Warm less dense air flows up and over cooler, denser air.",
      "choices": [
        "Friction Layer",
        "Valley",
        "Subsidence",
        "Frontal"
      ],
      "answer": "Frontal"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Siberian __________ the tropopause exists at about FL 220.",
      "choices": [
        "summer",
        "spring",
        "winter",
        "autumn"
      ],
      "answer": "winter"
    },
    {
      "question": "Unsaturated air compresses and warms when it is forced to __________.",
      "choices": [
        "descend",
        "rise",
        "float",
        "cool"
      ],
      "answer": "descend"
    },
    {
      "question": "When descending through the transition layer, vertical position is expressed as __________.",
      "choices": [
        "flight level",
        "height",
        "altitude",
        "pressure level"
      ],
      "answer": "altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the International Standard Atmosphere the decrease in temperature with height below 11 km is:",
      "choices": [
        "0.5\u00b0C per 100 m.",
        "0.65\u00b0C per 100 m.",
        "0.6\u00b0C per 100 m.",
        "1\u00b0C per 100 m."
      ],
      "answer": "0.65\u00b0C per 100 m."
    },
    {
      "question": "Air density is approximately 50% of MSL at __________ 000 ft and 25% of MSL at __________ 000 ft.",
      "choices": [
        "30; 50",
        "10; 20",
        "22; 40",
        "40; 22"
      ],
      "answer": "22; 40"
    },
    {
      "question": "Isothermal layers and inversions __________ the vertical motion of the air.",
      "choices": [
        "has no effect on",
        "inhibit",
        "promote",
        "decrease"
      ],
      "answer": "inhibit"
    },
    {
      "question": "When air converges at high level and diverges at the surface:",
      "choices": [
        "The mass of air in the column increases because the air can't leave the column as quickly at the bottom as it enters at the top.",
        "The mass of air in the column increases because the volume of air in the column becomes steadily greater.",
        "The mass of air in the column decreases.",
        "The pressure increases"
      ],
      "answer": "The mass of air in the column increases because the air can't leave the column as quickly at the bottom as it enters at the top."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following values corresponds to a SW-wind?",
      "choices": [
        "045\u00b0",
        "225\u00b0",
        "315\u00b0",
        "135\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "225\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the term from its definition: The barometric pressure at the aerodrome reference point/runway threshold. It is the altimeter setting to obtain height above the reference point/threshold.",
      "choices": [
        "QFE",
        "Altitude",
        "QNH",
        "Height"
      ],
      "answer": "QFE"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following values corresponds to a NE-wind?",
      "choices": [
        "315\u00b0",
        "135\u00b0",
        "225\u00b0",
        "045\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "045\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify this pressure feature by its description: An area in which the atmospheric pressure is less than its surroundings.",
      "choices": [
        "Trough",
        "Low Pressure",
        "Ridge",
        "Anticyclone"
      ],
      "answer": "Low Pressure"
    },
    {
      "question": "The SI unit of atmospheric pressure used in aviation is the _____.",
      "choices": [
        "inches of mercury (inHg)",
        "pounds per square inch (psi)",
        "hectopascal (hPa)",
        "millibar (mb)"
      ],
      "answer": "hectopascal (hPa)"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the day, as the ambient temperature increases, the relative humidity __________.",
      "choices": [
        "stays the same",
        "increases",
        "decreases",
        "fluctuates"
      ],
      "answer": "decreases"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ anticyclones are large-scale patterns that are nearly stationary and which prevent the normal west to east flow.",
      "choices": [
        "Blocking",
        "Warm",
        "Cold",
        "Intense"
      ],
      "answer": "Blocking"
    },
    {
      "question": "__________ is the barometric pressure at an observation point, reduced to MSL using the observed temperature at the surface and assuming an isothermal layer from the point to MSL.",
      "choices": [
        "QDH",
        "QFF",
        "QNH.",
        "QNE"
      ],
      "answer": "QFF"
    },
    {
      "question": "The very lowest part of the atmosphere is in direct contact with the Earth's surface. It changes temperature from day to night by the process of __________.",
      "choices": [
        "convection",
        "radiation",
        "advection",
        "conduction"
      ],
      "answer": "conduction"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which FL corresponds with the 500 hPa pressure level?",
      "choices": [
        "FL180",
        "FL160",
        "FL100",
        "FL390"
      ],
      "answer": "FL180"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the terms from the definition: The phase change from liquid water to water vapour.",
      "choices": [
        "Evaporation",
        "Sublimation",
        "Condensation",
        "Freezing"
      ],
      "answer": "Evaporation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Up to which flight level could the effects of mountain waves be expected to be encountered?",
      "choices": [
        "FL150",
        "FL300",
        "FL450",
        "FL250"
      ],
      "answer": "FL600"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pressure decreases with height at a __________ rate.",
      "choices": [
        "constant",
        "decreasing",
        "increasing",
        "fluctuating"
      ],
      "answer": "decreasing"
    },
    {
      "question": "Supercooled condensation droplets will probably freeze:",
      "choices": [
        "Once their temperature drops below -10\u00b0C.",
        "If they come into contact with a cold surface.",
        "If they are heated quickly.",
        "Never"
      ],
      "answer": "If they come into contact with a cold surface."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the troposphere the temperature lapse rate is approximately __________\u00b0C per 1000 ft. The average height of the tropopause is about __________ km.",
      "choices": [
        "3; 11",
        "2; 11000",
        "2; 11",
        "3;11 000"
      ],
      "answer": "2; 11"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the type of inversion with the appropriate descriptor: Created by turbulent mixing modifying the surface layer lapse rate.",
      "choices": [
        "Frontal",
        "Valley",
        "Subsidence",
        "Friction Layer"
      ],
      "answer": "Friction Layer"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify this pressure feature by its description: An extension of a low, characterised by a protrusion of isobars away from the centre of the low.",
      "choices": [
        "Anticyclone",
        "Low Pressure",
        "Trough",
        "High Pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "Trough"
    },
    {
      "question": "The wide variation of temperature lapse rates in the troposphere is primarily caused by:",
      "choices": [
        "Global warming.",
        "ISA conditions.",
        "Changes in surface temperature and air mass movement.",
        "The reduction in air density with height."
      ],
      "answer": "Changes in surface temperature and air mass movement."
    },
    {
      "question": "An 'ANABATIC' wind is a wind which:",
      "choices": [
        "Blows up a hill or mountain mainly during the day.",
        "Blows up a hill or mountain mainly during the night.",
        "Blows down a hill or mountain mainly during the night.",
        "Blows down a hill or mountain mainly during the day."
      ],
      "answer": "Blows up a hill or mountain mainly during the day."
    },
    {
      "question": "Liquid water existing at a temperature below its freezing point is said to be __________.",
      "choices": [
        "ice",
        "supercooled",
        "chilled",
        "Frozen"
      ],
      "answer": "supercooled"
    },
    {
      "question": "Solar radiation helps to provide sufficient energy for __________.",
      "choices": [
        "sublimation",
        "sublimation and deposition",
        "deposition",
        "Evaporation"
      ],
      "answer": "sublimation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The vertical position of an aircraft at, or above, the transition level is normally expressed as a __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "flight level",
        "altitude",
        "height",
        "Air pressure altitude"
      ],
      "answer": "flight level"
    },
    {
      "question": "____________________ is absorbed or released whenever water in the atmosphere changes its state (for example, from liquid to ice).",
      "choices": [
        "Latent heat",
        "Molecular energy",
        "Kinetic energy",
        "Potential energy"
      ],
      "answer": "Latent heat"
    },
    {
      "question": "What, approximately, is the average height of the tropopause over the equator?",
      "choices": [
        "11 km",
        "8 km",
        "16 km",
        "40 km"
      ],
      "answer": "16 km"
    },
    {
      "question": "The lapse rate within and between layers __________ constant and uniform.",
      "choices": [
        "may be",
        "is not",
        "is",
        "could be"
      ],
      "answer": "is not"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are planning an IFR flight eastbound and find that the highest obstacle along the route has an elevation of 5400 ft. The ISA deviation is -20\u00b0C and QNH 990. What is the lowest usable flight level on this flight?",
      "choices": [
        "FL070",
        "FL060",
        "FL080",
        "FL090"
      ],
      "answer": "FL090"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assign the appropriate type of stability to the description of event: Warm air advection over a cooler surface.",
      "choices": [
        "Lapse rate",
        "Increased instability.",
        "Increased stability.",
        "Absolute stability"
      ],
      "answer": "Increased stability."
    },
    {
      "question": "Lines of equal (constant) pressure on a pressure map are called __________.",
      "choices": [
        "isotherm",
        "isobars",
        "isographs",
        "isallobars"
      ],
      "answer": "isobars"
    },
    {
      "question": "An elongated or extended region of relatively low atmospheric pressure, often associated with fronts is known as an isobaric __________.",
      "choices": [
        "trough",
        "ridge",
        "Col",
        "High"
      ],
      "answer": "trough"
    },
    {
      "question": "An omega block is an extreme version of a blocking high. This feature remains stationary __________ period.",
      "choices": [
        "short, very intense",
        "for a prolonged",
        "long, very intense",
        "short"
      ],
      "answer": "for a prolonged"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the ELR is greater than both the DALR and SALR, then the atmosphere is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "unconditionally stable",
        "absolutely unstable",
        "absolutely stable",
        "conditionally stable"
      ],
      "answer": "absolutely unstable"
    },
    {
      "question": "Flight towards an area of low temperature causes the indicated altitude to be __________ than the true altitude. This error is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "lower; unsafe",
        "higher; safe",
        "higher; unsafe",
        "lower; safe"
      ],
      "answer": "higher; unsafe"
    },
    {
      "question": "High pressure regions on charts can be identified by:",
      "choices": [
        "Widely spaced isobars whose values are decreasing with distance from the core.",
        "Isobars marked with light line weights (rather than the heavy line weights used for lows).",
        "Closely spaced isobars whose values are decreasing with distance from the core.",
        "Widely spaced isobars whose values are increasing with distance from the core."
      ],
      "answer": "Widely spaced isobars whose values are decreasing with distance from the core."
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft flies from London to South France and experiences a strong wind from the left. Which of the following is correct?",
      "choices": [
        "The true altitude will decrease.",
        "The true altitude will increase.",
        "The true altitude remains constant.",
        "The indicated altitude will decrease"
      ],
      "answer": "The true altitude will decrease."
    },
    {
      "question": "The typical height of the vertical area affected by sea breeze in mid-latitudes is approximately:",
      "choices": [
        "5000 ft",
        "100 ft",
        "10 000 ft",
        "1000 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "1000 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "The atmospheric layer above the troposphere, where temperature is constant with height up to about __________ km, is called the __________.",
      "choices": [
        "20; stratosphere",
        "50; stratopause",
        "20; stratopause",
        "50; troposphere"
      ],
      "answer": "20; stratosphere"
    },
    {
      "question": "After climbing though the transition altitude vertical position is expressed as a __________ __________.",
      "choices": [
        "height",
        "flight level",
        "altitude",
        "pressure"
      ],
      "answer": "flight level"
    },
    {
      "question": "Solar radiation has a __________ wavelength than terrestrial radiation.",
      "choices": [
        "shorter",
        "longer",
        "the same",
        "stronger"
      ],
      "answer": "shorter"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is true of a 'land breeze'?",
      "choices": [
        "It blows by day.",
        "It blows from land to water.",
        "It blows only at noon.",
        "It blows from water to land."
      ],
      "answer": "It blows from land to water."
    },
    {
      "question": "It is the early afternoon on a sunny day in summer, and you are flying over the west coast of the Netherlands. If there is a non-frontal environment with a slack pressure gradient, the wind direction at the surface is likely to be:",
      "choices": [
        "southerly",
        "westerly",
        "easterly",
        "Northerly"
      ],
      "answer": "westerly"
    },
    {
      "question": "On traditional mean sea level pressure (MSLP) synoptic charts the plotted __________ use these values.",
      "choices": [
        "isobars",
        "isphases",
        "isohypse",
        "isotherm"
      ],
      "answer": "isobars"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 'greenhouse effect' describes how:",
      "choices": [
        "Energy is trapped in the atmosphere because of the layer of ozone at the tropopause.",
        "Energy is added to the atmosphere because water vapour, CO\u2082 and methane absorb long wave terrestrial radiation.",
        "Energy is added to the atmosphere because water vapour, CO\u2082 and methane allow more solar radiation to penetrate the atmosphere.",
        "Energy is added to the atmosphere because water vapour, CO\u2082 and methane absorb long wave solar radiation."
      ],
      "answer": "Energy is added to the atmosphere because water vapour, CO\u2082 and methane absorb long wave terrestrial radiation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the correct statement relating density and moisture.",
      "choices": [
        "The density of moist air is greater than the density of dry air because water is heavier than air.",
        "The density of moist air is less than the density of dry air because water vapour has a lower mass than oxygen and nitrogen.",
        "The density of air doesn't depend on its moisture content, it depends only on its temperature.",
        "In humid air, the oxygen and nitrogen displace the water vapour."
      ],
      "answer": "The density of moist air is less than the density of dry air because water vapour has a lower mass than oxygen and nitrogen."
    },
    {
      "question": "The troposphere is the:",
      "choices": [
        "Boundary between the mesosphere and thermosphere.",
        "Boundary between the stratosphere and the mesosphere.",
        "Part of the atmosphere below the tropopause.",
        "Part of the atmosphere above the stratosphere."
      ],
      "answer": "Part of the atmosphere below the tropopause."
    },
    {
      "question": "What will the altimeter be indicating if the aircraft\u2019s true altitude is 10 000 ft when the OAT is -30\u00b0C at a pressure altitude of 10 000 ft?",
      "choices": [
        "10 000 ft.",
        "11 000 ft.",
        "12 000 ft.",
        "9000 ft."
      ],
      "answer": "11 000 ft."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which of the following circumstances would the formation of a low-level jet stream in the evening be most likely?",
      "choices": [
        "An inflow of cold air over land or strong radiation cooling in the evening can lead to an inversion; at or just below the top of the inversion a low-level jet stream can form.",
        "The inflow of air into the base of a CB or TS at night can result, occasionally, in the concentration of the wind near the cold surface, which leads to the formation of a low-level jet stream.",
        "When warm air in the evening moves into the friction layer near the surface, a low-level jet stream can sometimes form, within or above the top of the layer.",
        "When the airflow near the surface is forced against a mass of cold air ahead of a warm front at night, the low-level wind increases and can occasionally form a low-level jet stream."
      ],
      "answer": "An inflow of cold air over land or strong radiation cooling in the evening can lead to an inversion; at or just below the top of the inversion a low-level jet stream can form."
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the term from its definition: The vertical distance above mean sea level.",
      "choices": [
        "Height",
        "QNH",
        "QFE",
        "Altitude"
      ],
      "answer": "Altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "Subsiding air creates a column of relatively warmer air which decreases the average ELR and __________ atmospheric stability. This __________ cloud formation.",
      "choices": [
        "decreases; promotes",
        "increases; prevents",
        "increases; promotes",
        "decreases; prevents"
      ],
      "answer": "increases; prevents"
    },
    {
      "question": "Turbulence __________ the transfer of heat energy between atmospheric layers.",
      "choices": [
        "has no effect on",
        "restricts",
        "promotes",
        "increases"
      ],
      "answer": "promotes"
    },
    {
      "question": "The transition altitude for the day is 4500 ft. The QNH on this summer day is 1030 hPa. At the transition altitude you change the altimeter to the SPS. It now reads:",
      "choices": [
        "3490 ft",
        "FL 45.",
        "5010 ft",
        "3990 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "3990 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "When a parcel of air contains the maximum amount of water vapour that is possible to hold at the current temperature and pressure (RH 100%) the air is said to be __________.",
      "choices": [
        "relatively full",
        "saturated",
        "absolute",
        "humid"
      ],
      "answer": "saturated"
    },
    {
      "question": "The atmosphere comprises 78% __________, 21% __________ and 1% of other gases.",
      "choices": [
        "nitrogen; oxygen",
        "nitrogen; carbon dioxide",
        "carbon dioxide; oxygen",
        "oxygen; nitrogen"
      ],
      "answer": "nitrogen; oxygen"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sea level __________ pressure is the result of the weight force of the mass of the atmosphere bearing down on it.",
      "choices": [
        "dynamic",
        "static",
        "air",
        "absolute"
      ],
      "answer": "static"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given:  Pressure altitude: 3000 ft  indicated altitude: 2500 ft  Temperature : ISA +21\u00b0C What is the true altitude?",
      "choices": [
        "4914 ft",
        "3200 ft",
        "2290 ft",
        "2710 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "2710 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the ELR is less than both the DALR and SALR then the atmosphere is __________.",
      "choices": [
        "absolutely stable",
        "unconditionally stable",
        "conditionally stable",
        "absolutely unstable"
      ],
      "answer": "absolutely stable"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a valid explanation for the lack of visible weather in the stratosphere?",
      "choices": [
        "The complete absence of water vapour in the stratosphere means that weather can't form.",
        "Very strong winds at the tropopause (jet streams) prevent clouds from rising higher.",
        "The relatively hot air of the stratosphere (heated by insolation) traps the relatively cold air of the troposphere.",
        "The isothermic or inversion conditions in the stratosphere create a physical barrier to further vertical development of cloud."
      ],
      "answer": "The isothermic or inversion conditions in the stratosphere create a physical barrier to further vertical development of cloud."
    },
    {
      "question": "Up to a height of about 20 km, 1 of the 2 principal layers in the atmosphere is the __________ where temperature __________ with height.",
      "choices": [
        "stratopause; is approximately constant",
        "stratosphere; increases",
        "stratopause; decreases",
        "stratosphere; is approximately constant"
      ],
      "answer": "stratosphere; is approximately constant"
    },
    {
      "question": "Troll Troll Troll H\u00c6H\u00c6, ser du denne er du taper! Hvem er mest taper av alle?",
      "choices": [
        "Deg",
        "Meg",
        "Han ved siden av deg",
        "Ta meg bakifra"
      ],
      "answer": "Ta meg bakifra"
    }
  ],
  "ALW": [
    {
      "question": "How could a pilot counter the effects of reverse sensing when flying a LOC BC approach?",
      "choices": [
        "By using an OBI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the ILS front course .",
        "By using a HSI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the ILS front course.",
        "By using an OBI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the LOC back-course .",
        "By using a HSI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the LOC back-course."
      ],
      "answer": "By using a HSI and setting the course selector at the bearing of the ILS front course."
    },
    {
      "question": "When preparing your aircraft to commence a descent the ATS unit requests you to arrive at a level overhead the waypoint at a specified time. Which RNAV system would be required for this?",
      "choices": [
        "3D RNAV",
        "4D RNAV",
        "2D Precision RNAV",
        "2D Basic RNAV"
      ],
      "answer": "4D RNAV"
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio waves in the VHF and higher frequency bands propagate mainly as:",
      "choices": [
        "Space waves.",
        "Sky waves.",
        "Surface waves.",
        "Earth reflected waves."
      ],
      "answer": "Space waves."
    },
    {
      "question": "Modulation is:",
      "choices": [
        "a continuous wave which is capable of carrying audible signals without modification.",
        "the process of impressing and transporting information by radio waves.",
        "to allow the signal to be amplified to the required power level.",
        "the process to provide a radio carrier wave for transmission."
      ],
      "answer": "the process of impressing and transporting information by radio waves."
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio waves in the VHF and higher frequency bands propagate mainly as:",
      "choices": [
        "Space waves.",
        "Sky waves.",
        "Surface waves.",
        "Earth reflected waves."
      ],
      "answer": "Space waves."
    },
    {
      "question": "Diffraction is the process by which:",
      "choices": [
        "Radio waves travel over and around obstacles.",
        "A ground wave is attenuated over rough ground.",
        "A direct wave is bent around the form of the earth.",
        "A space wave penetrates the ionosphere."
      ],
      "answer": "Radio waves travel over and around obstacles."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the recommended nominal GP angle?",
      "choices": [
        "3.2\u00b0",
        "3.5\u00b0",
        "4\u00b0",
        "3\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "3\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the reason a DME-interrogator makes use of an irregular transmission sequence?",
      "choices": [
        "In this way the DME-transponder is able to determine from which aircraft each sequence of pulse pairs is received.",
        "In this way the DME-interrogator is able to distinguish between his own reply pulse pairs and the reply pulse pairs of other aircraft.",
        "In this way the DME-interrogator is able to estimate the size of the error in the range measurement.",
        "In this way the DME-transponder is able to apply the correct delay time to each sequence of pulse pairs received."
      ],
      "answer": "In this way the DME-interrogator is able to distinguish between his own reply pulse pairs and the reply pulse pairs of other aircraft."
    },
    {
      "question": "In what increments does Mode S carry out enhanced vertical tracking?",
      "choices": [
        "75 ft",
        "50 ft",
        "25 ft",
        "100 ft"
      ],
      "answer": "25 ft"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following contain the principle elements of a GNSS?",
      "choices": [
        "Satellite, User and Ground segments.",
        "Space, Receiver, Ground and Control segments.",
        "Satellite, Receiver and Ground segments.",
        "Space, User and Control segments."
      ],
      "answer": "Space, User and Control segments."
    },
    {
      "question": "A Cat II ILS glide path transmitter facillity provides reliable guidance information down to:",
      "choices": [
        "A max height of 200 ft above the runway",
        "A max height of 100 ft above the runway",
        "A max height of 50 ft above the runway",
        "The surface of the runway"
      ],
      "answer": "A max height of 50 ft above the runway"
    },
    {
      "question": "Glide path antenna is located on the side of the runway approximately",
      "choices": [
        "300 m beyond the threshold",
        "300 m from the fat end of the runway",
        "200 m beyond the threshold",
        "200 m beyond the ILS reference point"
      ],
      "answer": "300 m beyond the threshold"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is lateral position determined on an ILS LOC?",
      "choices": [
        "Phase difference, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 150 Hz and 90 Hz respectively.",
        "Difference in depth of modulation, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 150 Hz and 90 Hz respectively.",
        "Phase difference, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz respectively.",
        "Difference in depth of modulation, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz respectively."
      ],
      "answer": "Difference in depth of modulation, calculated from 2 overlapping left and right lobes of energy, modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz respectively."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the principle of operation in an ILS, the glide path indicator needle is centred when the Difference in Depth of Modulation (DDM) is:",
      "choices": [
        "More than 150 Hz",
        "Maximum",
        "Zero",
        "Less than 90 Hz"
      ],
      "answer": "Zero"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following contain the principle elements of a GNSS?",
      "choices": [
        "Satellite, User and Ground segments.",
        "Space, Receiver, Ground and Control segments.",
        "Satellite, Receiver and Ground segments.",
        "Space, User and Control segments."
      ],
      "answer": "Space, User and Control segments."
    },
    {
      "question": "Errors in GPS satellite orbits are due to:",
      "choices": [
        "The lunar wind and gravitation of earth, moon and stars.",
        "Solar and Lunar precession.",
        "Earth and Lunar precession.",
        "The solar wind and gravitation of sun, moon and planets."
      ],
      "answer": "The solar wind and gravitation of sun, moon and planets."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following navigation specifications requires 2 x Long Range Navigation Systems (LRNS), one of which may be IRS?",
      "choices": [
        "RNP 0.3",
        "RNP 1",
        "RNP 10",
        "RNP 4"
      ],
      "answer": "RNP 10"
    },
    {
      "question": "The super position of two EM-waves of the same or nearly the same frequency is called:",
      "choices": [
        "Refraction.",
        "Diffraction.",
        "Reflection.",
        "Interference."
      ],
      "answer": "Interference."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the order of colours, with increasing intensity of precipitation, on a modern airborne weather radar system?",
      "choices": [
        "Black, White, Amber, Red",
        "Green, Amber, Red, Magenta",
        "Amber, Red, Magenta, Green",
        "Black, Amber, Red, Green"
      ],
      "answer": "Green, Amber, Red, Magenta"
    },
    {
      "question": "At what speed do radio waves travel?",
      "choices": [
        "30 000 m/s",
        "300 000 000 km/s",
        "300 000 000 m/s",
        "300 000 m/s"
      ],
      "answer": "300 000 000 m/s"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the minimum coverage area of the final approach path (FAP) for a ground-based augmentation system (GBAS) augmented approach?",
      "choices": [
        "10\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance between 15 and 20 NM, and 35\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 15 NM.",
        "10\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance of 25 NM, and 35\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 17 NM.",
        "35\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance of 20 NM, and 20\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 10 NM.",
        "10\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance between 17 NM and 22 NM, and 30\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 17 NM."
      ],
      "answer": "10\u00b0 either side of the FAP to a distance between 15 and 20 NM, and 35\u00b0 either side of the FAP up to a distance of 15 NM."
    },
    {
      "question": "For a satellite to be visible to a GPS reveiver",
      "choices": [
        "It needs a higher elevation than 5 degrees above the horizon",
        "It needs a higher elevation than 15 degrees above the horizon",
        "It needs a higher elevation than 5 degrees below the horizon",
        "It needs a higher elevation than 15 degrees below the horizon"
      ],
      "answer": "It needs a higher elevation than 5 degrees above the horizon"
    },
    {
      "question": "The frequency which corresponds to a wavelength of 12 cm is:",
      "choices": [
        "2500 KHz",
        "360 MHz",
        "2.5 GHz",
        "3600 MHz"
      ],
      "answer": "2.5 GHz"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a potential threat to the safety of a flight by setting the tilt of the airborne weather radar beam too high during a climb?",
      "choices": [
        "Interference from satellite signals of similar frequencies may interfere with the beam, causing false readings.",
        "The aircraft may climb through its own beam, causing false reflections.",
        "The beam may not detect the dry, frozen ice particles in the upper sections of thunderstorms.",
        "The higher the beam is tilted the less power that is available to reflect from thunderstorms."
      ],
      "answer": "The beam may not detect the dry, frozen ice particles in the upper sections of thunderstorms."
    },
    {
      "question": "By what angle should a 4\u00b0 beam be tilted to determine whether distant clouds are above the flight path of an aircraft in level flight?",
      "choices": [
        "Tilt down by 4\u00b0",
        "Tilt up by 2\u00b0",
        "The tilt angle should be maintained at 0\u00b0 and the gain increased",
        "Tilt up by 4\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "Tilt up by 2\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "With thunderstorms reported in the vicinity, when lining up on the runway what would you do with the weather radar?",
      "choices": [
        "Select map mode to get a wider coverage during the take-off period.",
        "Turn the Ground clutter switch to off.",
        "Increase the gain to get a better image.",
        "After scanning upwards to look for weather, set the tilt a few degrees up."
      ],
      "answer": "After scanning upwards to look for weather, set the tilt a few degrees up."
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum safe deviation below the glide path during ILS approach is indicated by half scale deflection on your intrument. The indicated deflection is more than half-scale deflection, what shall the pilot do?",
      "choices": [
        "Act at the discretion of the commander in any case",
        "Act his/her discretion (pilot's discretion).",
        "Try to get back to the correct glide path.",
        "Initiate a go-around."
      ],
      "answer": "Initiate a go-around."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the required tracking accuracy for en-route NDB tracking?",
      "choices": [
        "+/-10\u00b0",
        "+/-2.5\u00b0",
        "+/-0.7\u00b0",
        "+/-5\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/-5\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "A RAIM system has excluded a satellite. How many satellites are required to maintain a 3D Position fix with RAIM capability?",
      "choices": [
        "4",
        "6",
        "5",
        "3"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the usual order of priority for navigation equipment in the RNAV hierarchy?",
      "choices": [
        "DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR, IRS, GNSS",
        "GNSS, IRS, DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR",
        "GNSS, DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR, IRS",
        "IRS, GNSS, DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR"
      ],
      "answer": "GNSS, IRS, DME/DME, VOR/DME, VOR/VOR"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which aircraft would a DME transponder preferentially respond to?",
      "choices": [
        "The 100 aircraft with the strongest signals.",
        "The 100 aircraft at the lowest altitudes.",
        "The 100 aircraft at the highest altitudes.",
        "The 100 closest aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "The 100 aircraft with the strongest signals."
    },
    {
      "question": "How is a ground range calculated from a DME range?",
      "choices": [
        "Ground Range = \u00bd x DME Range x Altitude",
        "Ground Range = 1.2 x DME Range x Altitude",
        "Ground Range = 1.23 x (\u221aDME Range + \u221a Altitude)",
        "Ground Range\u00b2 = DME Range\u00b2 \u2013 Altitude\u00b2"
      ],
      "answer": "Ground Range\u00b2 = DME Range\u00b2 \u2013 Altitude\u00b2"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the advantages of a SBAS over GBAS is",
      "choices": [
        "an SBAS does not, like a GBAS, need ground stations for the estimation of the pseudo-range corrections",
        "the coberage area of an SBAS is much larger than that of a GBAS",
        "the rate at which pseudo-range corrections reach the users is much higher for a GBAS than for an SBAS",
        "the pseudo-range corrections of an SBAS are much more accurate than those of a GBAS"
      ],
      "answer": "the coberage area of an SBAS is much larger than that of a GBAS"
    },
    {
      "question": "Basic RNAV requires a track-keeping accuracy of:",
      "choices": [
        "+/- 5NM or better for 95% of the flight time.",
        "+/- 3NM or better for 90% of the flight time.",
        "+/- 2NM or better for 75% of the flight time.",
        "+/- 5NM or better throughout the flight."
      ],
      "answer": "+/- 5NM or better for 95% of the flight time."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the principle behind the windshear-warning capability of an airborne weather radar?",
      "choices": [
        "The Doppler shift of particles of dust, sand and soot is measured.",
        "The change in intensity of detectable precipitation is measured.",
        "The Doppler shift is detectable precipitation is measured.",
        "The aircraft's groundspeed is measured in the MAP mode and this is compared to the airspeed"
      ],
      "answer": "The Doppler shift is detectable precipitation is measured."
    },
    {
      "question": "\"Managed by gross reasonableness checks of navigation data during procedure design, and usually negligible\" is a description of what navigation accuracy?",
      "choices": [
        "Flight Technical Error",
        "Navigation Systems Error",
        "Path Definition Error",
        "System Definition Error"
      ],
      "answer": "Path Definition Error"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are permitted by the use of offset flight paths?",
      "choices": [
        "They allow the RNAV computer to automatically select any route, off the defined route, at a fixed distance from a navaid.",
        "They allow the crew to fly a route, offset from a defined airway between two VORs, at a fixed distance from airway.",
        "They allow the crew to fly any route, entered into the RNAV computer off the defined route, at a fixed distance from a navaid.",
        "They allow the crew to fly a parallel route, entered into the RNAV computer, at a fixed distance from defined route."
      ],
      "answer": "They allow the crew to fly a parallel route, entered into the RNAV computer, at a fixed distance from defined route."
    },
    {
      "question": "SBAS systems improve the navigational accuracy of GPS by:",
      "choices": [
        "Providing an additional signal coming from the geostationary satellites.",
        "Providing an additional signal to GPS receivers.",
        "Providing an additional signal coming from the navigation satellites.",
        "Correcting ranging errors."
      ],
      "answer": "Correcting ranging errors."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the International Telecommunication Union (ITU} code, a radio signal may be classified by three symbols. The abbreviation A3E is used for the type of transmission in which the carrier wave is:",
      "choices": [
        "A continuous wave interrupted with a keyed Morse code ident as used by an NDB.",
        "A double sideband carrier wave, frequency modulated for speech, such as is used for VHF-COM.",
        "Amplitude modulated to transmit the Morse code ident, as is used by a VOR.",
        "Amplitude modulated by a speech signal, such as is used for VHF-COM."
      ],
      "answer": "Amplitude modulated by a speech signal, such as is used for VHF-COM."
    },
    {
      "question": "In accordance with the International Telecommunication Union (ITU) a radio signal can be classified by three symbols. What is indicated by the first character of the group A1A?",
      "choices": [
        "Type of information to be transmitted.",
        "Type of modulation of the secondary carrier.",
        "Nature of the signal modulating the main carrier.",
        "Type of modulation of the main carrier."
      ],
      "answer": "Type of modulation of the main carrier."
    },
    {
      "question": "International Telecommunication Union (ITU) classification abbreviations used in aviation include the (1) ____ _ abbreviation. This designates carrier wave emissions amplitude modulated with Morse code which is used by (2) _____ .",
      "choices": [
        "(1) A3E; (2) NDBs",
        "(1) A2A; (2) VORs",
        "(1) A3E; (2) VORs",
        "(1) A2A; (2) NDBs"
      ],
      "answer": "(1) A2A; (2) NDBs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Reflections from large objects within the ILS coverage area may cause:",
      "choices": [
        "Doppler errors",
        "Static noise",
        "Single path interference",
        "Multi-path interference"
      ],
      "answer": "Multi-path interference"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the accuracy definition for a Class A QDM?",
      "choices": [
        "+/-5\u00b0",
        "+/-15\u00b0",
        "+/-10\u00b0",
        "+/-2\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/-2\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "3D RNAV fixing gives you:",
      "choices": [
        "Horizontal, vertical profile and time guidance.",
        "2D RNAV plus speed control.",
        "2D RNAV plus time guidance.",
        "Horizontal and vertical profile guidance."
      ],
      "answer": "Horizontal and vertical profile guidance."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is true with regard to RNP/RNAV navigation specifications?",
      "choices": [
        "Accuracy requirements are always similar to functional requirements.",
        "Aircraft approved to more stringent accuracy requirements will never meet the functional requirements of a navigation specification with a less stringent accuracy requirement.",
        "Aircraft approved to more stringent accuracy requirements may not necessarily meet some of the functional requirements of a navigation specification with a less stringent accuracy requirement.",
        "Aircraft approved to more stringent accuracy requirements automatically meet the functional requirements of a navigation specification with a less stringent accuracy requirement."
      ],
      "answer": "Aircraft approved to more stringent accuracy requirements may not necessarily meet some of the functional requirements of a navigation specification with a less stringent accuracy requirement."
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the worldwide SBAS in use is: _________ - India.",
      "choices": [
        "EGNOS",
        "MSAS",
        "WAAS",
        "GAGAN"
      ],
      "answer": "GAGAN"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which aircraft would a DME transponder preferentially respond to?",
      "choices": [
        "The 100 aircraft with the strongest signals.",
        "The 100 aircraft at the lowest altitudes.",
        "The 100 aircraft at the highest altitudes.",
        "The 100 closest aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": "The 100 aircraft with the strongest signals."
    },
    {
      "question": "PBN path terminator DF means:",
      "choices": [
        "Doppler Fix",
        "Destination Fix",
        "Direct to a Fix",
        "Designated Fix"
      ],
      "answer": "Direct to a Fix"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following data sets provides precise positioning information of an individual satellite within the NAVSTAR/GPS constellation?",
      "choices": [
        "Almanac.",
        "SBAS.",
        "Navigation database.",
        "Ephemeris."
      ],
      "answer": "Ephemeris."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following are significant factors affecting the accuracy of a GNSS position fix?\n\n1. ionospheric propagation delay\n2. dilution of precision\n3. satellite clock error\n4. lunar orbital variations\n5. UTC to standard time variations\n6. atomic time fluctuations",
      "choices": [
        "2, 4 and 6",
        "1, 3 and 6",
        "2, 3 and 5",
        "1, 2 and 3"
      ],
      "answer": "1, 2 and 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum deviation that can be shown by the deviation bar on a standard omni-bearing indicator in VOR mode?",
      "choices": [
        "+/-5\u00b0",
        "+/-2.5\u00b0",
        "+/-15\u00b0",
        "+/-10\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "+/-10\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the maximum LOC and GP deviations on an ILS cockpit indicator?",
      "choices": [
        "LOC +/- 2.5\u00b0 and GP +/- 1\u00b0",
        "LOC +/- 10\u00b0 and GP +/- 2.5\u00b0",
        "LOC +/- 5\u00b0 and GP +/- 2\u00b0",
        "LOC +/- 2.5\u00b0 and GP +/- 0.7\u00b0"
      ],
      "answer": "LOC +/- 2.5\u00b0 and GP +/- 0.7\u00b0"
    },
    {
      "question": "An error during PBN operations arising from the RNAV system and its inability to accurately specify the desired path is a:",
      "choices": [
        "Crew Error (CE)",
        "Flight Technical Error (FTE)",
        "Path Definition Error (PDE)",
        "Navigation System Error (NSE)"
      ],
      "answer": "Path Definition Error (PDE)"
    },
    {
      "question": "How is Estimated Position Error (EPE) defined?",
      "choices": [
        "Comparison by system of probable amount of current error against margin of error allowable; variable by statistical analysis of all available sensors.",
        "Comparison by flight crew of probable amount of current error against margin of error allowable; variable by sensor used.",
        "Comparison by system of probable amount of current error against margin of error allowable; variable by sensor used.",
        "Comparison by system of actual amount of current error against margin of potential error allowable; variable by statistical analysis of all available sensors."
      ],
      "answer": "Comparison by system of probable amount of current error against margin of error allowable; variable by sensor used."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the components of Total System Error is considered negligible and not factored into the mathematical solution for TSE?",
      "choices": [
        "Path Definition Error.",
        "Minimal Position Error.",
        "Navigation Systems Error.",
        "Flight Technical Error."
      ],
      "answer": "Path Definition Error."
    },
    {
      "question": "The Total System Error assumed in PBN operations encompasses:",
      "choices": [
        "Path Definition Error (PDE), Flight Technical Error (FTE), Navigation System Error (NSE)",
        "Path Terminator Error (PTE), Path Calculation Error (PCE), Flight Technical Error (FTE)",
        "Flight Technical Error (FTE), Navigation System Error (NSE), Path Calculation Error (PCE)",
        "Path Calculation Error (PCE), Navigation System Error (NSE), Flight Crew Error (FCE)"
      ],
      "answer": "Path Definition Error (PDE), Flight Technical Error (FTE), Navigation System Error (NSE)"
    },
    {
      "question": "On modern passenger aircraft, the navigation data base usually contains:",
      "choices": [
        "Aircraft performance data.",
        "Obstacle altitudes.",
        "Airport reference data.",
        "ATC frequencies."
      ],
      "answer": "Airport reference data."
    },
    {
      "question": "What would be the approximate range over the sea of an NDB transmitting at 250 watts?",
      "choices": [
        "70 NM",
        "50 NM",
        "60 NM",
        "80 NM"
      ],
      "answer": "50 NM"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the range of an NDB locator beacon?",
      "choices": [
        "20 \u2013 35 nm",
        "25 \u2013 50 nm",
        "10 \u2013 25 nm",
        "15 \u2013 30 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "10 \u2013 25 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Marker beacons are identified visually (cockpit lights) and audibly (Morse identification) as follows: Outer marker - __________ coloured - __________ dashes per second at __________frequency.",
      "choices": [
        "Amber; continuous; medium",
        "White; 6; high",
        "Blue; 4; low",
        "Blue; 2; low"
      ],
      "answer": "Blue; 2; low"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Range of an outer marker",
      "choices": [
        "4-7nm",
        "2-4nm",
        "7-10nm",
        "10-14nm"
      ],
      "answer": "4-7nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the components of Total System Error?",
      "choices": [
        "MPE, NSE, FET",
        "PEM, ETE, FTA",
        "PDE, NSE, FTE",
        "PDA, NSE, FET"
      ],
      "answer": "PDE, NSE, FTE"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which form of modulation adjusts the frequency of the signal, whilst maintaining a constant amplitude?",
      "choices": [
        "Phase",
        "Frequency",
        "Amplitude",
        "Pulse"
      ],
      "answer": "Frequency"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following forms of modulation maintains a constant frequency?",
      "choices": [
        "Deciduous",
        "Frequency",
        "Volumetric",
        "Amplitude"
      ],
      "answer": "Amplitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "PBN Path terminator CA means:",
      "choices": [
        "Course to Altitude",
        "Certified Altitude",
        "Centre Altitude",
        "Centre Approach"
      ],
      "answer": "Course to Altitude"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the minimum number of VDF stations required to triangulate a position fix for an aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "3",
        "2",
        "4",
        "1"
      ],
      "answer": "2"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aircraft has a Magnetic Heading of 290 and is on VOR radial 280. Which value has to be selected on the OBS to get a TO indication and the CDI centered?",
      "choices": [
        "290",
        "100",
        "280",
        "110"
      ],
      "answer": "100"
    },
    {
      "question": "The electromagnetic waves refracted from the E and F layers of the ionosphere are called:",
      "choices": [
        "Refracted waves.",
        "Ground waves.",
        "Space waves.",
        "Sky waves."
      ],
      "answer": "Sky waves."
    },
    {
      "question": "By what term is Mode S Selective Surveillance Call more commonly known?",
      "choices": [
        "Mode S Select.",
        "Addressing Call.",
        "All Call.",
        "Roll Call."
      ],
      "answer": "Roll Call."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the range of an NDB locator beacon?",
      "choices": [
        "20 \u2013 35 nm",
        "25 \u2013 50 nm",
        "10 \u2013 25 nm",
        "15 \u2013 30 nm"
      ],
      "answer": "10 \u2013 25 nm"
    },
    {
      "question": "Locators are:\n1. High powered NDBs used for en route and airways navigation.\n2. Low powered NDBs used ofr airfield or runway approach.\n3. Beacons with a usually range of 10 to 250 NM.\n4. Beacons with a usually range of 10 to 25 NM.",
      "choices": [
        "1 and 4",
        "2 and 4",
        "2 and 3",
        "1 and 3"
      ],
      "answer": "2 and 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following lists all the stages of flight when it is possible to change the route in the active flight plan on an FMS equipped aircraft?",
      "choices": [
        "Only before the flight plan is activated.",
        "Only once the aircraft is airborne.",
        "Only before take-off.",
        "At any time before take-off and throughout the flight."
      ],
      "answer": "At any time before take-off and throughout the flight."
    },
    {
      "question": "PBN path terminator 'TF' means:",
      "choices": [
        "Terminal Fix",
        "Tower Fix",
        "Track to Fix",
        "Time to Fix"
      ],
      "answer": "Track to Fix"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which has a Higher orbit",
      "choices": [
        "NAVSTAR",
        "GLONASS",
        "WAAS",
        "EGNOS"
      ],
      "answer": "NAVSTAR"
    },
    {
      "question": "Modulation is:",
      "choices": [
        "the transformation of the radio wave into a digital signal",
        "the separation of information from a radio wave during receiving",
        "the amplificaction of the received radio wave in the detector",
        "the addition of information onto a radio wave during transmission"
      ],
      "answer": "the addition of information onto a radio wave during transmission"
    }
  ]
}
